<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="DEU" style="id">- Literal Standard Version</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Book of Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc2">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc3">Deu</para>
  <para style="mt">Deuteronomy</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="DEU 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 1:1"/>These [are] the words which Moses has spoken to all Israel beyond the Jordan in the wilderness, in the plain opposite Suph, between Paran, and Tophel, and Laban, and Hazeroth, and Di-Zahab. <verse eid="DEU 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 1:2"/>[It takes] eleven days [to go] from Horeb, the way of Mount Seir, to Kadesh-Barnea. <verse eid="DEU 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 1:3"/>And it comes to pass in the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first of the month, Moses has spoken to the sons of Israel according to all that YHWH has commanded him concerning them, <verse eid="DEU 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 1:4"/>after his striking Sihon king of the Amorite who is dwelling in Heshbon, and Og king of Bashan who is dwelling in Ashtaroth in Edrei. <verse eid="DEU 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 1:5"/>Beyond the Jordan, in the land of Moab, Moses has begun to explain this law, saying, <verse eid="DEU 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 1:6"/>“Our God YHWH has spoken to us in Horeb, saying, For you dwell at this mountain long enough; <verse eid="DEU 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 1:7"/>turn and journey for yourselves, and go to the mountain of the Amorite, and to all its neighboring places in the plain, in the hill-country, and in the low country, and in the south, and in the haven of the sea, the land of the Canaanite, and of Lebanon, as far as the great river, the Euphrates River; <verse eid="DEU 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 1:8"/>see, I have set the land before you; go in and possess the land which YHWH has sworn to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to them and to their seed after them. <verse eid="DEU 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 1:9"/>And I speak to you at that time, saying, I am not able to bear you by myself; <verse eid="DEU 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 1:10"/>your God YHWH has multiplied you, and behold, today you [are] as the stars of the heavens for multitude; <verse eid="DEU 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 1:11"/>YHWH, God of your fathers, is adding to you, as you [are], one thousand times, and blesses you as He has spoken to you. <verse eid="DEU 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 1:12"/>How do I bear your pressure, and your burden, and your strife by myself? <verse eid="DEU 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 1:13"/>Provide wise and understanding men for yourselves that are known to your tribes, and I set them for your heads; <verse eid="DEU 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 1:14"/>and you answer me and say, The thing which you have spoken [is] good to do. <verse eid="DEU 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 1:15"/>And I take the heads of your tribes, wise men that are known, and I appoint them [as] heads over you, princes of thousands, and princes of hundreds, and princes of fifties, and princes of tens, and authorities for your tribes. <verse eid="DEU 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 1:16"/>And I command your judges at that time, saying, Listen between your brothers—then you have judged [in] righteousness between a man, and his brother, and his sojourner; <verse eid="DEU 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 1:17"/>you do not discern faces in judgment; you hear the little as well as the great; you are not afraid of the face of any, for the judgment is God’s, and the thing which is too hard for you, you bring near to me, and I have heard it. <verse eid="DEU 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 1:18"/>And I command you at that time all the things which you do. <verse eid="DEU 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 1:19"/>And we journey from Horeb, and go [through] all that great and fearful wilderness which you have seen, the way of the hill-country of the Amorite, as our God YHWH has commanded us, and we come to Kadesh-Barnea. <verse eid="DEU 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 1:20"/>And I say to you, You have come to the hill-country of the Amorite, which our God YHWH is giving to us; <verse eid="DEU 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 1:21"/>see, your God YHWH has set the land before you; go up, possess, as YHWH, God of your fathers, has spoken to you; do not fear, nor be frightened. <verse eid="DEU 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 1:22"/>And you come near to me, all of you, and say, Let us send men before us, and they search the land for us, and they bring us back word [concerning] the way in which we go up into it, and the cities to which we come in; <verse eid="DEU 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 1:23"/>and the thing is good in my eyes, and I take twelve men from you, one man for the tribe. <verse eid="DEU 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 1:24"/>And they turn and go up to the hill-country, and come to the Valley of Eshcol, and spy it out, <verse eid="DEU 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 1:25"/>and they take in their hand from the fruit of the land, and bring [it] down to us, and bring us back word, and say, The land is good which our God YHWH is giving to us. <verse eid="DEU 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 1:26"/>And you have not been willing to go up, and you provoke the mouth of your God YHWH, <verse eid="DEU 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 1:27"/>and murmur in your tents, and say, In YHWH’s hating us He has brought us out of the land of Egypt, to give us into the hand of the Amorite—to destroy us; <verse eid="DEU 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 1:28"/>to where are we going up? Our brothers have melted our heart, saying, [The] people [are] greater and taller than we; [the] cities [are] great and fortified up to the heavens, and we have also seen sons of Anakim there. <verse eid="DEU 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 1:29"/>And I say to you, Do not be terrified, nor be afraid of them; <verse eid="DEU 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 1:30"/>your God YHWH, who is going before you—He fights for you, according to all that He has done with you in Egypt before your eyes, <verse eid="DEU 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 1:31"/>and in the wilderness where you have seen that your God YHWH has carried you, as a man carries his son, in all the way which you have gone until your coming to this place. <verse eid="DEU 1:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 1:32"/>And in this thing you are not steadfast in your God YHWH, <verse eid="DEU 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 1:33"/>who is going before you in the way to search out for you a place for your encamping, in fire by night, to show you in the way in which you go, and in a cloud by day. <verse eid="DEU 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 1:34"/>And YHWH hears the voice of your words, and is angry, and swears, saying, <verse eid="DEU 1:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 1:35"/>Not one of these men of this evil generation sees the good land which I have sworn to give to your fathers, <verse eid="DEU 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 1:36"/>except Caleb son of Jephunneh—he sees it, and to him I give the land on which he has trodden, and to his sons, because that he has been fully after YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 1:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 1:37"/>Moreover, YHWH has been angry with me for your sake, saying, Indeed, you do not go in there; <verse eid="DEU 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 1:38"/>Joshua son of Nun, who is standing before you, he goes in there; strengthen him, for he causes Israel to inherit [it]. <verse eid="DEU 1:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 1:39"/>And your infants, of whom you have said, They are for a prey, and your sons who today have not known good and evil, they go in there, and I give it to them, and they possess it; <verse eid="DEU 1:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 1:40"/>but you, turn and journey for yourselves toward the wilderness, the way of the Red Sea. <verse eid="DEU 1:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 1:41"/>And you answer and say to me, We have sinned against YHWH; we go up and we have fought, according to all that which our God YHWH has commanded us; and you each gird on his weapons of war, and you are ready to go up into the hill-country; <verse eid="DEU 1:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 1:42"/>and YHWH says to me, Say to them, You do not go up, nor fight, for I am not in your midst, and you are not struck before your enemies. <verse eid="DEU 1:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 1:43"/>And I speak to you, and you have not listened, and provoke the mouth of YHWH, and act proudly, and go up into the hill-country; <verse eid="DEU 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 1:44"/>and the Amorite who is dwelling in that hill-country comes out to meet you, and they pursue you as the bees do, and strike you in Seir, even to Hormah. <verse eid="DEU 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 1:45"/>And you return and weep before YHWH, and YHWH has not listened to your voice, nor has He given ear to you; <verse eid="DEU 1:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 1:46"/>and you dwell in Kadesh [for] many days, according to the days which you had dwelt.”<verse eid="DEU 1:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="DEU 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 2:1"/>“And we turn and journey into the wilderness, the way of the Red Sea, as YHWH has spoken to me, and we go around Mount Seir [for] many days. <verse eid="DEU 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 2:2"/>And YHWH speaks to me, saying, <verse eid="DEU 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 2:3"/>For you go around this mountain long enough; turn for yourselves northward. <verse eid="DEU 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 2:4"/>And the people command you, saying, You are passing over into the border of your brothers, sons of Esau, who are dwelling in Seir, and they are afraid of you; and you have been very watchful; <verse eid="DEU 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 2:5"/>you do not strive with them, for I do not give [any] of their land to you—even the treading of the sole of a foot; I have given Mount Seir to Esau for a possession. <verse eid="DEU 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 2:6"/>You buy food from them with money, and have eaten; and you also buy water from them with money, and have drunk. <verse eid="DEU 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 2:7"/>For your God YHWH has blessed you in all the work of your hands; He has known your walking in this great wilderness these forty years; your God YHWH [is] with you; you have not lacked anything. <verse eid="DEU 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 2:8"/>And we pass by from our brothers, sons of Esau, who are dwelling in Seir, by the way of the plain, by Elath and by Ezion-Gaber, and we turn and pass over the way of the wilderness of Moab; <verse eid="DEU 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 2:9"/>and YHWH says to me, Do not distress Moab, nor stir yourself up against them [in] battle, for I do not give [any] of their land to you [for] a possession; for I have given Ar to the sons of Lot [for] a possession. <verse eid="DEU 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 2:10"/>The Emim have formerly dwelt in it, a people great, and numerous, and tall as the Anakim; <verse eid="DEU 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 2:11"/>they are reckoned [as] Rephaim, they also, as the Anakim; and the Moabites call them Emim. <verse eid="DEU 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 2:12"/>And the Horim have formerly dwelt in Seir, but the sons of Esau dispossess them, and destroy them from before them, and dwell in their stead, as Israel has done to the land of his possession which YHWH has given to them. <verse eid="DEU 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 2:13"/>Now rise and pass over the Brook of Zered for yourselves; and we pass over the Brook of Zered. <verse eid="DEU 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 2:14"/>And the days which we have walked from Kadesh-Barnea until we have passed over the Brook of Zered [are] thirty-eight years, until the consumption of all the generation of the men of battle from the midst of the camp, as YHWH has sworn to them; <verse eid="DEU 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 2:15"/>and indeed the hand of YHWH has been against them, to destroy them from the midst of the camp until they are consumed. <verse eid="DEU 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 2:16"/>And it comes to pass, when all the men of battle have finished dying from the midst of the people, <verse eid="DEU 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 2:17"/>that YHWH speaks to me, saying, <verse eid="DEU 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 2:18"/>Today you are passing over the border of Moab, even Ar, <verse eid="DEU 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 2:19"/>and [when] you have come near the sons of Ammon, you do not distress them, nor stir yourself up against them, for I do not give [any] of the land of the sons of Ammon to you [for] a possession; for I have given it to the sons of Lot [for] a possession. <verse eid="DEU 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 2:20"/>It is reckoned [as] a land of Rephaim, even it; Rephaim formerly dwelt in it, and the Ammonites call them Zamzummim, <verse eid="DEU 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 2:21"/>a people great, and numerous, and tall as the Anakim, and YHWH destroys them before them, and they dispossess them, and dwell in their stead, <verse eid="DEU 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 2:22"/>as He has done for the sons of Esau who are dwelling in Seir, when He destroyed the Horim from before them, and they dispossess them, and dwell in their stead to this day. <verse eid="DEU 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 2:23"/>As for the Avim who are dwelling in villages as far as Gaza, the Caphtorim—who are coming out from Caphtor—have destroyed them, and dwell in their stead. <verse eid="DEU 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 2:24"/>Rise, journey, and pass over the Brook of Arnon; see, I have given into your hand Sihon king of Heshbon, the Amorite, and his land; begin to possess [it], and stir yourself up against him [in] battle. <verse eid="DEU 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 2:25"/>This [is] the day I begin to put your dread and your fear on the face of the peoples under the whole heavens, who hear your fame, and have trembled and been pained because of you. <verse eid="DEU 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 2:26"/>And I send messengers from the wilderness of Kedemoth to Sihon king of Heshbon, [with] words of peace, saying, <verse eid="DEU 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 2:27"/>Let me pass over through your land; in the way—in the way I go, I do not turn aside [to the] right or left. <verse eid="DEU 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 2:28"/>You sell me food for money, and I have eaten; and you give to me water for money, and I have drunk; only, let me pass over on my feet, <verse eid="DEU 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 2:29"/>as the sons of Esau who are dwelling in Seir and the Moabites who are dwelling in Ar have done for me, until I pass over the Jordan to the land which our God YHWH is giving to us. <verse eid="DEU 2:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 2:30"/>And Sihon king of Heshbon has not been willing to let us pass over by him, for your God YHWH has hardened his spirit and strengthened his heart, so as to give him into your hand as at this day. <verse eid="DEU 2:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 2:31"/>And YHWH says to me, See, I have begun to give Sihon and his land before your faces; begin to possess—to possess his land. <verse eid="DEU 2:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 2:32"/>And Sihon comes out to meet us, he and all his people, to the battle at Jahaz; <verse eid="DEU 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 2:33"/>and our God YHWH gives him before our faces, and we strike him, and his sons, and all his people; <verse eid="DEU 2:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 2:34"/>and we capture all his cities at that time, and devote the whole city—men, and the women, and the infants; we have not left a remnant; <verse eid="DEU 2:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 2:35"/>only, we have spoiled the livestock for ourselves, and the spoil of the cities which we have captured. <verse eid="DEU 2:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 2:36"/>From Aroer, which [is] by the edge of the Brook of Arnon, and the city which [is] by the brook, even to Gilead, there has not been a city which [is] too high for us; our God YHWH has given the whole before our faces. <verse eid="DEU 2:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 2:37"/>Only, you have not drawn near to the land of the sons of Ammon—any part of the Brook of Jabbok, and cities of the hill-country, and anything which our God YHWH has [not] commanded.”<verse eid="DEU 2:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="DEU 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 3:1"/>“And we turn and go up the way to Bashan, and Og king of Bashan comes out to meet us, he and all his people, to the battle [at] Edrei. <verse eid="DEU 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 3:2"/>And YHWH says to me, Do not fear him, for I have given him, and all his people, and his land into your hand, and you have done to him as you have done to Sihon king of the Amorite who is dwelling in Heshbon. <verse eid="DEU 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 3:3"/>And our God YHWH indeed gives Og king of Bashan and all his people into our hands, and we strike him until there has been no remnant left to him; <verse eid="DEU 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 3:4"/>and we capture all his cities at that time; there has not been a city which we have not taken from them—sixty cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan. <verse eid="DEU 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 3:5"/>All these [are] cities fortified with high walls, double gates, and bar, apart from very many cities of the open place; <verse eid="DEU 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 3:6"/>and we devote them, as we have done to Sihon king of Heshbon, devoting [the] men, the women, and the infants of every city; <verse eid="DEU 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 3:7"/>and all the livestock, and the spoil of the cities, we have spoiled for ourselves. <verse eid="DEU 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 3:8"/>And at that time we take the land out of the hand of the two kings of the Amorite, which is beyond the Jordan, from the Brook of Arnon to Mount Hermon <verse eid="DEU 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 3:9"/>(Sidonians call Hermon Sirion, and the Amorites call it Senir), <verse eid="DEU 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 3:10"/>all the cities of the plain, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, as far as Salchah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan. <verse eid="DEU 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 3:11"/>For only Og king of Bashan had been left of the remnant of the Rephaim; behold, his bedstead [is] a bedstead of iron. Is it not in Rabbath of the sons of Ammon? Its length [is] nine cubits and its breadth [is] four cubits, by the cubit of a man. <verse eid="DEU 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 3:12"/>And this land, [which] we had possessed at that time, from Aroer, which [is] by the Brook of Arnon, and the half of Mount Gilead and its cities, I have given to the Reubenite and to the Gadite; <verse eid="DEU 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 3:13"/>and the rest of Gilead and all Bashan, the kingdom of Og, I have given to the half tribe of Manasseh; all the region of Argob, with all Bashan—it is called the land of [the] Rephaim. <verse eid="DEU 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 3:14"/>Jair son of Manasseh has taken all the region of Argob, as far as the border of Geshuri and Maachathi ([namely] Bashan), and calls them by his own name, Havoth-Jair, to this day. <verse eid="DEU 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 3:15"/>And I have given Gilead to Machir. <verse eid="DEU 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 3:16"/>And to the Reubenite and to the Gadite I have given from Gilead even to the Brook of Arnon, the middle of the valley and the border, even to the Brook of Jabbok, the border of the sons of Ammon, <verse eid="DEU 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 3:17"/>and the plain, and the Jordan, and the border, from Chinnereth even to the Sea of the Plain (the Salt Sea), under the Springs of Pisgah, at the [sun]-rising. <verse eid="DEU 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 3:18"/>And at that time I command you, saying, Your God YHWH has given this land to you to possess it; you pass over armed before your brothers the sons of Israel, all the sons of might. <verse eid="DEU 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 3:19"/>Only your wives, and your infants, and your livestock—I have known that you have much livestock—dwell in your cities which I have given to you, <verse eid="DEU 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 3:20"/>until YHWH gives rest to your brothers like yourselves, and they also have possessed the land which your God YHWH is giving to them beyond the Jordan; then you have each turned back to his possession which I have given to you. <verse eid="DEU 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 3:21"/>And I have commanded Joshua at that time, saying, Your eyes are seeing all that which your God YHWH has done to these two kings—so YHWH does to all the kingdoms to where you are passing over; <verse eid="DEU 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 3:22"/>do not fear them, for your God YHWH—He is fighting for you. <verse eid="DEU 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 3:23"/>And to YHWH I beg for grace at that time, saying, <verse eid="DEU 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 3:24"/>Lord YHWH, You have begun to show Your servant Your greatness and Your strong hand; for who [is] a god in the heavens or in earth who does according to Your works and according to Your might? <verse eid="DEU 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 3:25"/>Please let me pass over and see the good land which [is] beyond the Jordan, this good hill-country, and Lebanon. <verse eid="DEU 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 3:26"/>And YHWH shows Himself angry with me for your sake, and has not listened to me, and YHWH says to me, Enough of you; do not add to speak to Me about this thing anymore; <verse eid="DEU 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 3:27"/>go up [to] the top of Pisgah, and lift up your eyes westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and see with your eyes, for you do not pass over this Jordan; <verse eid="DEU 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 3:28"/>and charge Joshua, and strengthen him, and harden him, for he passes over before this people, and he causes them to inherit the land which you see. <verse eid="DEU 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 3:29"/>And we dwell in a valley opposite Beth-Peor.”<verse eid="DEU 3:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="DEU 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 4:1"/>“And now, O Israel, listen to the statutes and to the judgments which I am teaching you to do, so that you live, and have gone in, and possessed the land which YHWH God of your fathers is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 4:2"/>You do not add to the word which I am commanding you, nor diminish from it, to keep the commands of your God YHWH which I am commanding you. <verse eid="DEU 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 4:3"/>Your eyes are seeing that which YHWH has done in Ba‘al-Peor, for every man who has gone after Ba‘al-Peor, your God YHWH has destroyed him from your midst; <verse eid="DEU 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 4:4"/>and you who are cleaving to your God YHWH [are] alive today—all of you. <verse eid="DEU 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 4:5"/>See, I have taught you statutes and judgments, as my God YHWH has commanded me, to do so in the midst of the land to where you are going in to possess it; <verse eid="DEU 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 4:6"/>and you have kept and done [them] (for it [is] your wisdom and your understanding) before the eyes of the peoples who hear all these statutes, and they have said, Surely a people wise and understanding [is] this great nation. <verse eid="DEU 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 4:7"/>For which [is] the great nation that has God [so] near to it, as our God YHWH, in all we have called to Him? <verse eid="DEU 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 4:8"/>And which [is] the great nation which has righteous statutes and judgments according to all this law which I am setting before you today? <verse eid="DEU 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 4:9"/>Only, take heed to yourself, and watch your soul exceedingly, lest you forget the things which your eyes have seen, and lest they turn aside from your heart all [the] days of your life; and you have made them known to your sons and to your sons’ sons. <verse eid="DEU 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 4:10"/>[Never forget] the day when you have stood before your God YHWH in Horeb, in YHWH’s saying to me, Assemble the people to Me, and I cause them to hear My words, so that they learn to fear Me all the days that they are alive on the ground, and they teach their sons; <verse eid="DEU 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 4:11"/>and you draw near and stand under the mountain, and the mountain is burning with fire to the heart of the heavens, [with] darkness, cloud, and thick darkness, <verse eid="DEU 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 4:12"/>and YHWH speaks to you out of the midst of the fire; you are hearing a voice of words, but you are seeing no likeness, only a voice; <verse eid="DEU 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 4:13"/>and He declares His covenant to you, which He has commanded you to do, the Ten Commandments, and He writes them on two tablets of stone. <verse eid="DEU 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 4:14"/>And YHWH has commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and judgments, for your doing them in the land to where you are passing over to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 4:15"/>And you have been very watchful of your souls, for you have not seen any likeness in the day of YHWH’s speaking to you in Horeb out of the midst of the fire, <verse eid="DEU 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 4:16"/>lest you do corruptly, and have made for yourselves a carved image, a likeness of any figure: a form of male or female, <verse eid="DEU 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 4:17"/>a form of any beast which [is] in the earth, a form of any winged bird which flies in the heavens, <verse eid="DEU 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 4:18"/>a form of any creeping thing on the ground, a form of any fish which [is] in the waters below the earth. <verse eid="DEU 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 4:19"/>And lest you lift up your eyes to the heavens, and have seen the sun, and the moon, and the stars, all the host of the heavens, and have been drawn away, and have bowed yourself to them and served them, which your God YHWH has apportioned to all the peoples under all the heavens. <verse eid="DEU 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 4:20"/>And YHWH has taken you, and He is bringing you out from the iron furnace, from Egypt, to be to Him for a people, an inheritance, as [at] this day. <verse eid="DEU 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 4:21"/>And YHWH has showed Himself angry with me because of your words, and swears to my not passing over the Jordan, and to my not going into the good land which your God YHWH is giving to you [for] an inheritance; <verse eid="DEU 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 4:22"/>for I am dying in this land; I am not passing over the Jordan, but you are passing over and have possessed this good land. <verse eid="DEU 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 4:23"/>Take heed to yourselves lest you forget the covenant of your God YHWH which He has made with you, and have made a carved image for yourselves, a likeness of anything [concerning] which your God YHWH has charged you; <verse eid="DEU 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 4:24"/>for your God YHWH is a consuming fire—a zealous God. <verse eid="DEU 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 4:25"/>When you beget sons and sons’ sons, and you have become old in the land, and have done corruptly, and have made a carved image, a likeness of anything, and have done evil in the eyes of YHWH to provoke Him to anger, <verse eid="DEU 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 4:26"/>I have caused the heavens and the earth to testify against you this day, that you perish utterly quickly from off the land to where you are passing over the Jordan to possess it; you do not prolong days on it, but are utterly destroyed; <verse eid="DEU 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 4:27"/>and YHWH has scattered you among the peoples, and you have been left few in number among the nations to where YHWH leads you, <verse eid="DEU 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 4:28"/>and you have served gods there, work of man’s hands, wood and stone, which do not see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell. <verse eid="DEU 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 4:29"/>And you have sought your God YHWH from there, and have found [Him] when you seek Him with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 4:30"/>In the distress of yours, when all these things have found you in the latter end of the days, and you have turned back to your God YHWH and have listened to His voice— <verse eid="DEU 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 4:31"/>for your God YHWH [is] a merciful God—He does not fail you, nor destroy you, nor forget the covenant of your fathers which He has sworn to them. <verse eid="DEU 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 4:32"/>For ask now of the former days which have been before you, from the day that God created man on the earth, and from the [one] end of the heavens even to the [other] end of the heavens, whether there has been as this great thing, or [if anything] has been heard like it. <verse eid="DEU 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 4:33"/>Has a people heard the voice of God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as you have heard, you—and live? <verse eid="DEU 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 4:34"/>Or has God tried to go in to take a nation for Himself from the midst of a nation, by trials, by signs, and by wonders, and by war, and by a strong hand, and by an outstretched arm, and by great terrors, according to all that your God YHWH has done to you in Egypt before your eyes? <verse eid="DEU 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 4:35"/>You—you have been shown [it], to know that He, YHWH, [is] God; there is none else besides Him. <verse eid="DEU 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 4:36"/>He has caused you to hear His voice from the heavens, to instruct you; and on earth He has showed you His great fire, and you have heard His words out of the midst of the fire. <verse eid="DEU 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 4:37"/>And because that He has loved your fathers, He also fixes on their seed after them, and brings you out in His presence, by His great power, from Egypt, <verse eid="DEU 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 4:38"/>to dispossess nations greater and stronger than you from your presence, to bring you in to give their land to you [for] an inheritance, as [at] this day. <verse eid="DEU 4:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 4:39"/>And you have known today, and have turned [it] back to your heart, that He, YHWH, [is] God in the heavens above and on the earth below—there is none else; <verse eid="DEU 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 4:40"/>and you have kept His statutes and His commands which I am commanding you today, so that it is well for you, and for your sons after you, and so that you prolong days on the ground which your God YHWH is giving to you—all the days.” <verse eid="DEU 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 4:41"/>Then Moses separates three cities beyond the Jordan, toward the sun-rising, <verse eid="DEU 4:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 4:42"/>for the fleeing there of the manslayer who slays his neighbor unknowingly, and he is not hating him before, and he has fled to one of these cities and he has lived: <verse eid="DEU 4:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 4:43"/>Bezer in the wilderness, in the land of the plain, for the Reubenite; and Ramoth in Gilead for the Gadite; and Golan in Bashan for the Manassite. <verse eid="DEU 4:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 4:44"/>And this [is] the law which Moses has set before the sons of Israel; <verse eid="DEU 4:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 4:45"/>these [are] the testimonies, and the statutes, and the judgments, which Moses has spoken to the sons of Israel in their coming out of Egypt, <verse eid="DEU 4:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 4:46"/>beyond the Jordan, in the valley opposite Beth-Peor, in the land of Sihon, king of the Amorite, who is dwelling in Heshbon, whom Moses and the sons of Israel have struck in their coming out of Egypt; <verse eid="DEU 4:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 4:47"/>and they possess his land and the land of Og king of Bashan, two kings of the Amorite who [are] beyond the Jordan, [toward] the sun-rising, <verse eid="DEU 4:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 4:48"/>from Aroer, which [is] by the edge of the Brook of Arnon, even to Mount Zion, which [is] Hermon— <verse eid="DEU 4:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 4:49"/>and all the plain beyond the Jordan eastward, even to the Sea of the Plain, below the Springs of Pisgah.<verse eid="DEU 4:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="DEU 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 5:1"/>And Moses calls to all Israel and says to them, “Hear, O Israel, the statutes and the judgments which I am speaking in your ears today, and you have learned them and have observed to do them. <verse eid="DEU 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 5:2"/>Our God YHWH made a covenant with us in Horeb; <verse eid="DEU 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 5:3"/>YHWH has not made this covenant with our fathers, but with us, we—these here—all of us living today. <verse eid="DEU 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 5:4"/>YHWH has spoken with you face to face on the mountain, out of the midst of the fire; <verse eid="DEU 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 5:5"/>I am standing between YHWH and you, at that time, to declare the word of YHWH to you, for you have been afraid from the presence of the fire, and you have not gone up into the mountain; for [He] says: <verse eid="DEU 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 5:6"/>I, YHWH, [am] your God who has brought you out from the land of Egypt, from a house of servants. <verse eid="DEU 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 5:7"/>You have no other gods in My presence. <verse eid="DEU 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 5:8"/>You do not make a carved image for yourself, any likeness which [is] in the heavens above, or which [is] in the earth beneath, or which [is] in the waters under the earth. <verse eid="DEU 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 5:9"/>You do not bow yourself to them, nor serve them: for I, your God YHWH, [am] a zealous God, charging iniquity of fathers on sons, and on a third and on a fourth [generation] of those hating Me, <verse eid="DEU 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 5:10"/>and doing kindness to thousands, of those loving Me and of those keeping My commands. <verse eid="DEU 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 5:11"/>You do not take up the Name of your God YHWH for a vain thing, for YHWH does not acquit him who takes up His Name for a vain thing. <verse eid="DEU 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 5:12"/>Observe the Sabbath day to sanctify it, as your God YHWH has commanded you; <verse eid="DEU 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 5:13"/>six days you labor and have done all your work, <verse eid="DEU 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 5:14"/>and the seventh day [is] a Sabbath to your God YHWH; you do not do any work, you, and your son, and your daughter, and your manservant, and your handmaid, and your ox, and your donkey, and all your livestock, and your sojourner who [is] within your gates, so that your manservant and your handmaid rest like yourself. <verse eid="DEU 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 5:15"/>And you have remembered that you have been a servant in the land of Egypt, and your God YHWH brings you out from there by a strong hand and by an outstretched arm; therefore your God YHWH has commanded you to keep the Sabbath day. <verse eid="DEU 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 5:16"/>Honor your father and your mother, as your God YHWH has commanded you, so that your days are prolonged, and so that it is well with you on the ground which your God YHWH is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 5:17"/>You do not murder. <verse eid="DEU 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 5:18"/>You do not commit adultery. <verse eid="DEU 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 5:19"/>You do not steal. <verse eid="DEU 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 5:20"/>You do not answer [with] a false testimony against your neighbor. <verse eid="DEU 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 5:21"/>You do not desire your neighbor’s wife, nor do you covet your neighbor’s house, his field, and his manservant, and his handmaid, his ox, and his donkey, and anything which [is] your neighbor’s. <verse eid="DEU 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 5:22"/>YHWH has spoken these words to all your assembly in the mountain, out of the midst of the fire, [and] of the cloud, and of the thick darkness, [with] a great voice; and He has not added; and He writes them on two tablets of stone and gives them to me. <verse eid="DEU 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 5:23"/>And it comes to pass, as you hear the voice out of the midst of the darkness and of the mountain burning with fire, that you come near to me, all [the] heads of your tribes and your elderly, <verse eid="DEU 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 5:24"/>and say, Behold, our God YHWH has showed us His glory and His greatness; and we have heard His voice out of the midst of the fire; this day we have seen that God speaks with man—and he has lived. <verse eid="DEU 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 5:25"/>And now, why do we die? For this great fire consumes us if we add to hear the voice of our God YHWH anymore—then we have died. <verse eid="DEU 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 5:26"/>For who of all flesh [is] he who has heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire like us, and lives? <verse eid="DEU 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 5:27"/>Draw near and hear all that which our God YHWH says, and you, you speak to us all that which our God YHWH speaks to you, and we have listened and done it. <verse eid="DEU 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 5:28"/>And YHWH hears the voice of your words in your speaking to me, and YHWH says to me, I have heard the voice of the words of this people which they have spoken to you; they have done well [in] all that they have spoken. <verse eid="DEU 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 5:29"/>O that their heart had been thus to them, to fear Me and to keep My commands [for] all the days, that it may be well with them and with their sons for all time! <verse eid="DEU 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 5:30"/>Go, say to them, Return for yourselves, to your tents; <verse eid="DEU 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 5:31"/>and you, stand here with Me, and let Me speak to you all the command, and the statutes, and the judgments which you teach them, and they have done [them] in the land which I am giving to them to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 5:32"/>And you have observed to do as your God YHWH has commanded you, you do not turn aside [to] the right or left; <verse eid="DEU 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 5:33"/>in all the way which your God YHWH has commanded you—walk, so that you live, and [it is] well with you, and you have prolonged days in the land which you possess.”<verse eid="DEU 5:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="DEU 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 6:1"/>“And this [is] the command, the statutes and the judgments which your God YHWH has commanded to teach you to do in the land which you are passing over there to possess it, <verse eid="DEU 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 6:2"/>so that you fear your God YHWH, to keep all His statutes and His commands which I am commanding you, you, and your son, and your son’s son, all [the] days of your life, and so that your days are prolonged. <verse eid="DEU 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 6:3"/>And you have heard, O Israel, and observed to do [them], that it may be well with you, and that you may multiply exceedingly, as YHWH, God of your fathers, has spoken to you, [in] the land flowing with milk and honey. <verse eid="DEU 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 6:4"/>Hear, O Israel: Our God YHWH—YHWH [is] one! <verse eid="DEU 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 6:5"/>And you have loved your God YHWH with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your might. <verse eid="DEU 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 6:6"/>And these words which I am commanding you today have been on your heart, <verse eid="DEU 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 6:7"/>and you have repeated them to your sons, and spoken of them in your sitting in your house, and in your walking in the way, and in your lying down, and in your rising up, <verse eid="DEU 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 6:8"/>and have bound them for a sign on your hand, and they have been for frontlets between your eyes, <verse eid="DEU 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 6:9"/>and you have written them on doorposts of your house and on your gates. <verse eid="DEU 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 6:10"/>And it has been, when your God YHWH brings you into the land which He has sworn to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to you great and good cities which you have not built, <verse eid="DEU 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 6:11"/>and houses full of all good things which you have not filled, and wells dug which you have not dug, vineyards and olive-yards which you have not planted, that you have eaten and been satisfied. <verse eid="DEU 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 6:12"/>Take heed to yourself lest you forget YHWH who has brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of servants. <verse eid="DEU 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 6:13"/>You fear your God YHWH, and you serve Him, and you swear by His Name. <verse eid="DEU 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 6:14"/>You do not go after other gods, of the gods of the peoples who [are] around you, <verse eid="DEU 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 6:15"/>for your God YHWH [is] a zealous God in your midst—lest the anger of your God YHWH burns against you, and He has destroyed you from off the face of the ground. <verse eid="DEU 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 6:16"/>You do not try your God YHWH as you tried [Him] in Massah. <verse eid="DEU 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 6:17"/>You diligently keep the commands of your God YHWH, and His testimonies and His statutes which He has commanded you, <verse eid="DEU 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 6:18"/>and you have done that which is right and good in the eyes of YHWH, so that it is well with you, and you have gone in and possessed the good land which YHWH has sworn to your fathers, <verse eid="DEU 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 6:19"/>to drive away all your enemies from your presence, as YHWH has spoken. <verse eid="DEU 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 6:20"/>When your son asks you hereafter, saying, What [are] the testimonies, and the statutes, and the judgments which our God YHWH has commanded you? <verse eid="DEU 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 6:21"/>Then you have said to your son, We have been servants of Pharaoh in Egypt, and YHWH brings us out of Egypt by a high hand; <verse eid="DEU 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 6:22"/>and YHWH gives signs and wonders, great and severe, on Egypt, on Pharaoh, and on all his house, before our eyes; <verse eid="DEU 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 6:23"/>and He has brought us out from there, in order to bring us in, to give to us the land which He had sworn to our fathers. <verse eid="DEU 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 6:24"/>And YHWH commands us to do all these statutes, to fear our God YHWH, for good to ourselves [for] all the days, to keep us alive, as [at] this day; <verse eid="DEU 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 6:25"/>and it is righteousness for us when we observe to do all this command before our God YHWH, as He has commanded us.”<verse eid="DEU 6:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="DEU 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 7:1"/>“When your God YHWH brings you into the land to where you are going in to possess it, and He has cast out many nations from your presence, the Hittite, and the Girgashite, and the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite, seven nations more numerous and mighty than you, <verse eid="DEU 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 7:2"/>and your God YHWH has given them before you, then you have struck them—you utterly devote them—you do not make a covenant with them, nor do you favor them. <verse eid="DEU 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 7:3"/>And you do not join in marriage with them; you do not give your daughter to his son, and you do not take his daughter to your son, <verse eid="DEU 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 7:4"/>for he turns aside your son from after Me, and they have served other gods; and the anger of YHWH has burned against you and has destroyed you quickly. <verse eid="DEU 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 7:5"/>But thus you do to them: you break down their altars, and you shatter their standing pillars, and you cut down their Asherim, and you burn their carved images with fire. <verse eid="DEU 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 7:6"/>For you [are] a holy people to your God YHWH; your God YHWH has fixed on you, to be to Him for a peculiar people, out of all the peoples who [are] on the face of the ground. <verse eid="DEU 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 7:7"/>YHWH has delighted in you and fixes on you, not because of your being more numerous than any of the peoples, for you [are] the least of all the peoples, <verse eid="DEU 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 7:8"/>but because of YHWH’s loving you, and because of His keeping the oath which He has sworn to your fathers; YHWH has brought you out by a strong hand, and ransoms you from a house of servants, from the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 7:9"/>And you have known that He, your God YHWH, [is] God, the faithful God keeping the covenant and the kindness with those loving Him and with those keeping His commands, for one thousand generations, <verse eid="DEU 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 7:10"/>and repaying to those hating Him to their face, to destroy them; He does not delay to him who is hating Him, He repays [it] to him to his face. <verse eid="DEU 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 7:11"/>And you have kept the command, and the statutes, and the judgments, which I am commanding you today to do them. <verse eid="DEU 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 7:12"/>And it has been, because you hear these judgments, and have kept and done them, that your God YHWH has kept the covenant and the kindness with you which He has sworn to your fathers, <verse eid="DEU 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 7:13"/>and has loved you, and blessed you, and multiplied you, and has blessed the fruit of your womb, and the fruit of your ground, your grain, and your new wine, and your oil, the increase of your oxen, and the wealth of your flock, on the ground which He has sworn to your fathers to give to you. <verse eid="DEU 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 7:14"/>Blessed are you above all the peoples; there is not a barren man or a barren woman in you—nor among your livestock; <verse eid="DEU 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 7:15"/>and YHWH has turned aside every sickness from you, and none of the evil diseases of Egypt (which you have known) does He put on you, and He has put them on all hating you. <verse eid="DEU 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 7:16"/>And you have consumed all the peoples whom your God YHWH is giving to you; your eye has no pity on them, and you do not serve their gods, for it [is] a snare to you. <verse eid="DEU 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 7:17"/>When you say in your heart, These nations [are] more numerous than I, how am I able to dispossess them? <verse eid="DEU 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 7:18"/>You are not afraid of them; you surely remember that which your God YHWH has done to Pharaoh and to all of Egypt, <verse eid="DEU 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 7:19"/>the great trials which your eyes have seen, and the signs, and the wonders, and the strong hand, and the outstretched arm, with which your God YHWH has brought you out; so does your God YHWH do to all the peoples of whose presence you are afraid. <verse eid="DEU 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 7:20"/>And your God YHWH also sends the locust among them, until the destruction of those who are left, even those who are hidden from your presence; <verse eid="DEU 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 7:21"/>you are not terrified by their presence, for your God YHWH [is] in your midst, a God great and fearful. <verse eid="DEU 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 7:22"/>And your God YHWH has cast out these nations from your presence little [by] little (you are not able to consume them quickly, lest the beast of the field multiplies against you), <verse eid="DEU 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 7:23"/>and your God YHWH has given them before you, and confused them [with] a great destruction until their being destroyed; <verse eid="DEU 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 7:24"/>and He has given their kings into your hand, and you have destroyed their name from under the heavens; no man stations himself in your presence until you have destroyed them. <verse eid="DEU 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 7:25"/>You burn the carved images of their gods with fire; you do not desire the silver and gold on them, nor have you taken [it] for yourself, lest you are snared by it, for it [is] an abomination [to] your God YHWH; <verse eid="DEU 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 7:26"/>and you do not bring in an abomination to your house, or you have been devoted like it—you utterly detest it and you utterly abhor it; for it [is] devoted.”<verse eid="DEU 7:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="DEU 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 8:1"/>“All the command which I am commanding you today you observe to do, so that you live, and have multiplied, and gone in, and possessed the land which YHWH has sworn to your fathers; <verse eid="DEU 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 8:2"/>and you have remembered all the way which your God YHWH has caused you to go these forty years in the wilderness, in order to humble you to try you, to know that which [is] in your heart, whether you keep His commands or not. <verse eid="DEU 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 8:3"/>And He humbles you, and causes you to hunger, and causes you to eat the manna (which you have not known, even your fathers have not known), in order to cause you to know that man does not live by bread alone, but man lives by everything proceeding [from] the mouth of YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 8:4"/>Your raiment has not worn out from off you, and your foot has not swelled these forty years, <verse eid="DEU 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 8:5"/>and you have known with your heart that as a man disciplines his son, your God YHWH is disciplining you, <verse eid="DEU 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 8:6"/>and you have kept the commands of your God YHWH, to walk in His ways and to fear Him. <verse eid="DEU 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 8:7"/>For your God YHWH is bringing you into a good land, a land of brooks of waters, of fountains, and of depths coming out in valley and in mountain; <verse eid="DEU 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 8:8"/>a land of wheat, and barley, and vine, and fig, and pomegranate; a land of oil olive and honey; <verse eid="DEU 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 8:9"/>a land in which you eat bread without scarcity—you do not lack anything in it; a land whose stones [are] iron, and you dig bronze out of its mountains. <verse eid="DEU 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 8:10"/>And you have eaten and been satisfied, and have blessed your God YHWH on the good land which he has given to you. <verse eid="DEU 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 8:11"/>Take heed to yourself lest you forget your God YHWH so as not to keep His commands, and His judgments, and His statutes which I am commanding you today; <verse eid="DEU 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 8:12"/>lest you eat and have been satisfied, and build good houses and have inhabited [them], <verse eid="DEU 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 8:13"/>and your herd and your flock are multiplied, and silver and gold are multiplied to you, and all that is yours is multiplied, <verse eid="DEU 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 8:14"/>and your heart has been high, and you have forgotten your God YHWH who is bringing you out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of servants; <verse eid="DEU 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 8:15"/>who is causing you to go in the great and the terrible wilderness [with] burning serpent, and scorpion, and thirst—where there is no water; who is bringing out waters to you from the flinty rock; <verse eid="DEU 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 8:16"/>who is causing you to eat manna in the wilderness, which your fathers have not known, in order to humble you, and in order to try you, to do you good in your latter end; <verse eid="DEU 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 8:17"/>and you have said in your heart, My power and the might of my hand have made this wealth for me. <verse eid="DEU 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 8:18"/>And you have remembered your God YHWH, for it [is] He who is giving power to you to make wealth, in order to establish His covenant which He has sworn to your fathers, as [at] this day. <verse eid="DEU 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 8:19"/>And it has been, if you really forget your God YHWH, and have gone after other gods, and served them, and bowed yourself to them, I have testified against you today that you utterly perish. <verse eid="DEU 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 8:20"/>As the nations whom YHWH is destroying from your presence, so you perish, because you do not listen to the voice of your God YHWH.”<verse eid="DEU 8:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="DEU 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 9:1"/>“Hear, O Israel: You are passing over the Jordan today to go in to possess nations greater and mightier than yourself, cities great and fortified up to the heavens, <verse eid="DEU 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 9:2"/>a people great and tall, sons of Anakim, whom you have known, and [of whom] you have heard: Who stations himself before sons of Anak? <verse eid="DEU 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 9:3"/>And you have known today that your God YHWH [is] He who is passing over before you [as] a consuming fire; He destroys them, and He humbles them before you, and you have dispossessed them, and destroyed them quickly, as YHWH has spoken to you. <verse eid="DEU 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 9:4"/>You do not speak in your heart (in your God YHWH’s driving them away from before you), saying, In my righteousness YHWH has brought me in to possess this land; but in YHWH dispossessing these nations from your presence, [it is because of] their being wicked. <verse eid="DEU 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 9:5"/>[It is] not in your righteousness and in the uprightness of your heart [that] you are going in to possess their land, but in YHWH dispossessing these nations from your presence, [it is because of] their being wicked, and in order to establish the word which YHWH has sworn to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob; <verse eid="DEU 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 9:6"/>and you have known that [it is] not in your righteousness [that] your God YHWH is giving this good land to you to possess it, for you [are] a people stiff of neck. <verse eid="DEU 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 9:7"/>Remember [and] do not forget that [with] which you have made your God YHWH angry in the wilderness; from the day that you have come out of the land of Egypt until your coming to this place, you have been rebellious against YHWH; <verse eid="DEU 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 9:8"/>even in Horeb you have made YHWH angry, and YHWH shows Himself angry against you—to destroy you. <verse eid="DEU 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 9:9"/>In my going up into the mountain to receive the tablets of stone (tablets of the covenant which YHWH has made with you), then I abide on the mountain forty days and forty nights; I have not eaten bread and I have not drunk water; <verse eid="DEU 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 9:10"/>and YHWH gives to me the two tablets of stone written with the finger of God, and on them [is] according to all the words which YHWH has spoken with you on the mountain, out of the midst of the fire, in the day of the assembly. <verse eid="DEU 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 9:11"/>And it comes to pass, at the end of forty days and forty nights, YHWH has given the two tablets of stone to me—tablets of the covenant. <verse eid="DEU 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 9:12"/>Then YHWH says to me, Rise, go down, hurry from here, for your people whom you have brought out of Egypt have done corruptly; they have quickly turned aside from the way which I have commanded them—they have made a molten thing for themselves! <verse eid="DEU 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 9:13"/>And YHWH speaks to me, saying, I have seen this people, and behold, it [is] a people stiff of neck. <verse eid="DEU 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 9:14"/>Desist from Me, and I destroy them, and blot out their name from under the heavens, and I make you become a nation more mighty and numerous than it. <verse eid="DEU 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 9:15"/>And I turn and come down from the mountain, and the mountain is burning with fire, and the two tablets of the covenant [are] on my two hands, <verse eid="DEU 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 9:16"/>and I see, and behold, you have sinned against your God YHWH; you have made a molten calf for yourselves; you have quickly turned aside from the way which YHWH has commanded you. <verse eid="DEU 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 9:17"/>And I lay hold on the two tablets, and cast them out of my two hands, and break them before your eyes, <verse eid="DEU 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 9:18"/>and I throw myself before YHWH, as at first, [for] forty days and forty nights; I have not eaten bread and I have not drunk water, because of all your sins which you have sinned by doing evil in the eyes of YHWH, to make Him angry. <verse eid="DEU 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 9:19"/>For I have been afraid because of the anger and the fury with which YHWH has been angry against you, to destroy you; and YHWH also listens to me at this time. <verse eid="DEU 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 9:20"/>And YHWH has showed Himself very angry with Aaron, to destroy him, and I also pray for Aaron at that time. <verse eid="DEU 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 9:21"/>And I have taken your sin, the calf which you have made, and I burn it with fire, and beat it, grinding well until it [is] small as dust, and I cast its dust into the brook which is going down out of the mountain. <verse eid="DEU 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 9:22"/>And in Taberah, and in Massah, and in Kibroth-Hattaavah, you have been making YHWH angry; <verse eid="DEU 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 9:23"/>also in YHWH’s sending you from Kadesh-Barnea, saying, Go up and possess the land which I have given to you; then you provoke the mouth of your God YHWH, and have not given credence to Him, nor listened to His voice. <verse eid="DEU 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 9:24"/>You have been rebellious against YHWH from the day of my knowing you. <verse eid="DEU 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 9:25"/>And I throw myself before YHWH—the forty days and the forty nights when I had thrown myself—because YHWH has commanded to destroy you; <verse eid="DEU 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 9:26"/>and I pray to YHWH, and say, Lord YHWH, do not destroy Your people and Your inheritance whom You have ransomed in Your greatness, whom You have brought out of Egypt with a strong hand; <verse eid="DEU 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 9:27"/>be mindful of Your servants, of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Jacob; do not turn to the stiffness of this people, and to its wickedness, and to its sin, <verse eid="DEU 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 9:28"/>lest the land from which You have brought us out says, Because of YHWH’s want of ability to bring them into the land of which He has spoken to them, and because of His hating them, He brought them out to put them to death in the wilderness. <verse eid="DEU 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 9:29"/>And they [are] Your people and Your inheritance, whom You have brought out by Your great power and by Your outstretched arm!”<verse eid="DEU 9:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="DEU 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 10:1"/>“At that time YHWH has said to me, Hew two tablets of stone for yourself like the first, and come up to Me into the mountain, and you have made an ark of wood for yourself, <verse eid="DEU 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 10:2"/>and I write on the tablets the words which were on the first tablets, which you have broken, and you have placed them in the Ark. <verse eid="DEU 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 10:3"/>And I make an ark of shittim wood, and hew two tablets of stone like the first, and go up to the mountain with the two tablets in my hand. <verse eid="DEU 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 10:4"/>And He writes on the tablets according to the first writing, the Ten Commandments, which YHWH has spoken to you in the mountain, out of the midst of the fire, in the day of the assembly, and YHWH gives them to me, <verse eid="DEU 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 10:5"/>and I turn and come down from the mountain, and put the tablets in the Ark which I had made, and they are there, as YHWH commanded me. <verse eid="DEU 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 10:6"/>And the sons of Israel have journeyed from Beeroth of the sons of Jaakan to Mosera; Aaron died there, and he is buried there, and his son Eleazar acts as priest in his stead. <verse eid="DEU 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 10:7"/>From there they journeyed to Gudgodah, and from Gudgodah to Jotbathah, a land of brooks of water. <verse eid="DEU 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 10:8"/>At that time YHWH has separated the tribe of Levi to carry the Ark of the Covenant of YHWH, to stand before YHWH, to serve Him, and to bless in His Name to this day; <verse eid="DEU 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 10:9"/>therefore there has not been a portion and inheritance for Levi with his brothers; YHWH Himself [is] his inheritance, as your God YHWH has spoken to him. <verse eid="DEU 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 10:10"/>And I have stood in the mountain, as the former days, [for] forty days and forty nights, and YHWH also listens to me at that time; YHWH has not willed to destroy you. <verse eid="DEU 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 10:11"/>And YHWH says to me, Rise, go to journey before the people, and they go in and possess the land which I have sworn to their fathers to give to them. <verse eid="DEU 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 10:12"/>And now, O Israel, what is your God YHWH asking from you, except to fear your God YHWH, to walk in all His ways, and to love Him, and to serve your God YHWH with all your heart and with all your soul, <verse eid="DEU 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 10:13"/>to keep the commands of YHWH, and His statutes which I am commanding you today, for good for you? <verse eid="DEU 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 10:14"/>Behold, the heavens, even the heavens of the heavens, [belong] to your God YHWH, [as does] the earth and all that [is] in it. <verse eid="DEU 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 10:15"/>Only, YHWH has delighted in your fathers, to love them, and He fixes on their seed after them—on you, out of all the peoples, as [at] this day. <verse eid="DEU 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 10:16"/>And you have circumcised the foreskin of your heart, and you do not harden your neck anymore. <verse eid="DEU 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 10:17"/>For He, your God YHWH, [is] God of the gods and Lord of the lords—the great, the mighty, and the fearful God, who does not accept by appearances, nor takes a bribe; <verse eid="DEU 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 10:18"/>He is doing the judgment of fatherless and widow, and loving the sojourner, to give bread and raiment to him. <verse eid="DEU 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 10:19"/>And you have loved the sojourner, for you were sojourners in the land of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 10:20"/>You fear your God YHWH, you serve Him, and you cleave to Him, and you swear by His Name. <verse eid="DEU 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 10:21"/>He [is] your praise, and He [is] your God, who has done these great and fearful [things] with you which your eyes have seen. <verse eid="DEU 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 10:22"/>Your fathers went down to Egypt with seventy persons, and now your God YHWH has made you as [the] stars of the heavens for multitude.”<verse eid="DEU 10:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="DEU 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 11:1"/>“And you have loved your God YHWH, and kept His charge, and His statutes, and His judgments, and His commands, [for] all the days; <verse eid="DEU 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 11:2"/>and you have known today—for it is not your sons who have not known and who have not seen the discipline of your God YHWH, His greatness, His strong hand, and His outstretched arm; <verse eid="DEU 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 11:3"/>and His signs and His doings which He has done in the midst of Egypt, to Pharaoh king of Egypt and to all his land; <verse eid="DEU 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 11:4"/>and that which He has done to the force of Egypt, to its horses, and to its chariot, when He has caused the waters of the Red Sea to flow against their faces in their pursuing after them, and YHWH destroys them, to this day; <verse eid="DEU 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 11:5"/>and that which He has done to you in the wilderness until your coming to this place; <verse eid="DEU 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 11:6"/>and that which He has done to Dathan and to Abiram, sons of Eliab, sons of Reuben, when the earth has opened her mouth and swallows them, and their houses, and their tents, and all that lives which is at their feet, in the midst of all Israel— <verse eid="DEU 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 11:7"/>but [it is] your eyes which are seeing all the great work of YHWH which He has done. <verse eid="DEU 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 11:8"/>And you have kept all the command which I am commanding you today, so that you are strong, and have gone in, and possessed the land to where you are passing over to possess it, <verse eid="DEU 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 11:9"/>and so that you prolong days on the ground which YHWH has sworn to your fathers to give to them and to their seed—a land flowing with milk and honey. <verse eid="DEU 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 11:10"/>For the land to where you are going in to possess it is not as the land of Egypt from where you have come out, where you sow your seed and have watered with your foot, as a garden of the green herb; <verse eid="DEU 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 11:11"/>but the land to where you are passing over to possess it [is] a land of hills and valleys—it drinks water of the rain of the heavens— <verse eid="DEU 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 11:12"/>a land which your God YHWH is searching; the eyes of your God YHWH [are] continually on it, from the beginning of the year even to the latter end of the year. <verse eid="DEU 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 11:13"/>And it has been, if you listen diligently to My commands which I am commanding you today, to love your God YHWH, and to serve Him with all your heart and with all your soul, <verse eid="DEU 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 11:14"/>then I have given the rain of your land in its season—autumn rain and spring rain—and you have gathered your grain, and your new wine, and your oil, <verse eid="DEU 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 11:15"/>and I have given herbs in your field for your livestock, and you have eaten and been satisfied. <verse eid="DEU 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 11:16"/>Take heed to yourselves lest your heart be enticed, and you have turned aside, and served other gods, and bowed yourselves to them, <verse eid="DEU 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 11:17"/>and the anger of YHWH has burned against you, and He has restrained the heavens and there is no rain, and the ground does not give her increase, and you have perished quickly from off the good land which YHWH is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 11:18"/>And you have placed these words of mine on your heart and on your soul, and have bound them for a sign on your hand, and they have been for frontlets between your eyes; <verse eid="DEU 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 11:19"/>and you have taught them to your sons by speaking of them in your sitting in your house, and in your going in the way, and in your lying down, and in your rising up, <verse eid="DEU 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 11:20"/>and have written them on the doorposts of your house and on your gates, <verse eid="DEU 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 11:21"/>so that your days are multiplied, and the days of your sons, on the ground which YHWH has sworn to your fathers to give to them, as the days of the heavens above the earth. <verse eid="DEU 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 11:22"/>For if you diligently keep all this command which I am commanding you to do—to love your God YHWH, to walk in all His ways, and to cleave to Him— <verse eid="DEU 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 11:23"/>then YHWH has dispossessed all these nations from before you, and you have possessed nations greater and mightier than you. <verse eid="DEU 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 11:24"/>Every place on which the sole of your foot treads is yours: from the wilderness and Lebanon, from the river, the Euphrates River, even to the Western Sea, is your border. <verse eid="DEU 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 11:25"/>No man stations himself in your presence; your God YHWH puts your dread and your fear on the face of all the land on which you tread, as He has spoken to you. <verse eid="DEU 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 11:26"/>See, today I am setting before you a blessing and a reviling: <verse eid="DEU 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 11:27"/>the blessing when you listen to the commands of your God YHWH which I am commanding you today; <verse eid="DEU 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 11:28"/>and the reviling if you do not listen to the commands of your God YHWH, and have turned aside from the way which I am commanding you today, to go after other gods which you have not known. <verse eid="DEU 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 11:29"/>And it has been, when your God YHWH brings you into the land to where you are going in to possess it, that you have given the blessing on Mount Gerizim and the reviling on Mount Ebal; <verse eid="DEU 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 11:30"/>are they not beyond the Jordan, behind the way of the going in of the sun, in the land of the Canaanite who is dwelling in the plain opposite Gilgal, near the oaks of Moreh? <verse eid="DEU 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 11:31"/>For you are passing over the Jordan to go in to possess the land which your God YHWH is giving to you; and you have possessed it, and dwelt in it, <verse eid="DEU 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 11:32"/>and observed to do all the statutes and the judgments which I am setting before you today.”<verse eid="DEU 11:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="DEU 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 12:1"/>“These [are] the statutes and the judgments which you observe to do in the land which YHWH, God of your fathers, has given to you to possess it, all the days that you are living on the ground. <verse eid="DEU 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 12:2"/>You utterly destroy all the places where the nations which you are dispossessing served their gods, on the high mountains, and on the heights, and under every green tree; <verse eid="DEU 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 12:3"/>and you have broken down their altars, and shattered their standing pillars, and you burn their Asherim with fire, and you cut down carved images of their gods, and have destroyed their name out of that place. <verse eid="DEU 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 12:4"/>You do not do so to your God YHWH; <verse eid="DEU 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 12:5"/>rather—that you seek after the place which your God YHWH chooses out of all your tribes to put His Name there, for His Dwelling Place, and you have entered there, <verse eid="DEU 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 12:6"/>and have brought in there your burnt-offerings, and your sacrifices, and your tithes, and the raised-offering of your hand, and your vows, and your free-will offerings, and the firstlings of your herd and of your flock; <verse eid="DEU 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 12:7"/>and you have eaten there before your God YHWH, and have rejoiced in every putting forth of your hand, you and your households, with which your God YHWH has blessed you. <verse eid="DEU 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 12:8"/>You do not do according to all that we are doing here today—each [doing] anything that is right in his own eyes— <verse eid="DEU 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 12:9"/>for until now you have not come to the rest and to the inheritance which your God YHWH is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 12:10"/>When you have passed over the Jordan, and have dwelt in the land which your God YHWH is causing you to inherit, and He has given rest to you from all your surrounding enemies, and you have dwelt confidently, <verse eid="DEU 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 12:11"/>then it has been, the place on which your God YHWH fixes to cause His Name to dwell there, there you bring in all that which I am commanding you: your burnt-offerings, and your sacrifices, your tithes, and the raised-offering of your hand, and all the choice of your vows which you vow to YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 12:12"/>And you have rejoiced before your God YHWH, you, and your sons, and your daughters, and your menservants, and your handmaids, and the Levite who [is] within your gates, for he has no part and inheritance with you. <verse eid="DEU 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 12:13"/>Take heed to yourself lest you cause your burnt-offerings to ascend in any place which you see; <verse eid="DEU 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 12:14"/>rather—that in the place which YHWH chooses in one of your tribes, there you cause your burnt-offerings to ascend, and there you do all that which I am commanding you. <verse eid="DEU 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 12:15"/>Nevertheless, you slaughter anything of the desire of your soul, and have eaten [its] flesh according to the blessing of your God YHWH which He has given to you in all your gates; the unclean and the clean eat it, as [if] the roe and as [if] the deer. <verse eid="DEU 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 12:16"/>Only, you do not eat the blood—you pour it on the earth as water; <verse eid="DEU 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 12:17"/>you are not able to eat within your gates the tithe of your grain, and of your new wine, and your oil, and the firstlings of your herd and of your flock, and any of your vows which you vow, and your free-will offerings, and a raised-offering of your hand; <verse eid="DEU 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 12:18"/>but you eat it before your God YHWH in the place which your God YHWH fixes on, you, and your son, and your daughter, and your manservant, and your handmaid, and the Levite who [is] within your gates, and you have rejoiced before your God YHWH in every putting forth of your hand; <verse eid="DEU 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 12:19"/>take heed to yourself lest you forsake the Levite [for] all your days on your ground. <verse eid="DEU 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 12:20"/>When your God YHWH enlarges your border, as He has spoken to you, and you have said, Let me eat flesh—for your soul desires to eat flesh—you eat flesh of all the desire of your soul. <verse eid="DEU 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 12:21"/>When the place is far from you [in] which your God YHWH chooses to put His Name there, then you have sacrificed from your herd and from your flock which YHWH has given to you, as I have commanded you, and have eaten within your gates, of all the desire of your soul; <verse eid="DEU 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 12:22"/>only, as the roe and the deer is eaten, so do you eat it; the unclean and the clean alike eat it. <verse eid="DEU 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 12:23"/>Only, be sure not to eat the blood, for the blood [is] the life, and you do not eat the life with the flesh; <verse eid="DEU 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 12:24"/>you do not eat it—you pour it on the earth as water; <verse eid="DEU 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 12:25"/>you do not eat it, in order that it may be well with you and with your sons after you when you do that which [is] right in the eyes of YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 12:26"/>Only, your holy things which you have, and your vows, you take up, and have gone to the place which YHWH chooses, <verse eid="DEU 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 12:27"/>and you have made your burnt-offerings—the flesh and the blood—on the altar of your God YHWH; and the blood of your sacrifices is poured out by the altar of your God YHWH, and you eat the flesh. <verse eid="DEU 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 12:28"/>Observe, and you have obeyed all these words which I am commanding you, in order that it may be well with you and with your sons after you for all time, when you do that which [is] good and right in the eyes of your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 12:29"/>When your God YHWH cuts off the nations—to where you are going in to possess them—from your presence, and you have possessed them, and have dwelt in their land— <verse eid="DEU 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 12:30"/>take heed to yourself lest you are ensnared after them, after their being destroyed out of your presence, and lest you inquire about their gods, saying, How do these nations serve their gods, that I also do so? <verse eid="DEU 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 12:31"/>You do not do so to your God YHWH; for every abomination that YHWH has hated they have done for their gods, for they even burn their sons and their daughters with fire for their gods. <verse eid="DEU 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 12:32"/>The whole thing which I am commanding you, you observe to do it; you do not add to it, nor diminish from it.”<verse eid="DEU 12:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="DEU 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 13:1"/>“When a prophet or a dreamer of a dream arises in your midst, and he has given a sign or wonder to you, <verse eid="DEU 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 13:2"/>and the sign and the wonder has come to pass, which he has spoken of to you, saying, Let us go after other gods (which you have not known) and serve them, <verse eid="DEU 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 13:3"/>you do not listen to the words of that prophet or to that dreamer of the dream, for your God YHWH is trying you to know whether you are loving your God YHWH with all your heart and with all your soul; <verse eid="DEU 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 13:4"/>you walk after your God YHWH, and you fear Him, and you keep His commands, and you listen to His voice, and you serve Him, and you cleave to Him. <verse eid="DEU 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 13:5"/>And that prophet or that dreamer of the dream is put to death, for he has spoken apostasy against your God YHWH (who is bringing you out of the land of Egypt, and has ransomed you out of a house of servants), to drive you out of the way in which your God YHWH has commanded you to walk, and you have put away evil from your midst. <verse eid="DEU 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 13:6"/>When your brother, son of your mother, or your son, or your daughter, or the wife of your bosom, or your friend who [is] as your own soul, moves you in secret, saying, Let us go and serve other gods (which you have not known, you and your fathers, <verse eid="DEU 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 13:7"/>of the gods of the peoples who [are] around you, who are near to you, or who are far off from you, from the end of the earth even to the [other] end of the earth), <verse eid="DEU 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 13:8"/>you do not consent to him, nor listen to him, nor does your eye have pity on him, nor do you spare, nor do you cover him over. <verse eid="DEU 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 13:9"/>But you surely kill him; your hand is on him in the first place to put him to death, and the hand of all the people last; <verse eid="DEU 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 13:10"/>and you have stoned him with stones and he has died, for he has sought to drive you away from your God YHWH, who is bringing you out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of servants; <verse eid="DEU 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 13:11"/>and all Israel hears and fears, and does not add to do like this evil thing in your midst. <verse eid="DEU 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 13:12"/>When you hear [someone] in one of your cities, which your God YHWH is giving to you to dwell there, saying, <verse eid="DEU 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 13:13"/>Men, sons of worthlessness, have gone out of your midst, and they force away the inhabitants of their city, saying, Let us go and serve other gods (which you have not known), <verse eid="DEU 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 13:14"/>then you have inquired, and searched, and asked diligently, and behold, [if] truth, the thing is established; this abomination has been done in your midst— <verse eid="DEU 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 13:15"/>you surely strike the inhabitants of that city by the mouth of the sword, devoting it and all that [is] in it, even its livestock, by the mouth of the sword. <verse eid="DEU 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 13:16"/>And you gather all its spoil into the midst of its broad place, and have completely burned the city and all its spoil with fire for your God YHWH, and it has been a continuous heap, it is not built anymore; <verse eid="DEU 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 13:17"/>and nothing from any of that [which is] devoted stays in your hand, so that YHWH turns back from the fierceness of His anger, and has given mercies to you, and loved you, and multiplied you, as He has sworn to your fathers, <verse eid="DEU 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 13:18"/>because you listen to the voice of your God YHWH, to keep all his commands which I am commanding you today, to do that which [is] right in the eyes of your God YHWH.”<verse eid="DEU 13:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="DEU 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 14:1"/>“You [are] sons of your God YHWH; you do not cut yourselves, nor make baldness between your eyes for the dead; <verse eid="DEU 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 14:2"/>for you [are] a holy people to your God YHWH, and YHWH has fixed on you to be to Him for a people, a peculiar treasure, out of all the peoples who [are] on the face of the ground. <verse eid="DEU 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 14:3"/>You do not eat any abomination; <verse eid="DEU 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 14:4"/>this [is] the beast which you eat: ox, lamb of the sheep, or kid of the goats, <verse eid="DEU 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 14:5"/>deer, and roe, and fallow deer, and wild goat, and ibex, and antelope, and zemer; <verse eid="DEU 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 14:6"/>and every beast dividing the hoof, and cleaving the cleft into two hooves, bringing up the cud, among the beasts—you eat it. <verse eid="DEU 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 14:7"/>Only, this you do not eat, of those bringing up the cud, and of those dividing the cloven hoof: the camel, and the hare, and the hyrax, for they are bringing up the cud, but the hoof has not divided—they [are] unclean to you; <verse eid="DEU 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 14:8"/>and the sow, for it is dividing the hoof, and not [bringing] up the cud—it [is] unclean to you; you do not eat of their flesh, and you do not come against their carcass. <verse eid="DEU 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 14:9"/>This you eat of all which [are] in the waters: anything that has fins and scales you eat; <verse eid="DEU 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 14:10"/>and anything which does not have fins and scales you do not eat—it [is] unclean to you. <verse eid="DEU 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 14:11"/>Any clean bird you eat; <verse eid="DEU 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 14:12"/>and these [are] they of which you do not eat: the eagle, and the bearded vulture, and the osprey, <verse eid="DEU 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 14:13"/>and the kite, and the falcon, and the vulture after its kind, <verse eid="DEU 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 14:14"/>and every raven after its kind; <verse eid="DEU 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 14:15"/>and the ostrich, and the nightjar <char style="bd">[[</char><char style="it">or</char> male ostrich<char style="bd">]]</char>, and the seagull, and the hawk after its kind; <verse eid="DEU 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 14:16"/>the little owl, and the great owl, and the waterhen, <verse eid="DEU 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 14:17"/>and the pelican, and the Egyptian vulture, and the cormorant, <verse eid="DEU 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 14:18"/>and the stork, and the heron after its kind, and the hoopoe, and the bat. <verse eid="DEU 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 14:19"/>And every teeming thing which is flying—it [is] unclean to you; they are not eaten; <verse eid="DEU 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 14:20"/>any clean bird you eat. <verse eid="DEU 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 14:21"/>You do not eat of any carcass; you give it to the sojourner who [is] within your gates, and he has eaten it; or sell [it] to a stranger; for you [are] a holy people to your God YHWH. You do not boil a kid in its mother’s milk. <verse eid="DEU 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 14:22"/>You certainly tithe all the increase of your seed which the field is bringing forth year by year; <verse eid="DEU 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 14:23"/>and you have eaten before your God YHWH, in the place where He chooses to cause His Name to dwell, the tithe of your grain, of your new wine, and of your oil, and the firstlings of your herd, and of your flock, so that you learn to fear your God YHWH [for] all the days. <verse eid="DEU 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 14:24"/>And when the way is too much for you, that you are not able to carry it—when the place is too far off from you which your God YHWH chooses to put His Name there, when your God YHWH blesses you— <verse eid="DEU 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 14:25"/>then you have given [it] in money, and have bound up the money in your hand, and gone to the place on which your God YHWH fixes; <verse eid="DEU 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 14:26"/>and you have given the money for anything which your soul desires, for oxen, and for sheep, and for wine, and for strong drink, and for anything which your soul asks for, and you have eaten before your God YHWH there, and you have rejoiced, you and your house. <verse eid="DEU 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 14:27"/>As for the Levite who [is] within your gates, you do not forsake him, for he has no portion and inheritance with you. <verse eid="DEU 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 14:28"/>At the end of three years you bring out all the tithe of your increase in that year, and have placed [it] within your gates; <verse eid="DEU 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 14:29"/>and the Levite has come in—for he has no part and inheritance with you—and the sojourner, and the fatherless, and the widow, who [are] within your gates, and they have eaten, and been satisfied, so that your God YHWH blesses you in all the work of your hand which you do.”<verse eid="DEU 14:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="DEU 15"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 15:1"/>“At the end of seven years you make a release, <verse eid="DEU 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 15:2"/>and this [is] the matter of the release: every owner of a loan [is] to release his hand which he lifts up against his neighbor, he does not exact of his neighbor and of his brother, but has proclaimed a release to YHWH; <verse eid="DEU 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 15:3"/>of the stranger you may exact, but that which is yours with your brother your hand releases, <verse eid="DEU 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 15:4"/>except there is an end [when] no poor [are] with you; for YHWH greatly blesses you in the land which your God YHWH is giving to you [for] an inheritance to possess it, <verse eid="DEU 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 15:5"/>only if you listen diligently to the voice of your God YHWH, to observe to do all this command which I am commanding you today. <verse eid="DEU 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 15:6"/>For your God YHWH has blessed you as He has spoken to you; and you have lent [to] many nations, but you have not borrowed; and you have ruled over many nations, but they do not rule over you. <verse eid="DEU 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 15:7"/>When there is with you any poor of one of your brothers, in one of your cities, in your land which your God YHWH is giving to you, you do not harden your heart, nor shut your hand from your needy brother; <verse eid="DEU 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 15:8"/>for you certainly open your hand to him, and certainly lend him sufficiency for his lack which he lacks. <verse eid="DEU 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 15:9"/>Take heed to yourself lest there be a worthless word in your heart, saying, The seventh year [is] near, the year of release; and your eye is evil against your needy brother, and you do not give to him, and he has called to YHWH concerning you, and it has been sin in you; <verse eid="DEU 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 15:10"/>you certainly give to him, and your heart is not sad in your giving to him, for because of this thing your God YHWH blesses you in all your works and in every putting forth of your hand; <verse eid="DEU 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 15:11"/>because the poor does not cease out of the land, therefore I am commanding you, saying, You certainly open your hand to your brother, to your poor and to your needy one in your land. <verse eid="DEU 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 15:12"/>When your brother is sold to you, a Hebrew or a Hebrewess, and he has served you [for] six years, then in the seventh year you send him away free from you. <verse eid="DEU 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 15:13"/>And when you send him away free from you, you do not send him away empty; <verse eid="DEU 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 15:14"/>you certainly adorn him from your flock, and from your threshing-floor, and from your wine-vat; you give to him [from] that which your God YHWH has blessed you [with], <verse eid="DEU 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 15:15"/>and you have remembered that you have been a servant in the land of Egypt, and your God YHWH ransoms you; therefore I am commanding you this thing today. <verse eid="DEU 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 15:16"/>And it has been, when he says to you, I do not go out from you, because he has loved you and your house, because [it is] good for him with you, <verse eid="DEU 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 15:17"/>then you have taken the awl, and have put [it] through his ear, and through the door, and he has been a perpetual servant to you; and you also do so to your handmaid. <verse eid="DEU 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 15:18"/>It is not hard in your eyes in your sending him away free from you; for [his worth has been] double the hire of a hired worker [when] he has served you six years; and your God YHWH has blessed you in all that you do. <verse eid="DEU 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 15:19"/>Every firstling that is born in your herd and in your flock—you sanctify the male to your God YHWH; you do not work with the firstling of your ox, nor shear the firstling of your flock; <verse eid="DEU 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 15:20"/>you eat it before your God YHWH year by year, in the place which YHWH chooses, you and your house. <verse eid="DEU 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 15:21"/>And when there is a blemish in it, [or it is] lame or blind, [or has] any evil blemish, you do not sacrifice it to your God YHWH; <verse eid="DEU 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 15:22"/>you eat it within your gates, the unclean and the clean alike, as the roe and as the deer. <verse eid="DEU 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 15:23"/>Only, you do not eat its blood—you pour it on the earth as water.”<verse eid="DEU 15:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="DEU 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 16:1"/>“Observe the month of Abib, and you have made a Passover to your God YHWH, for in the month of Abib your God YHWH has brought you out of Egypt by night; <verse eid="DEU 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 16:2"/>and you have sacrificed a Passover to your God YHWH, of the flock and of the herd, in the place which YHWH chooses to cause His Name to dwell there. <verse eid="DEU 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 16:3"/>You do not eat any fermented thing with it; [for] seven days you eat unleavened things with it, bread of affliction (for you have come out of the land of Egypt in haste), so that you remember the day of your coming out of the land of Egypt all [the] days of your life; <verse eid="DEU 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 16:4"/>and leaven is not seen with you in all your border [for] seven days, and there does not remain [any] of the flesh which you sacrifice at evening on the first day until morning. <verse eid="DEU 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 16:5"/>You are not able to sacrifice the Passover within any of your gates which your God YHWH is giving to you, <verse eid="DEU 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 16:6"/>except at the place which your God YHWH chooses to cause His Name to dwell—there you sacrifice the Passover in the evening, at the going in of the sun, the season of your coming out of Egypt; <verse eid="DEU 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 16:7"/>and you have cooked and eaten in the place on which your God YHWH fixes, and have turned in the morning and gone to your tents; <verse eid="DEU 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 16:8"/>[for] six days you eat unleavened things, and on the seventh day [is] a restraint to your God YHWH; you do no work. <verse eid="DEU 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 16:9"/>You number seven weeks for yourself; you begin to number seven weeks from the beginning of the sickle among the standing grain, <verse eid="DEU 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 16:10"/>and you have observed the Celebration of Weeks to your God YHWH, a tribute of a free-will offering of your hand, which you give as your God YHWH blesses you. <verse eid="DEU 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 16:11"/>And you have rejoiced before your God YHWH, you, and your son, and your daughter, and your manservant, and your handmaid, and the Levite who [is] within your gates, and the sojourner, and the fatherless, and the widow, who [are] in your midst, in the place which your God YHWH chooses to cause His Name to dwell there, <verse eid="DEU 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 16:12"/>and you have remembered that you have been a servant in Egypt, and have observed and done these statutes. <verse eid="DEU 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 16:13"/>You observe the Celebration of Shelters for yourself [for] seven days, in your ingathering of your threshing-floor and of your wine-vat; <verse eid="DEU 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 16:14"/>and you have rejoiced in your celebration, you, and your son, and your daughter, and your manservant, and your handmaid, and the Levite, and the sojourner, and the fatherless, and the widow, who [are] within your gates. <verse eid="DEU 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 16:15"/>[For] seven days you celebrate before your God YHWH in the place which YHWH chooses, for your God YHWH blesses you in all your increase and in every work of your hands, and you have been only rejoicing. <verse eid="DEU 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 16:16"/>Three times in a year all of your males appear before your God YHWH in the place which He chooses: in the Celebration of Unleavened Things, and in the Celebration of Weeks, and in the Celebration of Shelters; and they do not appear before YHWH empty; <verse eid="DEU 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 16:17"/>each [gives] according to the gift of his hand, according to the blessing of your God YHWH, which He has given to you. <verse eid="DEU 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 16:18"/>You set for yourself judges and authorities within all your gates which your God YHWH is giving to you, for your tribes; and they have judged the people [with] a righteous judgment. <verse eid="DEU 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 16:19"/>You do not turn aside judgment; you do not discern faces, nor take a bribe, for the bribe blinds the eyes of the wise and perverts the words of the righteous. <verse eid="DEU 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 16:20"/>Righteousness—you pursue righteousness, so that you live and have possessed the land which your God YHWH is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 16:21"/>You do not plant an Asherah of any trees for yourself near the altar of your God YHWH, which you make for yourself, <verse eid="DEU 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 16:22"/>and you do not raise up any standing image for yourself which your God YHWH is hating.”<verse eid="DEU 16:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="DEU 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 17:1"/>“You do not sacrifice to your God YHWH ox or sheep in which there is a blemish—any bad thing; for it [is] an abomination [to] your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 17:2"/>When there is found in your midst, in one of your cities which your God YHWH is giving to you, a man or a woman who does evil in the eyes of your God YHWH by transgressing His covenant, <verse eid="DEU 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 17:3"/>and he goes and serves other gods, and bows himself to them, and to the sun, or to the moon, or to any of the host of the heavens, which I have not commanded, <verse eid="DEU 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 17:4"/>and it has been declared to you, and you have heard, and have searched diligently, and behold, [if] truth, the thing is established; this abomination has been done in Israel— <verse eid="DEU 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 17:5"/>then you have brought out that man or that woman who has done this evil thing, to your gates—the man or the woman—and you have stoned them with stones, and they have died. <verse eid="DEU 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 17:6"/>By the mouth of two witnesses or three witnesses is he who is being put to death put to death; he is not put to death by the mouth of one witness; <verse eid="DEU 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 17:7"/>the hand of the witnesses is on him in the first place to put him to death, and the hand of all the people last; and you have put away evil out of your midst. <verse eid="DEU 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 17:8"/>When anything is too hard for you for judgment, between blood and blood, between plea and plea, and between stroke and stroke—matters of strife within your gates—then you have risen and gone up to the place on which your God YHWH fixes, <verse eid="DEU 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 17:9"/>and have come to the priests, the Levites, and to the judge who is in those days, and have inquired, and they have declared the word of judgment to you, <verse eid="DEU 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 17:10"/>and you have done according to the tenor of the word which they declare to you ([they] of that place which YHWH chooses); and you have observed to do according to all that they direct you. <verse eid="DEU 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 17:11"/>According to the tenor of the law which they direct you, and according to the judgment which they say to you, you do; you do not turn aside from the word which they declare to you [to] the right or left. <verse eid="DEU 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 17:12"/>And the man who acts with presumption, so as not to listen to the priest (who is standing to serve your God YHWH there), or to the judge, even that man has died, and you have put away evil from Israel, <verse eid="DEU 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 17:13"/>and all the people hear and fear, and do not presume anymore. <verse eid="DEU 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 17:14"/>When you come into the land which your God YHWH is giving to you, and have possessed it, and dwelt in it, and you have said, Let me set a king over me like all the nations which [are] around me— <verse eid="DEU 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 17:15"/>you certainly set a king over you on whom YHWH fixes; you set a king over you from the midst of your brothers; you are not able to set a stranger over you, who is not your brother. <verse eid="DEU 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 17:16"/>Only, he does not multiply horses for himself, nor cause the people to return to Egypt, so as to multiply horses, seeing YHWH has said to you, You do not add to return in this way anymore. <verse eid="DEU 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 17:17"/>And he does not multiply wives for himself, and his heart does not turn aside, and he does not exceedingly multiply silver and gold for himself. <verse eid="DEU 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 17:18"/>And it has been, when he sits on the throne of his kingdom, that he has written a copy of this law for himself, on a scroll, from [that] before the priests, the Levites, <verse eid="DEU 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 17:19"/>and it has been with him, and he has read in it all [the] days of his life, so that he learns to fear his God YHWH, to keep all the words of this law and these statutes—to do them, <verse eid="DEU 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 17:20"/>so that his heart is not high above his brothers, and so as not to turn aside from the command [to] the right or left, so that he prolongs days over his kingdom, he and his sons in the midst of Israel.”<verse eid="DEU 17:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="DEU 18"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 18:1"/>“There is not for the priests, the Levites—all the tribe of Levi—a portion and inheritance with Israel; they eat fire-offerings of YHWH, even His inheritance, <verse eid="DEU 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 18:2"/>and he has no inheritance in the midst of his brothers; YHWH Himself [is] his inheritance, as He has spoken to him. <verse eid="DEU 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 18:3"/>And this is the priest’s right from the people, from those sacrificing a sacrifice, whether ox or sheep, he has even given to the priest the leg, and the two cheeks, and the stomach; <verse eid="DEU 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 18:4"/>you give to him the first of your grain, of your new wine, and of your oil, and the first of the fleece of your flock; <verse eid="DEU 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 18:5"/>for your God YHWH has fixed on him, out of all your tribes, to stand to serve in the Name of YHWH—him and his sons continually. <verse eid="DEU 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 18:6"/>And when the Levite comes from one of your cities, out of all Israel where he has sojourned, and has come with all the desire of his soul to the place which YHWH chooses, <verse eid="DEU 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 18:7"/>then he has ministered in the Name of his God YHWH like all his brothers, the Levites, who are standing there before YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 18:8"/>They eat portion like portion, apart from his sold things from the fathers. <verse eid="DEU 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 18:9"/>When you are coming into the land which your God YHWH is giving to you, you do not learn to do according to the abominations of those nations. <verse eid="DEU 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 18:10"/>There is not found in you one causing his son and his daughter to pass over into fire, a user of divinations, an observer of clouds, and an enchanter, and a sorcerer, <verse eid="DEU 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 18:11"/>and a charmer, and one inquiring from a familiar spirit, and a wizard, and one seeking to the dead. <verse eid="DEU 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 18:12"/>For everyone doing these [is] an abomination [to] YHWH, and because of these abominations your God YHWH is dispossessing them from your presence. <verse eid="DEU 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 18:13"/>You must be perfect with your God YHWH, <verse eid="DEU 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 18:14"/>for these nations whom you are possessing listen to observers of clouds and to diviners; but you—your God YHWH has not permitted you so. <verse eid="DEU 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 18:15"/>Your God YHWH raises up for you a Prophet like me out of your midst, out of your brothers—you must listen to Him, <verse eid="DEU 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 18:16"/>according to all that you asked from your God YHWH in Horeb, in the day of the assembly, saying, Do not let me add to hear the voice of my God YHWH, and do not let me see this great fire anymore, and I do not die; <verse eid="DEU 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 18:17"/>and YHWH says to me, They have done well [in] what they have spoken; <verse eid="DEU 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 18:18"/>I raise up for them a Prophet like you out of the midst of their brothers, and I have given My words in His mouth, and He has spoken to them all that which I command Him; <verse eid="DEU 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 18:19"/>and it has been [that] the man who does not listen to My words which He speaks in My Name, I require [it] of him. <verse eid="DEU 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 18:20"/>Only, the prophet who presumes to speak a word in My Name, which I have not commanded him to speak, and who speaks in the name of other gods, indeed, that prophet has died. <verse eid="DEU 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 18:21"/>And when you say in your heart, How do we know the word which YHWH has not spoken? <verse eid="DEU 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 18:22"/>That which the prophet speaks in the Name of YHWH, and the thing is not, and does not come—it [is] the word which YHWH has not spoken; the prophet has spoken it in presumption; you are not afraid of him.”<verse eid="DEU 18:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="DEU 19"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 19:1"/>“When your God YHWH cuts off the nations whose land your God YHWH is giving to you, and you have dispossessed them, and dwelt in their cities and in their houses, <verse eid="DEU 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 19:2"/>you separate three cities for yourself in the midst of your land which your God YHWH is giving to you to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 19:3"/>You prepare the way for yourself, and have divided into three parts the border of your land which your God YHWH causes you to inherit, and it has been for the fleeing there of every manslayer. <verse eid="DEU 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 19:4"/>And this [is] the matter of the manslayer who flees there, and has lived: he who strikes his neighbor unknowingly, and is not hating him before— <verse eid="DEU 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 19:5"/>even he who comes into a forest with his neighbor to hew wood, and his hand has driven with an axe to cut the tree, and the iron has slipped from the wood, and has met his neighbor, and he has died—he flees to one of these cities, and has lived, <verse eid="DEU 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 19:6"/>lest the redeemer of blood pursue after the manslayer when his heart is hot and has overtaken him, because the way is great, and has struck his life, and he has no sentence of death, for he is not hating him before; <verse eid="DEU 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 19:7"/>therefore I am commanding you, saying, You separate three cities for yourself. <verse eid="DEU 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 19:8"/>And if your God YHWH enlarges your border, as He has sworn to your fathers, and has given to you all the land which He has spoken to give to your fathers— <verse eid="DEU 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 19:9"/>when you keep all this command to do it, which I am commanding you today, to love your God YHWH and to walk in His ways [for] all the days—then you have added three more cities for yourself to these three; <verse eid="DEU 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 19:10"/>and [do this] lest innocent blood is shed in the midst of your land which your God YHWH is giving to you [for] an inheritance, and there has been blood on you. <verse eid="DEU 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 19:11"/>And when a man is hating his neighbor, and has lain in wait for him, and risen against him, and struck his life, and he has died, then he has fled to one of these cities, <verse eid="DEU 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 19:12"/>and [the] elderly of his city have sent and taken him from there, and given him into the hand of the redeemer of blood, and he has died; <verse eid="DEU 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 19:13"/>your eye has no pity on him, and you have put away the innocent blood from Israel, and it is well with you. <verse eid="DEU 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 19:14"/>You do not remove a border of your neighbor, which they of former times have made, in your inheritance, which you inherit in the land which your God YHWH is giving to you to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 19:15"/>One witness does not rise against a man for any iniquity and for any sin, in any sin which he sins; by the mouth of two witnesses or by the mouth of three witnesses is a thing established. <verse eid="DEU 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 19:16"/>When a violent witness rises against a man to testify against him apostasy, <verse eid="DEU 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 19:17"/>then both of the men who have the strife have stood before YHWH, before the priests and the judges who are in those days, <verse eid="DEU 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 19:18"/>and the judges have searched diligently, and behold, the witness [is] a false witness who has testified a falsehood against his brother, <verse eid="DEU 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 19:19"/>then you have done to him as he devised to do to his brother, and you have put away evil out of your midst, <verse eid="DEU 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 19:20"/>and those who are left hear and fear, and do not add to do according to this evil thing in your midst anymore. <verse eid="DEU 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 19:21"/>And your eye does not pity—life for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.”<verse eid="DEU 19:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="DEU 20"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 20:1"/>“When you go out to battle against your enemy, and have seen horse and chariot—a people more numerous than you—you are not afraid of them, for your God YHWH [is] with you, who is bringing you up out of the land of Egypt; <verse eid="DEU 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 20:2"/>and it has been, in your drawing near to the battle, that the priest has come near, and spoken to the people, <verse eid="DEU 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 20:3"/>and said to them, Hear, O Israel: You are drawing near today to battle against your enemies, do not let your hearts be tender, do not fear, nor make haste, nor be terrified at their presence, <verse eid="DEU 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 20:4"/>for your God YHWH [is] He who is going with you, to fight for you with your enemies—to save you. <verse eid="DEU 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 20:5"/>And the authorities have spoken to the people, saying, Who [is] the man that has built a new house and has not dedicated it? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in battle and another man dedicate it. <verse eid="DEU 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 20:6"/>And who [is] the man that has planted a vineyard and has not made it common? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in battle, and another man make it common. <verse eid="DEU 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 20:7"/>And who [is] the man that has betrothed a woman and has not taken her? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in battle, and another man take her. <verse eid="DEU 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 20:8"/>And the authorities have added to speak to the people and said, Who [is] the man that is afraid and tender of heart? Let him go and return to his house, and the heart of his brothers does not melt like his heart. <verse eid="DEU 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 20:9"/>And it has come to pass, as the authorities finish to speak to the people, that they have appointed princes of the hosts at the head of the people. <verse eid="DEU 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 20:10"/>When you draw near to a city to fight against it, then you have called to it for peace, <verse eid="DEU 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 20:11"/>and it has been, if it answers you [with] peace, and has opened to you, then it has come to pass, all the people who are found in it are for tributaries to you, and have served you. <verse eid="DEU 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 20:12"/>And if it does not make peace with you, and has made war with you, then you have laid siege against it, <verse eid="DEU 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 20:13"/>and your God YHWH has given it into your hand, and you have struck every male of it by the mouth of the sword. <verse eid="DEU 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 20:14"/>Only, the women, and the infants, and the livestock, and all that is in the city, all its spoil, you seize for yourself, and you have eaten the spoil of your enemies which your God YHWH has given to you. <verse eid="DEU 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 20:15"/>So you do to all the cities which are very far off from you, which are not of the cities of these nations. <verse eid="DEU 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 20:16"/>Only, of the cities of these peoples which your God YHWH is giving to you [for] an inheritance, you do not keep alive any [that are] breathing; <verse eid="DEU 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 20:17"/>for you certainly devote the Hittite, and the Amorite, the Canaanite, and the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, as your God YHWH has commanded you, <verse eid="DEU 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 20:18"/>so that they do not teach you to do according to all their abominations which they have done for their gods, and you have sinned against your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 20:19"/>When you lay siege to a city [for] many days to fight against it, to capture it, you do not destroy its trees to force an axe against them, for you eat of them, and you do not cut them down—for the tree of the field [is] man’s—to go in at your presence in the siege. <verse eid="DEU 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 20:20"/>Only, the tree of which you know that it [is] not a fruit-tree, you destroy it, and have cut [it] down, and have built a bulwark against the city which is making war with you until you have subdued it.”<verse eid="DEU 20:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="DEU 21"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 21:1"/>“When one is found slain, fallen in a field on the ground which your God YHWH is giving to you to possess it, [and] it is not known who has struck him, <verse eid="DEU 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 21:2"/>then your elderly and yours [of those] judging have gone out and measured to the cities which [are] around the slain one, <verse eid="DEU 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 21:3"/>and it has been, the city which [is] near to the slain one, even [the] elderly of that city have taken a heifer of the herd, which has not been worked with, which has not drawn in a yoke, <verse eid="DEU 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 21:4"/>and [the] elderly of that city have brought down the heifer to a hard valley, which is not tilled nor sown, and have beheaded the heifer there in the valley. <verse eid="DEU 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 21:5"/>And the priests, sons of Levi, have come near—for your God YHWH has fixed on them to serve Him and to bless in the Name of YHWH, and by their mouth is every strife and every stroke— <verse eid="DEU 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 21:6"/>and all [the] elderly of that city, who are near to the slain one, wash their hands over the heifer which is beheaded in the valley, <verse eid="DEU 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 21:7"/>and they have answered and said, Our hands have not shed this blood, and our eyes have not seen— <verse eid="DEU 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 21:8"/>receive atonement for Your people Israel, whom You have ransomed, O YHWH, and do not permit innocent blood in the midst of Your people Israel; and the blood has been pardoned to them, <verse eid="DEU 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 21:9"/>and you put away the innocent blood out of your midst, for you do that which [is] right in the eyes of YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 21:10"/>When you go out to battle against your enemies, and your God YHWH has given them into your hand, and you have taken captive its captivity, <verse eid="DEU 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 21:11"/>and have seen a woman of beautiful form in the captivity, and have delighted in her, and have taken [her] to yourself for a wife, <verse eid="DEU 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 21:12"/>then you have brought her into the midst of your household, and she has shaved her head, and prepared her nails, <verse eid="DEU 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 21:13"/>and turned aside the raiment of her captivity from off her, and has dwelt in your house, and lamented her father and her mother [for] a month of days, and afterward you go in to her and have married her, and she has been to you for a wife. <verse eid="DEU 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 21:14"/>And it has been, if you have not delighted in her, that you have sent her away at her desire, and surely you do not sell her for money; you do not tyrannize over her, because that you have humbled her. <verse eid="DEU 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 21:15"/>When a man has two wives, one loved and the other hated, and they have borne sons to him (the loved one and the hated one), and the firstborn son has been to the hated one, <verse eid="DEU 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 21:16"/>then it has been, in the day of his causing his sons to inherit that which he has, he is not able to declare firstborn the son of the loved one, in the face of the son of the hated one—the firstborn. <verse eid="DEU 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 21:17"/>But the firstborn, son of the hated one, he acknowledges, to give to him a double portion of all that is found with him, for he [is] the beginning of his strength; to him [is] the right of the firstborn. <verse eid="DEU 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 21:18"/>When a man has a son apostatizing and being rebellious—he is not listening to the voice of his father and to the voice of his mother, and they have disciplined him, and he does not listen to them— <verse eid="DEU 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 21:19"/>then his father and his mother have laid hold on him, and they have brought him out to [the] elderly of his city, and to the gate of his place, <verse eid="DEU 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 21:20"/>and have said to [the] elderly of his city, Our son—this one—is apostatizing and being rebellious; he is not listening to our voice—a glutton and drunkard. <verse eid="DEU 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 21:21"/>Then all the men of his city have stoned him with stones and he has died, and you have put away the evil out of your midst, and all Israel hears and fears. <verse eid="DEU 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 21:22"/>And when there is a sin in a man [with] a judgment of death, and he has been put to death, and you have hanged him on a tree, <verse eid="DEU 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 21:23"/>his corpse does not remain on the tree, for you certainly bury him in the day—for he who is hanged [becomes] a curse of God—and you do not defile your ground which your God YHWH is giving to you [for] an inheritance.”<verse eid="DEU 21:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="DEU 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 22:1"/>“You do not see the ox of your brother or his sheep driven away, and have hidden yourself from them, you certainly turn them back to your brother; <verse eid="DEU 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 22:2"/>and if your brother [is] not near to you, and you have not known him, then you have removed it to the midst of your house, and it has been with you until your brother seeks it, and you have given it back to him; <verse eid="DEU 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 22:3"/>and so you do to his donkey, and so you do to his garment, and so you do to any lost thing of your brother’s, which is lost by him, and you have found it; you are not able to hide yourself. <verse eid="DEU 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 22:4"/>You do not see the donkey of your brother, or his ox, falling in the way, and have hid yourself from them; you certainly raise [them] up for him. <verse eid="DEU 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 22:5"/>Anything of a man is not on a woman, nor does a man put on the garment of a woman, for anyone doing these [is] an abomination [to] your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 22:6"/>When a bird’s nest comes before you in the way, in any tree, or on the earth, [with] brood or eggs, and the mother is sitting on the brood or on the eggs, you do not take the mother with the young ones; <verse eid="DEU 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 22:7"/>you certainly send the mother away, and take the young ones for yourself, so that it is well with you and you have prolonged days. <verse eid="DEU 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 22:8"/>When you build a new house, then you have made a parapet for your roof, and you do not put blood on your house when one falls from it. <verse eid="DEU 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 22:9"/>You do not sow your vineyard [with] two kinds [of seed], lest the fullness of the seed which you sow and the increase of the vineyard be separated. <verse eid="DEU 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 22:10"/>You do not plow with an ox and with a donkey together. <verse eid="DEU 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 22:11"/>You do not put on mixed material, wool and linens together. <verse eid="DEU 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 22:12"/>You make fringes for yourself on the four skirts of your covering with which you cover [yourself]. <verse eid="DEU 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 22:13"/>When a man takes a wife, and has gone in to her, and hated her, <verse eid="DEU 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 22:14"/>and laid evil deeds of words against her, and brought out an evil name against her, and said, I have taken this woman, and I draw near to her, and I have not found proofs of virginity in her; <verse eid="DEU 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 22:15"/>then the father of the girl, and her mother, have taken and brought out the girl’s proofs of virginity to [the] elderly of the city in the gate, <verse eid="DEU 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 22:16"/>and the father of the girl has said to the elderly, I have given my daughter to this man for a wife, and he hates her; <verse eid="DEU 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 22:17"/>and behold, he has laid evil deeds of words, saying, I have not found proofs of virginity for your daughter—and these [are] the proofs of virginity of my daughter! And they have spread out the garment before [the] elderly of the city. <verse eid="DEU 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 22:18"/>And [the] elderly of that city have taken the man, and discipline him, <verse eid="DEU 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 22:19"/>and fined him one hundred pieces of silver, and given [them] to the father of the girl, because he has brought out an evil name on a virgin of Israel; and she is to him for a wife—he is not able to send her away [for] all his days. <verse eid="DEU 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 22:20"/>And if this thing has been truth—proofs of virginity have not been found for the girl— <verse eid="DEU 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 22:21"/>then they have brought out the girl to the opening of her father’s house, and the men of her city have stoned her with stones and she has died, for she has done folly in Israel, to go whoring [in] her father’s house; and you have put away evil out of your midst. <verse eid="DEU 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 22:22"/>When a man is found lying with a woman married to a husband, then both of them have died—the man who is lying with the woman, and the woman; and you have put away evil out of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 22:23"/>When there is a girl, a virgin, betrothed to a man, and a man has found her in a city and lain with her, <verse eid="DEU 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 22:24"/>then you have brought them both out to the gate of that city, and stoned them with stones, and they have died: the girl, because that she has not cried in a city; and the man, because that he has humbled his neighbor’s wife; and you have put away evil out of your midst. <verse eid="DEU 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 22:25"/>And if the man finds the girl who is betrothed in a field, and the man has laid hold on her, and lain with her, then the man who has lain with her has died alone; <verse eid="DEU 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 22:26"/>and you do not do anything to the girl—the girl has no deadly sin; for as a man rises against his neighbor and has murdered him, [taking] a life, so [is] this thing; <verse eid="DEU 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 22:27"/>for he found her in a field, [and when] she has cried—the girl who is betrothed—then she has no savior. <verse eid="DEU 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 22:28"/>When a man finds a girl, a virgin who is not betrothed, and has caught her, and lain with her, and they have been found, <verse eid="DEU 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 22:29"/>then the man who is lying with her has given fifty pieces of silver to the father of the girl, and she is to him for a wife; because that he has humbled her, he is not able to send her away [for] all his days. <verse eid="DEU 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 22:30"/>A man does not take his father’s wife, nor uncover his father’s skirt.”<verse eid="DEU 22:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="DEU 23"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 23:1"/>“No one wounded, bruised, or cut in the genitals enters into the assembly of YHWH; <verse eid="DEU 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 23:2"/>a bastard does not enter into the assembly of YHWH; even a tenth generation of him does not enter into the assembly of YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 23:3"/>An Ammonite and a Moabite do not enter into the assembly of YHWH; even a tenth generation of them do not enter into the assembly of YHWH—for all time, <verse eid="DEU 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 23:4"/>because that they have not come before you with bread and with water in the way, in your coming out from Egypt, and because he has hired against you Balaam son of Beor, of Pethor of Aram-Naharaim, to revile you; <verse eid="DEU 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 23:5"/>and your God YHWH has not been willing to listen to Balaam, and your God YHWH turns the reviling to a blessing for you, because your God YHWH has loved you; <verse eid="DEU 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 23:6"/>you do not seek their peace and their good all your days—for all time. <verse eid="DEU 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 23:7"/>You do not detest an Edomite, for he [is] your brother; you do not detest an Egyptian, for you have been a sojourner in his land; <verse eid="DEU 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 23:8"/>sons who are begotten of them, a third generation of them, enter into the assembly of YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 23:9"/>When a camp goes out against your enemies, then you have kept from every evil thing. <verse eid="DEU 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 23:10"/>When there is a man who is not clean in you, from an accident at night, then he has gone out to the outside of the camp; he does not come into the midst of the camp; <verse eid="DEU 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 23:11"/>and it has been, at the turning of the evening, he bathes with water, and at the going in of the sun he comes into the midst of the camp. <verse eid="DEU 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 23:12"/>And you have a station at the outside of the camp, and you have gone out there outside; <verse eid="DEU 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 23:13"/>and you have a peg on your staff, and it has been, in your sitting outside, that you have dug with it, and turned back, and covered your filth. <verse eid="DEU 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 23:14"/>For your God YHWH is walking up and down in the midst of your camp, to deliver you and to give your enemies before you, and your camp has been holy, and He does not see the nakedness of anything in you, and has turned back from after you. <verse eid="DEU 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 23:15"/>You do not shut up a servant to his lord, who escapes to you from his lord; <verse eid="DEU 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 23:16"/>he dwells with you in your midst, in the place which he chooses within one of your gates, where it is pleasing to him; you do not oppress him. <verse eid="DEU 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 23:17"/>There is not a whore among the daughters of Israel, nor is there a whoremonger among the sons of Israel; <verse eid="DEU 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 23:18"/>you do not bring the wage of a whore or the price of a dog into the house of your God YHWH for any vow; for even both of them [are] an abomination [to] your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 23:19"/>You do not lend in usury to your brother—usury of money, usury of food, usury of anything which is lent on usury. <verse eid="DEU 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 23:20"/>You may lend in usury to a stranger, but you do not lend in usury to your brother, so that your God YHWH blesses you in every putting forth of your hand on the land to where you go in to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 23:21"/>When you vow a vow to your God YHWH, you do not delay to complete it; for your God YHWH certainly requires it from you, lest it has been sin in you. <verse eid="DEU 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 23:22"/>And when you refrain to vow, it is not sin in you. <verse eid="DEU 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 23:23"/>You keep and have done the utterance of your lips, as you have vowed to your God YHWH, a free-will offering which you have spoken with your mouth. <verse eid="DEU 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 23:24"/>When you come into the vineyard of your neighbor, then you have eaten grapes according to your desire, your sufficiency, but you do not put [any] into your vessel. <verse eid="DEU 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 23:25"/>When you come in among the standing grain of your neighbor, then you have plucked the ears with your hand, but you do not wave a sickle over the standing grain of your neighbor.”<verse eid="DEU 23:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="DEU 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 24:1"/>“When a man takes a wife and has married her, and it has been, if she does not find grace in his eyes (for he has found nakedness in her of anything), then he has written a writing of divorce for her, and given [it] into her hand, and sent her out of his house; <verse eid="DEU 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 24:2"/>when she has gone out of his house, and has gone and been another man’s, <verse eid="DEU 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 24:3"/>and the latter man has hated her, and written a writing of divorce for her, and given [it] into her hand, and sent her out of his house, or when the latter man dies, who has taken her to himself for a wife, <verse eid="DEU 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 24:4"/>her former husband who sent her away is not able to return to take her to be to him for a wife, after that she has become defiled; for it [is] an abomination before YHWH, and you do not cause the land to sin which your God YHWH is giving to you [for] an inheritance. <verse eid="DEU 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 24:5"/>When a man takes a new wife, he does not go out into the host, and [one] does not pass over to him for anything; he is free at his own house [for] one year, and his wife, whom he has taken, he has made glad. <verse eid="DEU 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 24:6"/>No one takes millstones and rider in pledge, for it [is one’s] life he is taking in pledge. <verse eid="DEU 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 24:7"/>When a man is found stealing a person from his brothers, from the sons of Israel, and has tyrannized over him and sold him, then that thief has died, and you have put away evil out of your midst. <verse eid="DEU 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 24:8"/>Take heed in the plague of leprosy, to watch greatly, and to do according to all that the priests, the Levites, teach you; you observe to do as I have commanded them; <verse eid="DEU 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 24:9"/>remember that which your God YHWH has done to Miriam in the way, in your coming out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 24:10"/>When you lift up a debt of anything on your brother, you do not go into his house to obtain his pledge; <verse eid="DEU 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 24:11"/>you stand at the outside, and the man on whom you are lifting [it] up is bringing out the pledge to you at the outside. <verse eid="DEU 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 24:12"/>And if he is a poor man, you do not lie down with his pledge; <verse eid="DEU 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 24:13"/>you certainly give back the pledge to him at the going in of the sun, and he has lain down in his own raiment and has blessed you; and it is righteousness to you before your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 24:14"/>You do not oppress a hired worker, poor and needy, of your brothers or of your sojourner who is in your land within your gates; <verse eid="DEU 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 24:15"/>you give his hire in his day, and the sun does not go in on it, for he [is] poor, and he is supporting his life on it, lest he cries against you to YHWH, and it has been sin in you. <verse eid="DEU 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 24:16"/>Fathers are not put to death for sons, and sons are not put to death for fathers—they are each put to death for his own sin. <verse eid="DEU 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 24:17"/>You do not turn aside the judgment of a fatherless sojourner, nor take the garment of a widow in pledge; <verse eid="DEU 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 24:18"/>and you have remembered that you have been a servant in Egypt, and your God YHWH ransoms you from there; therefore I am commanding you to do this thing. <verse eid="DEU 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 24:19"/>When you reap your harvest in your field, and have forgotten a sheaf in a field, you do not return to take it; it is for the sojourner, for the fatherless, and for the widow, so that your God YHWH blesses you in all the work of your hands. <verse eid="DEU 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 24:20"/>When you beat your olive, you do not examine the branch behind you; it is for the sojourner, for the fatherless, and for the widow. <verse eid="DEU 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 24:21"/>When you cut your vineyard, you do not glean behind you; it is for the sojourner, for the fatherless, and for the widow; <verse eid="DEU 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 24:22"/>and you have remembered that you have been a servant in the land of Egypt; therefore I am commanding you to do this thing.”<verse eid="DEU 24:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="DEU 25"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 25:1"/>“When there is a strife between men, and they have come near to the judgment, and they have judged, and declared righteous the righteous, and declared wrong the wrongdoer, <verse eid="DEU 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 25:2"/>then it has come to pass, if the wrongdoer is to be struck, that the judge has caused him to fall down, and [one] has struck him in his presence, according to the sufficiency of his wrongdoing, by number; <verse eid="DEU 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 25:3"/>he strikes him forty [times]; he is not adding, lest he is adding to strike him above these many stripes, and your brother be lightly esteemed in your eyes. <verse eid="DEU 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 25:4"/>You do not muzzle an ox in its threshing. <verse eid="DEU 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 25:5"/>When brothers dwell together, and one of them has died and has no son, the wife of the dead is not given to a strange man; her husband’s brother goes in to her, and has taken her to him for a wife, and performs the duty of her husband’s brother; <verse eid="DEU 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 25:6"/>and it has been, the firstborn which she bears rises for the name of his dead brother, and his name is not wiped away out of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 25:7"/>And if the man does not delight to take his brother’s wife, then his brother’s wife has gone up to the gate, to the elderly, and said, My husband’s brother is refusing to raise up a name for his brother in Israel; he has not been willing to perform the duty of my husband’s brother; <verse eid="DEU 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 25:8"/>and [the] elderly of his city have called for him, and spoken to him, and he has stood and said, I have no desire to take her. <verse eid="DEU 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 25:9"/>Then his brother’s wife has drawn near to him before the eyes of the elderly, and drawn his shoe from off his foot, and spat in his face, and answered and said, Thus it is done to the man who does not build up the house of his brother; <verse eid="DEU 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 25:10"/>and his name has been called in Israel, The house of him whose shoe is drawn off. <verse eid="DEU 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 25:11"/>When men strive together with one another, and the wife of one has drawn near to deliver her husband out of the hand of his striker, and has put forth her hand, and laid hold on his private parts, <verse eid="DEU 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 25:12"/>then you have cut off her hand; your eye does not spare. <verse eid="DEU 25:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 25:13"/>You do not have [both] a great stone and a small stone in your bag. <verse eid="DEU 25:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 25:14"/>You do not have a great ephah and a small ephah in your house. <verse eid="DEU 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 25:15"/>You have a complete and just stone, [and] you have a complete and just ephah, so that they prolong your days on the ground which your God YHWH is giving to you; <verse eid="DEU 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 25:16"/>for anyone doing these things, anyone doing iniquity, [is] an abomination [to] your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 25:17"/>Remember that which Amalek has done to you in the way in your going out from Egypt, <verse eid="DEU 25:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 25:18"/>that he has met you in the way, and strikes among you all those feeble behind you (when you [were] weary and fatigued), and is not fearing God. <verse eid="DEU 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 25:19"/>And it has been, in your God YHWH giving rest to you from all your surrounding enemies, in the land which your God YHWH is giving to you [for] an inheritance to possess it, you blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under the heavens—you do not forget.”<verse eid="DEU 25:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="DEU 26"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 26:1"/>“And it has been, when you come into the land which your God YHWH is giving to you [for] an inheritance, and you have possessed it and dwelt in it, <verse eid="DEU 26:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 26:2"/>that you have taken from the first of all the fruits of the ground, which you bring in out of your land which your God YHWH is giving to you, and have put [it] in a basket, and gone to the place which your God YHWH chooses to cause His Name to dwell there. <verse eid="DEU 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 26:3"/>And you have come to the priest who is in those days, and have said to him, I have declared to your God YHWH today that I have come into the land which YHWH has sworn to our fathers to give to us; <verse eid="DEU 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 26:4"/>and the priest has taken the basket out of your hand and placed it before the altar of your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 26:5"/>And you have answered and said before your God YHWH, My father [is] a perishing Aramean! And he goes down to Egypt, and sojourns there with few men, and becomes a great, mighty, and populous nation there; <verse eid="DEU 26:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 26:6"/>and the Egyptians do us evil, and afflict us, and put hard service on us; <verse eid="DEU 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 26:7"/>and we cry to YHWH, God of our fathers, and YHWH hears our voice, and sees our affliction, and our labor, and our oppression; <verse eid="DEU 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 26:8"/>and YHWH brings us out from Egypt by a strong hand, and by an outstretched arm, and by great fear, and by signs, and by wonders, <verse eid="DEU 26:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 26:9"/>and He brings us to this place, and gives this land to us—a land flowing with milk and honey. <verse eid="DEU 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 26:10"/>And now, behold, I have brought in the first of the fruits of the ground which you have given to me, O YHWH. (And you have placed it before your God YHWH, and bowed yourself before your God YHWH, <verse eid="DEU 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 26:11"/>and rejoiced in all the good which your God YHWH has given to you and to your house—you, and the Levite, and the sojourner who [is] in your midst.) <verse eid="DEU 26:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 26:12"/>When you complete to tithe all the tithe of your increase in the third year, the year of the tithe, then you have given to the Levite, to the sojourner, to the fatherless, and to the widow, and they have eaten within your gates and been satisfied, <verse eid="DEU 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 26:13"/>and you have said before your God YHWH, I have put away the separated thing out of the house, and have also given it to the Levite, and to the sojourner, and to the orphan, and to the widow, according to all Your command which You have commanded me; I have not passed over from Your commands, nor have I forgotten. <verse eid="DEU 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 26:14"/>I have not eaten of it in my affliction, nor have I put away of it for uncleanness, nor have I given of it for the dead; I have listened to the voice of my God YHWH; I have done according to all that You have commanded me; <verse eid="DEU 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 26:15"/>look from Your holy habitation, from the heavens, and bless Your people Israel and the ground which You have given to us, as You have sworn to our fathers—a land flowing [with] milk and honey. <verse eid="DEU 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 26:16"/>This day your God YHWH is commanding you to do these statutes and judgments; and you have listened and done them with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 26:17"/>Today you have proclaimed YHWH to be to you for God, that [you are] to walk in His ways, and to keep His statutes, and His commands, and His judgments, and to listen to His voice. <verse eid="DEU 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 26:18"/>And today YHWH has proclaimed you to be to Him for a people, a peculiar treasure, as He has spoken to you, that [you are] to keep all His commands, <verse eid="DEU 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 26:19"/>so as to make you highest above all the nations whom He has made for a praise, and for a name, and for beauty, and for your being a holy people to your God YHWH, as He has spoken.”<verse eid="DEU 26:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="DEU 27"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 27:1"/>And Moses and [the] elderly of Israel command the people, saying, “Keep all the command which I am commanding you today; <verse eid="DEU 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 27:2"/>and it has been, in the day that you pass over the Jordan to the land which your God YHWH is giving to you, that you have raised up great stones for yourself, and plastered them with plaster, <verse eid="DEU 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 27:3"/>and written on them all the words of this law in your passing over, so that you go into the land which your God YHWH is giving to you—a land flowing with milk and honey, as YHWH, God of your fathers, has spoken to you. <verse eid="DEU 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 27:4"/>And it has been, in your passing over the Jordan, you raise up these stones which I am commanding you today, in Mount Ebal, and you have plastered them with plaster, <verse eid="DEU 27:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 27:5"/>and built an altar there to your God YHWH, an altar of stones; you do not wave iron over them. <verse eid="DEU 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 27:6"/>You build the altar of your God YHWH [with] complete stones, and have caused burnt-offerings to ascend on it to your God YHWH, <verse eid="DEU 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 27:7"/>and sacrificed peace-offerings, and eaten there, and rejoiced before your God YHWH, <verse eid="DEU 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 27:8"/>and written on the stones all the words of this law, well engraved.” <verse eid="DEU 27:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 27:9"/>And Moses speaks—the priests, the Levites, also—to all Israel, saying, “Keep silent and hear, O Israel: This day you have become a people for your God YHWH; <verse eid="DEU 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 27:10"/>and you have listened to the voice of your God YHWH, and done His commands and His statutes which I am commanding you today.” <verse eid="DEU 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 27:11"/>And Moses commands the people on that day, saying, <verse eid="DEU 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 27:12"/>“These stand on Mount Gerizzim to bless the people, in your passing over the Jordan: Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Joseph, and Benjamin. <verse eid="DEU 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 27:13"/>And these stand, for the reviling, on Mount Ebal: Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali.” <verse eid="DEU 27:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 27:14"/>And the Levites have answered and said to every man of Israel [with] a loud voice: <verse eid="DEU 27:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 27:15"/>“Cursed [is] the man who makes a carved and molten image, an abomination [to] YHWH, work of the hands of a craftsman, and has put [it] in a secret place.” And all the people have answered and said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 27:16"/>“Cursed [is] he who is making light of his father and his mother.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 27:17"/>“Cursed [is] he who is removing his neighbor’s border.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 27:18"/>“Cursed [is] he who is causing the blind to err in the way.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 27:19"/>“Cursed [is] he who is turning aside the judgment of fatherless, sojourner, and widow.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 27:20"/>“Cursed [is] he who is lying with his father’s wife, for he has uncovered his father’s skirt.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 27:21"/>“Cursed [is] he who is lying with any beast.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 27:22"/>“Cursed [is] he who is lying with his sister, daughter of his father or daughter of his mother.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 27:23"/>“Cursed [is] he who is lying with his mother-in-law.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 27:24"/>“Cursed [is] he who is striking his neighbor in secret.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 27:25"/>“Cursed [is] he who is taking a bribe to strike a person, innocent blood.” And all the people have said, “Amen.” <verse eid="DEU 27:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 27:26"/>“Cursed [is] he who does not establish the words of this law, to do them.” And all the people have said, “Amen.”<verse eid="DEU 27:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="DEU 28"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 28:1"/>“And it has been, if you listen diligently to the voice of your God YHWH, to observe to do all His commands which I am commanding you today, that your God YHWH has made you highest above all the nations of the earth, <verse eid="DEU 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 28:2"/>and all these blessings have come on you and overtaken you, because you listen to the voice of your God YHWH: <verse eid="DEU 28:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 28:3"/>Blessed [are] you in the city, and blessed [are] you in the field. <verse eid="DEU 28:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 28:4"/>Blessed [is] the fruit of your womb, and the fruit of your ground, and the fruit of your livestock, the increase of your oxen, and the wealth of your flock. <verse eid="DEU 28:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 28:5"/>Blessed [is] your basket and your kneading-trough. <verse eid="DEU 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 28:6"/>Blessed [are] you in your coming in, and blessed [are] you in your going out. <verse eid="DEU 28:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 28:7"/>YHWH makes your enemies, who are rising up against you, to be struck before your face; in one way they come out to you, and in seven ways they flee before you. <verse eid="DEU 28:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 28:8"/>YHWH commands the blessing with you in your storehouses, and in every putting forth of your hand, and has blessed you in the land which your God YHWH is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 28:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 28:9"/>YHWH establishes you to Himself for a holy people, as He has sworn to you, when you keep the commands of your God YHWH and have walked in His ways; <verse eid="DEU 28:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 28:10"/>and all the peoples of the land have seen that the Name of YHWH is called by you, and they have been afraid of you. <verse eid="DEU 28:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 28:11"/>And YHWH has made you abundant in good, in the fruit of the womb, and in the fruit of your livestock, and in the fruit of your ground, on the ground which YHWH has sworn to your fathers to give to you. <verse eid="DEU 28:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 28:12"/>YHWH opens his good treasure to you—the heavens—to give the rain of your land in its season, and to bless all the work of your hand, and you have lent to many nations, and you do not borrow. <verse eid="DEU 28:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 28:13"/>And YHWH has set you for head and not for tail; and you have been only above, and are not beneath, for you listen to the commands of your God YHWH, which I am commanding you today, to keep and to do, <verse eid="DEU 28:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 28:14"/>and you do not turn aside from all the words which I am commanding you today [to] the right or left, to go after other gods, to serve them. <verse eid="DEU 28:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 28:15"/>And it has been, if you do not listen to the voice of your God YHWH, to observe to do all His commands and His statutes which I am commanding you today, that all these revilings have come on you and overtaken you: <verse eid="DEU 28:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 28:16"/>Cursed [are] you in the city, and cursed [are] you in the field. <verse eid="DEU 28:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 28:17"/>Cursed [is] your basket and your kneading-trough. <verse eid="DEU 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 28:18"/>Cursed [is] the fruit of your body, and the fruit of your land, the increase of your oxen, and the wealth of your flock. <verse eid="DEU 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 28:19"/>Cursed [are] you in your coming in, and cursed [are] you in your going out. <verse eid="DEU 28:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 28:20"/>YHWH sends the curse, the trouble, and the rebuke on you, in every putting forth of your hand which you do, until you are destroyed, and until you perish quickly, because of the evil of your doings [by] which you have forsaken Me. <verse eid="DEU 28:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 28:21"/>YHWH causes the pestilence to cleave to you until He consumes you from off the ground to where you are going in to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 28:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 28:22"/>YHWH strikes you with consumption, and with fever, and with inflammation, and with extreme burning, and with sword, and with blasting, and with mildew, and they have pursued you until you perish <verse eid="DEU 28:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 28:23"/>And your heavens which [are] over your head have been bronze, and the earth which [is] under you iron; <verse eid="DEU 28:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 28:24"/>YHWH gives dust and ashes [for] the rain of your land; it comes down on you from the heavens until you are destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 28:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 28:25"/>YHWH makes you struck before your enemies; in one way you go out to them, and in seven ways you flee before them, and you have been for a trembling to all kingdoms of the earth; <verse eid="DEU 28:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 28:26"/>and your carcass has been for food for every bird of the heavens and for the beast of the earth, and there is none causing [them] to tremble. <verse eid="DEU 28:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 28:27"/>YHWH strikes you with the ulcer of Egypt, and with lumps, and with scurvy, and with itch, of which you are not able to be healed. <verse eid="DEU 28:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 28:28"/>YHWH strikes you with madness, and with blindness, and with astonishment of heart; <verse eid="DEU 28:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 28:29"/>and you have been groping at noon, as the blind gropes in darkness; and you do not cause your ways to prosper; and you have been only oppressed and plundered [for] all the days, and there is no savior. <verse eid="DEU 28:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 28:30"/>You betroth a woman, and another man lies with her; you build a house, and do not dwell in it; you plant a vineyard, and do not make it common; <verse eid="DEU 28:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 28:31"/>your ox [is] slaughtered before your eyes, and you do not eat of it; your donkey [is] violently taken away from before you, and it is not given back to you; your sheep [are] given to your enemies, and there is no savior for you. <verse eid="DEU 28:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 28:32"/>Your sons and your daughters [are] given to another people, and your eyes are looking and consumed for them all the day, but your hand is not to God! <verse eid="DEU 28:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 28:33"/>A people whom you have not known eat the fruit of your ground and all your labor; and you have been only oppressed and bruised [for] all the days; <verse eid="DEU 28:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 28:34"/>and you have been mad because of the sight of your eyes which you see. <verse eid="DEU 28:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 28:35"/>YHWH strikes you with a severe ulcer on the knees and on the legs (of which you are not able to be healed), from the sole of your foot even to your crown. <verse eid="DEU 28:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 28:36"/>YHWH causes you and your king whom you raise up over you to go to a nation which you have not known, you and your fathers, and you have served other gods there—wood and stone; <verse eid="DEU 28:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 28:37"/>and you have been for an astonishment, for an allegory, and for a byword among all the peoples to where YHWH leads you. <verse eid="DEU 28:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 28:38"/>You take much seed out into the field, and you gather little in, for the locust consumes it; <verse eid="DEU 28:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 28:39"/>you plant vineyards and have labored, but you do not drink wine, nor gather [grapes], for the worm consumes it; <verse eid="DEU 28:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 28:40"/>olives are yours in all your border, but you do not pour out oil, for your olive falls off. <verse eid="DEU 28:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 28:41"/>You beget sons and daughters, but they are not with you, for they go into captivity; <verse eid="DEU 28:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 28:42"/>the locust possesses all your trees and the fruit of your ground; <verse eid="DEU 28:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 28:43"/>the sojourner who [is] in your midst goes up very high above you, and you go down very low; <verse eid="DEU 28:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 28:44"/>he lends [to] you, and you do not lend [to] him; he is for head and you are for tail. <verse eid="DEU 28:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 28:45"/>And all these curses have come on you, and pursued you, and overtaken you, until you are destroyed, because you have not listened to the voice of your God YHWH, to keep His commands and His statutes which he has commanded you; <verse eid="DEU 28:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 28:46"/>and they have been on you for a sign and for a wonder, also on your seed—for all time. <verse eid="DEU 28:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 28:47"/>Because that you have not served your God YHWH with joy and with gladness of heart, because of the abundance of all things— <verse eid="DEU 28:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 28:48"/>you have served your enemies, whom YHWH sends against you, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in lack of all things; and He has put a yoke of iron on your neck until He has destroyed you. <verse eid="DEU 28:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 28:49"/>YHWH lifts up a nation against you from afar, from the end of the earth—it flies as the eagle—a nation whose tongue you have not heard, <verse eid="DEU 28:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="DEU 28:50"/>a nation of fierce countenance, which does not accept the face of the aged and does not favor the young; <verse eid="DEU 28:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="DEU 28:51"/>and it has eaten the fruit of your livestock and the fruit of your ground, until you are destroyed; which does not leave to you grain, new wine, and oil, the increase of your oxen, and the wealth of your flock, until it has destroyed you. <verse eid="DEU 28:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="DEU 28:52"/>And it has laid siege to you in all your gates until your walls come down—the high and the fortified ones in which you are trusting, in all your land; indeed, it has laid siege to you in all your gates, in all your land which your God YHWH has given to you. <verse eid="DEU 28:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="DEU 28:53"/>And you have eaten the fruit of your body, [the] flesh of your sons and your daughters (whom your God YHWH has given to you), in the siege and in the constriction with which your enemies constrict you. <verse eid="DEU 28:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="DEU 28:54"/>The man who is tender in you, and who [is] very delicate—his eye is evil against his brother, and against the wife of his bosom, and against the remnant of his sons whom he leaves, <verse eid="DEU 28:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="DEU 28:55"/>against giving to one of them of the flesh of his sons whom he eats, because he has nothing left for himself in the siege and in the constriction with which your enemy constricts you in all your gates. <verse eid="DEU 28:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="DEU 28:56"/>The tender woman in you, and the delicate, who has not tried the sole of her foot to place on the ground because of delicateness and because of tenderness—her eye is evil against the husband of her bosom, and against her son, and against her daughter, <verse eid="DEU 28:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="DEU 28:57"/>and against her seed which comes out from between her feet, even against her sons whom she bears, for she eats them in secret, in the lacking of everything, in the siege and in the constriction with which your enemy constricts you within your gates. <verse eid="DEU 28:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="DEU 28:58"/>If you do not observe to do all the words of this law which are written in this scroll, to fear this honored and fearful Name—your God YHWH— <verse eid="DEU 28:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="DEU 28:59"/>then YHWH has made your strokes extraordinary, and the strokes [against] your seed [are] great strokes that are persisting and severe sicknesses that are persisting. <verse eid="DEU 28:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="DEU 28:60"/>And He has brought back all the diseases of Egypt on you, from the presence of which you have been afraid, and they have cleaved to you. <verse eid="DEU 28:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="DEU 28:61"/>Also every sickness and every stroke which is not written in the scroll of this law—YHWH causes them to go up on you until you are destroyed, <verse eid="DEU 28:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="DEU 28:62"/>and you have been left with few men, whereas that you would have been as stars of the heavens for multitude, for you have not listened to the voice of your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 28:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="DEU 28:63"/>And it has been, as YHWH has rejoiced over you to do you good and to multiply you, so YHWH rejoices over you to destroy you and to lay you waste; and you have been pulled away from off the ground to where you are going in to possess it; <verse eid="DEU 28:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="DEU 28:64"/>and YHWH has scattered you among all the peoples, from the end of the earth even to the [other] end of the earth; and you have served other gods there which you have not known, you and your fathers—wood and stone. <verse eid="DEU 28:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="DEU 28:65"/>And you do not rest among those nations, indeed, there is no resting place for the sole of your foot, and YHWH has given to you a trembling heart, and failing of eyes, and grief of soul there; <verse eid="DEU 28:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="DEU 28:66"/>and your life has been hanging in suspense before you, and you have been afraid by night and by day, and you do not have assurance in your life; <verse eid="DEU 28:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="DEU 28:67"/>in the morning you say, O that it were evening! And in the evening you say, O that it were morning! (From the fear of your heart, with which you are afraid, and from the sight of your eyes which you see.) <verse eid="DEU 28:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="DEU 28:68"/>And YHWH has brought you back to Egypt in ships, by the way of which I said to you, You do not add to see it anymore; and you have sold yourselves to your enemies there, for menservants and for maidservants, and there is no buyer.”<verse eid="DEU 28:68"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="DEU 29"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 29:1"/>These [are] the words of the covenant which YHWH has commanded Moses to make with the sons of Israel in the land of Moab, apart from the covenant which He made with them in Horeb. <verse eid="DEU 29:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 29:2"/>And Moses calls to all Israel and says to them, “You have seen all that which YHWH has done before your eyes in the land of Egypt, to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land— <verse eid="DEU 29:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 29:3"/>the great trials which your eyes have seen, the signs, and those great wonders. <verse eid="DEU 29:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 29:4"/>And YHWH has not given to you a heart to know, and eyes to see, and ears to hear, until this day. <verse eid="DEU 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 29:5"/>And I cause you to go in a wilderness [for] forty years; your garments have not been consumed from off you, and your shoe has not worn away from off your foot; <verse eid="DEU 29:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 29:6"/>you have not eaten bread, and you have not drunk wine and strong drink, so that you know that I [am] your God YHWH. <verse eid="DEU 29:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 29:7"/>And you come to this place, and Sihon king of Heshbon—also Og king of Bashan—comes out to meet us to battle, and we strike them, <verse eid="DEU 29:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 29:8"/>and take their land, and give it for an inheritance to the Reubenite, and to the Gadite, and to the half of the tribe of the Manassite; <verse eid="DEU 29:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 29:9"/>and you have kept the words of this covenant and done them, so that you cause all that you do to prosper. <verse eid="DEU 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 29:10"/>You are standing today, all of you, before your God YHWH: your heads, your tribes, your elderly, and your authorities, every man of Israel, <verse eid="DEU 29:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 29:11"/>your infants, your wives, and your sojourner who [is] in the midst of your camps, from the hewer of your wood to the drawer of your water, <verse eid="DEU 29:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 29:12"/>for your passing over into the covenant of your God YHWH, and into His oath which your God YHWH is making with you today, <verse eid="DEU 29:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 29:13"/>in order to establish you to Himself for a people today, and He Himself is your God, as He has spoken to you, and as He has sworn to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. <verse eid="DEU 29:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 29:14"/>And I am not making this covenant and this oath with you alone, <verse eid="DEU 29:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 29:15"/>but with him who is here with us, standing before our God YHWH today, and with him who is not here with us today, <verse eid="DEU 29:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 29:16"/>for you have known how you dwelt in the land of Egypt, and how we passed by through the midst of the nations which you have passed by; <verse eid="DEU 29:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 29:17"/>and you see their abominations, and their idols of wood and stone, silver and gold, which [are] with them, <verse eid="DEU 29:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 29:18"/>lest there be among you a man or woman, or family or tribe, whose heart is turning from our God YHWH today, to go to serve the gods of those nations, lest there be in you a root bearing the fruit of gall and wormwood; <verse eid="DEU 29:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 29:19"/>and it has been, in his hearing the words of this oath, that he has blessed himself in his heart, saying, I have peace, though I go on in the stubbornness of my heart—in order to sweep away the watered with the thirsty. <verse eid="DEU 29:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 29:20"/>YHWH is not willing to be propitious to him, for then the anger of YHWH smokes, also His zeal, against that man, and all the oath which is written in this scroll has lain down on him, and YHWH has blotted out his name from under the heavens, <verse eid="DEU 29:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 29:21"/>and YHWH has separated him for calamity out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the oaths of the covenant which is written in this Scroll of the Law. <verse eid="DEU 29:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 29:22"/>And the latter generation of your sons who rise after you, and the stranger who comes in from a far-off land, have said, when they have seen the strokes of that land and its sicknesses which YHWH has sent into it: <verse eid="DEU 29:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 29:23"/>The whole land is burned [with] brimstone and salt, it is not sown, nor does it shoot up, nor does any herb go up on it there, like the overthrow of Sodom and Gomorrah, Admah and Zeboim, which YHWH overturned in His anger and in His fury. <verse eid="DEU 29:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 29:24"/>Indeed, all the nations have said, Why has YHWH done thus to this land? Why the heat of this great anger? <verse eid="DEU 29:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 29:25"/>And they have said, Because that they have forsaken the covenant of YHWH, God of their fathers, which He made with them in His bringing them out of the land of Egypt, <verse eid="DEU 29:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 29:26"/>and they go and serve other gods, and bow themselves to them—gods which they have not known, and which He has not apportioned to them; <verse eid="DEU 29:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 29:27"/>and the anger of YHWH burns against that land, to bring in on it all the reviling that is written in this scroll, <verse eid="DEU 29:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 29:28"/>and YHWH plucks them from off their ground in anger, and in fury, and in great wrath, and casts them into another land, as [at] this day. <verse eid="DEU 29:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 29:29"/>The things hidden [belong] to our God YHWH, and the things revealed [belong] to us and to our sons for all time, to do all the words of this law.”<verse eid="DEU 29:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="DEU 30"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 30:1"/>“And it has been, when all these things come on you, the blessing and the reviling, which I have set before you, and you have brought [them] back to your heart among all the nations to where your God YHWH has driven you away, <verse eid="DEU 30:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 30:2"/>and have turned back to your God YHWH and listened to His voice, according to all that I am commanding you today, you and your sons, with all your heart and with all your soul— <verse eid="DEU 30:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 30:3"/>then your God YHWH has turned back [to] your captivity and pitied you, indeed, He has turned back and gathered you out of all the peoples to where your God YHWH has scattered you. <verse eid="DEU 30:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 30:4"/>If your outcast is in the extremity of the heavens, your God YHWH gathers you from there and He takes you from there; <verse eid="DEU 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 30:5"/>and your God YHWH has brought you into the land which your fathers have possessed, and you have inherited it, and He has done you good, and multiplied you above your fathers. <verse eid="DEU 30:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 30:6"/>And your God YHWH has circumcised your heart and the heart of your seed, to love your God YHWH with all your heart and with all your soul, for the sake of your life; <verse eid="DEU 30:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 30:7"/>and your God YHWH has put all this oath on your enemies and on those hating you, who have pursued you. <verse eid="DEU 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 30:8"/>And you turn back, and have listened to the voice of YHWH, and have done all His commands which I am commanding you today; <verse eid="DEU 30:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 30:9"/>and your God YHWH has made you abundant in every work of your hand, in the fruit of your body, and in the fruit of your livestock, and in the fruit of your ground, for good; for YHWH turns back to rejoice over you for good, as He rejoiced over your fathers, <verse eid="DEU 30:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 30:10"/>for you listen to the voice of your God YHWH, to keep His commands and His statutes which are written in the scroll of this law, for you turn back to your God YHWH with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 30:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 30:11"/>For this command which I am commanding you today, it is not too wonderful for you, nor [is] it far off. <verse eid="DEU 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 30:12"/>It is not in the heavens, saying, Who goes up into the heavens for us, and takes it for us, and causes us to hear it, that we may do it? <verse eid="DEU 30:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 30:13"/>And it [is] not beyond the sea, saying, Who passes over beyond the sea for us, and takes it for us, and causes us to hear it, that we may do it? <verse eid="DEU 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 30:14"/>For the word is very near to you, in your mouth, and in your heart—to do it. <verse eid="DEU 30:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 30:15"/>See, today I have set before you life and good, and death and evil, <verse eid="DEU 30:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 30:16"/>in that today I am commanding you to love your God YHWH, to walk in His ways, and to keep His commands, and His statutes, and His judgments; and you have lived and multiplied, and your God YHWH has blessed you in the land to where you are going in to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 30:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 30:17"/>And if your heart turns, and you do not listen, and have been drawn away, and have bowed yourself to other gods and served them, <verse eid="DEU 30:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 30:18"/>I have declared to you this day that you certainly perish, you do not prolong days on the ground which you are passing over the Jordan to go in there to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 30:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 30:19"/>I have caused the heavens and the earth to testify against you today—I have set before you life and death, the blessing and the reviling, and you have fixed on life, so that you live, you and your seed, <verse eid="DEU 30:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 30:20"/>to love your God YHWH, to listen to His voice, and to cleave to Him (for He [is] your life and the length of your days), to dwell on the ground which YHWH has sworn to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to them.”<verse eid="DEU 30:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="DEU 31"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 31:1"/>And Moses goes and speaks these words to all Israel, <verse eid="DEU 31:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 31:2"/>and he says to them, “I [am] a son of one hundred and twenty years today; I am not able to go out and to come in anymore, and YHWH has said to me, You do not pass over this Jordan. <verse eid="DEU 31:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 31:3"/>Your God YHWH—He is passing over before you; He destroys these nations from before you, and you have possessed them; Joshua—he is passing over before you, as YHWH has spoken. <verse eid="DEU 31:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 31:4"/>And YHWH has done to them as he has done to Sihon and to Og, kings of the Amorite, and to their land, whom He destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 31:5"/>And YHWH has given them before your face, and you have done to them according to all the command which I have commanded you; <verse eid="DEU 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 31:6"/>be strong and courageous, do not fear, nor be terrified because of them, for your God YHWH [is] He who is going with you; He does not fail you nor forsake you.” <verse eid="DEU 31:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 31:7"/>And Moses calls for Joshua and says to him before the eyes of all Israel, “Be strong and courageous, for you go in with this people to the land which YHWH has sworn to their fathers to give to them, and you cause them to inherit it; <verse eid="DEU 31:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 31:8"/>and YHWH [is] He who is going before you, He Himself is with you; He does not fail you nor forsake you; do not fear, nor be frightened.” <verse eid="DEU 31:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 31:9"/>And Moses writes this law and gives it to the priests (sons of Levi, those carrying the Ark of the Covenant of YHWH), and to all [the] elderly of Israel, <verse eid="DEU 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 31:10"/>and Moses commands them, saying, “At the end of seven years, in the appointed time, the year of release, in the Celebration of Shelters, <verse eid="DEU 31:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 31:11"/>in the coming in of all Israel to see the face of YHWH in the place which He chooses, you proclaim this law before all Israel in their ears. <verse eid="DEU 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 31:12"/>Assemble the people, the men, and the women, and the infants, and your sojourner who [is] within your gates, so that they hear, and so that they learn, and have feared your God YHWH, and observed to do all the words of this law; <verse eid="DEU 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 31:13"/>and their sons, who have not known, hear and have learned to fear your God YHWH [for] all the days which you are living on the ground to where you are passing over the Jordan to possess it.” <verse eid="DEU 31:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 31:14"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Behold, your days have drawn near to die; call Joshua, and station yourselves in the Tent of Meeting, and I charge him”; and Moses goes—Joshua also—and they station themselves in the Tent of Meeting, <verse eid="DEU 31:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 31:15"/>and YHWH is seen in the tent in a pillar of a cloud; and the pillar of the cloud stands at the opening of the tent. <verse eid="DEU 31:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 31:16"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Behold, you are lying down with your fathers, and this people has risen and gone whoring after the gods of the stranger of the land, into the midst of which it has entered, and it has forsaken Me and broken My covenant which I made with it; <verse eid="DEU 31:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 31:17"/>and My anger has burned against it in that day, and I have forsaken them, and hidden My face from them, and it has been for consumption, and many evils and distresses have found it, and it has said in that day, [Is] it not because my God is not in my midst that these evils have found me? <verse eid="DEU 31:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 31:18"/>And I certainly hide My face in that day for all the evil which it has done, for it has turned to other gods. <verse eid="DEU 31:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 31:19"/>And now, write this song for yourselves, and teach it [to] the sons of Israel; put it in their mouths, so that this song is to Me for a witness against the sons of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 31:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 31:20"/>When I bring them to the ground flowing with milk and honey, which I have sworn to their fathers, and they have eaten, and been satisfied, and been fat, and have turned to other gods, and they have served them, and despised Me, and broken My covenant, <verse eid="DEU 31:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 31:21"/>then it has been, when many evils and distresses meet it, that this song has testified to its face for a witness; for it is not forgotten out of the mouth of its seed, for I have known its imagining which it is doing today, before I bring them into the land of which I have sworn.” <verse eid="DEU 31:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 31:22"/>And Moses writes this song on that day, and teaches it [to] the sons of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 31:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 31:23"/>Then He commands Joshua son of Nun, and says, “Be strong and courageous, for you bring in the sons of Israel to the land which I have sworn to them, and I am with you.” <verse eid="DEU 31:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 31:24"/>And it comes to pass, when Moses finishes to write the words of this law on a scroll, until their completion, <verse eid="DEU 31:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 31:25"/>that Moses commands the Levites carrying the Ark of the Covenant of YHWH, saying, <verse eid="DEU 31:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 31:26"/>“Take this Scroll of the Law, and you have set it on the side of the Ark of the Covenant of your God YHWH, and it has been against you for a witness there; <verse eid="DEU 31:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 31:27"/>for I have known your rebellion and your stiff neck; behold, in my being yet alive with you today, you have been rebelling against YHWH, and surely also after my death. <verse eid="DEU 31:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 31:28"/>Assemble to me all the elderly of your tribes, and your authorities, and I speak these words in their ears, and cause the heavens and the earth to testify against them, <verse eid="DEU 31:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 31:29"/>for I have known that you act very corruptly after my death, and have turned aside from the way which I commanded you, and evil has met you in the latter end of the days, because you do evil in the eyes of YHWH, to make Him angry with the work of your hands.” <verse eid="DEU 31:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 31:30"/>And Moses speaks the words of this song in the ears of all the assembly of Israel, until their completion:<verse eid="DEU 31:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 31"/>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="DEU 32"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 32:1"/>“Give ear, O heavens, and I speak; And you hear, O earth, sayings of my mouth! <verse eid="DEU 32:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 32:2"/>My doctrine drops as rain; My sayings flow as dew; As storms on the tender grass, || And as showers on the herb, <verse eid="DEU 32:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 32:3"/>For I proclaim the Name of YHWH; Ascribe greatness to our God! <verse eid="DEU 32:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 32:4"/>The Rock—His work [is] perfect, || For all His ways [are] just; God of steadfastness, and without iniquity; Righteous and upright [is] He. <verse eid="DEU 32:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 32:5"/>It has done corruptly to Him; Their blemish is not of His sons, || A generation perverse and crooked! <verse eid="DEU 32:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 32:6"/>Do you act thus to YHWH, || O people foolish and not wise? Is He not your Father—He who bought you? He made you, and establishes you. <verse eid="DEU 32:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 32:7"/>Remember days of old—Understand the years of many generations—Ask your father, and he tells you; Your elderly, and they say to you: <verse eid="DEU 32:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 32:8"/>In the Most High causing nations to inherit, || In His separating sons of Adam—He sets up the borders of the peoples || By the number of the sons of God <char style="bd">[[</char><char style="it">or</char> sons of Israel<char style="bd">]]</char>. <verse eid="DEU 32:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 32:9"/>For YHWH’s portion [is] His people, || Jacob [is] the line of His inheritance. <verse eid="DEU 32:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 32:10"/>He finds him in a land—a desert, || And in a void—a howling wilderness, || He turns him around—He causes him to understand—He keeps him as the apple of His eye. <verse eid="DEU 32:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 32:11"/>As an eagle wakes up its nest, || Flutters over its young ones, || Spreads its wings [and] takes them, || Carries them on its pinions— <verse eid="DEU 32:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 32:12"/>YHWH alone leads him, || And there is no strange god with him. <verse eid="DEU 32:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 32:13"/>He makes him ride on high places of earth, || And he eats increase of the fields, || And He makes him suck honey from a rock, || And oil out of the flint of a rock; <verse eid="DEU 32:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 32:14"/>Butter of the herd, and milk of the flock, || With fat of lambs, and rams of sons of Bashan, || And male goats, with fat of kidneys of wheat; And of the blood of the grape you drink wine! <verse eid="DEU 32:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 32:15"/>And Yeshurun waxes fat, and kicks: You have been fat, you have been thick, || You have been covered. And he leaves God who made him, || And dishonors the Rock of his salvation. <verse eid="DEU 32:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 32:16"/>They make Him zealous with strangers, || They make Him angry with abominations. <verse eid="DEU 32:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 32:17"/>They sacrifice to the demons, not God, || To gods they have not known, || New ones—they came from the vicinity; Your fathers have not feared them! <verse eid="DEU 32:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 32:18"/>You forget the Rock that begot you, || And neglect God who forms you. <verse eid="DEU 32:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 32:19"/>And YHWH sees and despises—For the provocation of His sons and His daughters. <verse eid="DEU 32:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 32:20"/>And He says: I hide My face from them, || I see what their latter end [is]; For they [are] a contrary generation, || Sons in whom is no steadfastness. <verse eid="DEU 32:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 32:21"/>They have made Me jealous by [what is] not God, || They made Me angry by their vanities; And I make them jealous by [what is] not a people, || I make them angry by a foolish nation. <verse eid="DEU 32:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 32:22"/>For a fire has been kindled in My anger, || And it burns to the lowest [part] of Sheol, || And consumes earth and its increase, || And sets on fire [the] foundations of mountains. <verse eid="DEU 32:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 32:23"/>I heap calamities on them, || I consume My arrows on them. <verse eid="DEU 32:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 32:24"/>Exhausted by famine, || And consumed by heat and bitter destruction—I also send the teeth of beasts on them, || With poison of fearful things of the dust. <verse eid="DEU 32:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 32:25"/>The sword destroys from outside, || And out of the inner-chambers—terror, || Both youth and virgin, || Suckling with man of grey hair. <verse eid="DEU 32:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 32:26"/>I have said: I blow them away, || I cause their remembrance to cease from man; <verse eid="DEU 32:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 32:27"/>If I do not fear the anger of an enemy, || Lest their adversaries know—Lest they say, Our hand is high, || And YHWH has not worked all this. <verse eid="DEU 32:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 32:28"/>For they [are] a nation lost to counsels, || And there is no understanding in them. <verse eid="DEU 32:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 32:29"/>If only they were wise, || They would deal wisely [with] this, || They would attend to their latter end! <verse eid="DEU 32:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 32:30"/>How does one pursue a thousand, || And two cause a myriad to flee, || If not that their Rock has sold them, || And YHWH has shut them up? <verse eid="DEU 32:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 32:31"/>For their rock [is] not as our Rock || (And our enemies [are] judges!) <verse eid="DEU 32:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 32:32"/>For their vine [is] of the vine of Sodom, || And of the fields of Gomorrah; Their grapes [are] grapes of gall—They have bitter clusters; <verse eid="DEU 32:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 32:33"/>The poison of dragons [is] their wine || And the fierce venom of cobras. <verse eid="DEU 32:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 32:34"/>Is it not laid up with Me? Sealed among My treasures? <verse eid="DEU 32:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 32:35"/>Vengeance and retribution [are] Mine, || At the due time—their foot slides; For near is a day of their calamity, || And things prepared for them have hastened. <verse eid="DEU 32:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 32:36"/>For YHWH judges His people, || And gives comfort over His servants. For He sees the going away of power, || And none is restrained and left. <verse eid="DEU 32:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 32:37"/>And He has said, Where [are] their gods—The rock in which they trusted? <verse eid="DEU 32:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 32:38"/>Who eat the fat of their sacrifices, || [And] drink the wine of their drink-offering? Let them arise and help you, || Let it be a hiding place for you! <verse eid="DEU 32:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 32:39"/>See, now, that I [am] He, || And there is no god besides Me; I put to death and I keep alive; I have struck and I heal; And there is not a deliverer from My hand, <verse eid="DEU 32:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 32:40"/>For I lift up My hand to the heavens, || And have said, I live for all time! <verse eid="DEU 32:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 32:41"/>If I have sharpened the brightness of My sword, || And My hand lays hold on judgment, || I return vengeance to My adversaries, || And to those hating Me—I repay! <verse eid="DEU 32:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 32:42"/>I make My arrows drunk with blood, || And My sword devours flesh, || From the blood of the pierced and captive, || From the head of the leaders of the enemy. <verse eid="DEU 32:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 32:43"/>Sing, O nations, [with] His people, || For He avenges the blood of His servants, || And He turns back vengeance on His adversaries, || And has pardoned His land [and] His people.” <verse eid="DEU 32:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 32:44"/>And Moses comes and speaks all the words of this song in the ears of the people, he and Hoshea son of Nun; <verse eid="DEU 32:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 32:45"/>and Moses finishes to speak all these words to all Israel, <verse eid="DEU 32:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 32:46"/>and says to them, “Set your heart to all the words which I am testifying against you today, that you command your sons to observe to do all the words of this law, <verse eid="DEU 32:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 32:47"/>for it [is] not a vain thing for you, for it [is] your life, and by this thing you prolong days on the ground to where you are passing over the Jordan to possess it.” <verse eid="DEU 32:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 32:48"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses on this very same day, saying, <verse eid="DEU 32:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 32:49"/>“Go up to this Mount Abarim, Mount Nebo, which [is] in the land of Moab, which [is] on the front of Jericho, and see the land of Canaan which I am giving to the sons of Israel for a possession; <verse eid="DEU 32:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="DEU 32:50"/>and die on the mountain to where you are going up, and be gathered to your people, as your brother Aaron has died on Mount Hor and is gathered to his people; <verse eid="DEU 32:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="DEU 32:51"/>because you trespassed against Me in the midst of the sons of Israel at the waters of Meribath-Kadesh, the wilderness of Zin, because you did not sanctify Me in the midst of the sons of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 32:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="DEU 32:52"/>Indeed, you see the land before [you], but you do not go in there to the land which I am giving to the sons of Israel.”<verse eid="DEU 32:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 32"/>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="DEU 33"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 33:1"/>And this [is] the blessing [with] which Moses the man of God blessed the sons of Israel before his death, <verse eid="DEU 33:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 33:2"/>and he says: “YHWH has come from Sinai, || And has risen from Seir for them; He has shone from Mount Paran, || And has come [with] myriads of holy ones; At His right hand [came] a fiery law <char style="bd">[[</char><char style="it">or</char> a flaming fire<char style="bd">]]</char> for them. <verse eid="DEU 33:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 33:3"/>Indeed, He [is] loving the peoples; All His holy ones [are] in Your hand, || And they sat down at Your foot, || [Each] lifts up Your words. <verse eid="DEU 33:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 33:4"/>Moses has commanded a law for us, || A possession of the assembly of Jacob. <verse eid="DEU 33:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 33:5"/>And He is King in Yeshurun, || In the heads of the people gathering together, || The tribes of Israel! <verse eid="DEU 33:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 33:6"/>Let Reuben live, and not die, || And let his men be an [incalculable] number. <verse eid="DEU 33:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 33:7"/>And this [is] for Judah, and he says: Hear, O YHWH, the voice of Judah, || And You bring him in to his people; His hand has striven for him, || And You are a help from his adversaries. <verse eid="DEU 33:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 33:8"/>And of Levi he said: Your Perfections and your Lights [are] for your pious one, || Whom You have tried in Massah, || You strive with him at the waters of Meribah; <verse eid="DEU 33:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 33:9"/>Who is saying of his father and his mother, || I have not seen him; And he has not discerned his brothers, || And he has not known his sons; For they have observed Your saying, || And they keep Your covenant. <verse eid="DEU 33:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 33:10"/>They teach Your judgments to Jacob, || And Your law to Israel; They put incense in Your nose, || And whole burnt-offering on Your altar. <verse eid="DEU 33:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 33:11"/>Bless, O YHWH, his strength, || And accept the work of his hands, || Strike the loins of his withstanders, || And of those hating him—that they do not rise! <verse eid="DEU 33:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 33:12"/>Of Benjamin he said: The beloved of YHWH dwells confidently by Him, || Covering him over every day; Indeed, he dwells between His shoulders. <verse eid="DEU 33:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 33:13"/>And of Joseph he said: His land [is] blessed [by] YHWH, || By a precious thing of the heavens, || By dew, and by the deep crouching beneath, <verse eid="DEU 33:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 33:14"/>And by a precious thing—fruits of the sun, || And by a precious thing—cast forth by the months, <verse eid="DEU 33:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 33:15"/>And by a chief thing—of the ancient mountains, || And by a precious thing—of the continuous heights, <verse eid="DEU 33:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 33:16"/>And by a precious thing—of earth and its fullness, || And the good pleasure of Him who is dwelling in the bush; Let it come for the head of Joseph, || And for the crown of him [who is] separate from his brothers. <verse eid="DEU 33:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 33:17"/>His splendor [is] a firstling of his ox, || And his horns [are] horns of a wild ox; With them he pushes the peoples || Altogether to the ends of the earth; And they [are] the myriads of Ephraim, || And they [are] the thousands of Manasseh. <verse eid="DEU 33:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 33:18"/>And of Zebulun he said: Rejoice, O Zebulun, in your going out, || And, O Issachar, in your tents; <verse eid="DEU 33:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 33:19"/>They call peoples [to] the mountain, || There they sacrifice righteous sacrifices; For they suck up the abundance of the seas, || And hidden things hidden in the sand. <verse eid="DEU 33:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 33:20"/>And of Gad he said: Blessed is he who is enlarging Gad, || He dwells as a lioness, || And has torn the arm—also the crown! <verse eid="DEU 33:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 33:21"/>And he provides the first part for himself, || For there the portion of the lawgiver is covered, || And he comes [with] the heads of the people; He has done the righteousness of YHWH, || And His judgments with Israel. <verse eid="DEU 33:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 33:22"/>And of Dan he said: Dan [is] a lion’s whelp; He leaps from Bashan. <verse eid="DEU 33:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 33:23"/>And of Naphtali he said: O Naphtali, satisfied with pleasure, || And full of the blessing of YHWH, || Possess [the] west and [the] south. <verse eid="DEU 33:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 33:24"/>And of Asher he said: Asher [is] blessed with sons, || Let him be accepted by his brothers, || And dipping his foot in oil. <verse eid="DEU 33:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 33:25"/>Iron and bronze [are] your shoes, || And as your days—your strength. <verse eid="DEU 33:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 33:26"/>[There is] none like the God of Yeshurun, || Riding the heavens to your help, || And in His excellence the skies. <verse eid="DEU 33:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 33:27"/>The eternal God [is] a habitation, || And beneath [are] continuous arms. And He casts out the enemy from your presence and says, Destroy! <verse eid="DEU 33:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 33:28"/>And Israel dwells [in] confidence alone; The eye of Jacob [is] to a land of grain and wine; Also His heavens drop down dew. <verse eid="DEU 33:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 33:29"/>O your blessedness, O Israel! Who is like you? A people saved by YHWH, || The shield of your help, || And He who [is] the sword of your excellence! And your enemies are subdued for you, || And you tread on their high places.”<verse eid="DEU 33:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 33"/>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="DEU 34"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 34:1"/>And Moses goes up from the plains of Moab to Mount Nebo, the top of Pisgah, which [is] on the front of Jericho, and YHWH shows him all the land—Gilead to Dan, <verse eid="DEU 34:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 34:2"/>and all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim, and Manasseh, and all the land of Judah to the Western Sea, <verse eid="DEU 34:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 34:3"/>and the south, and the circuit of the Valley of Jericho, the city of palms, to Zoar. <verse eid="DEU 34:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 34:4"/>And YHWH says to him, “This [is] the land which I have sworn to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying, I give it to your seed; I have caused you to see with your eyes, but you do not pass over there.” <verse eid="DEU 34:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 34:5"/>And Moses, servant of the Lord, dies there in the land of Moab, according to the command of YHWH; <verse eid="DEU 34:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 34:6"/>and He buries him in a valley in the land of Moab, opposite Beth-Peor, and no man has known his burying place to this day. <verse eid="DEU 34:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 34:7"/>And Moses [is] a son of one hundred and twenty years when he dies; his eye has not become dim, nor has his moisture fled. <verse eid="DEU 34:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 34:8"/>And the sons of Israel lament Moses in the plains of Moab [for] thirty days; and the days of weeping [and] mourning for Moses are completed. <verse eid="DEU 34:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 34:9"/>And Joshua son of Nun is full of the spirit of wisdom, for Moses had laid his hands on him, and the sons of Israel listen to him, and do as YHWH commanded Moses. <verse eid="DEU 34:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 34:10"/>And there has not arisen a prophet in Israel like Moses anymore, whom YHWH has known face to face, <verse eid="DEU 34:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 34:11"/>in reference to all the signs and the wonders which YHWH sent him to do in the land of Egypt, to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land, <verse eid="DEU 34:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 34:12"/>and in reference to all the strong hand and to all the great fear which Moses did before the eyes of all Israel.<verse eid="DEU 34:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 34"/>
</usx>
