<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="EXO" style="id">- Literal Standard Version</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Exodus</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Book of Exodus</para>
  <para style="toc2">Exodus</para>
  <para style="toc3">Exo</para>
  <para style="mt">Exodus</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="EXO 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 1:1"/>And these [are] the names of the sons of Israel who are coming into Egypt; each man and his household have come with Jacob: <verse eid="EXO 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 1:2"/>Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, <verse eid="EXO 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 1:3"/>Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin, <verse eid="EXO 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 1:4"/>Dan, and Naphtali, Gad, and Asher. <verse eid="EXO 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 1:5"/>And all the persons coming out of the thigh of Jacob are seventy persons; as for Joseph, he was in Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 1:6"/>And Joseph dies, and all his brothers, and all that generation; <verse eid="EXO 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 1:7"/>and the sons of Israel have been fruitful, and they teem, and multiply, and are very, very mighty, and the land is filled with them. <verse eid="EXO 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 1:8"/>And there rises a new king over Egypt, who has not known Joseph, <verse eid="EXO 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 1:9"/>and he says to his people, “Behold, the people of the sons of Israel [are] more numerous and mighty than we. <verse eid="EXO 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 1:10"/>Give help! Let us act wisely concerning it, lest it multiply, and it has come to pass, when war happens, that it has been joined, even it, to those hating us, and has fought against us, and has gone up out of the land.” <verse eid="EXO 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 1:11"/>And they set princes of tribute over it, so as to afflict it with their burdens, and it builds the store-cities of Pithom and Rameses for Pharaoh; <verse eid="EXO 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 1:12"/>and as they afflict it, so it multiplies, and so it breaks forth, and they are distressed because of the sons of Israel; <verse eid="EXO 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 1:13"/>and the Egyptians cause the sons of Israel to serve with rigor, <verse eid="EXO 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 1:14"/>and make their lives bitter in hard service, in clay, and in brick, and in every [kind] of service in the field; all their service in which they have served [is] with rigor. <verse eid="EXO 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 1:15"/>And the king of Egypt speaks to the midwives, the Hebrewesses (of whom the name of the first [is] Shiphrah, and the name of the second Puah), <verse eid="EXO 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 1:16"/>and says, “When you cause the Hebrew women to bear, and have looked on the children, if it [is] a son, then you have put him to death; and if it [is] a daughter, then she has lived.” <verse eid="EXO 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 1:17"/>And the midwives fear God, and have not done as the king of Egypt has spoken to them, and they keep the boys alive; <verse eid="EXO 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 1:18"/>and the king of Egypt calls for the midwives and says to them, “Why have you done this thing, and keep the boys alive?” <verse eid="EXO 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 1:19"/>And the midwives say to Pharaoh, “Because the Hebrew women [are] not as the Egyptian women, for they [are] lively; before the midwife comes to them—they have borne!” <verse eid="EXO 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 1:20"/>And God does good to the midwives, and the people multiply, and are very mighty; <verse eid="EXO 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 1:21"/>and it comes to pass, because the midwives have feared God, that He makes households for them; <verse eid="EXO 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 1:22"/>and Pharaoh lays a charge on all his people, saying, “Every son who is born—you cast him into the River, and every daughter you keep alive.”<verse eid="EXO 1:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="EXO 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 2:1"/>And there goes a man of the house of Levi, and he takes the daughter of Levi, <verse eid="EXO 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 2:2"/>and the woman conceives, and bears a son, and she sees him, that he [is] beautiful, and she hides him [for] three months, <verse eid="EXO 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 2:3"/>and she has not been able to hide him anymore, and she takes an ark of rushes for him, and covers it with bitumen and with pitch, and puts the boy in it, and puts [it] in the weeds by the edge of the River; <verse eid="EXO 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 2:4"/>and his sister stations herself far off, to know what is done to him. <verse eid="EXO 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 2:5"/>And a daughter of Pharaoh comes down to bathe at the River, and her girls are walking by the side of the River, and she sees the ark in the midst of the weeds, and sends her handmaid, and she takes it, <verse eid="EXO 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 2:6"/>and opens, and sees him—the boy, and behold, a child weeping! And she has pity on him and says, “This is [one] of the Hebrews’ children.” <verse eid="EXO 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 2:7"/>And his sister says to the daughter of Pharaoh, “Do I go? When I have called a suckling woman of the Hebrews for you, then she suckles the boy for you”; <verse eid="EXO 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 2:8"/>and the daughter of Pharaoh says to her, “Go”; and the virgin goes, and calls the mother of the boy, <verse eid="EXO 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 2:9"/>and the daughter of Pharaoh says to her, “Take this boy away, and suckle him for me, and I give your hire”; and the woman takes the boy, and suckles him. <verse eid="EXO 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 2:10"/>And the boy grows, and she brings him to the daughter of Pharaoh, and he is to her for a son, and she calls his name Moses, and says, “Because I have drawn him from the water.” <verse eid="EXO 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 2:11"/>And it comes to pass, in those days, that Moses is grown, and he goes out to his brothers, and looks on their burdens, and sees a man, an Egyptian, striking a man, a Hebrew, [one] of his brothers, <verse eid="EXO 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 2:12"/>and he turns here and there, and sees that there is no man, and strikes the Egyptian, and hides him in the sand. <verse eid="EXO 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 2:13"/>And he goes out on the second day, and behold, two men, Hebrews, are striving, and he says to the wrongdoer, “Why do you strike your neighbor?” <verse eid="EXO 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 2:14"/>And he says, “Who set you for a head and judge over us? Are you saying [it] to slay me as you have slain the Egyptian?” And Moses fears and says, “Surely the thing has been known.” <verse eid="EXO 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 2:15"/>And Pharaoh hears of this thing, and seeks to slay Moses, and Moses flees from the face of Pharaoh, and dwells in the land of Midian, and dwells by the well. <verse eid="EXO 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 2:16"/>And to a priest of Midian [are] seven daughters, and they come and draw, and fill the troughs to water the flock of their father, <verse eid="EXO 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 2:17"/>and the shepherds come and drive them away, and Moses arises, and saves them, and waters their flock. <verse eid="EXO 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 2:18"/>And they come to their father Reuel, and he says, “Why have you hurried to come in today?” <verse eid="EXO 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 2:19"/>And they say, “A man, an Egyptian, has delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds, and has also diligently drawn for us, and waters the flock”; <verse eid="EXO 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 2:20"/>and he says to his daughters, “And where [is] he? Why [is] this [that] you left the man? Call for him, and he eats bread.” <verse eid="EXO 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 2:21"/>And Moses is willing to dwell with the man, and he gives his daughter Zipporah to Moses, <verse eid="EXO 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 2:22"/>and she bears a son, and he calls his name Gershom, for he said, “I have been a sojourner in a strange land.” <verse eid="EXO 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 2:23"/>And it comes to pass during these many days, that the king of Egypt dies, and the sons of Israel sigh because of the service, and cry, and their cry goes up to God, because of the service; <verse eid="EXO 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 2:24"/>and God hears their groaning, and God remembers His covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob; <verse eid="EXO 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 2:25"/>and God sees the sons of Israel, and God knows.<verse eid="EXO 2:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="EXO 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 3:1"/>And Moses has been feeding the flock of his father-in-law Jethro, priest of Midian, and he leads the flock behind the wilderness, and comes to the mountain of God, to Horeb; <verse eid="EXO 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 3:2"/>and the Messenger of YHWH appears to him in a flame of fire, out of the midst of the bush, and he sees, and behold, the bush is burning with fire, and the bush is not consumed. <verse eid="EXO 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 3:3"/>And Moses says, “Now I turn aside and see this great appearance. Why is the bush not burned?” <verse eid="EXO 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 3:4"/>And YHWH sees that he has turned aside to see, and God calls to him out of the midst of the bush and says, “Moses! Moses!” And he says, “Here I [am].” <verse eid="EXO 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 3:5"/>And He says, “Do not come near here. Cast your shoes from off your feet, for the place on which you are standing is holy ground.” <verse eid="EXO 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 3:6"/>He also says, “I [am] the God of your father, God of Abraham, God of Isaac, and God of Jacob”; and Moses hides his face, for he is afraid to look toward God. <verse eid="EXO 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 3:7"/>And YHWH says, “I have certainly seen the affliction of My people who [are] in Egypt, and I have heard their cry because of its exactors, for I have known its pains; <verse eid="EXO 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 3:8"/>and I go down to deliver it out of the hand of the Egyptians, and to cause it to go up out of the land to a land good and broad, to a land flowing with milk and honey—to the place of the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite. <verse eid="EXO 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 3:9"/>And now, behold, the cry of the sons of Israel has come to Me, and I have also seen the oppression with which the Egyptians are oppressing them, <verse eid="EXO 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 3:10"/>and now, come, and I send you to Pharaoh; and bring out My people, the sons of Israel, from Egypt.” <verse eid="EXO 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 3:11"/>And Moses says to God, “Who [am] I, that I go to Pharaoh, and that I bring out the sons of Israel from Egypt?” <verse eid="EXO 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 3:12"/>And He says, “Because I am with you, and this [is] the sign to you that I have sent you: in your bringing out the people from Egypt—you serve God on this mountain.” <verse eid="EXO 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 3:13"/>And Moses says to God, “Behold, I am coming to the sons of Israel, and have said to them, The God of your fathers has sent me to you, and they have said to me, What [is] His Name? What do I say to them?” <verse eid="EXO 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 3:14"/>And God says to Moses, “I AM THAT WHICH I AM.” He also says, “Thus you say to the sons of Israel: I AM has sent me to you.” <verse eid="EXO 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 3:15"/>And God says again to Moses, “Thus you say to the sons of Israel: YHWH, God of your fathers, God of Abraham, God of Isaac, and God of Jacob, has sent me to you; this [is] My Name for all time, and this [is] My memorial, to generation [and] generation. <verse eid="EXO 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 3:16"/>Go, and you have gathered the elderly of Israel, and have said to them: YHWH, God of your fathers, has appeared to me, God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, saying, I have certainly inspected you, and that which is done to you in Egypt; <verse eid="EXO 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 3:17"/>and I say [that] I bring you up out of the affliction of Egypt to the land of the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite, to a land flowing [with] milk and honey. <verse eid="EXO 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 3:18"/>And they have listened to your voice, and you have entered, you and [the] elderly of Israel, to the king of Egypt, and you have said to him: YHWH, God of the Hebrews, has met with us; and now, please let us go a journey of three days into the wilderness, and we sacrifice to our God YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 3:19"/>And I have known that the king of Egypt does not permit you to go, unless by a strong hand, <verse eid="EXO 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 3:20"/>and I have put forth My hand, and have struck Egypt with all My wonders, which I do in its midst—and afterward he sends you away. <verse eid="EXO 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 3:21"/>And I have given the grace of this people in the eyes of the Egyptians, and it has come to pass, when you go, you do not go empty; <verse eid="EXO 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 3:22"/>and [every] woman has asked from her neighbor, and from her who is sojourning in her house, [for] vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and garments, and you have put [them] on your sons and on your daughters, and have spoiled the Egyptians.”<verse eid="EXO 3:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="EXO 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 4:1"/>And Moses answers and says, “And if they do not give credence to me, nor listen to my voice, and say, YHWH has not appeared to you?” <verse eid="EXO 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 4:2"/>And YHWH says to him, “What [is] this in your hand?” And he says, “A rod”; <verse eid="EXO 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 4:3"/>and He says, “Cast it to the earth”; and he casts it to the earth, and it becomes a serpent—and Moses flees from its presence. <verse eid="EXO 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 4:4"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Put forth your hand, and lay hold on the tail of it”; and he puts forth his hand, and lays hold on it, and it becomes a rod in his hand— <verse eid="EXO 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 4:5"/>“so that they believe that YHWH, God of their fathers, has appeared to you, God of Abraham, God of Isaac, and God of Jacob.” <verse eid="EXO 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 4:6"/>And YHWH says to him again, “Now put your hand into your bosom”; and he puts his hand into his bosom, and he brings it out, and behold, his hand [is] leprous as snow; <verse eid="EXO 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 4:7"/>and He says, “Put your hand back into your bosom”; and he puts his hand back into his bosom, and he brings it out from his bosom, and behold, it has turned back as his flesh— <verse eid="EXO 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 4:8"/>“and it has come to pass, if they do not give credence to you, and do not listen to the voice of the first sign, that they have given credence to the voice of the latter sign. <verse eid="EXO 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 4:9"/>And it has come to pass, if they do not give credence even to these two signs, nor listen to your voice, that you have taken of the waters of the River, and have poured [it] on the dry land, and the waters which you take from the River have been, indeed, they have become blood on the dry land.” <verse eid="EXO 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 4:10"/>And Moses says to YHWH, “O my Lord, I [am] not a man of words, either yesterday, or before, or since Your speaking to Your servant, for I [am] slow of mouth, and slow of tongue.” <verse eid="EXO 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 4:11"/>And YHWH says to him, “Who appointed a mouth for man? Or who appoints the mute, or deaf, or open, or blind? Is it not I, YHWH? <verse eid="EXO 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 4:12"/>And now, go, and I am with your mouth, and have directed you that which you speak”; <verse eid="EXO 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 4:13"/>and he says, “O my Lord, please send by the hand [of another that] You send.” <verse eid="EXO 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 4:14"/>And the anger of YHWH burns against Moses, and He says, “Is Aaron the Levite not your brother? I have known that he speaks well, and also, behold, he is coming out to meet you; when he has seen you, then he has rejoiced in his heart, <verse eid="EXO 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 4:15"/>and you have spoken to him, and have set the words in his mouth, and I am with your mouth, and with his mouth, and have directed you that which you do; <verse eid="EXO 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 4:16"/>and he, he has spoken to the people for you, and it has come to pass, he is to you for a mouth, and you are to him for God; <verse eid="EXO 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 4:17"/>and you take this rod in your hand, with which you do the signs.” <verse eid="EXO 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 4:18"/>And Moses goes and turns back to his father-in-law Jethro, and says to him, “Please let me go, and I return to my brothers who [are] in Egypt, and I see whether they are yet alive.” And Jethro says to Moses, “Go in peace.” <verse eid="EXO 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 4:19"/>And YHWH says to Moses in Midian, “Go, return to Egypt, for all the men who seek your life have died”; <verse eid="EXO 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 4:20"/>and Moses takes his wife, and his sons, and causes them to ride on the donkey, and turns back to the land of Egypt, and Moses takes the rod of God in his hand. <verse eid="EXO 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 4:21"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “In your going to return to Egypt, see—all the wonders which I have put in your hand—that you have done them before Pharaoh, and I strengthen his heart, and he does not send the people away; <verse eid="EXO 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 4:22"/>and you have said to Pharaoh, Thus said YHWH: My son, My firstborn [is] Israel, <verse eid="EXO 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 4:23"/>and I say to you, send My son away, and he serves Me; and [if] you refuse to send him away, behold, I am slaying your son, your firstborn.” <verse eid="EXO 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 4:24"/>And it comes to pass in the way, in a lodging place, that YHWH meets him, and seeks to put him to death; <verse eid="EXO 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 4:25"/>and Zipporah takes a flint, and cuts off the foreskin of her son, and causes [it] to touch his feet, and says, “You [are] surely a bridegroom of blood to me”; <verse eid="EXO 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 4:26"/>and He desists from him. Then she said, “A bridegroom of blood,” in reference to the circumcision. <verse eid="EXO 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 4:27"/>And YHWH says to Aaron, “Go into the wilderness to meet Moses”; and he goes, and meets him on the mountain of God, and kisses him, <verse eid="EXO 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 4:28"/>and Moses declares to Aaron all the words of YHWH with which He has sent him, and all the signs with which He has charged him. <verse eid="EXO 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 4:29"/>And Moses goes—Aaron also—and they gather all the elderly of the sons of Israel, <verse eid="EXO 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 4:30"/>and Aaron speaks all the words which YHWH has spoken to Moses, and does the signs before the eyes of the people; <verse eid="EXO 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 4:31"/>and the people believe when they hear that YHWH has looked after the sons of Israel, and that He has seen their affliction; and they bow and pay respect.<verse eid="EXO 4:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="EXO 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 5:1"/>And afterward Moses and Aaron have entered, and they say to Pharaoh, “Thus said YHWH, God of Israel: Send My people away, and they keep a celebration for Me in the wilderness”; <verse eid="EXO 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 5:2"/>and Pharaoh says, “Who [is] YHWH, that I listen to His voice to send Israel away? I have not known YHWH, and I also do not send Israel away.” <verse eid="EXO 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 5:3"/>And they say, “The God of the Hebrews has met with us; please let us go a journey of three days into the wilderness, and we sacrifice to our God YHWH, lest He meet us with pestilence or with sword.” <verse eid="EXO 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 5:4"/>And the king of Egypt says to them, “Why, Moses and Aaron, do you free the people from its works? Go to your burdens.” <verse eid="EXO 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 5:5"/>Pharaoh also says, “Behold, the people of the land [are] numerous now, and you have caused them to cease from their burdens!” <verse eid="EXO 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 5:6"/>And on that day Pharaoh commands the exactors among the people and its authorities, saying, <verse eid="EXO 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 5:7"/>“You do not add to give straw to the people for the making of the bricks as before—they go and have gathered straw for themselves; <verse eid="EXO 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 5:8"/>and you put on them the proper quantity of the bricks which they are making before, you do not diminish from it, for they are remiss, therefore they are crying, saying, Let us go, let us sacrifice to our God; <verse eid="EXO 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 5:9"/>let the service be heavy on the men, and let them work at it, and not be dazzled by lying words.” <verse eid="EXO 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 5:10"/>And the exactors of the people, and its authorities, go out, and speak to the people, saying, “Thus said Pharaoh: I do not give you straw, <verse eid="EXO 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 5:11"/>you—go, take straw for yourselves where you can find [it], for there is nothing diminished of your service.” <verse eid="EXO 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 5:12"/>And the people are scattered over all the land of Egypt, to gather stubble for straw, <verse eid="EXO 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 5:13"/>and the exactors are making haste, saying, “Complete your works, the matter of a day in its day, as when there is straw.” <verse eid="EXO 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 5:14"/>And the authorities of the sons of Israel, whom the exactors of Pharaoh have placed over them, are beaten, saying, “Why have you not completed your portion in making brick as before, both yesterday and today?” <verse eid="EXO 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 5:15"/>And the authorities of the sons of Israel come in and cry to Pharaoh, saying, “Why do you do thus to your servants? <verse eid="EXO 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 5:16"/>Straw is not given to your servants, and they are saying to us, Make bricks, and behold, your servants are struck—and your people have sinned.” <verse eid="EXO 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 5:17"/>And he says, “Remiss—you are remiss, therefore you are saying, Let us go, let us sacrifice to YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 5:18"/>and now, go, serve; and straw is not given to you, and you give the [required] measure of bricks.” <verse eid="EXO 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 5:19"/>And the authorities of the sons of Israel see them in affliction, saying, “You do not diminish from your bricks; the matter of a day in its day.” <verse eid="EXO 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 5:20"/>And they meet Moses and Aaron standing to meet them in their coming out from Pharaoh, <verse eid="EXO 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 5:21"/>and say to them, “YHWH look on you, and judge, because you have caused our fragrance to stink in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of his servants—to give a sword into their hand to slay us.” <verse eid="EXO 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 5:22"/>And Moses turns back to YHWH and says, “Lord, why have You done evil to this people? Why [is] this [that] You have sent me? <verse eid="EXO 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 5:23"/>And since I have come to Pharaoh to speak in Your Name, he has done evil to this people, and You have not delivered Your people at all.”<verse eid="EXO 5:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="EXO 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 6:1"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Now you see that which I do to Pharaoh, for with a strong hand he sends them away, indeed, with a strong hand he casts them out of his land.” <verse eid="EXO 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 6:2"/>And God speaks to Moses and says to him, “I [am] YHWH, <verse eid="EXO 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 6:3"/>and I appear to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, as God Almighty; as for My Name YHWH, I have not been known to them; <verse eid="EXO 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 6:4"/>and I have also established My covenant with them, to give the land of Canaan to them, the land of their sojournings, wherein they have sojourned; <verse eid="EXO 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 6:5"/>and I have also heard the groaning of the sons of Israel, whom the Egyptians are causing to serve, and I remember My covenant. <verse eid="EXO 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 6:6"/>Therefore say to the sons of Israel: I [am] YHWH, and I have brought you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians, and have delivered you from their service, and have redeemed you by an outstretched arm, and by great judgments, <verse eid="EXO 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 6:7"/>and have taken you to Myself for a people, and I have been to you for God, and you have known that I [am] your God YHWH, who is bringing you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians; <verse eid="EXO 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 6:8"/>and I have brought you to the land which I have lifted up My hand to give it to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, and have given it to you—a possession; I [am] YHWH.” <verse eid="EXO 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 6:9"/>And Moses speaks so to the sons of Israel, and they did not listen to Moses, for anguish of spirit, and for harsh service. <verse eid="EXO 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 6:10"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 6:11"/>“Go in, speak to Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he sends the sons of Israel out of his land”; <verse eid="EXO 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 6:12"/>and Moses speaks before YHWH, saying, “Behold, the sons of Israel have not listened to me, and how does Pharaoh hear me, and I of uncircumcised lips?” <verse eid="EXO 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 6:13"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses and to Aaron, and charges them for the sons of Israel, and for Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 6:14"/>These [are] heads of the house of their fathers. Sons of Reuben firstborn of Israel: Enoch, and Phallu, Hezron, and Carmi; these [are] families of Reuben. <verse eid="EXO 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 6:15"/>And sons of Simeon: Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul, son of the Canaanite; these [are] families of Simeon. <verse eid="EXO 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 6:16"/>And these [are] the names of the sons of Levi, as to their births: Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari; and the years of the life of Levi [are] one hundred and thirty-seven years. <verse eid="EXO 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 6:17"/>The sons of Gershon: Libni and Shimi, as to their families. <verse eid="EXO 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 6:18"/>And the sons of Kohath: Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel; and the years of the life of Kohath [are] one hundred and thirty-three years. <verse eid="EXO 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 6:19"/>And the sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; these [are] families of Levi, as to their births. <verse eid="EXO 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 6:20"/>And Amram takes his aunt Jochebed to himself for a wife, and she bears Aaron and Moses to him; and the years of the life of Amram [are] one hundred and thirty-seven years. <verse eid="EXO 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 6:21"/>And sons of Izhar: Korah, and Nepheg, and Zichri. <verse eid="EXO 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 6:22"/>And sons of Uzziel: Mishael, and Elzaphan, and Sithri. <verse eid="EXO 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 6:23"/>And Aaron takes Elisheba daughter of Amminadab, sister of Naashon, to himself for a wife, and she bears to him Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. <verse eid="EXO 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 6:24"/>And sons of Korah: Assir, and Elkanah, and Abiasaph; these [are] families of the Korahite. <verse eid="EXO 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 6:25"/>And Eleazar, Aaron’s son, has taken to himself [one] of the daughters of Putiel for a wife for himself, and she bears Phinehas to him; these [are] heads of the fathers of the Levites, as to their families. <verse eid="EXO 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 6:26"/>This [is] Aaron—and Moses—to whom YHWH said, “Bring out the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt, by their hosts”; <verse eid="EXO 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 6:27"/>these are they who are speaking to Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the sons of Israel from Egypt, this [is] Moses—and Aaron. <verse eid="EXO 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 6:28"/>And it comes to pass in the day of YHWH’s speaking to Moses in the land of Egypt, <verse eid="EXO 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 6:29"/>that YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, “I [am] YHWH, speak to Pharaoh king of Egypt all that I am speaking to you.” <verse eid="EXO 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 6:30"/>And Moses says before YHWH, “Behold, I [am] of uncircumcised lips, and how does Pharaoh listen to me?”<verse eid="EXO 6:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="EXO 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 7:1"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “See, I have given you [as] a god to Pharaoh, and your brother Aaron is your prophet; <verse eid="EXO 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 7:2"/>you speak all that I command you, and your brother Aaron speaks to Pharaoh, and he has sent the sons of Israel out of his land. <verse eid="EXO 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 7:3"/>And I harden the heart of Pharaoh, and have multiplied My signs and My wonders in the land of Egypt, <verse eid="EXO 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 7:4"/>and Pharaoh does not listen, and I have put My hand on Egypt, and have brought out My hosts, My people, the sons of Israel, from the land of Egypt by great judgments; <verse eid="EXO 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 7:5"/>and the Egyptians have known that I [am] YHWH, in My stretching out My hand against Egypt; and I have brought out the sons of Israel from their midst.” <verse eid="EXO 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 7:6"/>And Moses does—Aaron also—as YHWH commanded them; so have they done; <verse eid="EXO 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 7:7"/>and Moses [is] a son of eighty years, and Aaron [is] a son of eighty-three years, in their speaking to Pharaoh. <verse eid="EXO 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 7:8"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse eid="EXO 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 7:9"/>“When Pharaoh speaks to you, saying, Give a wonder for yourselves; then you have said to Aaron, Take your rod and cast [it] before Pharaoh—it becomes a dragon.” <verse eid="EXO 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 7:10"/>And Moses goes in—Aaron also—to Pharaoh, and they do so as YHWH has commanded; and Aaron casts his rod before Pharaoh and before his servants, and it becomes a dragon. <verse eid="EXO 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 7:11"/>And Pharaoh also calls for wise men and for sorcerers; and the enchanters of Egypt, they also, with their [enchanting] flames, do so, <verse eid="EXO 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 7:12"/>and they each cast down his rod, and they become dragons, and the rod of Aaron swallows their rods; <verse eid="EXO 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 7:13"/>and the heart of Pharaoh is strong, and he has not listened to them, as YHWH has spoken. <verse eid="EXO 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 7:14"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “The heart of Pharaoh has been hard, he has refused to send the people away; <verse eid="EXO 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 7:15"/>go to Pharaoh in the morning, behold, he is going out to the water, and you have stood to meet him by the edge of the River, and the rod which was turned to a serpent you take in your hand, <verse eid="EXO 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 7:16"/>and you have said to him: YHWH, God of the Hebrews, has sent me to you, saying, Send My people away, and they serve Me in the wilderness; and behold, you have not listened until now. <verse eid="EXO 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 7:17"/>Thus said YHWH: By this you know that I [am] YHWH; behold, I am striking with the rod which [is] in my hand, on the waters which [are] in the River, and they have been turned to blood, <verse eid="EXO 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 7:18"/>and the fish that [are] in the River die, and the River has stunk, and the Egyptians have been wearied of drinking waters from the River.” <verse eid="EXO 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 7:19"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Say to Aaron, Take your rod, and stretch out your hand against the waters of Egypt, against their streams, against their rivers, and against their ponds, and against all their collections of waters; and they are blood—and there has been blood in all the land of Egypt, both in [vessels of] wood, and in [those of] stone.” <verse eid="EXO 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 7:20"/>And Moses and Aaron do so, as YHWH has commanded, and he lifts up [his hand] with the rod, and strikes the waters which [are] in the River, before the eyes of Pharaoh and before the eyes of his servants, and all the waters which [are] in the River are turned to blood, <verse eid="EXO 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 7:21"/>and the fish which [is] in the River has died, and the River stinks, and the Egyptians have not been able to drink water from the River; and the blood is in all the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 7:22"/>And the enchanters of Egypt do so with their secrets, and the heart of Pharaoh is strong, and he has not listened to them, as YHWH has spoken, <verse eid="EXO 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 7:23"/>and Pharaoh turns and goes into his house, and has not set his heart even to this; <verse eid="EXO 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 7:24"/>and all the Egyptians seek water all around the River to drink, for they have not been able to drink of the waters of the River. <verse eid="EXO 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 7:25"/>And seven days are completed after YHWH’s striking the River.<verse eid="EXO 7:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="EXO 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 8:1"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Go to Pharaoh, and you have said to him, Thus said YHWH: Send My people away, and they serve Me; <verse eid="EXO 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 8:2"/>and if you are refusing to send [them] away, behold, I am striking all your border with frogs; <verse eid="EXO 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 8:3"/>and the River has teemed [with] frogs, and they have gone up and gone into your house, and into the inner-chamber of your bed, and on your couch, and into the house of your servants, and among your people, and into your ovens, and into your kneading-troughs; <verse eid="EXO 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 8:4"/>indeed, on you, and on your people, and on all your servants the frogs go up.” <verse eid="EXO 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 8:5"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Say to Aaron, Stretch out your hand, with your rod, against the streams, against the rivers, and against the ponds, and cause the frogs to come up against the land of Egypt.” <verse eid="EXO 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 8:6"/>And Aaron stretches out his hand against the waters of Egypt, and the frog comes up, and covers the land of Egypt; <verse eid="EXO 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 8:7"/>and the enchanters do so with their secrets, and cause the frogs to come up against the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 8:8"/>And Pharaoh calls for Moses and for Aaron and says, “Make supplication to YHWH, that he may turn aside the frogs from me, and from my people, and I send the people away, and they sacrifice to YHWH.” <verse eid="EXO 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 8:9"/>And Moses says to Pharaoh, “Beautify yourself over me; when do I make supplication for you, and for your servants, and for your people, to cut off the frogs from you and from your houses—only in the River they remain?” <verse eid="EXO 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 8:10"/>And he says, “Tomorrow.” And he says, “According to your word [it is], so that you know that there is none like our God YHWH, <verse eid="EXO 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 8:11"/>and the frogs have turned aside from you, and from your houses, and from your servants, and from your people; only in the River they remain.” <verse eid="EXO 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 8:12"/>And Moses—Aaron also—goes out from Pharaoh, and Moses cries to YHWH concerning the matter of the frogs which He has set on Pharaoh; <verse eid="EXO 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 8:13"/>and YHWH does according to the word of Moses, and the frogs die out of the houses, out of the courts, and out of the fields, <verse eid="EXO 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 8:14"/>and they heap them up together, and the land stinks. <verse eid="EXO 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 8:15"/>And Pharaoh sees that there has been a respite, and he has hardened his heart, and has not listened to them, as YHWH has spoken. <verse eid="EXO 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 8:16"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Say to Aaron, Stretch out your rod, and strike the dust of the land, and it has become gnats in all the land of Egypt.” <verse eid="EXO 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 8:17"/>And they do so, and Aaron stretches out his hand with his rod, and strikes the dust of the land, and the gnats are on man and on beast; all the dust of the land has been gnats in all the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 8:18"/>And the enchanters do so with their secrets, to bring out the gnats, and they have not been able, and the gnats are on man and on beast; <verse eid="EXO 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 8:19"/>and the enchanters say to Pharaoh, “It [is] the finger of God”; and the heart of Pharaoh is strong, and he has not listened to them, as YHWH has spoken. <verse eid="EXO 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 8:20"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Rise early in the morning, and station yourself before Pharaoh, behold, he is going out to the waters, and you have said to him, Thus said YHWH: Send My people away, and they serve Me; <verse eid="EXO 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 8:21"/>for if you are not sending My people away, behold, I am sending against you, and against your servants, and against your people, and against your houses, the beetle, and the houses of the Egyptians have been full of the beetle, and also the ground on which they are. <verse eid="EXO 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 8:22"/>And I have separated in that day the land of Goshen, in which My people are staying, that the beetle is not there, so that you know that I [am] YHWH in the midst of the land, <verse eid="EXO 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 8:23"/>and I have put a division between My people and your people; this sign is tomorrow.” <verse eid="EXO 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 8:24"/>And YHWH does so, and the grievous beetle enters the house of Pharaoh, and the house of his servants, and in all the land of Egypt the land is corrupted from the presence of the beetle. <verse eid="EXO 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 8:25"/>And Pharaoh calls to Moses and to Aaron and says, “Go, sacrifice to your God in the land”; <verse eid="EXO 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 8:26"/>and Moses says, “[It is] not right to do so—for us to sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians to our God YHWH; behold, we sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians before their eyes—and they do not stone us! <verse eid="EXO 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 8:27"/>We go a journey of three days into the wilderness and have sacrificed to our God YHWH as He says to us.” <verse eid="EXO 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 8:28"/>And Pharaoh says, “I send you away, and you have sacrificed to your God YHWH in the wilderness, only do not go very far off; make supplication for me”; <verse eid="EXO 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 8:29"/>and Moses says, “Behold, I am going out from you, and have made supplication to YHWH, and tomorrow the beetle has turned aside from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people; only, do not let Pharaoh add to deceive in not sending the people away to sacrifice to YHWH.” <verse eid="EXO 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 8:30"/>And Moses goes out from Pharaoh, and makes supplication to YHWH, <verse eid="EXO 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 8:31"/>and YHWH does according to the word of Moses, and turns aside the beetle from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people—there has not been one left; <verse eid="EXO 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 8:32"/>and Pharaoh also hardens his heart at this time, and has not sent the people away.<verse eid="EXO 8:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="EXO 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 9:1"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Go to Pharaoh, and you have spoken to him, Thus said YHWH, God of the Hebrews: Send My people away, and they serve Me, <verse eid="EXO 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 9:2"/>for if you are refusing to send [them] away, and are still keeping hold on them, <verse eid="EXO 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 9:3"/>behold, the hand of YHWH is on your livestock which [are] in the field, on horses, on donkeys, on camels, on herd, and on flock—a very grievous pestilence. <verse eid="EXO 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 9:4"/>And YHWH has separated between the livestock of Israel and the livestock of Egypt, and there does not die a thing of all the sons of Israel; <verse eid="EXO 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 9:5"/>and YHWH sets an appointed time, saying, Tomorrow YHWH does this thing in the land.” <verse eid="EXO 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 9:6"/>And YHWH does this thing on the next day, and all the livestock of Egypt die, and of the livestock of the sons of Israel not one has died; <verse eid="EXO 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 9:7"/>and Pharaoh sends, and behold, not even one of the livestock of Israel has died, and the heart of Pharaoh is hard, and he has not sent the people away. <verse eid="EXO 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 9:8"/>And YHWH says to Moses and to Aaron, “Take for yourselves the fullness of your handfuls—soot of a furnace, and Moses has sprinkled it toward the heavens, before the eyes of Pharaoh, <verse eid="EXO 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 9:9"/>and it has become small dust over all the land of Egypt, and it has become on man and on livestock a boil breaking forth [with] blisters in all the land of Egypt.” <verse eid="EXO 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 9:10"/>And they take the soot of the furnace, and stand before Pharaoh, and Moses sprinkles it toward the heavens, and it is a boil [with] blisters breaking forth on man and on beast; <verse eid="EXO 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 9:11"/>and the enchanters have not been able to stand before Moses because of the boil, for the boil has been on the enchanters, and on all the Egyptians. <verse eid="EXO 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 9:12"/>And YHWH strengthens the heart of Pharaoh, and he has not listened to them, as YHWH has spoken to Moses. <verse eid="EXO 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 9:13"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Rise early in the morning, and station yourself before Pharaoh, and you have said to him, Thus said YHWH, God of the Hebrews: Send My people away, and they serve Me, <verse eid="EXO 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 9:14"/>for at this time I am sending all My plagues to your heart, and on your servants, and on your people, so that you know that there is none like Me in all the earth, <verse eid="EXO 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 9:15"/>for now I have put forth My hand, and I strike you, and your people, with pestilence, and you are hidden from the earth. <verse eid="EXO 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 9:16"/>And yet for this I have caused you to stand, so as to show you My power, and for the sake of declaring My Name in all the earth; <verse eid="EXO 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 9:17"/>still you are exalting yourself against My people—so as not to send them away; <verse eid="EXO 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 9:18"/>behold, I am raining very grievous hail about [this] time tomorrow, such as has not been in Egypt from the day of its founding and until now. <verse eid="EXO 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 9:19"/>And now, send, strengthen your livestock and all that you have in the field; every man and beast which is found in the field, and is not gathered into the house—the hail has come down on them, and they have died.” <verse eid="EXO 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 9:20"/>He who is fearing the word of YHWH among the servants of Pharaoh has caused his servants and his livestock to flee to the houses; <verse eid="EXO 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 9:21"/>and he who has not set his heart to the word of YHWH leaves his servants and his livestock in the field. <verse eid="EXO 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 9:22"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Stretch forth your hand toward the heavens, and there is hail in all the land of Egypt, on man, and on beast, and on every herb of the field in the land of Egypt.” <verse eid="EXO 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 9:23"/>And Moses stretches out his rod toward the heavens, and YHWH has given voices and hail, and fire goes toward the earth, and YHWH rains hail on the land of Egypt, <verse eid="EXO 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 9:24"/>and there is hail, and fire catching itself in the midst of the hail, very grievous, such as has not been in all the land of Egypt since it has become a nation. <verse eid="EXO 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 9:25"/>And the hail strikes all that [is] in the field in all the land of Egypt, from man even to beast, and the hail has struck every herb of the field, and it has broken every tree of the field; <verse eid="EXO 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 9:26"/>only in the land of Goshen, where the sons of Israel [are], there has been no hail. <verse eid="EXO 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 9:27"/>And Pharaoh sends, and calls for Moses and for Aaron, and says to them, “I have sinned this time—YHWH [is] the righteous, and I and my people [are] the wicked, <verse eid="EXO 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 9:28"/>make supplication to YHWH, and plead that there be no voices of God and hail, and I send you away, and you do not add to remain.” <verse eid="EXO 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 9:29"/>And Moses says to him, “At my going out of the city, I spread my palms to YHWH—the voices cease, and there is no more hail, so that you know that the earth [is] YHWH’s; <verse eid="EXO 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 9:30"/>but you and your servants—I have known that you are not yet afraid of the face of YHWH God.” <verse eid="EXO 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 9:31"/>And the flax and the barley have been struck, for the barley [is] budding, and the flax forming flowers, <verse eid="EXO 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 9:32"/>and the wheat and the rye have not been struck, for they are late. <verse eid="EXO 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 9:33"/>And Moses goes out from Pharaoh, [from] the city, and spreads his hands to YHWH, and the voices and the hail cease, and rain has not been poured out to the earth; <verse eid="EXO 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 9:34"/>and Pharaoh sees that the rain has ceased, and the hail and the voices, and he continues to sin, and hardens his heart, he and his servants; <verse eid="EXO 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 9:35"/>and the heart of Pharaoh is strong, and he has not sent the sons of Israel away, as YHWH has spoken by the hand of Moses.<verse eid="EXO 9:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="EXO 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 10:1"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Go to Pharaoh, for I have declared his heart hard, and the heart of his servants, so that I set these signs of Mine in their midst, <verse eid="EXO 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 10:2"/>and so that you recount in the ears of your son, and of your son’s son, that which I have done in Egypt, and My signs which I have set among them, and you have known that I [am] YHWH.” <verse eid="EXO 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 10:3"/>And Moses comes in—Aaron also—to Pharaoh, and they say to him, “Thus said YHWH, God of the Hebrews: Until when have you refused to be humbled at My presence? Send My people away, and they serve Me, <verse eid="EXO 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 10:4"/>for if you are refusing to send My people away, behold, tomorrow I am bringing in the locust into your border, <verse eid="EXO 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 10:5"/>and it has covered the eye of the land, and none is able to see the land, and it has eaten the remnant of that which is escaped, which is left to you from the hail, and it has eaten every tree which is springing out of the field for you; <verse eid="EXO 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 10:6"/>and they have filled your houses, and the houses of all your servants, and the houses of all the Egyptians, which neither your fathers nor your father’s fathers have seen, since the day of their being on the ground to this day.” And he turns and goes out from Pharaoh. <verse eid="EXO 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 10:7"/>And the servants of Pharaoh say to him, “Until when does this [one] become a snare to us? Send the men away, and they serve their God YHWH; do you not yet know that Egypt has perished?” <verse eid="EXO 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 10:8"/>And Moses is brought back—Aaron also—to Pharaoh, and he says to them, “Go, serve your God YHWH, but who—who [are] those going?” <verse eid="EXO 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 10:9"/>And Moses says, “With our young ones, and with our aged ones, we go, with our sons, and with our daughters, with our flock, and our herd, we go, for we have a festival to YHWH.” <verse eid="EXO 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 10:10"/>And he says to them, “Be it so, YHWH [is] with you when I send you and your infants away; see—for evil [is] before your faces. <verse eid="EXO 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 10:11"/>Not so! Go now, you who [are] men, and serve YHWH, for that you are seeking”; and [one] casts them out from the presence of Pharaoh. <verse eid="EXO 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 10:12"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Stretch out your hand against the land of Egypt for the locust, and it goes up against the land of Egypt, and eats every herb of the land—all that the hail has left.” <verse eid="EXO 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 10:13"/>And Moses stretches out his rod against the land of Egypt, and YHWH has led an east wind over the land all that day, and all the night; the morning has been, and the east wind has lifted up the locust. <verse eid="EXO 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 10:14"/>And the locust goes up against all the land of Egypt, and rests in all the border of Egypt—very grievous: before it there has not been such a locust as it, and after it there is none such; <verse eid="EXO 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 10:15"/>and it covers the eye of all the land, and the land is darkened; and it eats every herb of the land, and all the fruit of the trees which the hail has left, and there has not been left any green thing in the trees, or in the herb of the field, in all the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 10:16"/>And Pharaoh hurries to call for Moses and for Aaron and says, “I have sinned against your God YHWH, and against you, <verse eid="EXO 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 10:17"/>and now, please bear with my sin, only this time, and make supplication to your God YHWH, that He may turn aside from off me only this death.” <verse eid="EXO 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 10:18"/>And he goes out from Pharaoh, and makes supplication to YHWH, <verse eid="EXO 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 10:19"/>and YHWH turns a very strong sea wind, and it lifts up the locust, and blows it into the Red Sea—there has not been left one locust in all the border of Egypt; <verse eid="EXO 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 10:20"/>and YHWH strengthens the heart of Pharaoh, and he has not sent the sons of Israel away. <verse eid="EXO 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 10:21"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Stretch out your hand toward the heavens, and there is darkness over the land of Egypt, and the darkness is felt.” <verse eid="EXO 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 10:22"/>And Moses stretches out his hand toward the heavens, and there is darkness—thick darkness in all the land of Egypt [for] three days; <verse eid="EXO 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 10:23"/>they have not seen one another, and none has risen from his place [for] three days; but there has been light for all the sons of Israel in their dwellings. <verse eid="EXO 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 10:24"/>And Pharaoh calls to Moses and says, “Go, serve YHWH, only your flock and your herd are stayed, your infants also go with you”; <verse eid="EXO 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 10:25"/>and Moses says, “You also give sacrifices and burnt-offerings in our hand, and we have prepared for our God YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 10:26"/>and also our livestock go with us—there is not left a hoof, for we take from it to serve our God YHWH; and we do not know how we serve YHWH until our going there.” <verse eid="EXO 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 10:27"/>And YHWH strengthens the heart of Pharaoh, and he has not been willing to send them away; <verse eid="EXO 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 10:28"/>and Pharaoh says to him, “Go from me, take heed to yourself, do not add to see my face, for in the day you see my face you die”; <verse eid="EXO 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 10:29"/>and Moses says, “You have spoken correctly, I do not add to see your face anymore.”<verse eid="EXO 10:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="EXO 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 11:1"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “One more plague I bring in on Pharaoh and on Egypt, afterward he sends you away from this; when he is sending you away, he surely casts you out from this [place] altogether; <verse eid="EXO 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 11:2"/>now speak in the ears of the people, and they ask—each man from his neighbor, and each woman from her neighbor—[for] vessels of silver and vessels of gold.” <verse eid="EXO 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 11:3"/>And YHWH gives the grace of the people in the eyes of the Egyptians; also the man Moses [is] very great in the land of Egypt, in the eyes of the servants of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of the people. <verse eid="EXO 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 11:4"/>And Moses says, “Thus said YHWH: About midnight I am going out into the midst of Egypt, <verse eid="EXO 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 11:5"/>and every firstborn in the land of Egypt has died, from the firstborn of Pharaoh who is sitting on his throne, to the firstborn of the maidservant who [is] behind the millstones, and all the firstborn of beasts; <verse eid="EXO 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 11:6"/>and there has been a great cry in all the land of Egypt, such as there has not been, and such as there is not again; <verse eid="EXO 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 11:7"/>and against all the sons of Israel a dog does not sharpen its tongue, from man even to beast, so that you know that YHWH makes a separation between the Egyptians and Israel. <verse eid="EXO 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 11:8"/>And all these servants of yours have come down to me, and bowed themselves to me, saying, Go out, you and all the people who [are] at your feet; and afterward I go out”; and he goes out from Pharaoh in the heat of anger. <verse eid="EXO 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 11:9"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Pharaoh does not listen to you, so as to multiply My wonders in the land of Egypt”; <verse eid="EXO 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 11:10"/>and Moses and Aaron have done all these wonders before Pharaoh, and YHWH strengthens Pharaoh’s heart, and he has not sent the sons of Israel out of his land.<verse eid="EXO 11:10"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="EXO 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 12:1"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses and to Aaron in the land of Egypt, saying, <verse eid="EXO 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 12:2"/>“This month [is] the chief of months to you—it [is] the first of the months of the year to you; <verse eid="EXO 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 12:3"/>speak to all the congregation of Israel, saying, In the tenth of this month they take to themselves, each man, a lamb for the house of the fathers, a lamb for a house. <verse eid="EXO 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 12:4"/>And if the household is too few for a lamb, then he has taken, he and his neighbor who is near to his house, for the number of persons, each according to his eating you count for the lamb. <verse eid="EXO 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 12:5"/>A lamb, a perfect one, a male, a son of a year, let [it] be to you; you take [it] from the sheep or from the goats. <verse eid="EXO 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 12:6"/>And it has become a charge to you, until the fourteenth day of this month, and the whole assembly of the congregation of Israel has slaughtered it between the evenings; <verse eid="EXO 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 12:7"/>and they have taken of the blood, and have put [it] on the two doorposts, and on the lintel over the houses in which they eat it. <verse eid="EXO 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 12:8"/>And they have eaten the flesh in this night, a roast with fire; they eat it with unleavened things and bitters; <verse eid="EXO 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 12:9"/>you do not eat of it raw, or boiled in water at all, but a roast with fire, its head with its legs, and with its innards; <verse eid="EXO 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 12:10"/>and you do not leave of it until morning, and that which is remaining of it until morning you burn with fire. <verse eid="EXO 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 12:11"/>And thus you eat it: your loins girded, your sandals on your feet, and your staff in your hand, and you have eaten it in haste; it is YHWH’s Passover, <verse eid="EXO 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 12:12"/>and I have passed over through the land of Egypt during this night, and have struck every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from man even to beast, and I do judgments on all the gods of Egypt; I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 12:13"/>And the blood has become a sign for you on the houses where you [are], and I have seen the blood, and have passed over you, and a plague is not on you for destruction in My striking in the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 12:14"/>And this day has become a memorial to you, and you have kept it [for] a celebration to YHWH throughout your generations—a continuous statute; you keep it [for] a celebration. <verse eid="EXO 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 12:15"/>Seven days you eat unleavened things; only—in the first day you cause leaven to cease out of your houses; for anyone eating anything fermented from the first day until the seventh day, indeed, that person has been cut off from Israel. <verse eid="EXO 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 12:16"/>And in the first day [is] a holy convocation, and in the seventh day you have a holy convocation; any work is not done in them, only that which is eaten by any person—it alone is done by you, <verse eid="EXO 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 12:17"/>and you have observed the Unleavened Things, for in this very day I have brought out your hosts from the land of Egypt, and you have observed this day throughout your generations—a continuous statute. <verse eid="EXO 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 12:18"/>In the first [month], on the fourteenth day of the month, in the evening, you eat unleavened things until the twenty-first day of the month, at evening; <verse eid="EXO 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 12:19"/>seven days leaven is not found in your houses, for anyone eating anything fermented—that person has been cut off from the congregation of Israel, among the sojourners or among the natives of the land; <verse eid="EXO 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 12:20"/>you do not eat anything fermented—in all your dwellings you eat [only] unleavened things.” <verse eid="EXO 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 12:21"/>And Moses calls for all [the] elderly of Israel and says to them, “Draw out and take for yourselves [from] the flock, for your families, and slaughter the Passover-sacrifice; <verse eid="EXO 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 12:22"/>and you have taken a bunch of hyssop, and have dipped [it] in the blood which [is] in the basin, and have struck [it] on the lintel, and on the two doorposts, from the blood which [is] in the basin, and you, you do not go out—each from the opening of his house—until morning. <verse eid="EXO 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 12:23"/>And YHWH has passed on to strike the Egyptians, and has seen the blood on the lintel, and on the two doorposts, and YHWH has passed over the opening, and does not permit the destruction to come into your houses to strike. <verse eid="EXO 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 12:24"/>And you have observed this thing for a statute to you and to your sons for all time; <verse eid="EXO 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 12:25"/>and it has been, when you come to the land which YHWH gives to you as He has spoken, that you have kept this service; <verse eid="EXO 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 12:26"/>and it has come to pass, when your sons say to you, What [is] this service you have? <verse eid="EXO 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 12:27"/>That you have said, It [is] a sacrifice of Passover to YHWH, who passed over the houses of the sons of Israel in Egypt, in His striking the Egyptians, and our houses He delivered.” <verse eid="EXO 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 12:28"/>And the people bow and pay respect, and the sons of Israel go and do as YHWH commanded Moses and Aaron; so they have done. <verse eid="EXO 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 12:29"/>And it comes to pass, at midnight, that YHWH has struck every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of Pharaoh who is sitting on his throne, to the firstborn of the captive who [is] in the prison-house, and every firstborn of beasts. <verse eid="EXO 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 12:30"/>And Pharaoh rises by night, he and all his servants, and all the Egyptians, and there is a great cry in Egypt, for there is not a house where there is not [one] dead, <verse eid="EXO 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 12:31"/>and he calls for Moses and for Aaron by night and says, “Rise, go out from the midst of my people, both you and the sons of Israel, and go, serve YHWH according to your word; <verse eid="EXO 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 12:32"/>take both your flock and your herd as you have spoken, and go; then you have also blessed me.” <verse eid="EXO 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 12:33"/>And the Egyptians are urgent on the people, hastening to send them away out of the land, for they said, “We are all dead”; <verse eid="EXO 12:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 12:34"/>and the people take up their dough before it is fermented, their kneading-troughs [are] bound up in their garments on their shoulder. <verse eid="EXO 12:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 12:35"/>And the sons of Israel have done according to the word of Moses, and they ask for vessels of silver and vessels of gold, and garments, from the Egyptians; <verse eid="EXO 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 12:36"/>and YHWH has given the grace of the people in the eyes of the Egyptians, and they cause them to ask, and they spoil the Egyptians. <verse eid="EXO 12:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 12:37"/>And the sons of Israel journey from Rameses to Succoth, about six hundred thousand men on foot, apart from infants; <verse eid="EXO 12:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EXO 12:38"/>and a great rabble has also gone up with them, and flock and herd—very much livestock. <verse eid="EXO 12:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EXO 12:39"/>And they bake unleavened cakes with the dough which they have brought out from Egypt, for it has not fermented; for they have been cast out of Egypt, and have not been able to delay, and also they have not made provision for themselves. <verse eid="EXO 12:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EXO 12:40"/>And the dwelling of the sons of Israel [in] which they have dwelt in Egypt [is] four hundred and thirty years; <verse eid="EXO 12:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="EXO 12:41"/>and it comes to pass, at the end of four hundred and thirty years—indeed, it comes to pass on this very same day—all the hosts of YHWH have gone out from the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 12:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="EXO 12:42"/>It [is] a night of watchings to YHWH, to bring them out from the land of Egypt; it [is] this night of watchings to YHWH to all the sons of Israel throughout their generations. <verse eid="EXO 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="EXO 12:43"/>And YHWH says to Moses and Aaron, “This [is] a statute of the Passover; any son of a stranger does not eat of it; <verse eid="EXO 12:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="EXO 12:44"/>and any man’s servant, the purchase of money, when you have circumcised him—then he eats of it; <verse eid="EXO 12:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="EXO 12:45"/>a settler or hired servant does not eat of it; <verse eid="EXO 12:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="EXO 12:46"/>it is eaten in one house, you do not carry out of the house [any] of the flesh outside, and you do not break a bone of it; <verse eid="EXO 12:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="EXO 12:47"/>all the congregation of Israel keeps it. <verse eid="EXO 12:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="EXO 12:48"/>And when a sojourner sojourns with you, and has made a Passover to YHWH, every male of his [is] to be circumcised, and then he comes near to keep it, and he has been as a native of the land, but any uncircumcised one does not eat of it; <verse eid="EXO 12:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="EXO 12:49"/>one law is to a native, and to a sojourner who is sojourning in your midst.” <verse eid="EXO 12:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="EXO 12:50"/>And all the sons of Israel do as YHWH commanded Moses and Aaron; so they have done. <verse eid="EXO 12:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="EXO 12:51"/>And it comes to pass on this very same day, YHWH has brought out the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt by their hosts.<verse eid="EXO 12:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="EXO 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 13:1"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 13:2"/>“Sanctify to Me every firstborn, opening any womb among the sons of Israel, among man and among beast; it [is] Mine.” <verse eid="EXO 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 13:3"/>And Moses says to the people, “Remember this day [in] which you have gone out from Egypt, from the house of servants, for by strength of hand YHWH has brought you out from this, and anything fermented is not eaten; <verse eid="EXO 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 13:4"/>you are going out today, in the month of Abib. <verse eid="EXO 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 13:5"/>And it has been, when YHWH brings you to the land of the Canaanite, and of the Hittite, and of the Amorite, and of the Hivite, and of the Jebusite, which He has sworn to your fathers to give to you, a land flowing with milk and honey, that you have done this service in this month. <verse eid="EXO 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 13:6"/>Seven days you eat unleavened things, and in the seventh day [is] a celebration to YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 13:7"/>unleavened things are eaten the seven days, and anything fermented is not seen with you; indeed, leaven is not seen with you in all your border. <verse eid="EXO 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 13:8"/>And you have declared to your son in that day, saying, [It is] because of what YHWH did to me, in my going out from Egypt, <verse eid="EXO 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 13:9"/>and it has been to you for a sign on your hand, and for a memorial between your eyes, so that the Law of YHWH is in your mouth, for by a strong hand YHWH has brought you out from Egypt; <verse eid="EXO 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 13:10"/>and you have kept this statute at its appointed time from days to days. <verse eid="EXO 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 13:11"/>And it has been, when YHWH brings you to the land of the Canaanite as He has sworn to you and to your fathers, and has given it to you, <verse eid="EXO 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 13:12"/>that you have caused everyone opening a womb to pass over to YHWH, and every firstling—the increase of beasts which you have: the males [are] YHWH’s. <verse eid="EXO 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 13:13"/>And every firstling of a donkey you ransom with a lamb, and if you do not ransom [it], then you have beheaded it; and you ransom every firstborn of man among your sons. <verse eid="EXO 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 13:14"/>And it has been, when your son asks you hereafter, saying, What [is] this? That you have said to him, By strength of hand YHWH has brought us out from Egypt, from a house of servants; <verse eid="EXO 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 13:15"/>indeed, it comes to pass, when Pharaoh has been pained to send us away, that YHWH slays every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of man even to the firstborn of beast; therefore I am sacrificing to YHWH all opening a womb who [are] males, and I ransom every firstborn of my sons; <verse eid="EXO 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 13:16"/>and it has been for a token on your hand, and for frontlets between your eyes, for by strength of hand YHWH has brought us out of Egypt.” <verse eid="EXO 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 13:17"/>And it comes to pass in Pharaoh’s sending the people away, that God has not led them the way of the land of the Philistines, for it [is] near; for God said, “Lest the people sigh in their seeing war, and have turned back toward Egypt”; <verse eid="EXO 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 13:18"/>and God turns around the people the way of the wilderness of the Red Sea, and the sons of Israel have gone up by fifties from the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 13:19"/>And Moses takes the bones of Joseph with him, for he certainly caused the sons of Israel to swear, saying, “God certainly inspects you, and you have brought up my bones from this [place] with you.” <verse eid="EXO 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 13:20"/>And they journey from Succoth, and encamp in Etham at the extremity of the wilderness, <verse eid="EXO 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 13:21"/>and YHWH is going before them by day in a pillar of a cloud, to lead them in the way, and by night in a pillar of fire, to give light to them, to go by day and by night; <verse eid="EXO 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 13:22"/>He does not remove the pillar of the cloud by day, and the pillar of the fire by night, [from] before the people.<verse eid="EXO 13:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="EXO 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 14:1"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 14:2"/>“Speak to the sons of Israel, and they turn back and encamp before Pi-Hahiroth, between Migdol and the sea, before Ba‘al-Zephon; you encamp in front of it by the sea, <verse eid="EXO 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 14:3"/>and Pharaoh has said of the sons of Israel, They are entangled in the land, the wilderness has shut on them; <verse eid="EXO 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 14:4"/>and I have strengthened the heart of Pharaoh, and he has pursued after them, and I am honored by Pharaoh, and by all his force, and the Egyptians have known that I [am] YHWH”; and they do so. <verse eid="EXO 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 14:5"/>And it is declared to the king of Egypt that the people have fled, and the heart of Pharaoh and of his servants is turned against the people, and they say, “What [is] this we have done, that we have sent Israel away from our service?” <verse eid="EXO 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 14:6"/>And he harnesses his chariot, and he has taken his people with him, <verse eid="EXO 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 14:7"/>and he takes six hundred chosen chariots, even all the chariots of Egypt, and captains over them all; <verse eid="EXO 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 14:8"/>and YHWH strengthens the heart of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he pursues after the sons of Israel, and the sons of Israel are going out with a high hand, <verse eid="EXO 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 14:9"/>and the Egyptians pursue after them, and all the chariot horses of Pharaoh, and his horsemen, and his force, overtake them, encamping by the sea, by Pi-Hahiroth, before Ba‘al-Zephon. <verse eid="EXO 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 14:10"/>And Pharaoh has drawn near, and the sons of Israel lift up their eyes, and behold, the Egyptians are journeying after them, and they fear exceedingly, and the sons of Israel cry to YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 14:11"/>And they say to Moses, “Because there are no graves in Egypt, have you taken us away to die in a wilderness? What is this you have done to us—to bring us out from Egypt? <verse eid="EXO 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 14:12"/>Is this not the word which we spoke to you in Egypt, saying, Cease from us, and we serve the Egyptians; for [it is] better for us to serve the Egyptians than to die in a wilderness?” <verse eid="EXO 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 14:13"/>And Moses says to the people, “Do not fear, station yourselves, and see the salvation of YHWH, which He does for you today; for as you have seen the Egyptians today, you add no more to see them for all time; <verse eid="EXO 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 14:14"/>YHWH fights for you, and you keep silent.” <verse eid="EXO 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 14:15"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Why do you cry to Me? Speak to the sons of Israel, and they journey; <verse eid="EXO 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 14:16"/>and you, lift up your rod, and stretch out your hand toward the sea, and cleave it, and the sons of Israel go into the midst of the sea on dry land. <verse eid="EXO 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 14:17"/>And I—behold, I am strengthening the heart of the Egyptians, and they go in after them, and I am honored by Pharaoh, and by all his force, by his chariots, and by his horsemen; <verse eid="EXO 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 14:18"/>and the Egyptians have known that I [am] YHWH, in My being honored by Pharaoh, by his chariots, and by his horsemen.” <verse eid="EXO 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 14:19"/>And the Messenger of God, who is going before the camp of Israel, journeys and goes at their rear; and the pillar of the cloud journeys from their front, and stands at their rear, <verse eid="EXO 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 14:20"/>and comes in between the camp of the Egyptians and the camp of Israel, and the cloud and the darkness are, and he enlightens the night, and the one has not drawn near to the other all the night. <verse eid="EXO 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 14:21"/>And Moses stretches out his hand toward the sea, and YHWH causes the sea to go on by a strong east wind all the night, and makes the sea become dry ground, and the waters are cleaved, <verse eid="EXO 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 14:22"/>and the sons of Israel go into the midst of the sea on dry land, and the waters [are] a wall to them, on their right and on their left. <verse eid="EXO 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 14:23"/>And the Egyptians pursue, and go in after them (all the horses of Pharaoh, his chariots, and his horsemen) into the midst of the sea, <verse eid="EXO 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 14:24"/>and it comes to pass, in the morning watch, that YHWH looks to the camp of the Egyptians through the pillar of fire and of the cloud, and troubles the camp of the Egyptians, <verse eid="EXO 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 14:25"/>and turns aside the wheels of their chariots, and they lead them with difficulty, and the Egyptians say, “Let us flee from the face of Israel, for YHWH is fighting for them against the Egyptians.” <verse eid="EXO 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 14:26"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Stretch out your hand toward the sea, and the waters turn back on the Egyptians, on their chariots, and on their horsemen.” <verse eid="EXO 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 14:27"/>And Moses stretches out his hand toward the sea, and the sea turns back, at the turning of the morning, to its perennial flow, and the Egyptians are fleeing at its coming, and YHWH shakes off the Egyptians in the midst of the sea, <verse eid="EXO 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 14:28"/>and the waters turn back, and cover the chariots and the horsemen, even all the force of Pharaoh, who are coming in after them into the sea—there has not been left even one of them. <verse eid="EXO 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 14:29"/>And the sons of Israel have gone on dry land in the midst of the sea, and the waters [are] a wall to them, on their right and on their left; <verse eid="EXO 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 14:30"/>and YHWH saves Israel out of the hand of the Egyptians in that day, and Israel sees the Egyptians dead on the seashore, <verse eid="EXO 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 14:31"/>and Israel sees the great hand with which YHWH has worked against the Egyptians, and the people fear YHWH, and remain steadfast in YHWH, and in His servant Moses.<verse eid="EXO 14:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="EXO 15"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 15:1"/>Then Moses sings—and the sons of Israel—this song to YHWH, and they speak, saying, “I sing to YHWH, || For triumphing He has triumphed; The horse and its rider He has thrown into the sea. <verse eid="EXO 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 15:2"/>My strength and song is YAH, || And He is become my salvation: This [is] my God, and I glorify Him; God of my father, and I exalt Him. <verse eid="EXO 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 15:3"/>YHWH [is] a man of battle; YHWH [is] His Name. <verse eid="EXO 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 15:4"/>Chariots of Pharaoh and his force || He has cast into the sea; And the choice of his captains || Have sunk in the Red Sea! <verse eid="EXO 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 15:5"/>The depths cover them; They went down into the depths as a stone. <verse eid="EXO 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 15:6"/>Your right hand, O YHWH, || Has become honorable in power; Your right hand, O YHWH, || Crushes an enemy. <verse eid="EXO 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 15:7"/>And in the abundance of Your excellence || You throw down Your withstanders, || You send forth Your wrath—It consumes them as stubble. <verse eid="EXO 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 15:8"/>And by the wind of Your anger || Waters have been heaped together; Flowings have stood as a heap; Depths have been congealed || In the heart of a sea. <verse eid="EXO 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 15:9"/>The enemy said, I pursue, I overtake; I apportion spoil; My soul is filled with them; I draw out my sword; My hand destroys them— <verse eid="EXO 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 15:10"/>You have blown with Your wind || The sea has covered them; They sank as lead in mighty waters. <verse eid="EXO 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 15:11"/>Who [is] like You among the gods, O YHWH? Who [is] like You—honorable in holiness—Fearful in praises—doing wonders? <verse eid="EXO 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 15:12"/>You have stretched out Your right hand—Earth swallows them! <verse eid="EXO 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 15:13"/>You have led forth in Your kindness || The people whom You have redeemed. You have led on in Your strength || To Your holy habitation. <verse eid="EXO 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 15:14"/>Peoples have heard, they are troubled; Pain has seized inhabitants of Philistia. <verse eid="EXO 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 15:15"/>Then chiefs of Edom have been troubled; Mighty ones of Moab—Trembling seizes them! All inhabitants of Canaan have melted! <verse eid="EXO 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 15:16"/>Terror and dread fall on them; By the greatness of Your arm || They are still as a stone, || Until Your people pass over, O YHWH; Until the people pass over || Whom You have purchased. <verse eid="EXO 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 15:17"/>You bring them in, and plant them || In a mountain of Your inheritance, || A fixed place for Your dwelling You have made, O YHWH; A sanctuary, O Lord, Your hands have established; <verse eid="EXO 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 15:18"/>YHWH reigns—[for] all time and forever!” <verse eid="EXO 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 15:19"/>For the horse of Pharaoh has gone in with his chariots and with his horsemen into the sea, and YHWH turns back the waters of the sea on them, and the sons of Israel have gone on dry land in the midst of the sea. <verse eid="EXO 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 15:20"/>And Miriam the inspired one, sister of Aaron, takes the timbrel in her hand, and all the women go out after her, with timbrels and with choruses; <verse eid="EXO 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 15:21"/>and Miriam answers to them: “Sing to YHWH, || For triumphing He has triumphed; The horse and its rider He has thrown into the sea!” <verse eid="EXO 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 15:22"/>And Moses causes Israel to journey from the Red Sea, and they go out to the wilderness of Shur, and they go three days in the wilderness, and have not found water, <verse eid="EXO 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 15:23"/>and they come to Marah, and have not been able to drink the waters of Marah, for they [are] bitter; therefore [one] has called its name Marah. <verse eid="EXO 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 15:24"/>And the people murmur against Moses, saying, “What do we drink?” <verse eid="EXO 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 15:25"/>And he cries to YHWH, and YHWH shows him a tree, and he casts [it] into the waters, and the waters become sweet. He has made a statute for them there, and an ordinance, and He has tried them there, <verse eid="EXO 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 15:26"/>and He says, “If you really listen to the voice of your God YHWH, and do that which is right in His eyes, and have listened to His commands, and kept all His statutes, none of the sickness which I laid on the Egyptians do I lay on you, for I, YHWH, am healing you.” <verse eid="EXO 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 15:27"/>And they come to Elim, and there [are] twelve fountains of water, and seventy palm trees; and they encamp there by the waters.<verse eid="EXO 15:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="EXO 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 16:1"/>And they journey from Elim, and all the congregation of the sons of Israel come to the wilderness of Sin, which [is] between Elim and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second month of their going out from the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 16:2"/>And all the congregation of the sons of Israel murmur against Moses and against Aaron in the wilderness; <verse eid="EXO 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 16:3"/>and the sons of Israel say to them, “Oh that we had died by the hand of YHWH in the land of Egypt, in our sitting by the flesh-pot, in our eating bread to satiety—for you have brought us out to this wilderness to put all this assembly to death with hunger.” <verse eid="EXO 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 16:4"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Behold, I am raining bread from the heavens for you—and the people have gone out and gathered the matter of a day in its day—so that I try them whether they walk in My law or not; <verse eid="EXO 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 16:5"/>and it has been on the sixth day, that they have prepared that which they bring in, and it has been double above that which they gather day [by] day.” <verse eid="EXO 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 16:6"/>And Moses says—Aaron also—to all the sons of Israel, “Evening—and you have known that YHWH has brought you out from the land of Egypt; <verse eid="EXO 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 16:7"/>and morning—and you have seen the glory of YHWH, in His hearing your murmurings against YHWH, and what [are] we, that you murmur against us?” <verse eid="EXO 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 16:8"/>And Moses says, “In YHWH’s giving to you flesh to eat in the evening, and bread in the morning to satiety—in YHWH’s hearing your murmurings, which you are murmuring against Him, and what [are] we? Your murmurings [are] not against us, but against YHWH.” <verse eid="EXO 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 16:9"/>And Moses says to Aaron, “Say to all the congregation of the sons of Israel, Come near before YHWH, for He has heard your murmurings”; <verse eid="EXO 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 16:10"/>and it comes to pass, when Aaron is speaking to all the congregation of the sons of Israel, that they turn toward the wilderness, and behold, the glory of YHWH is seen in the cloud. <verse eid="EXO 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 16:11"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 16:12"/>“I have heard the murmurings of the sons of Israel; speak to them, saying, Between the evenings you eat flesh, and in the morning you are satisfied [with] bread, and you have known that I [am] your God YHWH.” <verse eid="EXO 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 16:13"/>And it comes to pass in the evening, that the quail comes up, and covers the camp, and in the morning there has been the lying of dew around the camp, <verse eid="EXO 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 16:14"/>and the lying of the dew goes up, and behold, on the face of the wilderness [is] a thin, bare thing, thin as hoarfrost on the earth. <verse eid="EXO 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 16:15"/>And the sons of Israel see, and say to one another, “What [is] it?” For they have not known what it [is]; and Moses says to them, “It [is] the bread which YHWH has given to you for food. <verse eid="EXO 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 16:16"/>This [is] the thing which YHWH has commanded: Gather of it, each according to his eating, an omer for the counted head; and the number of your persons, take, each, for those in his tent.” <verse eid="EXO 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 16:17"/>And the sons of Israel do so, and they gather, he who is [gathering] much, and he who is [gathering] little; <verse eid="EXO 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 16:18"/>and they measure with an omer, and he who is [gathering] much has nothing over, and he who is [gathering] little has no lack, each according to his eating they have gathered. <verse eid="EXO 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 16:19"/>And Moses says to them, “Let no man leave of it until morning”; <verse eid="EXO 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 16:20"/>and they have not listened to Moses, and some of them leave of it until morning, and it brings up worms and stinks; and Moses is angry with them. <verse eid="EXO 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 16:21"/>And they gather it morning by morning, each according to his eating; when the sun has been warm, then it has melted. <verse eid="EXO 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 16:22"/>And it comes to pass on the sixth day, they have gathered a second bread, two omers for one, and all the princes of the congregation come in, and declare [it] to Moses. <verse eid="EXO 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 16:23"/>And he says to them, “It [is] that which YHWH has spoken: A rest—a holy Sabbath to YHWH—[is] tomorrow; that which you bake, bake; and that which you boil, boil; and all that is remaining, let [it] rest for yourselves for preservation until the morning.” <verse eid="EXO 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 16:24"/>And they let it rest until the morning, as Moses has commanded, and it has not stunk, and a worm has not been in it. <verse eid="EXO 16:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 16:25"/>And Moses says, “Eat it today, for today [is] a Sabbath to YHWH; today you do not find it in the field: <verse eid="EXO 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 16:26"/>six days you gather it, and in the seventh day—the Sabbath—there is none in it.” <verse eid="EXO 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 16:27"/>And it comes to pass on the seventh day, some of the people have gone out to gather, and have not found. <verse eid="EXO 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 16:28"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “How long have you refused to keep My commands and My laws? <verse eid="EXO 16:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 16:29"/>See, because YHWH has given the Sabbath to you, therefore He is giving to you on the sixth day bread of two days; each abide [in] his place, no one goes out from his place on the seventh day.” <verse eid="EXO 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 16:30"/>And the people rest on the seventh day, <verse eid="EXO 16:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 16:31"/>and the house of Israel calls its name Manna, and it [is] as white coriander seed; and its taste [is] as a cake with honey. <verse eid="EXO 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 16:32"/>And Moses says, “This [is] the thing which YHWH has commanded: Fill the omer with it, for a charge for your generations, so that they see the bread which I have caused you to eat in the wilderness, in My bringing you out from the land of Egypt.” <verse eid="EXO 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 16:33"/>And Moses says to Aaron, “Take one pot, and put the fullness of the omer of manna [in] there, and let it rest before YHWH, for a charge for your generations”; <verse eid="EXO 16:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 16:34"/>as YHWH has given command to Moses, so Aaron lets it rest before the Testimony, for a charge. <verse eid="EXO 16:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 16:35"/>And the sons of Israel have eaten the manna [for] forty years, until their coming to the land to be inhabited; they have eaten the manna until their coming to the extremity of the land of Canaan. <verse eid="EXO 16:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 16:36"/>And the omer is a tenth of the ephah.<verse eid="EXO 16:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="EXO 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 17:1"/>And all the congregation of the sons of Israel journey from the wilderness of Sin, on their journeys, by the command of YHWH, and encamp in Rephidim, and there is no water for the people to drink; <verse eid="EXO 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 17:2"/>and the people strive with Moses, and say, “Give us water, and we drink.” And Moses says to them, “Why do you strive with me? Why do you try YHWH?” <verse eid="EXO 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 17:3"/>And the people thirst for water there, and the people murmur against Moses, and say, “Why [is] this [that] you have brought us up out of Egypt to put us to death, also our sons and our livestock, with thirst?” <verse eid="EXO 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 17:4"/>And Moses cries to YHWH, saying, “What do I do to this people? Yet a little, and they have stoned me.” <verse eid="EXO 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 17:5"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Pass over before the people, and take with you from [the] elderly of Israel, and take your rod in your hand, with which you have struck the River, and you have gone. <verse eid="EXO 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 17:6"/>Behold, I am standing before you there on the rock in Horeb, and you have struck on the rock, and waters have come out from it, and the people have drunk.” And Moses does so before the eyes of [the] elderly of Israel, <verse eid="EXO 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 17:7"/>and he calls the name of the place Massah, and Meribah, because of the strife of the sons of Israel, and because of their trying YHWH, saying, “Is YHWH in our midst or not?” <verse eid="EXO 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 17:8"/>And Amalek comes, and fights with Israel in Rephidim, <verse eid="EXO 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 17:9"/>and Moses says to Joshua, “Choose men for us, and go out, fight with Amalek: tomorrow I am standing on the top of the hill, and the rod of God in my hand.” <verse eid="EXO 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 17:10"/>And Joshua does as Moses has said to him, to fight with Amalek, and Moses, Aaron, and Hur have gone up [to] the top of the height; <verse eid="EXO 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 17:11"/>and it has come to pass, when Moses lifts up his hand, that Israel has been mighty, and when he lets his hands rest, that Amalek has been mighty. <verse eid="EXO 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 17:12"/>And the hands of Moses [are] heavy, and they take a stone and set [it] under him, and he sits on it, and Aaron and Hur have taken hold on his hands, one on this [side] and one on that [side]; and his hands are steadfast until the going in of the sun; <verse eid="EXO 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 17:13"/>and Joshua weakens Amalek and his people by the mouth of the sword. <verse eid="EXO 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 17:14"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Write this, a memorial in a Scroll, and set [it] in the ears of Joshua, that I utterly wipe away the remembrance of Amalek from under the heavens”; <verse eid="EXO 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 17:15"/>and Moses builds an altar, and calls its name YHWH-Nissi, <verse eid="EXO 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 17:16"/>and says, “Because a hand [is] on the throne of YAH, war [is] to YHWH with Amalek from generation [to] generation.”<verse eid="EXO 17:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="EXO 18"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 18:1"/>And Jethro priest of Midian, father-in-law of Moses, hears all that God has done for Moses and for His people Israel, that YHWH has brought out Israel from Egypt, <verse eid="EXO 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 18:2"/>and Jethro, father-in-law of Moses, takes Zipporah, wife of Moses, after her parting, <verse eid="EXO 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 18:3"/>and her two sons, of whom the name of one [is] Gershom, for he said, “I have been a sojourner in a strange land”; <verse eid="EXO 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 18:4"/>and the name of the other [is] Eliezer, for, “The God of my father [is] for my help, and He delivers me from the sword of Pharaoh.” <verse eid="EXO 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 18:5"/>And Jethro, father-in-law of Moses, comes, and his sons, and his wife, to Moses, to the wilderness where he is encamping—the mountain of God; <verse eid="EXO 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 18:6"/>and he says to Moses, “I, your father-in-law Jethro, am coming to you, and your wife, and her two sons with her.” <verse eid="EXO 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 18:7"/>And Moses goes out to meet his father-in-law, and bows himself, and kisses him, and they ask of one another of welfare, and come into the tent; <verse eid="EXO 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 18:8"/>and Moses recounts to his father-in-law all that YHWH has done to Pharaoh, and to the Egyptians, on account of Israel, all the travail which has found them in the way, and [how] YHWH delivers them. <verse eid="EXO 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 18:9"/>And Jethro rejoices for all the good which YHWH has done to Israel, whom He has delivered from the hand of the Egyptians; <verse eid="EXO 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 18:10"/>and Jethro says, “Blessed [is] YHWH, who has delivered you from the hand of the Egyptians, and from the hand of Pharaoh—who has delivered this people from under the hand of the Egyptians; <verse eid="EXO 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 18:11"/>now I have known that YHWH [is] greater than all the gods, for in the thing they have acted proudly—[He is] above them!” <verse eid="EXO 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 18:12"/>And Jethro, father-in-law of Moses, takes a burnt-offering and sacrifices [it] for God; and Aaron comes in, and all [the] elderly of Israel, to eat bread with the father-in-law of Moses, before God. <verse eid="EXO 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 18:13"/>And it comes to pass on the next day, that Moses sits to judge the people, and the people stand before Moses from the morning to the evening; <verse eid="EXO 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 18:14"/>and the father-in-law of Moses sees all that he is doing for the people and says, “What [is] this thing which you are doing for the people? Why are you sitting by yourself, and all the people standing by you from morning until evening?” <verse eid="EXO 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 18:15"/>And Moses says to his father-in-law, “Because the people come to me to seek God; <verse eid="EXO 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 18:16"/>when they have a matter, it has come to me, and I have judged between a man and his neighbor, and made known the statutes of God, and His laws.” <verse eid="EXO 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 18:17"/>And the father-in-law of Moses says to him, “The thing which you are doing [is] not good; <verse eid="EXO 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 18:18"/>you surely wear away, both you, and this people which [is] with you, for the thing is too heavy for you, you are not able to do it by yourself. <verse eid="EXO 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 18:19"/>Now listen to my voice, I counsel you, and God is with you: be for the people before God, and you have brought in the things to God; <verse eid="EXO 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 18:20"/>and you have warned them [concerning] the statutes and the laws, and have made known to them the way in which they go, and the work which they do. <verse eid="EXO 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 18:21"/>And you provide out of all the people men of ability, fearing God, men of truth, hating dishonest gain, and have placed [these] over them [for] heads of thousands, heads of hundreds, heads of fifties, and heads of tens, <verse eid="EXO 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 18:22"/>and they have judged the people at all times; and it has come to pass, they bring every great matter to you, and they judge every small matter themselves; and lighten it from off yourself, and they have borne with you. <verse eid="EXO 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 18:23"/>If you do this thing, and God has commanded you, then you have been able to stand, and all this people also goes to its place in peace.” <verse eid="EXO 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 18:24"/>And Moses listens to the voice of his father-in-law, and does all that he said, <verse eid="EXO 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 18:25"/>and Moses chooses men of ability out of all Israel, and makes them chiefs over the people [for] heads of thousands, heads of hundreds, heads of fifties, and heads of tens, <verse eid="EXO 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 18:26"/>and they have judged the people at all times; they bring the hard matter to Moses, and they judge every small matter themselves. <verse eid="EXO 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 18:27"/>And Moses sends his father-in-law away, and he goes away to his own land.<verse eid="EXO 18:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="EXO 19"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 19:1"/>In the third month of the going out of the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt, in this day they have come into the wilderness of Sinai, <verse eid="EXO 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 19:2"/>and they journey from Rephidim, and enter the wilderness of Sinai, and encamp in the wilderness; and Israel encamps there before the mountain. <verse eid="EXO 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 19:3"/>And Moses has gone up to God, and YHWH calls to him out of the mountain, saying, “Thus you say to the house of Jacob, and declare to the sons of Israel: <verse eid="EXO 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 19:4"/>You have seen that which I have done to the Egyptians, and [how] I carry you on eagles’ wings and bring you to Myself. <verse eid="EXO 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 19:5"/>And now, if you really listen to My voice, then you have kept My covenant, and have been a special treasure to Me more than all the peoples, for all the earth [is] Mine; <verse eid="EXO 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 19:6"/>and you are to Me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation: these [are] the words which you speak to the sons of Israel.” <verse eid="EXO 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 19:7"/>And Moses comes, and calls for [the] elderly of the people, and sets before them all these words which YHWH has commanded him; <verse eid="EXO 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 19:8"/>and all the people answer together and say, “All that YHWH has spoken we do”; and Moses returns the words of the people to YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 19:9"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Behold, I am coming to you in the thickness of the cloud, so that the people hear in My speaking with you, and also believe in you for all time”; and Moses declares the words of the people to YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 19:10"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Go to the people and you have sanctified them today and tomorrow, and they have washed their garments, <verse eid="EXO 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 19:11"/>and have been prepared for the third day; for on the third day YHWH comes down on Mount Sinai before the eyes of all the people. <verse eid="EXO 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 19:12"/>And you have made a border [for] the people all around, saying, Take heed to yourselves, going up into the mountain or coming against its extremity; whoever is coming against the mountain is certainly put to death; <verse eid="EXO 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 19:13"/>a hand does not come against him, for he is certainly stoned or shot through, whether beast or man—it does not live; in the prolonging of the ram’s horn they go up into the mountain.” <verse eid="EXO 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 19:14"/>And Moses comes down from the mountain to the people, and sanctifies the people, and they wash their garments; <verse eid="EXO 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 19:15"/>and he says to the people, “Be prepared for the third day, do not come near to a woman.” <verse eid="EXO 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 19:16"/>And it comes to pass, on the third day, while it is morning, that there are voices, and lightnings, and a heavy cloud on the mountain, and the sound of a very strong horn; and all the people who [are] in the camp tremble. <verse eid="EXO 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 19:17"/>And Moses brings out the people from the camp to meet God, and they station themselves at the lower part of the mountain, <verse eid="EXO 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 19:18"/>and Mount Sinai [is] wholly [in] smoke from the presence of YHWH, who has come down on it in fire, and its smoke goes up as smoke of the furnace, and the whole mountain trembles exceedingly; <verse eid="EXO 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 19:19"/>and the sound of the horn is going on, and [is] very strong; Moses speaks, and God answers him with a voice. <verse eid="EXO 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 19:20"/>And YHWH comes down on Mount Sinai, to the top of the mountain, and YHWH calls for Moses to the top of the mountain, and Moses goes up. <verse eid="EXO 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 19:21"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Go down, protest to the people, lest they break through to YHWH to see, and many of them have fallen; <verse eid="EXO 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 19:22"/>and also the priests who are coming near to YHWH sanctify themselves, lest YHWH break forth on them.” <verse eid="EXO 19:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 19:23"/>And Moses says to YHWH, “The people [are] unable to come up to Mount Sinai, for You have protested to us, saying, Make a border [for] the mountain, then you have sanctified it.” <verse eid="EXO 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 19:24"/>And YHWH says to him, “Go, descend, then you have come up, you and Aaron with you; and the priests and the people do not break through to come up to YHWH, lest He break forth on them.” <verse eid="EXO 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 19:25"/>And Moses goes down to the people and speaks to them.<verse eid="EXO 19:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="EXO 20"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 20:1"/>And God speaks all these words, saying, <verse eid="EXO 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 20:2"/>“I [am] your God YHWH, who has brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of servants. <verse eid="EXO 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 20:3"/>You have no other Gods before Me. <verse eid="EXO 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 20:4"/>You do not make a carved image for yourself, or any likeness which [is] in the heavens above, or which [is] in the earth beneath, or which [is] in the waters under the earth. <verse eid="EXO 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 20:5"/>You do not bow yourself to them, nor serve them: for I, your God YHWH, [am] a zealous God, charging iniquity of fathers on sons, on a third and on a fourth [generation] of those hating Me, <verse eid="EXO 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 20:6"/>and doing kindness to thousands, of those loving Me and keeping My commands. <verse eid="EXO 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 20:7"/>You do not take up the Name of your God YHWH for a vain thing, for YHWH does not acquit him who takes up His Name for a vain thing. <verse eid="EXO 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 20:8"/>Remember the Sabbath day to sanctify it; <verse eid="EXO 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 20:9"/>six days you labor and have done all your work, <verse eid="EXO 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 20:10"/>and the seventh day [is] a Sabbath to your God YHWH; you do not do any work, you, and your son, and your daughter, your manservant, and your handmaid, and your livestock, and your sojourner who is within your gates— <verse eid="EXO 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 20:11"/>for [in] six days YHWH has made the heavens and the earth, the sea, and all that [is] in them, and rests in the seventh day; therefore YHWH has blessed the Sabbath day and sanctifies it. <verse eid="EXO 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 20:12"/>Honor your father and your mother, so that your days are prolonged on the ground which your God YHWH is giving to you. <verse eid="EXO 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 20:13"/>You do not murder. <verse eid="EXO 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 20:14"/>You do not commit adultery. <verse eid="EXO 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 20:15"/>You do not steal. <verse eid="EXO 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 20:16"/>You do not answer [with] a false testimony against your neighbor. <verse eid="EXO 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 20:17"/>You do not desire the house of your neighbor, you do not desire the wife of your neighbor, or his manservant, or his handmaid, or his ox, or his donkey, or anything which [is] your neighbor’s.” <verse eid="EXO 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 20:18"/>And all the people are seeing the voices, and the flames, and the sound of the horn, and the mountain smoking; and the people see, and move, and stand far off, <verse eid="EXO 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 20:19"/>and say to Moses, “Speak with us, and we hear, and do not let God speak with us, lest we die.” <verse eid="EXO 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 20:20"/>And Moses says to the people, “Do not fear, for God has come to try you, and in order that His fear may be before your faces—that you do not sin.” <verse eid="EXO 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 20:21"/>And the people stand far off, and Moses has drawn near to the thick darkness where God [is]. <verse eid="EXO 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 20:22"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Thus you say to the sons of Israel: You have seen that I have spoken with you from the heavens; <verse eid="EXO 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 20:23"/>you do not make gods of silver and gods of gold [to be] with Me—you do not make [any idol] for yourselves. <verse eid="EXO 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 20:24"/>You make an altar of earth for Me, and you have sacrificed on it your burnt-offerings and your peace-offerings, your flock and your herd; in every place where I cause My Name to be remembered I come to you, and have blessed you. <verse eid="EXO 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 20:25"/>And if you make an altar of stones for Me, you do not build them of hewn work; when you have waved your tool over it, then you defile it; <verse eid="EXO 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 20:26"/>neither do you go up by steps on My altar, that your nakedness is not revealed on it.<verse eid="EXO 20:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="EXO 21"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 21:1"/>And these [are] the judgments which you set before them: <verse eid="EXO 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 21:2"/>When you buy a Hebrew servant, he serves [for] six years, and in the seventh he goes out as a freeman for nothing; <verse eid="EXO 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 21:3"/>if he comes in by himself, he goes out by himself; if he [is] owner of a wife, then his wife has gone out with him; <verse eid="EXO 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 21:4"/>if his lord gives a wife to him, and she has borne sons or daughters to him—the wife and her children are her lord’s, and he goes out by himself. <verse eid="EXO 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 21:5"/>And if the servant really says: I have loved my lord, my wife, and my sons—I do not go out free, <verse eid="EXO 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 21:6"/>then his lord has brought him near to God, and has brought him near to the door, or to the doorpost, and his lord has bored his ear with an awl, and he has served him for all time. <verse eid="EXO 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 21:7"/>And when a man sells his daughter for a handmaid, she does not go out according to the going out of the menservants; <verse eid="EXO 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 21:8"/>if [it is] evil in the eyes of her lord, so that he has not betrothed her, then he has let her be ransomed; he has no power to sell her to a strange people, in his dealing treacherously with her. <verse eid="EXO 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 21:9"/>And if he betroths her to his son, he does to her according to the right of daughters. <verse eid="EXO 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 21:10"/>If he takes another [woman] for him, he does not withdraw her food, her covering, and her habitation; <verse eid="EXO 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 21:11"/>and if he does not do these three for her, then she has gone out for nothing, without money. <verse eid="EXO 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 21:12"/>He who strikes a man so that he has died is certainly put to death; <verse eid="EXO 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 21:13"/>as for him who has not laid wait, but God has brought [him] to his hand, I have even set a place for you to where he flees. <verse eid="EXO 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 21:14"/>And when a man presumes against his neighbor to slay him with subtlety, you take him from My altar to die. <verse eid="EXO 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 21:15"/>And he who strikes his father or his mother is certainly put to death. <verse eid="EXO 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 21:16"/>And he who steals a man, and has sold him, and he has been found in his hand, is certainly put to death. <verse eid="EXO 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 21:17"/>And he who is reviling his father or his mother is certainly put to death. <verse eid="EXO 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 21:18"/>And when men contend, and a man has struck his neighbor with a stone, or with the fist, and he does not die, but has fallen on the bed; <verse eid="EXO 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 21:19"/>if he rises, and has gone up and down outside on his staff, then the striker has been acquitted; he only gives [for] his cessation, and he is thoroughly healed. <verse eid="EXO 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 21:20"/>And when a man strikes his manservant or his handmaid with a rod, and he has died under his hand—he is certainly avenged; <verse eid="EXO 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 21:21"/>only if he remains a day, or two days, he is not avenged, for he [is] his money. <verse eid="EXO 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 21:22"/>And when men strive, and have struck a pregnant woman, and her children have come out, and there is no harm [to them], he is certainly fined as the husband of the woman lays on him, and he has given through the judges; <verse eid="EXO 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 21:23"/>and if there is harm [to them], then you have given life for life, <verse eid="EXO 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 21:24"/>eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot, <verse eid="EXO 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 21:25"/>burning for burning, wound for wound, stripe for stripe. <verse eid="EXO 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 21:26"/>And when a man strikes the eye of his manservant, or the eye of his handmaid, and has destroyed it, he sends him away as a freeman for his eye; <verse eid="EXO 21:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 21:27"/>and if he knocks out a tooth of his manservant or a tooth of his handmaid, he sends him away as a freeman for his tooth. <verse eid="EXO 21:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 21:28"/>And when an ox gores man or woman, and they have died, the ox is certainly stoned, and his flesh is not eaten, and the owner of the ox [is] acquitted; <verse eid="EXO 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 21:29"/>and if the ox is [one] accustomed to gore before, and it has been testified to its owner, and he does not watch it, and it has put to death a man or woman, the ox is stoned, and its owner is also put to death. <verse eid="EXO 21:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 21:30"/>If atonement is laid on him, then he has given the ransom of his life, according to all that is laid on him; <verse eid="EXO 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 21:31"/>whether it gores a son or gores a daughter, according to this judgment it is done to him. <verse eid="EXO 21:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 21:32"/>If the ox gores a manservant or a handmaid, he gives thirty silver shekels to their lord, and the ox is stoned. <verse eid="EXO 21:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 21:33"/>And when a man opens a pit, or when a man digs a pit, and does not cover it, and an ox or donkey has fallen [in] there— <verse eid="EXO 21:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 21:34"/>the owner of the pit repays, he gives back money to its owner, and the dead is his. <verse eid="EXO 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 21:35"/>And when a man’s ox strikes the ox of his neighbor and it has died, then they have sold the living ox, and halved its money, and they also halve the dead one; <verse eid="EXO 21:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 21:36"/>or, [if] it has been known that the ox is [one] accustomed to gore before, and its owner does not watch it, he certainly repays ox for ox, and the dead is his.<verse eid="EXO 21:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="EXO 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 22:1"/>When a man steals an ox or sheep, and has slaughtered it or sold it, he repays [with] five of the herd for the ox, and four of the flock for the sheep. <verse eid="EXO 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 22:2"/>If in the breaking through, the thief is found, and he has been struck and has died, there is no blood for him; <verse eid="EXO 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 22:3"/>if the sun has risen on him, blood [is] for him, he certainly repays; if he has nothing, then he has been sold for his theft; <verse eid="EXO 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 22:4"/>if the theft is certainly found alive in his hand, whether ox, or donkey, or sheep—he repays double. <verse eid="EXO 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 22:5"/>When a man depastures a field or vineyard, and has sent out his beast, and it has pastured in the field of another, he repays [with] the best of his field, and the best of his vineyard. <verse eid="EXO 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 22:6"/>When fire goes forth and has found thorns, and a stack, or the standing grain, or the field has been consumed, he who causes the burning certainly repays. <verse eid="EXO 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 22:7"/>When a man gives silver or vessels to his neighbor to keep, and it has been stolen out of the man’s house; if the thief is found, he repays double. <verse eid="EXO 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 22:8"/>If the thief is not found, then the master of the house has been brought near to God [to see] whether he has not put forth his hand against the work of his neighbor. <verse eid="EXO 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 22:9"/>For every matter of transgression, for ox, for donkey, for sheep, for raiment, for any lost thing of which it is said that it is his, the matter of them both comes to God; he whom God condemns repays double to his neighbor. <verse eid="EXO 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 22:10"/>When a man gives to his neighbor a donkey, or ox, or sheep, or any beast to keep, and it has died, or has been hurt, or taken captive, [with] none seeing— <verse eid="EXO 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 22:11"/>an oath of YHWH is between them both, that he has not put forth his hand against the work of his neighbor, and its owner has accepted, and he does not repay; <verse eid="EXO 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 22:12"/>but if it is certainly stolen from him, he repays to its owner; <verse eid="EXO 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 22:13"/>if it is certainly torn, he brings it in [as] a witness; he does not repay the torn thing. <verse eid="EXO 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 22:14"/>And when a man asks for [anything] from his neighbor, and it has been hurt or has died—its owner not being with it—he certainly repays; <verse eid="EXO 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 22:15"/>if its owner [is] with it, he does not repay—if it [is] a hired thing, it has come for its hire. <verse eid="EXO 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 22:16"/>And when a man entices a virgin who [is] not betrothed, and has lain with her, he certainly endows her to himself for a wife; <verse eid="EXO 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 22:17"/>if her father utterly refuses to give her to him, he weighs out money according to the dowry of virgins. <verse eid="EXO 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 22:18"/>You do not keep a witch alive. <verse eid="EXO 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 22:19"/>Whoever lies with a beast is certainly put to death. <verse eid="EXO 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 22:20"/>He who is sacrificing to a god, except to YHWH alone, is devoted. <verse eid="EXO 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 22:21"/>And you do not oppress a sojourner, nor crush him, for you have been sojourners in the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 22:22"/>You do not afflict any widow or orphan; <verse eid="EXO 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 22:23"/>if you really afflict him, surely if he cries to Me at all, I certainly hear his cry; <verse eid="EXO 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 22:24"/>and My anger has burned, and I have slain you by the sword, and your wives have been widows, and your sons orphans. <verse eid="EXO 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 22:25"/>If you lend money [to] My poor people [who are] with you, you are not as a usurer to him; you do not lay usury on him; <verse eid="EXO 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 22:26"/>if you take the garment of your neighbor in pledge at all, you return it to him during the going in of the sun: <verse eid="EXO 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 22:27"/>for it is his only covering, it [is] his garment for his skin; wherein does he lie down? And it has come to pass, when he cries to Me, that I have heard, for I [am] gracious. <verse eid="EXO 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 22:28"/>You do not revile God, and you do not curse a prince among your people. <verse eid="EXO 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 22:29"/>You do not delay your fullness and your liquids; you give the firstborn of your sons to Me; <verse eid="EXO 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 22:30"/>so you do to your ox [and] to your sheep; it is with its mother [for] seven days, on the eighth day you give it to Me. <verse eid="EXO 22:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 22:31"/>And you are holy men to Me, and you do not eat flesh torn in the field, you cast it to a dog.<verse eid="EXO 22:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="EXO 23"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 23:1"/>You do not lift up a vain report; you do not put your hand with a wicked man to be a violent witness. <verse eid="EXO 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 23:2"/>You are not after many to [do] evil, nor do you testify concerning a strife, to turn aside after many to cause [others] to turn aside; <verse eid="EXO 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 23:3"/>and you do not honor a poor man in his strife. <verse eid="EXO 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 23:4"/>When you meet your enemy’s ox or his donkey going astray, you certainly turn it back to him; <verse eid="EXO 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 23:5"/>when you see the donkey of him who is hating you crouching under its burden, then you have ceased from leaving [it] to it—you certainly leave [it] with him. <verse eid="EXO 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 23:6"/>You do not turn aside the judgment of your poor in his strife; <verse eid="EXO 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 23:7"/>you keep far off from a false matter, and you do not slay an innocent and righteous man; for I do not justify a wicked man. <verse eid="EXO 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 23:8"/>And you do not take a bribe, for the bribe binds the open-[eyed] and perverts the words of the righteous. <verse eid="EXO 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 23:9"/>And you do not oppress a sojourner, since you have known the soul of the sojourner, for you have been sojourners in the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 23:10"/>And [for] six years you sow your land and have gathered its increase; <verse eid="EXO 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 23:11"/>and [in] the seventh you release it, and have left it, and the needy of your people have eaten, and the beast of the field eats their remainder; so you do to your vineyard [and] to your olive-yard. <verse eid="EXO 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 23:12"/>Six days you do your work, and on the seventh day you rest, so that your ox and your donkey rest, and the son of your handmaid and the sojourner is refreshed; <verse eid="EXO 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 23:13"/>and in all that which I have said to you—take heed; and you do not mention the name of other gods; it is not heard on your mouth. <verse eid="EXO 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 23:14"/>You keep a celebration to Me three times in a year: <verse eid="EXO 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 23:15"/>you keep the Celebration of Unleavened Things (you eat unleavened things [for] seven days as I have commanded you, at the time appointed [in] the month of Abib; for in it you have come forth out of Egypt, and you do not appear [in] My presence empty); <verse eid="EXO 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 23:16"/>and the Celebration of Harvest, the first-fruits of your works which you sow in the field; and the Celebration of the Ingathering in the outgoing of the year, in your gathering your works out of the field. <verse eid="EXO 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 23:17"/>Three times in a year all your males appear before [the] face of the Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 23:18"/>You do not sacrifice the blood of My sacrifice on a fermented thing, and the fat of My festival does not remain until morning; <verse eid="EXO 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 23:19"/>the beginning of the first-fruits of your ground you bring into the house of your God YHWH; you do not boil a kid in its mother’s milk. <verse eid="EXO 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 23:20"/>Behold, I am sending a Messenger before you to keep you in the way, and to bring you to the place which I have prepared; <verse eid="EXO 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 23:21"/>be watchful because of His presence, and listen to His voice, do not rebel against Him, for He does not bear with your transgression, for My Name [is] in His heart; <verse eid="EXO 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 23:22"/>for if you listen diligently to His voice, and have done all that which I speak, then I have been at enmity with your enemies, and have distressed those distressing you. <verse eid="EXO 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 23:23"/>For My Messenger goes before you, and has brought you to the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Canaanite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, and I have cut them off. <verse eid="EXO 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 23:24"/>You do not bow yourself to their gods, nor serve them, nor do according to their doings, but utterly devote them, and thoroughly break their standing pillars. <verse eid="EXO 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 23:25"/>And you have served your God YHWH, and He has blessed your bread and your water, and I have turned aside sickness from your heart; <verse eid="EXO 23:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 23:26"/>there is not a miscarrying and barren one in your land; I fulfill the number of your days. <verse eid="EXO 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 23:27"/>I send My terror before you, and I have put to death all the people among whom you come, and I have given the neck of all your enemies to you. <verse eid="EXO 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 23:28"/>And I have sent the hornet before you, and it has cast out the Hivite, the Canaanite, and the Hittite from before you; <verse eid="EXO 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 23:29"/>I do not cast them out from before you in one year, lest the land be a desolation, and the beast of the field has multiplied against you; <verse eid="EXO 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 23:30"/>I cast them out little [by] little from before you, until you are fruitful, and have inherited the land. <verse eid="EXO 23:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 23:31"/>And I have set your border from the Red Sea, even to the sea of the Philistines, and from the wilderness to the River; for I give the inhabitants of the land into your hand, and you have cast them out from before you. <verse eid="EXO 23:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 23:32"/>You do not make a covenant with them and with their gods; <verse eid="EXO 23:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 23:33"/>they do not dwell in your land, lest they cause you to sin against Me when you serve their gods, when it becomes a snare to you.”<verse eid="EXO 23:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="EXO 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 24:1"/>And He said to Moses, “Come up to YHWH, you, and Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, and seventy from [the] elderly of Israel, and you have bowed yourselves far off”; <verse eid="EXO 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 24:2"/>and Moses has drawn near to YHWH by himself; and they do not draw near, and the people do not go up with him. <verse eid="EXO 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 24:3"/>And Moses comes in, and recounts to the people all the words of YHWH, and all the judgments, and all the people answer [with] one voice, and say, “All the words which YHWH has spoken we do.” <verse eid="EXO 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 24:4"/>And Moses writes all the words of YHWH, and rises early in the morning, and builds an altar under the hill, and twelve standing pillars for the twelve tribes of Israel; <verse eid="EXO 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 24:5"/>and he sends the youths of the sons of Israel, and they cause burnt-offerings to ascend, and sacrifice sacrifices of peace-offerings to YHWH—calves. <verse eid="EXO 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 24:6"/>And Moses takes half of the blood and puts [it] in basins, and he has sprinkled half of the blood on the altar; <verse eid="EXO 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 24:7"/>and he takes the Scroll of the Covenant, and proclaims [it] in the ears of the people, and they say, “All that which YHWH has spoken we do, and we obey.” <verse eid="EXO 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 24:8"/>And Moses takes the blood and sprinkles [it] on the people, and says, “Behold, the blood of the covenant which YHWH has made with you, concerning all these things.” <verse eid="EXO 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 24:9"/>And Moses goes up, Aaron also, Nadab and Abihu, and seventy from [the] elderly of Israel, <verse eid="EXO 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 24:10"/>and they see the God of Israel, and under His feet [is] as the work of a pavement of sapphire, and as the substance of the heavens for purity; <verse eid="EXO 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 24:11"/>and He has not put forth His hand to those of the sons of Israel who are near, and they see God, and eat and drink. <verse eid="EXO 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 24:12"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Come up to Me [on] the mountain and be there, and I give to you the tablets of stone, and the Law, and the command, which I have written to direct them.” <verse eid="EXO 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 24:13"/>And Moses rises—his minister Joshua also—and Moses goes up to the mountain of God; <verse eid="EXO 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 24:14"/>and he has said to the elderly, “Abide for us in this [place] until we return to you, and behold, Aaron and Hur [are] with you—he who has matters comes near to them.” <verse eid="EXO 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 24:15"/>And Moses goes up to the mountain, and the cloud covers the mountain; <verse eid="EXO 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 24:16"/>and the glory of YHWH dwells on Mount Sinai, and the cloud covers it [for] six days, and He calls to Moses on the seventh day from the midst of the cloud. <verse eid="EXO 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 24:17"/>And the appearance of the glory of YHWH [is] as a consuming fire on the top of the mountain, before the eyes of the sons of Israel; <verse eid="EXO 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 24:18"/>and Moses goes into the midst of the cloud, and goes up to the mountain, and Moses is on the mountain forty days and forty nights.<verse eid="EXO 24:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="EXO 25"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 25:1"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 25:2"/>“Speak to the sons of Israel, and they take a raised-offering for Me; you take My raised-offering from every man whose heart impels him. <verse eid="EXO 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 25:3"/>And this [is] the raised-offering which you take from them: gold, and silver, and bronze, <verse eid="EXO 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 25:4"/>and blue, and purple, and scarlet, and linen, and goats’ [hair], <verse eid="EXO 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 25:5"/>and rams’ skins made red, and tachashim skins, and shittim wood, <verse eid="EXO 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 25:6"/>oil for the light, spices for the anointing oil, and for the incense of the spices, <verse eid="EXO 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 25:7"/>shoham stones, and stones for setting for an ephod, and for a breastplate. <verse eid="EXO 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 25:8"/>And they have made a sanctuary for Me, and I have dwelt in their midst; <verse eid="EXO 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 25:9"/>according to all that which I am showing you, the pattern of the Dwelling Place, and the pattern of all its vessels, even so you make [it]. <verse eid="EXO 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 25:10"/>And they have made an ark of shittim wood; two cubits and a half its length, and a cubit and a half its breadth, and a cubit and a half its height; <verse eid="EXO 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 25:11"/>and you have overlaid it [with] pure gold, you overlay it inside and outside, and you have made a ring of gold on it all around. <verse eid="EXO 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 25:12"/>And you have cast four rings of gold for it, and have put [them] on its four feet, even two rings on its one side, and two rings on its second side; <verse eid="EXO 25:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 25:13"/>and you have made poles of shittim wood, and have overlaid them [with] gold, <verse eid="EXO 25:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 25:14"/>and have brought the poles into the rings on the sides of the Ark, to carry the Ark by them; <verse eid="EXO 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 25:15"/>the poles are in the rings of the Ark, they are not turned aside from it; <verse eid="EXO 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 25:16"/>and you have put the Testimony which I give to you into the Ark. <verse eid="EXO 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 25:17"/>And you have made a propitiatory covering of pure gold, two cubits and a half its length, and a cubit and a half its breadth; <verse eid="EXO 25:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 25:18"/>and you have made two cherubim of gold; you make them beaten work at the two ends of the propitiatory covering; <verse eid="EXO 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 25:19"/>and make one cherub at the end on this [side] and one cherub at the end on that [side]; at the propitiatory covering you make the cherubim on its two ends. <verse eid="EXO 25:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 25:20"/>And the cherubim have been spreading out wings on high, covering over the propitiatory covering with their wings, and their faces [are] toward one another—the faces of the cherubim are toward the propitiatory covering. <verse eid="EXO 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 25:21"/>And you have put the propitiatory covering on the Ark above, and you put the Testimony which I give to you into the Ark; <verse eid="EXO 25:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 25:22"/>and I have met with you there, and have spoken with you from off the propitiatory covering (from between the two cherubim, which [are] on the Ark of the Testimony) all that which I command you concerning the sons of Israel. <verse eid="EXO 25:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 25:23"/>And you have made a table of shittim wood, two cubits its length, and a cubit its breadth, and a cubit and a half its height, <verse eid="EXO 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 25:24"/>and have overlaid it [with] pure gold, and have made a crown of gold for it all around, <verse eid="EXO 25:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 25:25"/>and have made a border of a handbreadth for it all around, and have made a crown of gold for its border all around. <verse eid="EXO 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 25:26"/>And you have made four rings of gold for it, and have put the rings on the four corners, which [are] at its four feet; <verse eid="EXO 25:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 25:27"/>close by the border are the rings for places for poles to carry the table; <verse eid="EXO 25:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 25:28"/>and you have made the poles of shittim wood, and have overlaid them with gold, and the table has been carried with them; <verse eid="EXO 25:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 25:29"/>and you have made its dishes, and its bowls, and its covers, and its cups, with which they pour out; you make them of pure gold; <verse eid="EXO 25:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 25:30"/>and you have put Bread of the Presentation on the table before Me continually. <verse eid="EXO 25:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 25:31"/>And you have made a lampstand of pure gold; the lampstand is made of beaten work; its base, and its branch, its calyxes, its knobs, and its flowers are of the same; <verse eid="EXO 25:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 25:32"/>and six branches are coming out of its sides, three branches of the lampstand out of the first side, and three branches of the lampstand out of the second side; <verse eid="EXO 25:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 25:33"/>three calyxes made like almonds in one branch, a knob and a flower, and three calyxes made like almonds in one branch, a knob and a flower—so for the six branches which are coming out from the lampstand. <verse eid="EXO 25:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 25:34"/>And in the lampstand [are] four calyxes made like almonds, its knobs and its flowers; <verse eid="EXO 25:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 25:35"/>and a knob under two branches of the same, and a knob under two branches of the same, and a knob under two branches of the same, for the six branches which are coming out of the lampstand; <verse eid="EXO 25:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 25:36"/>their knobs and their branches are of the same, all of it one beaten work of pure gold; <verse eid="EXO 25:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 25:37"/>and you have made its seven lamps, and [one] has caused its lamps to go up, and it has given light over [and] beyond its front. <verse eid="EXO 25:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EXO 25:38"/>And its snuffers and its snuff dishes [are] of pure gold; <verse eid="EXO 25:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EXO 25:39"/>he makes it of a talent of pure gold, with all these vessels. <verse eid="EXO 25:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EXO 25:40"/>Now see and make [them] by their pattern which you are shown on the mountain.”<verse eid="EXO 25:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="EXO 26"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 26:1"/>“And you make the Dwelling Place [with] ten curtains of twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet; [with] cherubim, the work of a designer, you make them; <verse eid="EXO 26:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 26:2"/>the length of the one curtain [is] twenty-eight by the cubit, and the breadth of the one curtain [is] four by the cubit, one measure [is] for all the curtains; <verse eid="EXO 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 26:3"/>five of the curtains are joining to one another, and five curtains are joining to one another. <verse eid="EXO 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 26:4"/>And you have made loops of blue on the edge of the first curtain, at the end in the joining; and so you make in the edge of the outermost curtain, in the joining of the second. <verse eid="EXO 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 26:5"/>You make fifty loops in the first curtain, and you make fifty loops in the edge of the curtain which [is] in the joining of the second, causing the loops to take hold to one another; <verse eid="EXO 26:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 26:6"/>and you have made fifty hooks of gold, and have joined the curtains to one another by the hooks, and the Dwelling Place has been one. <verse eid="EXO 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 26:7"/>And you have made curtains of goats’ [hair] for a tent over the Dwelling Place; you make eleven curtains: <verse eid="EXO 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 26:8"/>the length of one curtain [is] thirty by the cubit, and the breadth of one curtain [is] four by the cubit; one measure [is] for the eleven curtains; <verse eid="EXO 26:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 26:9"/>and you have joined the five curtains apart, and the six curtains apart, and have doubled the six curtains at the front of the tent. <verse eid="EXO 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 26:10"/>And you have made fifty loops on the edge of the first curtain, the outermost in the joining, and fifty loops on the edge of the curtain which is joining the second; <verse eid="EXO 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 26:11"/>and you have made fifty hooks of bronze, and have brought in the hooks into the loops, and have joined the tent, and it has been one. <verse eid="EXO 26:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 26:12"/>And the excess remaining in the curtains of the tent—the half of the curtain which is remaining—has spread over the back part of the Dwelling Place; <verse eid="EXO 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 26:13"/>and the cubit on this [side], and the cubit on that [side], in the remaining [part] of the length of the curtains of the tent, is spread out over the sides of the Dwelling Place, on this [side] and on that [side], to cover it; <verse eid="EXO 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 26:14"/>and you have made a covering for the tent of rams’ skins made red, and a covering of tachashim skins above. <verse eid="EXO 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 26:15"/>And you have made the boards for the Dwelling Place of shittim wood, standing up; <verse eid="EXO 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 26:16"/>ten cubits [is] the length of the board, and a cubit and a half the breadth of one board; <verse eid="EXO 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 26:17"/>two handles [are] to one board, joined to one another; so you make for all the boards of the Dwelling Place; <verse eid="EXO 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 26:18"/>and you have made the boards of the Dwelling Place—twenty boards for the south side southward; <verse eid="EXO 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 26:19"/>and you make forty sockets of silver under the twenty boards, two sockets under one board for its two handles, and two sockets under the other board for its two handles. <verse eid="EXO 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 26:20"/>And for the second side of the Dwelling Place, for the north side, [are] twenty boards, <verse eid="EXO 26:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 26:21"/>and their forty sockets of silver, two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board. <verse eid="EXO 26:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 26:22"/>And for the sides of the Dwelling Place westward, you make six boards. <verse eid="EXO 26:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 26:23"/>And you make two boards for the corners of the Dwelling Place in the two sides. <verse eid="EXO 26:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 26:24"/>And they are pairs beneath, and together they are pairs above its head to one ring; so is it for them both, they are for the two corners. <verse eid="EXO 26:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 26:25"/>And they have been eight boards, and their sockets of silver [are] sixteen sockets, two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board. <verse eid="EXO 26:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 26:26"/>And you have made bars of shittim wood: five for the boards of the first side of the Dwelling Place, <verse eid="EXO 26:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 26:27"/>and five bars for the boards of the second side of the Dwelling Place, and five bars for the boards of the side of the Dwelling Place at the two sides, westward; <verse eid="EXO 26:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 26:28"/>and one has caused the middle bar in the midst of the boards to reach from end to end; <verse eid="EXO 26:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 26:29"/>and you overlay the boards [with] gold, and you make their rings of gold [for] places for bars, and have overlaid their bars with gold; <verse eid="EXO 26:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 26:30"/>and you have raised up the Dwelling Place according to its fashion which you have been shown on the mountain. <verse eid="EXO 26:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 26:31"/>And you have made a veil of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, the work of a designer; he makes it [with] cherubim; <verse eid="EXO 26:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 26:32"/>and you have put it on four pillars of shittim wood, overlaid [with] gold, their pegs [are] of gold, on four sockets of silver. <verse eid="EXO 26:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 26:33"/>And you have put the veil under the hooks, and have brought in the Ark of the Testimony there within the veil; and the veil has made a separation for you between the holy and the Holy of Holies. <verse eid="EXO 26:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 26:34"/>And you have put the propitiatory covering on the Ark of the Testimony in the Holy of Holies. <verse eid="EXO 26:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 26:35"/>And you have set the table at the outside of the veil, and the lampstand opposite the table on the side of the Dwelling Place southward, and you put the table on the north side. <verse eid="EXO 26:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 26:36"/>And you have made a covering for the opening of the tent of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, the work of an embroiderer; <verse eid="EXO 26:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 26:37"/>and you have made five pillars of shittim [wood] for the covering, and have overlaid them [with] gold, their pegs [are] of gold, and you have cast five sockets of bronze for them.”<verse eid="EXO 26:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="EXO 27"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 27:1"/>“And you have made the altar of shittim wood, five cubits the length, and five cubits the breadth—the altar is square—and three cubits [is] its height. <verse eid="EXO 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 27:2"/>And you have made its horns on its four corners, its horns are of the same, and you have overlaid it [with] bronze. <verse eid="EXO 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 27:3"/>And you have made its pots to remove its ashes, and its shovels, and its bowls, and its forks, and its fire-pans, even all its vessels you make of bronze. <verse eid="EXO 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 27:4"/>And you have made a grate of network of bronze for it, and have made four rings of bronze on the net on its four extremities, <verse eid="EXO 27:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 27:5"/>and have put it under the rim of the altar beneath, and the net has been up to the middle of the altar. <verse eid="EXO 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 27:6"/>And you have made poles for the altar, poles of shittim wood, and have overlaid them [with] bronze. <verse eid="EXO 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 27:7"/>And the poles have been brought into the rings, and the poles have been on the two sides of the altar in carrying it. <verse eid="EXO 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 27:8"/>You make it hollow [with] boards; as it has been showed [to] you on the mountain, so do they make [it]. <verse eid="EXO 27:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 27:9"/>And you have made the court of the Dwelling Place: for the south side southward, hangings for the court of twined linen, the length of the first side [is] one hundred by the cubit, <verse eid="EXO 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 27:10"/>and its twenty pillars and their twenty sockets [are] of bronze, the pegs of the pillars and their fillets [are] of silver; <verse eid="EXO 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 27:11"/>and so for the north side in length, hangings of one hundred [cubits] in length, and its twenty pillars and their twenty sockets [are] of bronze, the pegs of the pillars and their fillets [are] of silver. <verse eid="EXO 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 27:12"/>And [for] the breadth of the court at the west side [are] hangings of fifty cubits, their pillars ten, and their sockets ten. <verse eid="EXO 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 27:13"/>And the breadth of the court at the east side, eastward, [is] fifty cubits. <verse eid="EXO 27:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 27:14"/>And the hangings at the side [are] fifteen cubits, their pillars three, and their sockets three. <verse eid="EXO 27:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 27:15"/>And at the second side [are] hangings of fifteen [cubits], their pillars three, and their sockets three. <verse eid="EXO 27:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 27:16"/>And for the gate of the court [is] a covering of twenty cubits of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, the work of an embroiderer; their pillars four, their sockets four. <verse eid="EXO 27:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 27:17"/>All the pillars of the court all around [are] filleted [with] silver, their pegs [are] silver, and their sockets bronze. <verse eid="EXO 27:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 27:18"/>The length of the court [is] one hundred by the cubit, and the breadth fifty by fifty, and the height five cubits, of twined linen, and their sockets [are] bronze; <verse eid="EXO 27:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 27:19"/>for all the vessels of the Dwelling Place, in all its service, and all its pins, and all the pins of the court, [are] bronze. <verse eid="EXO 27:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 27:20"/>And you command the sons of Israel, and they bring pure oil of beaten olive to you for the light, to cause the lamp to go up continually. <verse eid="EXO 27:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 27:21"/>In the Tent of Meeting, at the outside of the veil, which [is] over the Testimony, Aaron—his sons also—arrange it from evening until morning before YHWH. [It is] a continuous statute for their generations, from the sons of Israel.”<verse eid="EXO 27:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="EXO 28"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 28:1"/>“And you, bring your brother Aaron near to you, and his sons with him, from the midst of the sons of Israel, for his being priest to Me, [even] Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar, sons of Aaron; <verse eid="EXO 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 28:2"/>and you have made holy garments for your brother Aaron, for glory and for beauty; <verse eid="EXO 28:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 28:3"/>and you speak to all the wise of heart, whom I have filled [with] a spirit of wisdom, and they have made the garments of Aaron to sanctify him for his being priest to Me. <verse eid="EXO 28:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 28:4"/>And these [are] the garments which they make: a breastplate, and an ephod, and an upper robe, and an embroidered coat, a turban, and a girdle; indeed, they have made holy garments for your brother Aaron, and for his sons, for his being priest to Me. <verse eid="EXO 28:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 28:5"/>And they take the gold, and the blue, and the purple, and the scarlet, and the linen, <verse eid="EXO 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 28:6"/>and have made the ephod of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, the work of a designer; <verse eid="EXO 28:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 28:7"/>it has two shoulders joining at its two ends, and it is joined. <verse eid="EXO 28:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 28:8"/>And the girdle of his ephod which [is] on him, according to its work, is of the same, of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen. <verse eid="EXO 28:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 28:9"/>And you have taken the two shoham stones, and have engraved the names of the sons of Israel on them; <verse eid="EXO 28:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 28:10"/>six of their names on the first stone, and the names of the remaining six on the second stone, according to their births; <verse eid="EXO 28:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 28:11"/>the work of an engraver of stone, [as] engravings of a signet—you engrave the names of the sons of Israel on the two stones; encompassing, you make them [with] filigrees of gold. <verse eid="EXO 28:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 28:12"/>And you have set the two stones on the shoulders of the ephod—stones of memorial to the sons of Israel—and Aaron has borne their names before YHWH, on his two shoulders, for a memorial. <verse eid="EXO 28:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 28:13"/>And you have made filigrees of gold, <verse eid="EXO 28:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 28:14"/>and you make them [with] two chains of pure gold [as] wreathed work, work of thick bands, and you have put the thick chains on the filigrees. <verse eid="EXO 28:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 28:15"/>And you have made a breastplate of judgment, the work of a designer; you make it according to the work of the ephod; you make it of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen; <verse eid="EXO 28:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 28:16"/>it is square, doubled, a span its length, and a span its breadth. <verse eid="EXO 28:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 28:17"/>And you have set settings of stone in it, four rows of stone: a row of sardius, topaz, and carbuncle [is] the first row; <verse eid="EXO 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 28:18"/>and the second row [is] emerald, sapphire, and diamond; <verse eid="EXO 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 28:19"/>and the third row [is] opal, agate, and amethyst; <verse eid="EXO 28:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 28:20"/>and the fourth row [is] beryl, and onyx, and jasper; they are embroidered with gold in their settings, <verse eid="EXO 28:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 28:21"/>and the stones are according to the names of the sons of Israel, twelve according to their names, [as] engravings of a signet, each with his name; they are for the twelve tribes. <verse eid="EXO 28:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 28:22"/>And you have made wreathed chains on the breastplate, [the] work of thick bands of pure gold; <verse eid="EXO 28:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 28:23"/>and you have made two rings of gold on the breastplate, and have put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate; <verse eid="EXO 28:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 28:24"/>and you have put the two thick bands of gold on the two rings at the ends of the breastplate; <verse eid="EXO 28:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 28:25"/>and you put the two ends of the two thick bands on the two filigrees, and you have put [them] on the shoulders of the ephod toward the front of its face. <verse eid="EXO 28:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 28:26"/>And you have made two rings of gold, and have set them on the two ends of the breastplate, on its border, which [is] toward the side of the ephod within it; <verse eid="EXO 28:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 28:27"/>and you have made two rings of gold, and have put them on the two shoulders of the ephod, from beneath, in front of its face, close by its joining, above the girdle of the ephod, <verse eid="EXO 28:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 28:28"/>and they bind the breastplate by its rings to the rings of the ephod with a ribbon of blue, to be above the girdle of the ephod, and the breastplate is not loosed from the ephod. <verse eid="EXO 28:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 28:29"/>And Aaron has borne the names of the sons of Israel in the breastplate of judgment, on his heart, in his going into the holy place, for a memorial before YHWH continually. <verse eid="EXO 28:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 28:30"/>And you have put the Lights and the Perfections into the breastplate of judgment, and they have been on the heart of Aaron, in his going in before YHWH, and Aaron has borne the judgment of the sons of Israel on his heart before YHWH continually. <verse eid="EXO 28:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 28:31"/>And you have made the upper robe of the ephod completely of blue, <verse eid="EXO 28:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 28:32"/>and the opening for his head has been in its midst; there is a border for its opening all around—the work of a weaver—[and] there is as the opening of a [linen] habergeon for it; it is not torn. <verse eid="EXO 28:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 28:33"/>And you have made on its hem pomegranates of blue, and purple, and scarlet, on its hem all around, and bells of gold in their midst all around; <verse eid="EXO 28:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 28:34"/>a bell of gold and a pomegranate [and] a bell of gold and a pomegranate [are] on the hems of the upper robe all around. <verse eid="EXO 28:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 28:35"/>And it has been on Aaron to minister in, and its sound has been heard in his coming into the holy place before YHWH, and in his going out, and he does not die. <verse eid="EXO 28:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 28:36"/>And you have made a flower of pure gold, and have engraved engravings of a signet on it: Holy to YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 28:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 28:37"/>and you have put it on a blue ribbon, and it has been on the turban—it is toward the front of the face of the turban; <verse eid="EXO 28:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EXO 28:38"/>and it has been on the forehead of Aaron, and Aaron has borne the iniquity of the holy things which the sons of Israel hallow, even all their holy gifts; and it has been on his forehead continually for a pleasing thing for them before YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 28:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EXO 28:39"/>And you have embroidered the coat of linen, and have made a turban of linen, and you make a girdle—the work of an embroiderer. <verse eid="EXO 28:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EXO 28:40"/>And you make coats for the sons of Aaron, and you have made girdles for them, and you make caps for them, for glory and for beauty; <verse eid="EXO 28:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="EXO 28:41"/>and you have clothed your brother Aaron with them, and his sons with him, and have anointed them, and have consecrated their hand, and have sanctified them, and they have been priests to Me. <verse eid="EXO 28:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="EXO 28:42"/>And make linen trousers for them to cover the naked flesh; they are from the loins even to the thighs; <verse eid="EXO 28:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="EXO 28:43"/>and they have been on Aaron and on his sons in their going into the Tent of Meeting, or in their drawing near to the altar to minister in the holy place, and they do not bear iniquity nor have they died; [it is] a continuous statute to him and to his seed after him.”<verse eid="EXO 28:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="EXO 29"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 29:1"/>“And this [is] the thing which you do to them, to hallow them, for being priests to Me: take one bullock, a son of the herd, and two rams, perfect ones, <verse eid="EXO 29:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 29:2"/>and unleavened bread, and unleavened cakes anointed with oil; you make them of fine wheat flour, <verse eid="EXO 29:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 29:3"/>and you have put them on one basket, and have brought them near in the basket, also the bullock and the two rams. <verse eid="EXO 29:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 29:4"/>And you bring Aaron and his sons near to the opening of the Tent of Meeting, and have bathed them with water; <verse eid="EXO 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 29:5"/>and you have taken the garments, and have clothed Aaron with the coat, and the upper robe of the ephod, and the ephod, and the breastplate, and have girded him with the girdle of the ephod, <verse eid="EXO 29:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 29:6"/>and have set the turban on his head, and have put the holy crown on the turban, <verse eid="EXO 29:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 29:7"/>and have taken the anointing oil, and have poured [it] on his head, and have anointed him. <verse eid="EXO 29:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 29:8"/>And you bring his sons near, and have clothed them [with] coats, <verse eid="EXO 29:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 29:9"/>and have girded them [with] a girdle (Aaron and his sons), and have bound caps on them; and the priesthood has been theirs by a continuous statute, and you have consecrated the hand of Aaron, and the hand of his sons, <verse eid="EXO 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 29:10"/>and have brought the bullock near before the Tent of Meeting, and Aaron has laid—his sons also—their hands on the head of the bullock. <verse eid="EXO 29:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 29:11"/>And you have slaughtered the bullock before YHWH, at the opening of the Tent of Meeting, <verse eid="EXO 29:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 29:12"/>and have taken of the blood of the bullock, and have put [it] on the horns of the altar with your finger, and you pour out all the blood at the foundation of the altar; <verse eid="EXO 29:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 29:13"/>and you have taken all the fat which is covering the innards, and the redundance on the liver, and the two kidneys, and the fat which [is] on them, and have made incense on the altar; <verse eid="EXO 29:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 29:14"/>and the flesh of the bullock, and his skin, and his dung, you burn with fire at the outside of the camp; it [is] a sin-offering. <verse eid="EXO 29:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 29:15"/>And you take the first ram, and Aaron and his sons have laid their hands on the head of the ram, <verse eid="EXO 29:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 29:16"/>and you have slaughtered the ram, and have taken its blood, and have sprinkled [it] around the altar, <verse eid="EXO 29:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 29:17"/>and you cut the ram into its pieces, and have washed its innards, and its legs, and have put [them] on its pieces, and on its head; <verse eid="EXO 29:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 29:18"/>and you have made incense with the whole ram on the altar. It [is] a burnt-offering to YHWH, a refreshing fragrance; it [is] a fire-offering to YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 29:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 29:19"/>And you have taken the second ram, and Aaron has laid—his sons also—their hands on the head of the ram, <verse eid="EXO 29:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 29:20"/>and you have slaughtered the ram, and have taken of its blood, and have put [it] on the tip of the right ear of Aaron, and on the tip of the right ear of his sons, and on the thumb of their right hand, and on the great toe of their right foot, and have sprinkled the blood around the altar; <verse eid="EXO 29:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 29:21"/>and you have taken of the blood which [is] on the altar, and of the anointing oil, and have sprinkled [it] on Aaron, and on his garments, and on his sons, and on the garments of his sons with him, and he has been hallowed, he and his garments, and his sons, and the garments of his sons with him. <verse eid="EXO 29:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 29:22"/>And you have taken from the ram the fat, and the fat tail, and the fat which is covering the innards, and the redundance on the liver, and the two kidneys, and the fat which [is] on them, and the right leg, for it [is] a ram of consecration, <verse eid="EXO 29:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 29:23"/>and one round cake of bread, and one cake of oiled bread, and one thin cake out of the basket of the unleavened things which [is] before YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 29:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 29:24"/>and you have set the whole on the hands of Aaron, and on the hands of his sons, and have waved them [for] a wave-offering before YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 29:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 29:25"/>and you have taken them out of their hand, and have made incense on the altar beside the burnt-offering, for refreshing fragrance before YHWH; it [is] a fire-offering to YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 29:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 29:26"/>And you have taken the breast from the ram of the consecration which [is] for Aaron, and have waved it [for] a wave-offering before YHWH, and it has become your portion; <verse eid="EXO 29:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 29:27"/>and you have sanctified the breast of the wave-offering, and the leg of the raised-offering, which has been waved, and which has been lifted up from the ram of the consecration, of that which [is] for Aaron, and of that which [is] for his sons; <verse eid="EXO 29:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 29:28"/>and it has been for Aaron and for his sons, by a continuous statute from the sons of Israel, for it [is] a raised-offering; and it is a raised-offering from the sons of Israel, from the sacrifices of their peace-offerings—their raised-offering to YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 29:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 29:29"/>And the holy garments which are Aaron’s are for his sons after him, to be anointed in them and to consecrate their hand in them; <verse eid="EXO 29:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 29:30"/>[for] seven days the priest in his stead (of his sons) puts them on when he goes into the Tent of Meeting to minister in the holy place. <verse eid="EXO 29:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 29:31"/>And you take the ram of the consecration and have boiled its flesh in the holy place; <verse eid="EXO 29:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 29:32"/>and Aaron has eaten—his sons also—the flesh of the ram, and the bread which [is] in the basket, at the opening of the Tent of Meeting; <verse eid="EXO 29:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 29:33"/>and they have eaten those things by which there is atonement to consecrate their hand, to sanctify them; and a stranger does not eat [them], for they [are] holy; <verse eid="EXO 29:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 29:34"/>and if there is left of the flesh of the consecration or of the bread until the morning, then you have burned that which is left with fire; it is not eaten, for it [is] holy. <verse eid="EXO 29:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 29:35"/>And you have done thus to Aaron and to his sons, according to all that I have commanded you; [for] seven days you consecrate their hand; <verse eid="EXO 29:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 29:36"/>and a bullock, a sin-offering, you prepare daily for the atonements, and you have atoned for the altar in your making atonement on it, and have anointed it to sanctify it; <verse eid="EXO 29:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 29:37"/>[for] seven days you make atonement for the altar, and have sanctified it, and the altar has been most holy; all that is coming against the altar is holy. <verse eid="EXO 29:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EXO 29:38"/>And this [is] that which you prepare on the altar: two lambs, sons of a year, daily continually; <verse eid="EXO 29:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EXO 29:39"/>you prepare the first lamb in the morning, and you prepare the second lamb between the evenings; <verse eid="EXO 29:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EXO 29:40"/>and a tenth part of fine flour mixed with a fourth part of a hin of beaten oil, and a fourth part of a hin of wine [for] a drink-offering, [is] for the first lamb. <verse eid="EXO 29:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="EXO 29:41"/>And you prepare the second lamb between the evenings; according to the present of the morning, and according to its drink-offering, you prepare for it, for refreshing fragrance, a fire-offering to YHWH— <verse eid="EXO 29:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="EXO 29:42"/>a continual burnt-offering for your generations [at] the opening of the Tent of Meeting before YHWH, to where I meet with you to speak to you there, <verse eid="EXO 29:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="EXO 29:43"/>and I have met with the sons of Israel there, and it has been sanctified by My glory. <verse eid="EXO 29:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="EXO 29:44"/>And I have sanctified the Tent of Meeting and the altar, and I sanctify Aaron and his sons for being priests to Me, <verse eid="EXO 29:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="EXO 29:45"/>and I have dwelt in the midst of the sons of Israel, and have become their God, <verse eid="EXO 29:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="EXO 29:46"/>and they have known that I [am] their God YHWH, who has brought them out of the land of Egypt, that I may dwell in their midst; I [am] their God YHWH.”<verse eid="EXO 29:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="EXO 30"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 30:1"/>“And you have made an altar [for] making incense; you make it of shittim wood; <verse eid="EXO 30:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 30:2"/>a cubit its length and a cubit its breadth (it is square), and two cubits its height; its horns [are] of the same. <verse eid="EXO 30:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 30:3"/>And you have overlaid it with pure gold—its top, and around its sides, and its horns; and you have made a crown of gold for it all around; <verse eid="EXO 30:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 30:4"/>and you make two rings of gold for it, under its crown on its two ribs; you make [them] on its two sides, and they have become places for poles to carry it with them. <verse eid="EXO 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 30:5"/>And you have made the poles of shittim wood, and have overlaid them with gold; <verse eid="EXO 30:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 30:6"/>and you have put it before the veil, which [is] by the Ark of the Testimony, before the propitiatory covering which [is] over the Testimony, where I meet with you. <verse eid="EXO 30:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 30:7"/>And Aaron has made incense on it, incense of spices, morning by morning; in his making the lamps right, he makes incense [on] it, <verse eid="EXO 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 30:8"/>and in Aaron’s causing the lamps to go up between the evenings, he makes incense [on] it; [it is] a continual incense before YHWH throughout your generations. <verse eid="EXO 30:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 30:9"/>You do not cause strange incense to go up on it—and burnt-offering and present; and you do not pour out a drink-offering on it; <verse eid="EXO 30:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 30:10"/>and Aaron has made atonement on its horns once in a year, by the blood of the sin-offering of atonements; once in a year he makes atonement for it, throughout your generations; it [is] most holy to YHWH.” <verse eid="EXO 30:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 30:11"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 30:12"/>“When you take up the census of the sons of Israel for their numbers, then they have each given an atonement [for] his soul to YHWH in their being numbered, and there is no plague among them in their being numbered. <verse eid="EXO 30:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 30:13"/>This they give, everyone passing over to those numbered, half a shekel, by the shekel of the holy place (the shekel [is] twenty gerahs); half a shekel [is] the raised-offering to YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 30:14"/>everyone passing over to those numbered, from a son of twenty years and upwards, gives the raised-offering of YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 30:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 30:15"/>the rich do not multiply, and the poor do not diminish from the half-shekel, to give the raised-offering of YHWH, to make atonement for your souls. <verse eid="EXO 30:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 30:16"/>And you have taken the atonement-money from the sons of Israel, and have given it for the service of the Tent of Meeting; and it has been to the sons of Israel for a memorial before YHWH, to make atonement for your souls.” <verse eid="EXO 30:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 30:17"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 30:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 30:18"/>“And you have made a laver of bronze (and its base of bronze), for washing; and you have put it between the Tent of Meeting and the altar, and have put water [in] there, <verse eid="EXO 30:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 30:19"/>and Aaron and his sons have washed their hands and their feet from it; <verse eid="EXO 30:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 30:20"/>they wash [with] water in their going into the Tent of Meeting, and do not die; or in their drawing near to the altar to minister, to make incense [as] a fire-offering to YHWH, <verse eid="EXO 30:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 30:21"/>then they have washed their hands and their feet, and they do not die, and it has been a continuous statute to them, to him and to his seed, throughout their generations.” <verse eid="EXO 30:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 30:22"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 30:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 30:23"/>“And you, take [these] principal spices for yourself: five hundred [shekels] of liquid myrrh, and the half of that—two hundred and fifty [shekels]—of spice-cinnamon, and two hundred and fifty [shekels] of spice-cane, <verse eid="EXO 30:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 30:24"/>and five hundred [shekels] of cassia, by the shekel of the holy place, and a hin of olive oil; <verse eid="EXO 30:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 30:25"/>and you have made it a holy anointing oil, a compound mixture, work of a compounder; it is a holy anointing oil. <verse eid="EXO 30:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 30:26"/>And with it you have anointed the Tent of Meeting, and the Ark of the Testimony, <verse eid="EXO 30:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 30:27"/>and the table and all its vessels, and the lampstand and its vessels, and the altar of incense, <verse eid="EXO 30:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 30:28"/>and the altar of burnt-offering and all its vessels, and the laver and its base; <verse eid="EXO 30:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 30:29"/>and you have sanctified them, and they have been most holy; all that is coming against them is holy; <verse eid="EXO 30:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 30:30"/>and you anoint Aaron and his sons, and have sanctified them for being priests to Me. <verse eid="EXO 30:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 30:31"/>And you speak to the sons of Israel, saying, This is a holy anointing oil to Me, throughout your generations; <verse eid="EXO 30:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 30:32"/>it is not poured on [the] flesh of man, and you make nothing [else] like it in its proportion; it [is] holy—it is holy to you; <verse eid="EXO 30:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 30:33"/>a man who compounds [any] like it, or who puts of it on a stranger, has even been cut off from his people.” <verse eid="EXO 30:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 30:34"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Take to yourself spices—stacte, and onycha, and galbanum—spices and pure frankincense; they are part for part; <verse eid="EXO 30:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 30:35"/>and you have made it an incense, a compound, work of a compounder, salted, pure, holy; <verse eid="EXO 30:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 30:36"/>and you have beaten [some] of it small, and have put of it before the Testimony in the Tent of Meeting, to where I meet with you; it is most holy to you. <verse eid="EXO 30:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 30:37"/>As for the incense which you make, you do not make [any] for yourselves in its proportion; it is holy to you for YHWH; <verse eid="EXO 30:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EXO 30:38"/>a man who makes [any] like it—to be refreshed by it—has even been cut off from his people.”<verse eid="EXO 30:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="EXO 31"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 31:1"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 31:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 31:2"/>“See, I have called by name Bezaleel, son of Uri, son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, <verse eid="EXO 31:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 31:3"/>and I fill him [with] the Spirit of God, in wisdom, and in understanding, and in knowledge, and in all work, <verse eid="EXO 31:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 31:4"/>to devise inventions to work in gold, and in silver, and in bronze, <verse eid="EXO 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 31:5"/>and in a carving of stone for settings, and in a carving of wood to work in all work. <verse eid="EXO 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 31:6"/>And I, behold, have given with him Aholiab, son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan, and I have given wisdom in the heart of every wise-hearted one, and they have made all that which I have commanded you. <verse eid="EXO 31:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 31:7"/>The Tent of Meeting, and the Ark of Testimony, and the propitiatory covering which [is] on it, and all the vessels of the tent, <verse eid="EXO 31:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 31:8"/>and the table and its vessels, and the pure lampstand and all its vessels, and the altar of the incense, <verse eid="EXO 31:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 31:9"/>and the altar of the burnt-offering and all its vessels, and the laver and its base, <verse eid="EXO 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 31:10"/>and the colored garments, and the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, for acting as priests in; <verse eid="EXO 31:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 31:11"/>and the anointing oil, and the incense of the spices for the holy place; according to all that I have commanded you—they do.” <verse eid="EXO 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 31:12"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 31:13"/>“And you, speak to the sons of Israel, saying, Surely you keep My Sabbaths, for it [is] a sign between Me and you throughout your generations, to know that I, YHWH, am sanctifying you; <verse eid="EXO 31:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 31:14"/>and you have kept the Sabbath, for it [is] holy to you, he who is defiling it is certainly put to death—for any who does work in it—that person has even been cut off from the midst of his people. <verse eid="EXO 31:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 31:15"/>[For] six days work is done, and in the seventh day [is] a Sabbath of holy rest to YHWH; any who does work in the Sabbath day is certainly put to death, <verse eid="EXO 31:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 31:16"/>and the sons of Israel have observed the Sabbath; to keep the Sabbath throughout their generations [is] a perpetual covenant— <verse eid="EXO 31:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 31:17"/>it [is] a sign between Me and the sons of Israel for all time; for [in] six days YHWH made the heavens and the earth, and in the seventh day He has ceased and is refreshed.” <verse eid="EXO 31:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 31:18"/>And He gives to Moses, when He finishes speaking with him in Mount Sinai, two tablets of the Testimony, tablets of stone, written by the finger of God.<verse eid="EXO 31:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 31"/>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="EXO 32"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 32:1"/>And the people see that Moses is delaying to come down from the mountain, and the people assemble against Aaron, and say to him, “Rise, make gods for us, who go before us, for this Moses—the man who brought us up out of the land of Egypt—we have not known what has happened to him.” <verse eid="EXO 32:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 32:2"/>And Aaron says to them, “Break off the rings of gold which [are] in the ears of your wives, your sons, and your daughters, and bring [them] to me”; <verse eid="EXO 32:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 32:3"/>and all the people break off the rings of gold which [are] in their ears, and bring [them] to Aaron, <verse eid="EXO 32:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 32:4"/>and he receives [it] from their hand, and fashions it with an engraving tool, and makes it [into] a molten calf, and they say, “These [are] your gods, O Israel, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt!” <verse eid="EXO 32:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 32:5"/>And Aaron sees, and builds an altar before it, and Aaron calls, and says, “A festival to YHWH—tomorrow”; <verse eid="EXO 32:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 32:6"/>and they rise early on the next day, and cause burnt-offerings to ascend, and bring peace-offerings near; and the people sit down to eat and to drink, and rise up to play. <verse eid="EXO 32:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 32:7"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Go, descend, for your people whom you have brought up out of the land of Egypt have done corruptly, <verse eid="EXO 32:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 32:8"/>they have quickly turned aside from the way that I have commanded them; they have made a molten calf for themselves, and bow themselves to it, and sacrifice to it, and say, These [are] your gods, O Israel, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt!” <verse eid="EXO 32:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 32:9"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “I have seen this people, and behold, it [is] a stiff-necked people; <verse eid="EXO 32:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 32:10"/>and now, leave Me alone, and My anger burns against them, and I consume them, and I make you become a great nation.” <verse eid="EXO 32:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 32:11"/>And Moses appeases the face of his God YHWH and says, “Why, O YHWH, does Your anger burn against Your people, whom You have brought forth out of the land of Egypt with great power and with a strong hand? <verse eid="EXO 32:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 32:12"/>Why do the Egyptians speak, saying, He brought them out in calamity to slay them among mountains, and to consume them from off the face of the ground? Turn back from the heat of Your anger, and relent from this calamity against Your people. <verse eid="EXO 32:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 32:13"/>Be mindful of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Israel, Your servants, to whom You have sworn by Yourself, and to whom You speak: I multiply your seed as stars of the heavens, and all this land, as I have said, I give to your seed, and they have inherited [it] for all time”; <verse eid="EXO 32:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 32:14"/>and YHWH relents from the evil which He has spoken of doing to His people. <verse eid="EXO 32:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 32:15"/>And Moses turns, and goes down from the mountain, and the two tablets of the Testimony [are] in his hand, tablets written on both their sides; they [are] written on this [side] and on that [side]; <verse eid="EXO 32:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 32:16"/>and the tablets are the work of God, and the writing is the writing of God, engraved on the tablets. <verse eid="EXO 32:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 32:17"/>And Joshua hears the voice of the people in their shouting and says to Moses, “A noise of battle in the camp!” <verse eid="EXO 32:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 32:18"/>And he says, “It is not the voice of the crying of might, nor is it the voice of the crying of weakness—I am hearing a voice of singing.” <verse eid="EXO 32:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 32:19"/>And it comes to pass, when he has drawn near to the camp, that he sees the calf, and the dancing, and the anger of Moses burns, and he casts the tablets out of his hands, and breaks them below the mountain; <verse eid="EXO 32:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 32:20"/>and he takes the calf which they have made, and burns [it] with fire, and grinds [it] until [it is] small, and scatters [it] on the face of the waters, and causes the sons of Israel to drink. <verse eid="EXO 32:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 32:21"/>And Moses says to Aaron, “What has this people done to you, that you have brought in a great sin on it?” <verse eid="EXO 32:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 32:22"/>And Aaron says, “Do not let the anger of my lord burn; you have known the people, that it [is beset] with evil; <verse eid="EXO 32:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 32:23"/>and they say to me, Make gods for us, who go before us, for this Moses—the man who brought us up out of the land of Egypt—we have not known what has happened to him; <verse eid="EXO 32:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 32:24"/>and I say to them, Whoever has gold, let them break [it] off, and they give [it] to me, and I cast it into the fire, and this calf comes out.” <verse eid="EXO 32:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 32:25"/>And Moses sees the people, that it [is] unbridled, for Aaron has made it unbridled for contempt among its withstanders, <verse eid="EXO 32:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 32:26"/>and Moses stands in the gate of the camp and says, “Who [is] for YHWH? [Come] to me!” And all the sons of Levi are gathered to him; <verse eid="EXO 32:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 32:27"/>and he says to them, “Thus said YHWH, God of Israel: Each put his sword by his thigh, pass over and turn back from gate to gate through the camp, and each slay his brother, and each his friend, and each his relation.” <verse eid="EXO 32:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 32:28"/>And the sons of Levi do according to the word of Moses, and there falls of the people on that day about three thousand men, <verse eid="EXO 32:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 32:29"/>and Moses says, “Consecrate your hand to YHWH today, for a man [is] against his son, and against his brother, so as to bring a blessing on you today.” <verse eid="EXO 32:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 32:30"/>And it comes to pass, on the next day, that Moses says to the people, “You have sinned a great sin, and now I go up to YHWH, perhaps I can atone for your sin.” <verse eid="EXO 32:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 32:31"/>And Moses turns back to YHWH and says, “Ah, now this people has sinned a great sin, that they make a god of gold for themselves; <verse eid="EXO 32:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 32:32"/>and now, if You take away their sin—and if not—please blot me out of Your scroll which You have written.” <verse eid="EXO 32:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 32:33"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Whoever has sinned against Me—I blot him out of My scroll; <verse eid="EXO 32:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 32:34"/>and now, go, lead the people wherever I have spoken to you of; behold, My Messenger goes before you, and in the day of my charging—then I have charged their sin on them.” <verse eid="EXO 32:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 32:35"/>And YHWH plagues the people because they made the calf which Aaron made.<verse eid="EXO 32:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 32"/>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="EXO 33"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 33:1"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, “Go, ascend from this [place], you and the people, whom you have brought up out of the land of Egypt, to the land which I have sworn to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying, I give it to your seed. <verse eid="EXO 33:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 33:2"/>And I have sent a Messenger before you, and have cast out the Canaanite, the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite. <verse eid="EXO 33:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 33:3"/>[Go up] to a land flowing with milk and honey, for I do not go up in your midst, for you [are] a stiff-necked people—lest I consume you in the way.” <verse eid="EXO 33:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 33:4"/>And the people hear this sad thing, and mourn; and none puts his ornaments on him. <verse eid="EXO 33:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 33:5"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Say to the sons of Israel: You [are] a stiff-necked people; [in] one moment I could come up into your midst and could have consumed you; and now, put down your ornaments from off you, and I know what I do to you”; <verse eid="EXO 33:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 33:6"/>and the sons of Israel take off their ornaments at Mount Horeb. <verse eid="EXO 33:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 33:7"/>And Moses takes the tent, and has stretched it out at the outside of the camp, far off from the camp, and has called it, “Tent of Meeting”; and it has come to pass, everyone seeking YHWH goes out to the Tent of Meeting, which [is] at the outside of the camp. <verse eid="EXO 33:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 33:8"/>And it has come to pass, at the going out of Moses to the tent, all the people rise, and have stood, each at the opening of his tent, and have looked expectingly after Moses, until his going into the tent. <verse eid="EXO 33:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 33:9"/>And it has come to pass, at the going in of Moses to the tent, the pillar of the cloud comes down, and has stood at the opening of the tent, and He has spoken with Moses; <verse eid="EXO 33:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 33:10"/>and all the people have seen the pillar of the cloud standing at the opening of the tent, and all the people have risen and bowed themselves, each at the opening of his tent. <verse eid="EXO 33:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 33:11"/>And YHWH has spoken to Moses face to face, as a man speaks to his friend; and he has turned back to the camp, and his minister Joshua, son of Nun, a youth, does not depart out of the tent. <verse eid="EXO 33:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 33:12"/>And Moses says to YHWH, “See, You are saying to me, Bring up this people, and You have not caused me to know whom You send with me; and You have said, I have known you by name, and you have also found grace in My eyes. <verse eid="EXO 33:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 33:13"/>And now, if, please, I have found grace in Your eyes, please cause me to know Your way, and I know You, so that I find grace in Your eyes, and consider that this nation [is] Your people”; <verse eid="EXO 33:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 33:14"/>and He says, “My presence goes, and I have given rest to you.” <verse eid="EXO 33:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 33:15"/>And he says to Him, “If Your presence is not going—do not take us up from this [place]; <verse eid="EXO 33:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 33:16"/>and in what is it known now, that I have found grace in Your eyes—I and Your people—is it not in Your going with us? And we have been distinguished—I and Your people—from all the people who [are] on the face of the ground.” <verse eid="EXO 33:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 33:17"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Even this thing which you have spoken I do; for you have found grace in My eyes, and I know you by name.” <verse eid="EXO 33:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 33:18"/>And he says, “Please show me Your glory”; <verse eid="EXO 33:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 33:19"/>and He says, “I cause all My goodness to pass before your face, and have called concerning the Name of YHWH before you, and favored him whom I favor, and loved him whom I love.” <verse eid="EXO 33:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 33:20"/>He also says, “You are unable to see My face, for man does not see Me and live”; <verse eid="EXO 33:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 33:21"/>YHWH also says, “Behold, a place [is] by Me, and you have stood on the rock, <verse eid="EXO 33:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 33:22"/>and it has come to pass, in the passing by of My glory, that I have set you in a cleft of the rock, and spread out My hands over you until My passing by, <verse eid="EXO 33:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 33:23"/>and I have turned aside My hands, and you have seen My back parts, and My face is not seen.”<verse eid="EXO 33:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 33"/>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="EXO 34"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 34:1"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Hew for yourself two tablets of stone like the first, and I have written on the tablets the words which were on the first tablets which you have broken; <verse eid="EXO 34:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 34:2"/>and be prepared at morning, and you have come up in the morning to Mount Sinai, and have stood before Me there, on the top of the mountain, <verse eid="EXO 34:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 34:3"/>and no man comes up with you, and also no man is seen in all the mountain, also the flock and the herd do not feed toward the front of that mountain.” <verse eid="EXO 34:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 34:4"/>And he hews two tablets of stone like the first, and Moses rises early in the morning, and goes up to Mount Sinai as YHWH commanded him, and takes [the] two tablets of stone in his hand. <verse eid="EXO 34:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 34:5"/>And YHWH comes down in a cloud, and stations Himself with him there, and calls in the Name of YHWH, <verse eid="EXO 34:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 34:6"/>and YHWH passes over before his face, and calls: “YHWH, YHWH God, merciful and gracious, slow to anger, and abundant in kindness and truth, <verse eid="EXO 34:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 34:7"/>keeping kindness for thousands, taking away iniquity, and transgression, and sin, and not entirely acquitting, charging iniquity of fathers on sons and on sons’ sons, on a third and on a fourth [generation].” <verse eid="EXO 34:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 34:8"/>And Moses hurries, and bows to the earth, and pays respect, <verse eid="EXO 34:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 34:9"/>and says, “Now if I have found grace in Your eyes, O my Lord, please let my Lord go in our midst (for it [is] a stiff-necked people), and you have forgiven our iniquity and our sin, and have inherited us.” <verse eid="EXO 34:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 34:10"/>And He says, “Behold, I am making a covenant. I do wonders before all your people, which have not been done in all the earth, or in any nation, and all the people in whose midst you [are in] have seen the work of YHWH, for it [is] fearful—that which I am doing with you. <verse eid="EXO 34:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 34:11"/>Observe for yourself that which I am commanding you today. Behold, I am casting out from before you the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite; <verse eid="EXO 34:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 34:12"/>take heed to yourself lest you make a covenant with the inhabitant of the land into which you are going, lest it become a snare in your midst; <verse eid="EXO 34:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 34:13"/>for you break down their altars, and you shatter their standing pillars, and you cut down its Asherim; <verse eid="EXO 34:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 34:14"/>for you do not bow yourselves to another god—for YHWH, whose Name [is] Zealous, is a zealous God. <verse eid="EXO 34:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 34:15"/>Lest you make a covenant with the inhabitant of the land, and they have gone whoring after their gods, and have sacrificed to their gods, and [one] has called to you, and you have eaten of his sacrifice, <verse eid="EXO 34:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 34:16"/>and you have taken of their daughters for your sons, and their daughters have gone whoring after their gods, and have caused your sons to go whoring after their gods; <verse eid="EXO 34:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 34:17"/>you do not make a molten god for yourself. <verse eid="EXO 34:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 34:18"/>You keep the Celebration of Unleavened Things; [for] seven days you eat unleavened things, as I have commanded you, at an appointed time, [in] the month of Abib: for in the month of Abib you came out from Egypt. <verse eid="EXO 34:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 34:19"/>All opening a womb [are] Mine, and every firstling of your livestock born a male, [whether] ox or sheep; <verse eid="EXO 34:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 34:20"/>and you ransom the firstling of a donkey with a lamb; and if you do not ransom, then you have beheaded it; you ransom every firstborn of your sons, and they do not appear before Me empty. <verse eid="EXO 34:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 34:21"/>[For] six days you work, and on the seventh day you rest; in plowing-time and in harvest you rest. <verse eid="EXO 34:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 34:22"/>And you observe [the] Celebration of Weeks for yourself, of [the] first-fruits of wheat-harvest; and the Celebration of Ingathering at the revolution of the year. <verse eid="EXO 34:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 34:23"/>Three times in a year all your males appear before the Lord YHWH, God of Israel; <verse eid="EXO 34:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 34:24"/>for I dispossess nations from before you, and have enlarged your border, and no man desires your land in your going up to appear before your God YHWH three times in a year. <verse eid="EXO 34:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 34:25"/>You do not slaughter the blood of My sacrifice with a fermented thing; and the sacrifice of the Celebration of the Passover does not remain until morning. <verse eid="EXO 34:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 34:26"/>You bring the first of the first-fruits of the land into the house of your God YHWH. You do not boil a kid in its mother’s milk.” <verse eid="EXO 34:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 34:27"/>And YHWH says to Moses, “Write these words for yourself, for I have made a covenant with you and with Israel according to the tenor of these words.” <verse eid="EXO 34:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 34:28"/>And he is there with YHWH forty days and forty nights; he has not eaten bread, and he has not drunk water; and he writes on the tablets the matters of the covenant—the Ten Commandments. <verse eid="EXO 34:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 34:29"/>And it comes to pass, when Moses is coming down from Mount Sinai (and the two tablets of the Testimony [are] in the hand of Moses in his coming down from the mountain), that Moses has not known that the skin of his face has shone in His speaking with him, <verse eid="EXO 34:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 34:30"/>and Aaron sees—all the sons of Israel also—Moses, and behold, the skin of his face has shone, and they are afraid of coming near to him. <verse eid="EXO 34:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 34:31"/>And Moses calls to them, and Aaron and all the princes in the congregation return to him, and Moses speaks to them; <verse eid="EXO 34:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 34:32"/>and afterward all the sons of Israel have come near, and he charges them with all that YHWH has spoken with him in Mount Sinai. <verse eid="EXO 34:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 34:33"/>And Moses finishes speaking with them, and puts a veil on his face; <verse eid="EXO 34:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 34:34"/>and in the going in of Moses before YHWH to speak with Him, he turns aside the veil until his coming out; and he has come out and has spoken to the sons of Israel that which he is commanded; <verse eid="EXO 34:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 34:35"/>and the sons of Israel have seen the face of Moses, that the skin of the face of Moses has shone, and Moses has put back the veil on his face until his going in to speak with Him.<verse eid="EXO 34:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 34"/>
  <chapter number="35" style="c" sid="EXO 35"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 35:1"/>And Moses assembles all the congregation of the sons of Israel and says to them, “These [are] the things which YHWH has commanded—to do them: <verse eid="EXO 35:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 35:2"/>[For] six days work is done, and on the seventh day there is a holy [day] for you, a Sabbath of rest to YHWH; any who does work in it is put to death; <verse eid="EXO 35:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 35:3"/>you do not burn a fire in any of your dwellings on the Sabbath day.” <verse eid="EXO 35:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 35:4"/>And Moses speaks to all the congregation of the sons of Israel, saying, “This [is] the thing which YHWH has commanded, saying, <verse eid="EXO 35:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 35:5"/>Take a raised-offering for YHWH from among you; everyone whose heart [is] willing brings it [as] the raised-offering of YHWH: gold, and silver, and bronze, <verse eid="EXO 35:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 35:6"/>and blue, and purple, and scarlet, and linen, and goats’ [hair], <verse eid="EXO 35:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 35:7"/>and rams’ skins made red, and tachashim skins, and shittim wood, <verse eid="EXO 35:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 35:8"/>and oil for the light, and spices for the anointing oil, and for the spice-incense, <verse eid="EXO 35:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 35:9"/>and shoham stones, and stones for settings, for an ephod, and for a breastplate. <verse eid="EXO 35:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 35:10"/>And all the wise-hearted among you come in, and make all that YHWH has commanded: <verse eid="EXO 35:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 35:11"/>the Dwelling Place, its tent, and its covering, its hooks, and its boards, its bars, its pillars, and its sockets, <verse eid="EXO 35:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 35:12"/>the Ark and its poles, the propitiatory covering, and the veil of the covering, <verse eid="EXO 35:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 35:13"/>the table and its poles, and all its vessels, and the Bread of the Presentation, <verse eid="EXO 35:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 35:14"/>and the lampstand for the light, and its vessels, and its lamps, and the oil for the light, <verse eid="EXO 35:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 35:15"/>and the altar of incense, and its poles, and the anointing oil, and the spice-incense, and the covering of the opening at the opening of the Dwelling Place, <verse eid="EXO 35:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 35:16"/>the altar of burnt-offering and the bronze grate which it has, its poles, and all its vessels, the laver and its base, <verse eid="EXO 35:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 35:17"/>the hangings of the court, its pillars, and their sockets, and the covering of the gate of the court, <verse eid="EXO 35:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 35:18"/>the pins of the Dwelling Place, and the pins of the court, and their cords, <verse eid="EXO 35:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 35:19"/>the colored garments, to do service in the holy place, the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons to act as priest in.” <verse eid="EXO 35:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 35:20"/>And all the congregation of the sons of Israel go out from the presence of Moses, <verse eid="EXO 35:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 35:21"/>and they come in—every man whom his heart has lifted up, and everyone whom his spirit has made willing—they have brought in the raised-offering of YHWH for the work of the Tent of Meeting, and for all its service, and for the holy garments. <verse eid="EXO 35:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 35:22"/>And they come in—the men with the women—every willing-hearted one—they have brought in nose-ring, and earring, and seal-ring, and necklace, all golden goods, even everyone who has waved a wave-offering of gold to YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 35:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 35:23"/>And every man with whom has been found blue, and purple, and scarlet, and linen, and goats’ [hair], and rams’ skins made red, and tachashim skins, have brought [them] in; <verse eid="EXO 35:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 35:24"/>everyone lifting up a raised-offering of silver and bronze has brought in the raised-offering of YHWH; and everyone with whom has been found shittim wood for any work of the service brought [it] in. <verse eid="EXO 35:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 35:25"/>And every wise-hearted woman has spun with her hands, and they bring in yarn—of the blue, and the purple, [and] the scarlet—and the linen; <verse eid="EXO 35:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 35:26"/>and all the women whose heart has lifted them up in wisdom, have spun the goats’ [hair]. <verse eid="EXO 35:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 35:27"/>And the princes have brought in the shoham stones, and the stones for settings, for the ephod, and for the breastplate, <verse eid="EXO 35:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 35:28"/>and the spices, and the oil for the light, and for the anointing oil, and for the spice-incense; <verse eid="EXO 35:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 35:29"/>every man and woman of the sons of Israel (whom their heart has made willing to bring in for all the work which YHWH commanded to be done by the hand of Moses) brought in a willing-offering to YHWH. <verse eid="EXO 35:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 35:30"/>And Moses says to the sons of Israel, “See, YHWH has called Bezaleel, son of Uri, son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, by name, <verse eid="EXO 35:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 35:31"/>and He fills him [with] the Spirit of God, in wisdom, in understanding, and in knowledge, and in all work, <verse eid="EXO 35:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 35:32"/>even to devise inventions to work in gold, and in silver, and in bronze, <verse eid="EXO 35:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 35:33"/>and in a carving of stones for settings, and in a carving of wood to work in any work of design. <verse eid="EXO 35:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 35:34"/>And He has put [it] in his heart to direct, he and Aholiab, son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan; <verse eid="EXO 35:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 35:35"/>He has filled them with wisdom of heart to do every work, of engraver, and designer, and embroiderer (in blue, and in purple, in scarlet, and in linen), and weaver, who does any work, and of designers of designs.”<verse eid="EXO 35:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 35"/>
  <chapter number="36" style="c" sid="EXO 36"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 36:1"/>And Bezaleel, and Aholiab, and every wise-hearted man, in whom YHWH has given wisdom and understanding to know to do every work of the service of the holy place, have done according to all that YHWH commanded. <verse eid="EXO 36:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 36:2"/>And Moses calls to Bezaleel, and to Aholiab, and to every wise-hearted man in whose heart YHWH has given wisdom, everyone whom his heart lifted up, to come near to the work to do it. <verse eid="EXO 36:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 36:3"/>And they take from before Moses all the raised-offering which the sons of Israel have brought in for the work of the service of the holy place to do it; and still they have brought to him a willing-offering morning by morning. <verse eid="EXO 36:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 36:4"/>And all the wise men, who are doing all the work of the holy place, each come from his work which they are doing, <verse eid="EXO 36:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 36:5"/>and speak to Moses, saying, “The people are multiplying to bring in more than sufficient for the service of the work which YHWH commanded [us] to do.” <verse eid="EXO 36:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 36:6"/>And Moses commands, and they cause a voice to pass over through the camp, saying, “Do not let man or woman make anymore work for the raised-offering of the holy place”; and the people are restrained from bringing, <verse eid="EXO 36:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 36:7"/>and the work has been sufficient for them, for all the work, to do it, and to leave. <verse eid="EXO 36:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 36:8"/>And all the wise-hearted ones among the doers of the work make the Dwelling Place; he has made them [with] ten curtains of twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, [with] cherubim, the work of a designer. <verse eid="EXO 36:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 36:9"/>The length of one curtain [is] twenty-eight by the cubit, and the breadth of one curtain [is] four by the cubit; one measure [is] for all the curtains. <verse eid="EXO 36:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 36:10"/>And he joins the five curtains to one another, and the [other] five curtains he has joined to one another; <verse eid="EXO 36:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 36:11"/>and he makes loops of blue on the edge of one curtain, at the end, in the joining; so he has made in the edge of the outmost curtain, in the joining of the second; <verse eid="EXO 36:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 36:12"/>he has made fifty loops in the first curtain, and he has made fifty loops in the end of the curtain which [is] in the joining of the second; the loops are taking hold on one another. <verse eid="EXO 36:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 36:13"/>And he makes fifty hooks of gold, and joins the curtains to one another by the hooks, and the Dwelling Place is one. <verse eid="EXO 36:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 36:14"/>And he makes curtains of goats’ [hair] for a tent over the Dwelling Place; eleven curtains he has made them; <verse eid="EXO 36:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 36:15"/>the length of one curtain [is] thirty by the cubit, and the breadth of one curtain [is] four cubits; one measure [is] for the eleven curtains; <verse eid="EXO 36:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 36:16"/>and he joins the five curtains apart, and the six curtains apart. <verse eid="EXO 36:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 36:17"/>And he makes fifty loops on the outer edge of the curtain, in the joining; and he has made fifty loops on the edge of the curtain which is joining the second; <verse eid="EXO 36:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 36:18"/>and he makes fifty hooks of bronze to join the tent—to be one; <verse eid="EXO 36:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 36:19"/>and he makes a covering for the tent of rams’ skins made red, and a covering of tachashim skins above. <verse eid="EXO 36:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 36:20"/>And he makes the boards for the Dwelling Place of shittim wood, standing up; <verse eid="EXO 36:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 36:21"/>ten cubits [is] the length of the [one] board, and a cubit and a half the breadth of the [one] board; <verse eid="EXO 36:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 36:22"/>two handles [are] to one board, joined to one another; so he has made for all the boards of the Dwelling Place. <verse eid="EXO 36:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 36:23"/>And he makes the boards for the Dwelling Place; twenty boards for the south side southward; <verse eid="EXO 36:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 36:24"/>and he has made forty sockets of silver under the twenty boards: two sockets under one board for its two handles, and two sockets under the other board for its two handles. <verse eid="EXO 36:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 36:25"/>And for the second side of the Dwelling Place, for the north side, he has made twenty boards, <verse eid="EXO 36:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 36:26"/>and their forty sockets of silver: two sockets under one board, and two sockets under the other board; <verse eid="EXO 36:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 36:27"/>and for the sides of the Dwelling Place westward, he has made six boards; <verse eid="EXO 36:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 36:28"/>and he has made two boards for the corners of the Dwelling Place, in the two sides; <verse eid="EXO 36:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 36:29"/>and they have been twins below, and together they are twins at its head, at one ring; so he has done to both of them at the two corners; <verse eid="EXO 36:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 36:30"/>and there have been eight boards; and their sockets of silver [are] sixteen sockets, two sockets under one board. <verse eid="EXO 36:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 36:31"/>And he makes bars of shittim wood: five for the boards of the first side of the Dwelling Place, <verse eid="EXO 36:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 36:32"/>and five bars for the boards of the second side of the Dwelling Place, and five bars for the boards of the Dwelling Place, for the sides westward; <verse eid="EXO 36:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 36:33"/>and he makes the middle bar to enter into the midst of the boards from end to end; <verse eid="EXO 36:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 36:34"/>and he has overlaid the boards with gold, and he has made their rings of gold, places for bars, and he overlays the bars with gold. <verse eid="EXO 36:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 36:35"/>And he makes the veil of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen; he has made it [with] cherubim—the work of a designer; <verse eid="EXO 36:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 36:36"/>and he makes four pillars of shittim [wood] for it, and overlays them with gold; their pegs [are] of gold; and he casts four sockets of silver for them. <verse eid="EXO 36:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 36:37"/>And he makes a covering for the opening of the tent, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, the work of an embroiderer, <verse eid="EXO 36:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EXO 36:38"/>also its five pillars, and their pegs; and he overlaid their tops and their fillets [with] gold, and their five sockets [are] bronze.<verse eid="EXO 36:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 36"/>
  <chapter number="37" style="c" sid="EXO 37"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 37:1"/>And Bezaleel makes the Ark of shittim wood; two cubits and a half its length, and a cubit and a half its breadth, and a cubit and a half its height; <verse eid="EXO 37:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 37:2"/>and he overlays it with pure gold inside and outside, and makes a wreath of gold for it all around; <verse eid="EXO 37:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 37:3"/>and he casts four rings of gold for it on its four feet, even two rings on its one side, and two rings on its second side; <verse eid="EXO 37:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 37:4"/>and he makes poles of shittim wood, and overlays them with gold, <verse eid="EXO 37:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 37:5"/>and he brings in the poles into the rings, by the sides of the Ark, to carry the Ark. <verse eid="EXO 37:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 37:6"/>And he makes a propitiatory covering of pure gold, two cubits and a half its length, and a cubit and a half its breadth; <verse eid="EXO 37:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 37:7"/>and he makes two cherubim of gold; he has made them of beaten work at the two ends of the propitiatory covering— <verse eid="EXO 37:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 37:8"/>one cherub at the end on this [side] and one cherub at the end on that [side]; he has made the cherubim from [above] the propitiatory covering, at its two ends; <verse eid="EXO 37:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 37:9"/>and the cherubim are spreading out wings on high, covering over the propitiatory covering with their wings, and their faces [are] toward one another; the faces of the cherubim have been toward the propitiatory covering. <verse eid="EXO 37:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 37:10"/>And he makes the table of shittim wood; two cubits its length, and a cubit its breadth, and a cubit and a half its height, <verse eid="EXO 37:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 37:11"/>and overlays it with pure gold, and makes a wreath of gold for it all around. <verse eid="EXO 37:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 37:12"/>And he makes a border for it of a handbreadth around, and makes a wreath of gold around for its border; <verse eid="EXO 37:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 37:13"/>and he casts four rings of gold for it, and puts the rings on the four corners which [are] at its four feet; <verse eid="EXO 37:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 37:14"/>the rings have been close by the border, places for poles to carry the table. <verse eid="EXO 37:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 37:15"/>And he makes the poles of shittim wood, and overlays them with gold, to carry the table; <verse eid="EXO 37:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 37:16"/>and he makes the vessels which [are] on the table, its dishes, and its bowls, and its cups, and the cups by which they pour out, of pure gold. <verse eid="EXO 37:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 37:17"/>And he makes the lampstand of pure gold; he has made the lampstand of beaten work, its base, and its branch, its calyxes, its knobs, and its flowers, have been of the same; <verse eid="EXO 37:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 37:18"/>and six branches are coming out of its sides, three branches of the lampstand out of its one side, and three branches of the lampstand out of its second side; <verse eid="EXO 37:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 37:19"/>three calyxes, made like almonds, in one branch, a knob and a flower; and three calyxes, made like almonds, in another branch, a knob and a flower; so for the six branches which are coming out of the lampstand. <verse eid="EXO 37:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 37:20"/>And in the lampstand [are] four calyxes, made like almonds, its knobs, and its flowers, <verse eid="EXO 37:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 37:21"/>and a knob under the two branches of the same, and a knob under the two branches of the same, and a knob under the two branches of the same, [are] for the six branches which are coming out of it; <verse eid="EXO 37:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 37:22"/>their knobs and their branches have been of the same; all of it one beaten work of pure gold. <verse eid="EXO 37:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 37:23"/>And he makes its seven lamps, and its snuffers, and its snuff-dishes, of pure gold; <verse eid="EXO 37:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 37:24"/>he has made it of a talent of pure gold, and with all its vessels. <verse eid="EXO 37:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 37:25"/>And he makes the incense-altar of shittim wood; a cubit its length, and a cubit its breadth (square), and two cubits its height; its horns have been of the same; <verse eid="EXO 37:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 37:26"/>and he overlays it with pure gold, around its top and its sides, and its horns; and he makes a wreath of gold for it all around; <verse eid="EXO 37:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 37:27"/>and he has made two rings of gold for it under its wreath, at its two corners, at its two sides, for places for poles to carry it with them. <verse eid="EXO 37:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 37:28"/>And he makes the poles of shittim wood, and overlays them with gold; <verse eid="EXO 37:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 37:29"/>and he makes the holy anointing oil, and the pure spice-incense—work of a compounder.<verse eid="EXO 37:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 37"/>
  <chapter number="38" style="c" sid="EXO 38"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 38:1"/>And he makes the altar of burnt-offering of shittim wood; five cubits its length, and five cubits its breadth (square), and three cubits its height; <verse eid="EXO 38:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 38:2"/>and he makes its horns on its four corners; its horns have been of the same; and he overlays it with bronze; <verse eid="EXO 38:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 38:3"/>and he makes all the vessels of the altar, the pots, and the shovels, and the sprinkling-pans, the forks, and the fire-pans; he has made all its vessels of bronze. <verse eid="EXO 38:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 38:4"/>And he makes a bronze grate of network for the altar, under its rim beneath, to its midst; <verse eid="EXO 38:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 38:5"/>and he casts four rings for the four ends of the bronze grate—places for bars; <verse eid="EXO 38:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 38:6"/>and he makes the poles of shittim wood, and overlays them with bronze; <verse eid="EXO 38:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 38:7"/>and he brings in the poles into the rings on the sides of the altar, to carry it with them; he made it hollow [with] boards. <verse eid="EXO 38:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 38:8"/>And he makes the laver of bronze, and its base of bronze, with the mirrors of the women assembling, who have assembled at the opening of the Tent of Meeting. <verse eid="EXO 38:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 38:9"/>And he makes the court: at the south side southward, the hangings of the court of twined linen, one hundred by the cubit, <verse eid="EXO 38:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 38:10"/>their pillars [are] twenty, and their bronze sockets twenty, the pegs of the pillars and their fillets [are] silver; <verse eid="EXO 38:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 38:11"/>and at the north side, one hundred by the cubit, their pillars [are] twenty, and their sockets of bronze twenty; the pegs of the pillars and their fillets [are] silver; <verse eid="EXO 38:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 38:12"/>and at the west side [are] hangings, fifty by the cubit; their pillars [are] ten, and their sockets ten; the pegs of the pillars and their fillets [are] silver; <verse eid="EXO 38:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 38:13"/>and at the east side eastward, fifty cubits. <verse eid="EXO 38:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 38:14"/>The hangings on the side [are] fifteen cubits, their pillars three, and their sockets three, <verse eid="EXO 38:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 38:15"/>and at the second side at the gate of the court, on this [side] and on that [side]—hangings of fifteen cubits, their pillars three, and their sockets three; <verse eid="EXO 38:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 38:16"/>all the hangings of the court around [are] of twined linen, <verse eid="EXO 38:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 38:17"/>and the sockets for the pillars of bronze, the pegs of the pillars and their fillets of silver, and the overlaying of their tops of silver, and all the pillars of the court are filleted with silver. <verse eid="EXO 38:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 38:18"/>And the covering of the gate of the court [is] the work of an embroiderer, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen; and twenty cubits [is] the length, and the height with the breadth [is] five cubits, corresponding to the hangings of the court; <verse eid="EXO 38:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 38:19"/>and their pillars [are] four, and their sockets of bronze four, their pegs [are] of silver, and the overlaying of their tops and their fillets [are] of silver; <verse eid="EXO 38:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 38:20"/>and all the pins for the Dwelling Place, and for the court all around, [are] of bronze. <verse eid="EXO 38:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 38:21"/>These are the numberings of the Dwelling Place (the Dwelling Place of Testimony), which has been numbered by the command of Moses, the service of the Levites, by the hand of Ithamar son of Aaron the priest. <verse eid="EXO 38:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 38:22"/>And Bezaleel son of Uri, son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, has made all that YHWH commanded Moses; <verse eid="EXO 38:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 38:23"/>and with him [is] Aholiab son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan, an engraver, and designer and embroiderer in blue, and in purple, and in scarlet, and in linen. <verse eid="EXO 38:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 38:24"/>All the gold which is prepared for the work in all the work of the holy place (and it is the gold of the wave-offering) [is] twenty-nine talents, and seven hundred and thirty shekels, by the shekel of the holy place. <verse eid="EXO 38:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 38:25"/>And the silver of those numbered of the congregation [is] one hundred talents, and one thousand and seven hundred and seventy-five shekels, by the shekel of the holy place; <verse eid="EXO 38:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 38:26"/>a bekah for the counted head (half a shekel, by the shekel of the holy place), for everyone who is passing over to those numbered, from a son of twenty years and upwards, for six hundred thousand and three thousand and five hundred and fifty. <verse eid="EXO 38:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 38:27"/>And one hundred talents of silver are for casting the sockets of the holy place, and the sockets of the veil; one hundred sockets for the hundred talents, a talent for a socket; <verse eid="EXO 38:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 38:28"/>and [from] the one thousand and seven hundred and seventy-five [shekels] he has made pegs for the pillars, and overlaid their tops, and filleted them. <verse eid="EXO 38:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 38:29"/>And the bronze of the wave-offering [is] seventy talents, and two thousand and four hundred shekels; <verse eid="EXO 38:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 38:30"/>and he makes with it the sockets of the opening of the Tent of Meeting, and the bronze altar, and the bronze grate which it has, and all the vessels of the altar, <verse eid="EXO 38:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 38:31"/>and the sockets of the court all around, and the sockets of the gate of the court, and all the pins of the Dwelling Place, and all the pins of the court all around.<verse eid="EXO 38:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 38"/>
  <chapter number="39" style="c" sid="EXO 39"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 39:1"/>And of the blue, and the purple, and the scarlet, they made colored garments, to minister in the holy place; and they make the holy garments which [are] for Aaron, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 39:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 39:2"/>And he makes the ephod, of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, <verse eid="EXO 39:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 39:3"/>and they expand the plates of gold, and have cut off wires to work in the midst of the blue, and in the midst of the purple, and in the midst of the scarlet, and in the midst of the linen—the work of a designer; <verse eid="EXO 39:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 39:4"/>they have made shoulder-pieces for it, joining; it is joined at its two ends. <verse eid="EXO 39:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 39:5"/>And the girdle of his ephod which [is] on it is of the same, according to its work, of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 39:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 39:6"/>And they prepare the shoham stones, set [with] filigrees of gold, engraved with engravings of a signet—the names of the sons of Israel on [them]; <verse eid="EXO 39:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 39:7"/>and he sets them on the shoulders of the ephod—stones of memorial for the sons of Israel, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 39:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 39:8"/>And he makes the breastplate, the work of a designer, like the work of the ephod, of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen; <verse eid="EXO 39:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 39:9"/>it has been square; they have made the breastplate double, a span its length, and a span its breadth, doubled. <verse eid="EXO 39:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 39:10"/>And they fill four rows of stones in it: a row of a sardius, a topaz, and a carbuncle [is] the first row; <verse eid="EXO 39:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 39:11"/>and the second row an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond; <verse eid="EXO 39:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 39:12"/>and the third row an opal, an agate, and an amethyst; <verse eid="EXO 39:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 39:13"/>and the fourth row a beryl, an onyx, and a jasper—set [with] filigrees of gold in their settings. <verse eid="EXO 39:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 39:14"/>And the stones, according to the names of the sons of Israel, are twelve, according to their names, engravings of a signet, each according to his name, for the twelve tribes. <verse eid="EXO 39:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 39:15"/>And they make wreathed chains on the breastplate, [the] work of thick bands of pure gold; <verse eid="EXO 39:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 39:16"/>and they make two filigrees of gold, and two rings of gold, and put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate, <verse eid="EXO 39:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 39:17"/>and they put the two thick bands of gold on the two rings on the ends of the breastplate; <verse eid="EXO 39:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 39:18"/>and they have put the two ends of the two thick bands on the two filigrees, and they put them on the shoulders of the ephod, toward the front of its face. <verse eid="EXO 39:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 39:19"/>And they make two rings of gold, and set [them] on the two ends of the breastplate, on its border, which [is] on the side of the ephod within; <verse eid="EXO 39:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 39:20"/>and they make two rings of gold, and put them on the two shoulders of the ephod below, in front of its front, close by its joining, above the girdle of the ephod; <verse eid="EXO 39:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 39:21"/>and they bind the breastplate by its rings to the rings of the ephod, with a ribbon of blue, to be above the girdle of the ephod, and the breastplate is not loosed from off the ephod, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 39:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 39:22"/>And he makes the upper robe of the ephod, the work of a weaver, completely of blue; <verse eid="EXO 39:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 39:23"/>and the opening of the upper robe [is] in its midst, as the opening of a [linen] habergeon, [with] a border for its opening all around; it is not torn; <verse eid="EXO 39:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 39:24"/>and they make on the hems of the upper robe pomegranates of blue, and purple, and scarlet, twined. <verse eid="EXO 39:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 39:25"/>And they make bells of pure gold, and put the bells in the midst of the pomegranates, on the hems of the upper robe, all around, in the midst of the pomegranates; <verse eid="EXO 39:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 39:26"/>a bell and a pomegranate [and] a bell and a pomegranate [are] on the hems of the upper robe all around, to minister in, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 39:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 39:27"/>And they make the coats of linen, the work of a weaver, for Aaron and for his sons, <verse eid="EXO 39:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 39:28"/>and the turban of linen, and the beautiful caps of linen, and the linen trousers, of twined linen, <verse eid="EXO 39:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 39:29"/>and the girdle of twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, the work of an embroiderer, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 39:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 39:30"/>And they make the flower of the holy crown of pure gold, and write a writing on it, engravings of a signet: “Holy to YHWH”; <verse eid="EXO 39:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 39:31"/>and they put a ribbon of blue on it, to put [it] on the turban above, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 39:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 39:32"/>And all the service of the Dwelling Place of the Tent of Meeting is completed; and the sons of Israel do according to all that YHWH has commanded Moses; so they have done. <verse eid="EXO 39:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 39:33"/>And they bring in the Dwelling Place to Moses, the tent, and all its vessels, its hooks, its boards, its bars, and its pillars, and its sockets; <verse eid="EXO 39:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 39:34"/>and the covering of rams’ skins, which are made red, and the covering of tachashim skins, and the veil of the covering; <verse eid="EXO 39:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 39:35"/>the Ark of the Testimony and its poles, and the propitiatory covering; <verse eid="EXO 39:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 39:36"/>the table, all its vessels, and the Bread of the Presentation; <verse eid="EXO 39:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 39:37"/>the pure lampstand, its lamps, the lamps of arrangement, and all its vessels, and the oil for the light. <verse eid="EXO 39:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EXO 39:38"/>And the golden altar, and the anointing oil, and the spice-incense, and the covering of the opening of the tent; <verse eid="EXO 39:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EXO 39:39"/>the bronze altar and the bronze grate which it has, its poles, and all its vessels, the laver and its base; <verse eid="EXO 39:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EXO 39:40"/>the hangings of the court, its pillars, and its sockets; and the covering for the gate of the court, its cords, and its pins; and all the vessels of the service of the Dwelling Place, for the Tent of Meeting; <verse eid="EXO 39:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="EXO 39:41"/>the colored clothes to minister in the holy place, the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to act as priest in. <verse eid="EXO 39:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="EXO 39:42"/>According to all that YHWH has commanded Moses, so the sons of Israel have done all the service; <verse eid="EXO 39:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="EXO 39:43"/>and Moses sees all the work, and behold, they have done it as YHWH has commanded; so they have done. And Moses blesses them.<verse eid="EXO 39:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 39"/>
  <chapter number="40" style="c" sid="EXO 40"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EXO 40:1"/>And YHWH speaks to Moses, saying, <verse eid="EXO 40:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EXO 40:2"/>“On the first day of the month, in the first month, you raise up the Dwelling Place of the Tent of Meeting, <verse eid="EXO 40:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EXO 40:3"/>and have set the Ark of the Testimony [in] there, and have covered over the Ark with the veil, <verse eid="EXO 40:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EXO 40:4"/>and have brought in the table, and set its arrangement in order, and have brought in the lampstand, and caused its lamps to go up. <verse eid="EXO 40:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EXO 40:5"/>And you have put the golden altar for incense before the Ark of the Testimony, and have put the covering of the opening to the Dwelling Place, <verse eid="EXO 40:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EXO 40:6"/>and have put the altar of the burnt-offering before the opening of the Dwelling Place of the Tent of Meeting, <verse eid="EXO 40:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EXO 40:7"/>and have put the laver between the Tent of Meeting and the altar, and have put water [in] there. <verse eid="EXO 40:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EXO 40:8"/>And you have set the court all around, and have placed the covering of the gate of the court, <verse eid="EXO 40:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EXO 40:9"/>and have taken the anointing oil, and anointed the Dwelling Place, and all that [is] in it, and hallowed it, and all its vessels, and it has been holy; <verse eid="EXO 40:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EXO 40:10"/>and you have anointed the altar of the burnt-offering, and all its vessels, and sanctified the altar, and the altar has been most holy; <verse eid="EXO 40:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EXO 40:11"/>and you have anointed the laver and its base, and sanctified it. <verse eid="EXO 40:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EXO 40:12"/>And you have brought Aaron and his sons near to the opening of the Tent of Meeting, and have bathed them with water; <verse eid="EXO 40:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EXO 40:13"/>and you have clothed Aaron with the holy garments, and anointed him, and sanctified him, and he has acted as priest to Me. <verse eid="EXO 40:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EXO 40:14"/>And you bring his sons near, and have clothed them with coats, <verse eid="EXO 40:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EXO 40:15"/>and anointed them as you have anointed their father, and they have acted as priests to Me, and their anointing has been to them for a continuous priesthood throughout their generations.” <verse eid="EXO 40:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EXO 40:16"/>And Moses does according to all that YHWH has commanded him; so he has done. <verse eid="EXO 40:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EXO 40:17"/>And it comes to pass, in the first month, in the second year, on the first of the month, the Dwelling Place has been raised up; <verse eid="EXO 40:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EXO 40:18"/>and Moses raises up the Dwelling Place, and sets its sockets, and places its boards, and places its bars, and raises its pillars, <verse eid="EXO 40:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EXO 40:19"/>and spreads the tent over the Dwelling Place, and puts the covering of the tent on it above, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 40:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EXO 40:20"/>And he takes and puts the Testimony into the Ark, and sets the poles on the Ark, and puts the propitiatory covering on the Ark above; <verse eid="EXO 40:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EXO 40:21"/>and brings the Ark into the Dwelling Place, and places the veil of the covering, and covers over the Ark of the Testimony, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 40:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EXO 40:22"/>And he puts the table in the Tent of Meeting, on the side of the Dwelling Place northward, at the outside of the veil, <verse eid="EXO 40:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EXO 40:23"/>and sets in order the arrangement of bread on it, before YHWH, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 40:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EXO 40:24"/>And he puts the lampstand in the Tent of Meeting, opposite the table, on the side of the Dwelling Place southward, <verse eid="EXO 40:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EXO 40:25"/>and causes the lamps to go up before YHWH, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 40:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EXO 40:26"/>And he sets the golden altar in the Tent of Meeting, before the veil, <verse eid="EXO 40:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EXO 40:27"/>and makes incense on it—spice-incense—as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 40:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EXO 40:28"/>And he sets the covering [at] the opening of the Dwelling Place, <verse eid="EXO 40:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EXO 40:29"/>and he has set the altar of the burnt-offering [at] the opening of the Dwelling Place of the Tent of Meeting, and causes the burnt-offering to go up on it, and the present, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 40:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EXO 40:30"/>And he puts the laver between the Tent of Meeting and the altar, and puts water [in] there for washing, <verse eid="EXO 40:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EXO 40:31"/>and Moses and Aaron and his sons have washed their hands and their feet at the same; <verse eid="EXO 40:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EXO 40:32"/>in their going into the Tent of Meeting, and in their drawing near to the altar, they wash, as YHWH has commanded Moses. <verse eid="EXO 40:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EXO 40:33"/>And he raises up the court all around the Dwelling Place, and around the altar, and places the covering of the gate of the court; and Moses completes the work. <verse eid="EXO 40:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EXO 40:34"/>And the cloud covers the Tent of Meeting, and the glory of YHWH has filled the Dwelling Place; <verse eid="EXO 40:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EXO 40:35"/>and Moses has not been able to go into the Tent of Meeting, for the cloud has dwelt on it, and the glory of YHWH has filled the Dwelling Place. <verse eid="EXO 40:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EXO 40:36"/>And in the going up of the cloud from off the Dwelling Place the sons of Israel journey in all their journeys; <verse eid="EXO 40:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EXO 40:37"/>and if the cloud does not go up then they do not journey, until the day of its going up. <verse eid="EXO 40:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EXO 40:38"/>For the cloud of YHWH [is] on the Dwelling Place by day, and fire is in it by night, before the eyes of all the house of Israel in all their journeys.<verse eid="EXO 40:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EXO 40"/>
</usx>
