<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="EZK" style="id">- Literal Standard Version</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Ezekiel</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Book of Ezekiel</para>
  <para style="toc2">Ezekiel</para>
  <para style="toc3">Ezk</para>
  <para style="mt">Ezekiel</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="EZK 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 1:1"/>And it comes to pass, in the thirtieth year, in the fourth [month], on the fifth of the month, and I [am] in the midst of the expulsion by the river Chebar, the heavens have been opened, and I see visions of God. <verse eid="EZK 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 1:2"/>In the fifth of the month—it is the fifth year of the expulsion of King Jehoiachin— <verse eid="EZK 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 1:3"/>the word of YHWH has certainly been to Ezekiel son of Buzi the priest, in the land of the Chaldeans, by the river Chebar, and there is on him there a hand of YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 1:4"/>And I look, and behold, a turbulent wind is coming from the north, a great cloud, and fire catching itself, and brightness to it all around, and out of its midst as the color of electrum, out of the midst of the fire. <verse eid="EZK 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 1:5"/>And out of its midst [is] a likeness of four living creatures, and this [is] their appearance; a likeness of man [is] to them, <verse eid="EZK 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 1:6"/>and each had four faces and each of them had four wings, <verse eid="EZK 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 1:7"/>and their feet [are] straight feet, and the sole of their feet [is] as a sole of a calf’s foot, and they are sparkling as the color of bright bronze; <verse eid="EZK 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 1:8"/>and on their four sides [each had] hands of man under their wings; and [each] of the four had their faces and their wings; <verse eid="EZK 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 1:9"/>their wings [are] joining to one another, they do not turn around in their going, they each go straight forward. <verse eid="EZK 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 1:10"/>As for the likeness of their faces, [each had] the face of a man, and toward the right the four had the face of a lion, and on the left the four had the face of an ox, and the four had the face of an eagle. <verse eid="EZK 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 1:11"/>And their faces and their wings dividing from above, of each [are] two joining together, and two are covering their bodies. <verse eid="EZK 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 1:12"/>And they each go straight forward, to where the Spirit is to go, they go, they do not turn around in their going. <verse eid="EZK 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 1:13"/>As for the likeness of the living creatures, their appearances [are] as coals of fire—burning as the appearance of lamps; it is going up and down between the living creatures, and brightness [is] to the fire, and lightning is going forth out of the fire. <verse eid="EZK 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 1:14"/>And the living creatures are running, and turning back, as the appearance of the flash. <verse eid="EZK 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 1:15"/>And I see the living creatures, and behold, one wheel [is] in the earth, near the living creatures, at its four faces. <verse eid="EZK 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 1:16"/>The appearance of the wheels and their works [is] as the color of beryl, and the four of them had one likeness, and their appearances and their works [are] as it were the wheel in the midst of the wheel. <verse eid="EZK 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 1:17"/>On their four sides, in their going they go, they do not turn around in their going. <verse eid="EZK 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 1:18"/>As for their rings, they are both high and fearful, and their rings, of the four of them, [are] full of eyes around them. <verse eid="EZK 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 1:19"/>And in the going of the living creatures, the wheels go beside them, and in the living creatures being lifted up from off the earth, the wheels are lifted up. <verse eid="EZK 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 1:20"/>To where the Spirit is to go, they go, there the Spirit [is] to go, and the wheels are lifted up alongside them, for a living spirit [is] in the wheels. <verse eid="EZK 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 1:21"/>In their going, they go; and in their standing, they stand; and in their being lifted up from off the earth, the wheels are lifted up alongside them; for a living spirit [is] in the wheels. <verse eid="EZK 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 1:22"/>And over the heads of the living creatures—a likeness of an expanse, as the color of the fearful ice, stretched out over their heads from above. <verse eid="EZK 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 1:23"/>And under the expanse their wings [are] straight, one toward [its] sister; two [wings] of each are covering them, and two [wings] of each are covering their bodies. <verse eid="EZK 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 1:24"/>And I hear the noise of their wings, as the noise of many waters, as the noise of the Mighty One, in their going—the noise of tumult, as the noise of a camp, in their standing they let their wings fall. <verse eid="EZK 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 1:25"/>And there is a voice from above the expanse, that [is] above their head: in their standing they let their wings fall. <verse eid="EZK 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 1:26"/>And above the expanse that [is] over their head, as an appearance of a sapphire stone, [is] the likeness of a throne, and on the likeness of the throne a likeness, as the appearance of man on it from above. <verse eid="EZK 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 1:27"/>And I see as the color of electrum, as the appearance of fire all around within it, from the appearance of His loins and upward; and from the appearance of His loins and downward, I have seen as the appearance of fire, and brightness [is] all around Him. <verse eid="EZK 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 1:28"/>As the appearance of the bow that is in a cloud in a day of rain, so [is] the appearance of the brightness all around.<verse eid="EZK 1:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="EZK 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 2:1"/>His appearance [was] of the likeness of the glory of YHWH, and I see, and fall on my face, and I hear a voice speaking, and He says to me, “Son of man, stand on your feet, and I speak with you.” <verse eid="EZK 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 2:2"/>And [the] Spirit comes into me when He has spoken to me, and causes me to stand on my feet, and I hear Him who is speaking to me. <verse eid="EZK 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 2:3"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, I am sending you to the sons of Israel, to rebelling nations who have rebelled against Me; they and their fathers have transgressed against Me, to this very day. <verse eid="EZK 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 2:4"/>And the sons [are] brazen-faced and hard-hearted to whom I am sending you, and you have said to them: Thus said Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 2:5"/>And they—whether they hear, or whether they refrain, for they [are] a house of rebellion—have known that a prophet has been in their midst. <verse eid="EZK 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 2:6"/>And you, son of man, you are not afraid of them, indeed, you are not afraid of their words, for briers and thorns are with you, and you are dwelling near scorpions, you are not afraid of their words, and you are not frightened of their faces, for they [are] a house of rebellion, <verse eid="EZK 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 2:7"/>and you have spoken My words to them, whether they hear or whether they refrain, for they [are] a rebellion. <verse eid="EZK 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 2:8"/>And you, son of man, hear that which I am speaking to you; do not be of rebellion like the house of rebellion, open your mouth and eat that which I am giving to you.” <verse eid="EZK 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 2:9"/>And I look, and behold, a hand [is] sent forth to me, and behold, a roll of a scroll [is] in it, <verse eid="EZK 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 2:10"/>and He spreads it before me, and it is written in front and behind, and written on it [are] lamentations, and mourning, and woe!<verse eid="EZK 2:10"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="EZK 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 3:1"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, eat that which you find, eat this scroll, and go, speak to the house of Israel.” <verse eid="EZK 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 3:2"/>And I open my mouth, and He causes me to eat this scroll. <verse eid="EZK 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 3:3"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, feed your belly, and fill your bowels with this scroll that I am giving to you”; and I eat it, and it is as honey for sweetness in my mouth. <verse eid="EZK 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 3:4"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, go forth, go to the house of Israel, and you have spoken to them with My words. <verse eid="EZK 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 3:5"/>For you [are] not sent to a people deep of lip and heavy of tongue—to the house of Israel; <verse eid="EZK 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 3:6"/>not to many peoples, deep of lip and heavy of tongue, whose words you do not understand. If I had not sent you to them—they listen to you, <verse eid="EZK 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 3:7"/>but the house of Israel are not willing to listen to you, for they are not willing to listen to Me, for all the house of Israel are brazen-faced and strong-hearted. <verse eid="EZK 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 3:8"/>Behold, I have made your face strong against their face, and your forehead strong against their forehead. <verse eid="EZK 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 3:9"/>As an adamant, harder than a rock, I have made your forehead; do not fear them, nor are you frightened before them, for they [are] a house of rebellion.” <verse eid="EZK 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 3:10"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, all My words that I speak to you, receive with your heart, and hear with your ears; <verse eid="EZK 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 3:11"/>and go forth, go to the expulsion, to the sons of your people, and you have spoken to them, and have said to them: Thus said Lord YHWH; whether they hear, or whether they refrain.” <verse eid="EZK 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 3:12"/>And a spirit lifts me up, and I hear a noise behind me, a great rushing—“Blessed [is] the glory of YHWH from His place!” <verse eid="EZK 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 3:13"/>Even a noise of the wings of the living creatures touching one another, and a noise of the wheels alongside them, even a noise of a great rushing. <verse eid="EZK 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 3:14"/>And [the] Spirit has lifted me up, and takes me away, and I go bitterly, in the heat of my spirit, and the hand of YHWH [is] strong on me. <verse eid="EZK 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 3:15"/>And I come to the expulsion, at Tel-Ahib, who are dwelling at the river Chebar, and where they are dwelling I also dwell [for] seven days, causing astonishment in their midst. <verse eid="EZK 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 3:16"/>And it comes to pass, at the end of seven days, <verse eid="EZK 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 3:17"/>that there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, “Son of man, I have given you [as] a watchman to the house of Israel, and you have heard a word from My mouth, and have warned them from Me. <verse eid="EZK 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 3:18"/>In My saying to the wicked: You surely die; and you have not warned him, nor have spoken to warn the wicked from his wicked way, so that he lives; he—the wicked—dies in his iniquity, and I require his blood from your hand. <verse eid="EZK 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 3:19"/>And you, because you have warned the wicked, and he has not turned back from his wickedness, and from his wicked way, he dies in his iniquity, and you have delivered your soul. <verse eid="EZK 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 3:20"/>And in the turning back of the righteous from his righteousness, and he has done perversity, and I have put a stumbling-block before him, he dies; because you have not warned him, he dies in his sin, and his righteousness that he has done is not remembered, and I require his blood from your hand. <verse eid="EZK 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 3:21"/>And you, because you have warned him—the righteous—that the righteous does not sin, and he has not sinned, he surely lives, because he has been warned; and you have delivered your soul.” <verse eid="EZK 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 3:22"/>And there is a hand of YHWH on me there, and He says to me, “Rise, go forth to the valley, and there I speak with you.” <verse eid="EZK 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 3:23"/>And I rise and go forth to the valley, and behold, there the glory of YHWH is standing as the glory that I had seen by the river Chebar, and I fall on my face. <verse eid="EZK 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 3:24"/>And [the] Spirit comes into me, and causes me to stand on my feet, and He speaks with me, and says to me, “Go in, be shut up in the midst of your house. <verse eid="EZK 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 3:25"/>And you, son of man, behold, they have put thick bands on you, and have bound you with them, and you do not go forth in their midst; <verse eid="EZK 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 3:26"/>and I cause your tongue to cleave to your palate, and you have been mute, and are not for a reprover to them, for they [are] a house of rebellion. <verse eid="EZK 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 3:27"/>And in My speaking with you, I open your mouth, and you have said to them: Thus said Lord YHWH; the hearer hears, and the refrainer refrains; for they [are] a house of rebellion.”<verse eid="EZK 3:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="EZK 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 4:1"/>“And you, son of man, take a brick for yourself, and you have put it before you, and have carved a city on it—Jerusalem, <verse eid="EZK 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 4:2"/>and have placed a siege against it, and built a fortification against it, and poured out a mound against it, and placed camps against it, indeed, set battering-rams against it all around. <verse eid="EZK 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 4:3"/>And you, take an iron pan for yourself, and you have made it a wall of iron between you and the city; and you have prepared your face against it, and it has been in a siege, indeed, you have laid siege against it. It [is] a sign to the house of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 4:4"/>And you, lie on your left side, and you have placed the iniquity of the house of Israel on it; the number of the days that you lie on it, you bear their iniquity. <verse eid="EZK 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 4:5"/>And I have laid the years of their iniquity on you, the number of days, three hundred and ninety days; and you have borne the iniquity of the house of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 4:6"/>And you have completed these, and have lain on your right side, a second time, and have borne the iniquity of the house of Judah forty days—a day for a year—a day for a year I have appointed to you. <verse eid="EZK 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 4:7"/>And to the siege of Jerusalem you prepare your face, and your arm [is] uncovered, and you have prophesied concerning it. <verse eid="EZK 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 4:8"/>And behold, I have put thick bands on you, and you do not turn from side to side until your completing the days of your siege. <verse eid="EZK 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 4:9"/>And you, take for yourself wheat, and barley, and beans, and lentiles, and millet, and spelt, and you have put them in one vessel, and made them for bread for yourself; the number of the days that you are lying on your side—three hundred and ninety days—you eat it. <verse eid="EZK 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 4:10"/>And your food that you eat [is] by weight, twenty shekels daily; from time to time you eat it. <verse eid="EZK 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 4:11"/>And you drink water by measure, a sixth part of the hin; from time to time you drink [it]. <verse eid="EZK 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 4:12"/>And you eat it [as] barley-cake, and it with dung—the filth of man—you bake before their eyes.” <verse eid="EZK 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 4:13"/>And YHWH says, “Thus the sons of Israel eat their defiled bread among the nations to where I drive them.” <verse eid="EZK 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 4:14"/>And I say, “Aah! Lord YHWH, behold, my soul is not defiled, and carcass, and torn thing, I have not eaten from my youth, even until now; nor has abominable flesh come into my mouth.” <verse eid="EZK 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 4:15"/>And He says to me, “See, I have given to you bullock’s dung instead of man’s dung, and you have made your bread by it.” <verse eid="EZK 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 4:16"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, behold, I am breaking the staff of bread in Jerusalem, and they have eaten bread by weight and with fear; and water by measure and with astonishment, they drink; <verse eid="EZK 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 4:17"/>so that they lack bread and water, and have been astonished with one another, and been consumed in their iniquity.”<verse eid="EZK 4:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="EZK 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 5:1"/>“And you, son of man, take a sharp weapon for yourself, take the barber’s razor for yourself, and you have caused [it] to pass over your head, and over your beard, and you have taken weighing scales for yourself, and apportioned them. <verse eid="EZK 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 5:2"/>You burn a third part with fire in the midst of the city, at the fullness of the days of the siege; and you have taken the third part, you strike with a weapon around it; and the third part you scatter to the wind, and I draw out a weapon after them. <verse eid="EZK 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 5:3"/>And you have taken there a few in number—and have bound them in your skirts; <verse eid="EZK 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 5:4"/>and you take of them again, and have cast them into the midst of the fire, and have burned them in the fire—out of it comes forth a fire to all the house of Israel.” <verse eid="EZK 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 5:5"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: “This [is] Jerusalem, || I have set her in the midst of the nations, || And the lands [are] around her. <verse eid="EZK 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 5:6"/>And she changes My judgments into wickedness more than the nations, || And My statutes more than the lands that [are] around her, || For they have kicked against My judgments, || And My statutes—they have not walked in them.” <verse eid="EZK 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 5:7"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: “Because of your multiplying above the nations that [are] around you, || You have not walked in My statutes, || And you have not done My judgments, || According to the judgments of the nations that [are] around you, you have not done.” <verse eid="EZK 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 5:8"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: “Behold, I [am] against you, even I, || And I have done judgments in your midst, || Before the eyes of the nations. <verse eid="EZK 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 5:9"/>And I have done in you that which I have not done, || And the like of which I do not do again, || Because of all your abominations. <verse eid="EZK 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 5:10"/>Therefore fathers eat sons in your midst, || And sons eat their fathers, || And I have done judgments in you, || And have scattered all your remnant to every wind. <verse eid="EZK 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 5:11"/>Therefore, [as] I live,” a declaration of Lord YHWH, || “Because you have defiled My sanctuary || With all your detestable things, || And with all your abominations, || Therefore I also diminish you, || And My eye does not pity, and I do not spare. <verse eid="EZK 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 5:12"/>Your third part dies by pestilence, || And are consumed by famine in your midst, || And the third part fall by sword around you, || And the third part I scatter to every wind, || And I draw out a sword after them. <verse eid="EZK 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 5:13"/>And My anger has been completed, || And I have caused My fury to rest on them, || And I have been comforted, || And they have known that I, YHWH, have spoken in My zeal, || In My completing My fury on them. <verse eid="EZK 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 5:14"/>And I give you for a ruin, || And for a reproach among nations that [are] around you, || Before the eyes of everyone passing by. <verse eid="EZK 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 5:15"/>And it has been a reproach and a reviling, || An instruction and an astonishment, || To nations that [are] around you, || In My doing judgments in you, || In anger and fury, and in furious reproofs, || I, YHWH, have spoken. <verse eid="EZK 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 5:16"/>In My sending the evil arrows of famine among them, || That have been for destruction, || That I send to destroy you, || And I am adding famine on you, || And I have broken your staff of bread. <verse eid="EZK 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 5:17"/>And I have sent famine and evil beasts on you, || And they have bereaved you, || And pestilence and blood pass over on you, || And I bring a sword in against you, || I, YHWH, have spoken!”<verse eid="EZK 5:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="EZK 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 6:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 6:2"/>“Son of man, set your face toward mountains of Israel, and prophesy concerning them: <verse eid="EZK 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 6:3"/>And you have said, Mountains of Israel, || Hear a word of Lord YHWH! Thus said Lord YHWH, || To the mountains, and to the hills, || To the streams, and to the valleys: Behold, I am bringing in a sword against you, || And I have destroyed your high places. <verse eid="EZK 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 6:4"/>And your altars have been desolated, || And your images have been broken, || And I have caused your wounded to fall before your idols, <verse eid="EZK 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 6:5"/>And I have put the carcasses of the sons of Israel before their idols, || And I have scattered your bones around your altars. <verse eid="EZK 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 6:6"/>In all your dwellings the cities are laid waste, || And the high places are desolate, || So that your altars are dry and desolate, || Your idols have broken and ceased, || And your images have been cut down, || And your works have been blotted out. <verse eid="EZK 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 6:7"/>And the wounded has fallen in your midst, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 6:8"/>And I have caused [some] to remain, || In their being for you the escaped of the sword among nations, || In your being scattered through lands. <verse eid="EZK 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 6:9"/>And your escaped have remembered Me among nations, || To where they have been taken captive, || Because I have been broken with their heart that is going whoring, || That has turned aside from off Me, || And with their eyes they are going whoring after their idols, || And they have been loathsome in their own faces, || For the evils that they have done—all their abominations. <verse eid="EZK 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 6:10"/>And they have known that I [am] YHWH, || I have not spoken to do this evil to them for nothing. <verse eid="EZK 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 6:11"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Strike with your palm, and stamp with your foot, || And say: Aah! For all the evil abominations of the house of Israel, || Which falls by sword, by famine, and by pestilence. <verse eid="EZK 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 6:12"/>The far-off dies by pestilence, || And the near falls by sword, || And the left and the besieged dies by famine, || And I have completed My fury on them. <verse eid="EZK 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 6:13"/>And you have known that I [am] YHWH, || In their wounded being in the midst of their idols, || Around their altars, || On every high hill, on all tops of mountains, || And under every green tree, and under every thick oak, || The place where they gave refreshing fragrance to all their idols. <verse eid="EZK 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 6:14"/>And I have stretched out My hand against them, || And have made the land a desolation, || Even a desolation from the wilderness to Diblath, || In all their dwellings, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 6:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="EZK 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 7:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, “And you, son of man, || Thus said Lord YHWH to the ground of Israel: <verse eid="EZK 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 7:2"/>An end, the end has come on the four corners of the land. <verse eid="EZK 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 7:3"/>Now [is] the end for you, || And I have sent My anger on you, || And judged you according to your ways, || And set all your abominations against you. <verse eid="EZK 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 7:4"/>And My eye has no pity on you, nor do I spare, || For I set your ways against you, || And your abominations are in your midst, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 7:5"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Calamity, a single calamity, behold, it has come. <verse eid="EZK 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 7:6"/>An end has come, the end has come, || It has awoken for you, behold, it has come. <verse eid="EZK 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 7:7"/>The circlet has come to you, O inhabitant of the land! The time has come, a day of trouble [is] near, || And not the shouting of mountains. <verse eid="EZK 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 7:8"/>Now shortly I pour out My fury on you, || And have completed My anger against you, || And judged you according to your ways, || And set all your abominations against you. <verse eid="EZK 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 7:9"/>And My eye does not pity, nor do I spare, || I give to you according to your ways, || And your abominations are in your midst, || And you have known that [it is] I, YHWH, striking. <verse eid="EZK 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 7:10"/>Behold, the day, behold, it has come, || The circlet has gone forth, || The rod has blossomed, the pride has flourished. <verse eid="EZK 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 7:11"/>The violence has risen to a rod of wickedness, || There is none of them, nor of their multitude, || Nor of their noise, nor is there wailing for them. <verse eid="EZK 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 7:12"/>The time has come, the day has arrived, || The buyer does not rejoice, || And the seller does not become a mourner, || For wrath [is] to all its multitude. <verse eid="EZK 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 7:13"/>For the seller does not turn to the sold thing, || And yet their life [is] among the living, || For the vision [is] to all its multitude, || It does not turn back, || And none strengthens his life by his iniquity. <verse eid="EZK 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 7:14"/>They have blown with a horn to prepare the whole, || And none is going to battle, || For My wrath [is] to all its multitude. <verse eid="EZK 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 7:15"/>The sword [is] outside, || And the pestilence and the famine within, || He who is in a field dies by sword, || And he who is in a city—Famine and pestilence devour him. <verse eid="EZK 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 7:16"/>And their fugitives have escaped away, || And they have been on the mountains || As doves of the valleys, || All of them making a noise—each for his iniquity. <verse eid="EZK 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 7:17"/>All the hands are feeble, and all knees go [as] waters. <verse eid="EZK 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 7:18"/>And they have girded on sackcloth, || And trembling has covered them, || And shame [is] on all faces, || And baldness on all their heads. <verse eid="EZK 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 7:19"/>They cast their silver into out-places, || And their gold becomes impurity. Their silver and gold are not able to deliver them, || In a day of the wrath of YHWH, || They do not satisfy their soul, || And they do not fill their bowels, || For it has been the stumbling-block of their iniquity. <verse eid="EZK 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 7:20"/>As for the beauty of his ornament, || He set it for excellence, || And the images of their abominations, || Their detestable things—they made in it, || Therefore I have given it to them for impurity, <verse eid="EZK 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 7:21"/>And I have given it into the hand of the strangers for a prey, || And to the wicked of the land for a spoil, || And they have defiled it. <verse eid="EZK 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 7:22"/>And I have turned My face from them, || And they have defiled My hidden place, || Indeed, destroyers have come into it, and defiled it. <verse eid="EZK 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 7:23"/>Make the chain; for the land || Has been full of bloody judgments, || And the city has been full of violence. <verse eid="EZK 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 7:24"/>And I have brought in the wicked of the nations, || And they have possessed their houses, || And I have caused the excellence of the strong to cease, || And those sanctifying them have been defiled. <verse eid="EZK 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 7:25"/>Destruction has come, || And they have sought peace, and there is none. <verse eid="EZK 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 7:26"/>Disaster comes on disaster, and report is on report, || And they have sought a vision from a prophet, || And law perishes from [the] priest, || And counsel from [the] elderly, <verse eid="EZK 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 7:27"/>The king becomes a mourner, || And a prince puts on desolation, || And the hands of the people of the land are troubled, || I deal with them from their own way, || And I judge them with their own judgments, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 7:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="EZK 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 8:1"/>And it comes to pass, in the sixth year, in the sixth [month], on the fifth of the month, I am sitting in my house, and [the] elderly of Judah are sitting before me, and there a hand of Lord YHWH falls on me, <verse eid="EZK 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 8:2"/>and I look, and behold, a likeness as the appearance of fire, from the appearance of His loins and downward—fire, and from His loins and upward, as the appearance of brightness, as the color of electrum. <verse eid="EZK 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 8:3"/>And He puts forth a form of a hand, and takes me by a lock of my head, and [the] Spirit lifts me up between the earth and the heavens, and brings me to Jerusalem in visions of God, to the opening of the inner gate that is facing the north, where the seat of the figure of jealousy [is] that is making jealous, <verse eid="EZK 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 8:4"/>and behold, there the glory of the God of Israel [is] as the appearance that I saw in the valley. <verse eid="EZK 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 8:5"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, now lift up your eyes [toward] the way of the north.” And I lift up my eyes [toward] the way of the north, and behold, on the north of the gate of the altar [is] this figure of jealousy, at the entrance. <verse eid="EZK 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 8:6"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, are you seeing what they are doing? The great abominations that the house of Israel is doing here, to keep far off from My sanctuary; and turn again, [and] see great abominations.” <verse eid="EZK 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 8:7"/>And He brings me to an opening of the court, and I look, and behold, a hole in the wall; <verse eid="EZK 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 8:8"/>and He says to me, “Son of man, now dig through the wall”; and I dig through the wall, and behold, an opening. <verse eid="EZK 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 8:9"/>And He says to me, “Go in, and see the evil abominations that they are doing here.” <verse eid="EZK 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 8:10"/>And I go in, and look, and behold, every form of creeping thing, and detestable beast—and all the idols of the house of Israel—carved on the wall, all around, <verse eid="EZK 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 8:11"/>and seventy men from [the] elderly of the house of Israel—and Jaazaniah son of Shaphan standing in their midst—are standing before them, and each [with] his censer in his hand, and [the] abundance of [the] cloud of the incense is going up. <verse eid="EZK 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 8:12"/>And He says to me, “Have you seen, son of man, that which elderly of the house of Israel are doing in the darkness, each in [the] inner chambers of his imagery, for they are saying, YHWH is not seeing us, YHWH has forsaken the land?” <verse eid="EZK 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 8:13"/>And He says to me, “Turn again, [and] see [the] great abominations that they are doing.” <verse eid="EZK 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 8:14"/>And He brings me to the opening of the gate of the house of YHWH that [is] at the north, and behold, there the women are sitting, weeping for Tammuz. <verse eid="EZK 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 8:15"/>And He says to me, “Have you seen, son of man? Turn again, [and] see greater abominations than these.” <verse eid="EZK 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 8:16"/>And He brings me into the inner court of the house of YHWH, and behold, at the opening of the temple of YHWH, between the porch and the altar, about twenty-five men, their backs toward the temple of YHWH, and their faces eastward, and they are bowing themselves eastward to the sun. <verse eid="EZK 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 8:17"/>And He says to me, “Have you seen, son of man? Has it been a light thing to the house of Judah to do the abomination that they have done here, that they have filled the land with violence, and turn back to provoke Me to anger? And behold, they are putting forth the branch to their nose! <verse eid="EZK 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 8:18"/>And I also deal in fury, My eye does not pity, nor do I spare, and they have cried [with] a loud voice in My ears and I do not hear them.”<verse eid="EZK 8:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="EZK 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 9:1"/>And He cries [with] a loud voice in my ears, saying, “Inspectors of the city have drawn near, and each [with] his destroying weapon in his hand.” <verse eid="EZK 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 9:2"/>And behold, six men are coming from the way of the upper gate, that is facing the north, and each [with] his slaughter-weapon in his hand, and one man in their midst is clothed with linen, and a scribe’s inkhorn at his loins, and they come in, and stand near the bronze altar. <verse eid="EZK 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 9:3"/>And the glory of the God of Israel has gone up from off the cherub, on which it has been, to the threshold of the house. <verse eid="EZK 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 9:4"/>And He calls to the man who is clothed with linen, who has the scribe’s inkhorn at his loins, and YHWH says to him, “Pass on into the midst of the city, into the midst of Jerusalem, and you have made a mark on the foreheads of the men who are sighing and who are groaning for all the abominations that are done in its midst.” <verse eid="EZK 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 9:5"/>And to the others he said in my ears, “Pass on into the city after him, and strike; your eye does not pity, nor do you spare; <verse eid="EZK 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 9:6"/>aged, young man, and virgin, and infant, and women, you slay—to destruction; and against any man on whom [is] the mark you do not go near, and you begin from My sanctuary.” <verse eid="EZK 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 9:7"/>And they begin among the aged men who [are] before the house, and He says to them, “Defile the house, and fill the courts with the wounded, go forth.” And they have gone forth and have struck in the city. <verse eid="EZK 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 9:8"/>And it comes to pass, as they are striking, and I am left—that I fall on my face, and cry, and say, “Aah! Lord YHWH, are You destroying all the remnant of Israel, in Your pouring out Your wrath on Jerusalem?” <verse eid="EZK 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 9:9"/>And He says to me, “The iniquity of the house of Israel and Judah [is] very, very great, and the land is full of blood, and the city has been full of perverseness, for they have said: YHWH has forsaken the land, and YHWH is not seeing. <verse eid="EZK 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 9:10"/>And I also, My eye does not pity, nor do I spare; I have put their way on their own head.” <verse eid="EZK 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 9:11"/>And behold, the man clothed with linen, at whose loins [is] the inkhorn, is bringing back word, saying, “I have done as You have commanded me.”<verse eid="EZK 9:11"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="EZK 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 10:1"/>And I look, and behold, on the expanse that [is] above the head of the cherubim, as a sapphire stone, as the appearance of the likeness of a throne, He has been seen over them. <verse eid="EZK 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 10:2"/>And He speaks to the man clothed with linen and says, “Go into the midst of the wheel, to the place of the cherub, and fill your hands with coals of fire from between the cherubim, and scatter over the city.” And he goes in before my eyes. <verse eid="EZK 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 10:3"/>And the cherubim are standing on the right side of the house, at the going in of the man, and the cloud has filled the inner court, <verse eid="EZK 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 10:4"/>and the glory of YHWH becomes high above the cherub, over the threshold of the house, and the house is filled with the cloud, and the court has been filled with the brightness of the glory of YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 10:5"/>And a noise of the wings of the cherubim has been heard in the outer court, as the voice of God—the Mighty One—in His speaking. <verse eid="EZK 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 10:6"/>And it comes to pass, in His commanding the man clothed with linen, saying, “Take fire from between the wheel, from between the cherubim,” and he goes in and stands near the wheel, <verse eid="EZK 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 10:7"/>that the [one] cherub puts forth his hand from between the cherubim to the fire that [is] between the cherubim, and lifts up, and gives [it] into the hands of him who is clothed with linen, and he receives, and comes forth. <verse eid="EZK 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 10:8"/>And there appears in the cherubim the form of a hand of man under their wings, <verse eid="EZK 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 10:9"/>and I look, and behold, four wheels near the cherubim, one wheel near one cherub, and another wheel near the other cherub, and the appearance of the wheels [is] as the color of a beryl stone. <verse eid="EZK 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 10:10"/>And [as for] their appearances, [the] four had one likeness, as it were the wheel in the midst of the wheel. <verse eid="EZK 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 10:11"/>In their going, they go on their four sides; they do not turn around in their going, for to the place to where the head turns, they go after it, they do not turn around in their going. <verse eid="EZK 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 10:12"/>And all their flesh, and their backs, and their hands, and their wings, and the wheels, are full of eyes all around—[the] wheels [the] four had. <verse eid="EZK 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 10:13"/>As for the wheels—they were called “Whirling Wheel” in my ears. <verse eid="EZK 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 10:14"/>And four faces [are] to each; the face of the first [is] the face of the cherub, and the face of the second [is] the face of man, and of the third the face of a lion, and of the fourth the face of an eagle. <verse eid="EZK 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 10:15"/>And the cherubim are lifted up, it [is] the living creature that I saw by the river Chebar. <verse eid="EZK 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 10:16"/>And in the going of the cherubim, the wheels go beside them; and in the cherubim lifting up their wings to be high above the earth, the wheels do not turn around, even they, from being beside them. <verse eid="EZK 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 10:17"/>In their standing they stand, and in their exaltation they are exalted with them: for [the] spirit of the living creature [is] in them. <verse eid="EZK 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 10:18"/>And the glory of YHWH goes forth from off the threshold of the house, and stands over the cherubim, <verse eid="EZK 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 10:19"/>and the cherubim lift up their wings, and are lifted up from the earth before my eyes; in their going forth, the wheels [are] also alongside them, and he stands at the opening of the east gate of the house of YHWH, and the glory of the God of Israel [is] over them from above. <verse eid="EZK 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 10:20"/>It [is] the living creature that I saw under the God of Israel by the river Chebar, and I know that they are cherubim. <verse eid="EZK 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 10:21"/>[The] four—each had four faces, and each had four wings, and the likeness of the hands of man [is] under their wings. <verse eid="EZK 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 10:22"/>And the likeness of their faces, they [are] the faces that I saw by the river Chebar, their appearances and themselves; they each go straight forward.<verse eid="EZK 10:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="EZK 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 11:1"/>And [the] Spirit lifts me up, and it brings me to the east gate of the house of YHWH, that is facing the east, and behold, at the opening of the gate [are] twenty-five men, and I see in their midst Jaazaniah son of Azzur, and Pelatiah son of Benaiah, heads of the people. <verse eid="EZK 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 11:2"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, these [are] the men who are devising iniquity, and who are giving evil counsel in this city; <verse eid="EZK 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 11:3"/>who are saying, It [is] not near—to build houses, it [is] the pot, and we [are] the flesh. <verse eid="EZK 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 11:4"/>Therefore prophesy concerning them, prophesy, son of man.” <verse eid="EZK 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 11:5"/>And [the] Spirit of YHWH falls on me, and He says to me, “Say, Thus said YHWH: You have said correctly, O house of Israel, || And I have known the steps of your spirit. <verse eid="EZK 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 11:6"/>You multiplied your wounded in this city, || And filled its out-places with the wounded. <verse eid="EZK 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 11:7"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Your wounded whom you placed in its midst, || They [are] the flesh, and it [is] the pot, || And He has brought you out from its midst. <verse eid="EZK 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 11:8"/>You have feared a sword, || And I bring in a sword against you, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 11:9"/>And I have brought you out of its midst, || And given you into the hand of strangers, || And I have done judgments among you. <verse eid="EZK 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 11:10"/>You fall by the sword, || I judge you on the border of Israel, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 11:11"/>It is not for a pot for you, || Nor are you for flesh in its midst, || I judge you at the border of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 11:12"/>And you have known that I [am] YHWH, || For you have not walked in My statutes, || And you have not done My judgments, || And according to the judgments of the nations || Who are around you, you have done!” <verse eid="EZK 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 11:13"/>And it comes to pass, at my prophesying, that Pelatiah son of Benaiah is dying, and I fall on my face, and cry—a loud voice—and say, “Aah! Lord YHWH, You are making an end of the remnant of Israel.” <verse eid="EZK 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 11:14"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 11:15"/>“Son of man, your brothers, your brothers, men of your family, and all the house of Israel—all of it—[are] they to whom inhabitants of Jerusalem have said, Keep far off from YHWH; <verse eid="EZK 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 11:16"/>it [is] ours, the land has been given for an inheritance; therefore say, Thus said Lord YHWH: Because I put them far off among nations, || And because I scattered them through lands, I am also for a little sanctuary to them, || In lands to where they have gone in. <verse eid="EZK 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 11:17"/>Therefore say, Thus said Lord YHWH: And I have assembled you from the peoples, || And I have gathered you from the lands, || Into which you have been scattered, || And I have given the ground of Israel to you. <verse eid="EZK 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 11:18"/>And they have gone in there, || And turned aside all its detestable things, || And all its abominations—out of it. <verse eid="EZK 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 11:19"/>And I have given one heart to them, || And I give a new spirit in your midst, || And I have turned the heart of stone out of their flesh, || And I have given a heart of flesh to them. <verse eid="EZK 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 11:20"/>So that they walk in My statutes, || And keep My judgments, and have done them, || And they have been to Me for a people, || And I am to them for God. <verse eid="EZK 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 11:21"/>As for those whose heart is going to the heart || Of their detestable things and their abominations, || I have put their way on their head, || A declaration of Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 11:22"/>And the cherubim lift up their wings, and the wheels [are] alongside them, and the glory of the God of Israel [is] over them above. <verse eid="EZK 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 11:23"/>And the glory of YHWH goes up from off the midst of the city, and stands on the mountain, that [is] on the east of the city. <verse eid="EZK 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 11:24"/>And [the] Spirit has lifted me up, and brings me to Chaldea, to the expulsion, in a vision, by [the] Spirit of God, and the vision that I have seen goes up from off me; <verse eid="EZK 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 11:25"/>and I speak to the expulsion all the matters of YHWH that He has showed me.<verse eid="EZK 11:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="EZK 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 12:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 12:2"/>“Son of man, you are dwelling in the midst of the house of rebellion, that have eyes to see, and they have not seen; they have ears to hear, and they have not heard; for they [are] a house of rebellion. <verse eid="EZK 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 12:3"/>And you, son of man, make your vessels of removal, and remove by day before their eyes, and you have removed from your place to another place before their eyes, it may be they consider, for they [are] a house of rebellion. <verse eid="EZK 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 12:4"/>And you have brought forth your vessels as vessels of removal by day before their eyes, and you go forth in the evening before their eyes, as the goings forth of a removal. <verse eid="EZK 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 12:5"/>You dig through the wall before their eyes, and you have brought forth by it. <verse eid="EZK 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 12:6"/>Carry on the shoulder before their eyes, bring forth in the darkness, cover your face, and you do not see the earth, for I have given you [as] a sign to the house of Israel.” <verse eid="EZK 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 12:7"/>And I do so, as I have been commanded; I have brought forth my vessels as vessels of removal by day, and I have dug through the wall with my hand in the evening; I have brought forth in the darkness, I have carried away on the shoulder, before their eyes. <verse eid="EZK 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 12:8"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, in the morning, saying, <verse eid="EZK 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 12:9"/>“Son of man, have they not said to you—the house of Israel—the house of rebellion—What are you doing? <verse eid="EZK 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 12:10"/>Say to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: This burden [concerns] the prince in Jerusalem, and all the house of Israel who are in their midst. <verse eid="EZK 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 12:11"/>Say: I [am] your sign; as I have done so it is done to them, into a removal, into a captivity, they go. <verse eid="EZK 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 12:12"/>As for the prince who [is] in their midst, he carries on the shoulder in the darkness, and he goes forth; they dig through the wall to bring forth by it; he covers his face that he may not look on the very surface of the land. <verse eid="EZK 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 12:13"/>And I have spread My net for him, and he has been caught in My snare, and I have brought him to Babylon, the land of the Chaldeans, and he does not see it—and he dies there. <verse eid="EZK 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 12:14"/>And all who are around him to help him, and all his bands, I scatter to every wind, and I draw out a sword after them. <verse eid="EZK 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 12:15"/>And they have known that I [am] YHWH, in My scattering them among nations, and I have spread them through lands; <verse eid="EZK 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 12:16"/>and I have left of them, a few in number, from the sword, from the famine, and from the pestilence, so that they recount all their abominations among the nations to where they have come, and they have known that I [am] YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 12:17"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 12:18"/>“Son of man, eat your bread in haste, and drink your water with trembling and with fear; <verse eid="EZK 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 12:19"/>and you have said to the people of the land, Thus said Lord YHWH concerning the inhabitants of Jerusalem, concerning the land of Israel: They eat their bread with fear, and drink their water with astonishment, because its land is desolate, because of its fullness, because of the violence of all who are dwelling in it. <verse eid="EZK 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 12:20"/>And the cities that are inhabited are laid waste, and the land is a desolation, and you have known that I [am] YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 12:21"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 12:22"/>“Son of man, what [is] this allegory to you, concerning the land of Israel, saying, The days are prolonged, and every vision has perished? <verse eid="EZK 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 12:23"/>Therefore say to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: I have caused this allegory to cease, || And they do not use it as an allegory in Israel again, || But speak to them: The days have drawn near, || And every vision has spoken. <verse eid="EZK 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 12:24"/>For there is no longer any vain vision, and flattering divination, || In the midst of the house of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 12:25"/>For I, YHWH, speak, || The word that I speak—it is done, || It is not prolonged anymore, || For in your days, O house of rebellion, I speak a word, and I have done it, || A declaration of Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 12:26"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 12:27"/>“Son of man, behold, the house of Israel is saying, The vision that he is seeing [is not] for many days, and he is prophesying of far-off times, <verse eid="EZK 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 12:28"/>therefore say to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: None of My words are prolonged anymore, || When I speak a word—it is done, || A declaration of Lord YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 12:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="EZK 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 13:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 13:2"/>“Son of man, prophesy concerning the prophets of Israel who are prophesying, and you have said to those prophesying from their own heart, Hear a word of YHWH! <verse eid="EZK 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 13:3"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Woe to the prophets who are foolish, || Who are going after their own spirit, || And they have seen nothing. <verse eid="EZK 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 13:4"/>Your prophets have been || As foxes in the wasteland, O Israel. <verse eid="EZK 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 13:5"/>You have not gone up into breaches, || Nor do you make a wall for the house of Israel, || To stand in battle in a day of YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 13:6"/>They have seen vanity, and lying divination, || Who are saying: A declaration of YHWH, || And YHWH has not sent them, || And they have hoped to establish a word. <verse eid="EZK 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 13:7"/>Have you not seen a vain vision, || And spoken a lying divination, || When you say, A declaration of YHWH, || And I have not spoken? <verse eid="EZK 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 13:8"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Because you have spoken vanity, and seen a lie, || Therefore, behold, I [am] against you, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 13:9"/>And My hand has been on the prophets, || Who are seeing vanity, and who are divining a lie, || They are not in the assembly of My people, || And they are not written in the writing of the house of Israel, || And they do not come to the ground of Israel, || And you have known that I [am] Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 13:10"/>Because, even because, they caused My people to err, || Saying, Peace! And there is no peace, || And that one is building a wall, || And behold, they are coating it with chalk. <verse eid="EZK 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 13:11"/>Say to those coating with chalk—It falls, || There has been an overflowing shower, || And you, O hailstones, fall, || And a turbulent wind breaks out, <verse eid="EZK 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 13:12"/>And behold, the wall has fallen! Does one not say to you, Where [is] the coating that you coated? <verse eid="EZK 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 13:13"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: I have broken with a turbulent wind in My fury, || And an overflowing shower is in My anger, || And hailstones in My fury—to consume. <verse eid="EZK 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 13:14"/>And I have broken down the wall that you coated with chalk, || And have caused it to come to the earth, || And its foundation has been revealed, || And it has fallen, || And you have been consumed in its midst, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 13:15"/>And I have completed My wrath on the wall, || And on those coating it with chalk, || And I say to you: The wall is not, || And those coating it are not, <verse eid="EZK 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 13:16"/>[These]—the prophets of Israel, who are prophesying concerning Jerusalem, || And who are seeing a vision of peace for her, || And there is no peace, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 13:17"/>And you, son of man, set your face against the daughters of your people, who are prophesying out of their own heart, and prophesy concerning them, <verse eid="EZK 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 13:18"/>And you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH: Woe to those sowing [magic] bands for all joints of the arm, || And to those making the veils || For the head of every stature—to hunt souls, || Do you hunt the souls of My people? And do your souls that live remain alive? <verse eid="EZK 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 13:19"/>Indeed, you pierce Me concerning My people, || For handfuls of barley, || And for pieces of bread, || To put to death souls that should not die, || And to keep alive souls that should not live, || By your lying to My people—listening to lies. <verse eid="EZK 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 13:20"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against your [magic] bands, || With which you are hunting there the souls of the flourishing, || And I have torn them from off your arms, || And have sent away the souls that you are hunting, || The souls of the flourishing. <verse eid="EZK 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 13:21"/>And I have torn your veils, || And delivered My people out of your hand, || And they are no longer for a prey in your hand, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 13:22"/>Because of paining the heart of the righteous with falsehood, || And I have not pained it, || And strengthening the hands of the wicked, || So as not to turn [him] back from his evil way, || To keep him alive, <verse eid="EZK 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 13:23"/>Therefore, you do not see vanity, || And you do not divine divination again, || And I have delivered My people out of your hand, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 13:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="EZK 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 14:1"/>And men from [the] elderly of Israel come to me, and sit before me. <verse eid="EZK 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 14:2"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 14:3"/>“Son of man, these men have caused their idols to go up on their heart, and they have put the stumbling-block of their iniquity before their faces; am I inquired of at all by them? <verse eid="EZK 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 14:4"/>Therefore, speak with them, and you have said to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: Everyone of the house of Israel who causes his idols to go up to his heart, and sets the stumbling-block of his iniquity before his face, and has gone to the prophet—I, YHWH, have given an answer to him for this, for the abundance of his idols, <verse eid="EZK 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 14:5"/>in order to catch the house of Israel by their heart, in that they have become estranged from off Me by their idols—all of them. <verse eid="EZK 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 14:6"/>Therefore say to the house of Israel, Thus said Lord YHWH: Turn back, indeed, turn back from your idols, and turn back your faces from all your abominations, <verse eid="EZK 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 14:7"/>for everyone of the house of Israel, and of the sojourners who sojourn in Israel, who is separated from after Me, and causes his idols to go up to his heart, and sets the stumbling-block of his iniquity before his face, and has come to the prophet to inquire of him concerning Me, I, YHWH, have answered him for Myself; <verse eid="EZK 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 14:8"/>and I have set My face against that man, and made him for a sign, and for allegories, and I have cut him off from the midst of My people, and you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 14:9"/>And the prophet, when he is enticed, and has spoken a word—I, YHWH, have enticed that prophet, and have stretched out My hand against him, and have destroyed him from the midst of My people Israel. <verse eid="EZK 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 14:10"/>And they have borne their iniquity: as the iniquity of the inquirer, so is the iniquity of the prophet; <verse eid="EZK 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 14:11"/>so that the house of Israel does not wander from after Me anymore, nor are they defiled with all their transgressions anymore, and they have been to Me for a people, and I am to them for God—a declaration of Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 14:12"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 14:13"/>“Son of man, when the land sins against Me to commit a trespass, and I have stretched out My hand against it, and broken the staff of bread for it, and sent famine into it, and cut off man and beast from it— <verse eid="EZK 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 14:14"/>and [despite] these three men [that] have been in its midst: Noah, Daniel, and Job—they [only] deliver their own soul by their righteousness,” a declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 14:15"/>“If I cause an evil beast to pass through the land, and it has bereaved, and it has been a desolation, without any passing through because of the beast— <verse eid="EZK 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 14:16"/>[despite] these three men in its midst—[as] I live,” a declaration of Lord YHWH, “they deliver neither sons nor daughters; they alone are delivered, and the land is a desolation. <verse eid="EZK 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 14:17"/>Or [if] I bring a sword in against that land, and I have said: Sword, pass over through the land, and I have cut off man and beast from it— <verse eid="EZK 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 14:18"/>and [despite] these three men in its midst—[as] I live,” a declaration of Lord YHWH, “they do not deliver sons and daughters, for they alone are delivered. <verse eid="EZK 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 14:19"/>Or [if] I send pestilence to that land, and I have poured out My fury against it in blood, to cut off man and beast from it— <verse eid="EZK 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 14:20"/>and [despite] Noah, Daniel, and Job, in its midst—[as] I live,” a declaration of Lord YHWH, “they deliver neither son nor daughter; they, by their righteousness, [only] deliver their own soul.” <verse eid="EZK 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 14:21"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: “Although My four severe judgments—sword, and famine, and wild beast, and pestilence—I have sent to Jerusalem, to cut off man and beast from it, <verse eid="EZK 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 14:22"/>yet, behold, there has been left an escape in it, who are brought forth, sons and daughters, behold, they are coming forth to you, and you have seen their way, and their doings, and have been comforted concerning the calamity that I have brought in against Jerusalem, all that which I have brought in against it. <verse eid="EZK 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 14:23"/>And they have comforted you, for you see their way and their doings, and you have known that I have not done all that which I have done in her for nothing,” a declaration of Lord YHWH.<verse eid="EZK 14:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="EZK 15"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 15:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 15:2"/>“Son of man, || What is the vine-tree more than any tree? The vine-branch that has been, || Among trees of the forest? <verse eid="EZK 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 15:3"/>Is wood taken from it to use for work? Do they take a pin of it to hang any vessel on it? <verse eid="EZK 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 15:4"/>Behold, it has been given to the fire for fuel, || The fire has eaten its two ends, || And its midst has been scorched! Is it profitable for work? <verse eid="EZK 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 15:5"/>Behold, in its being perfect it is not used for work, || How much less when fire has eaten of it, || And it is scorched, || Has it been used yet for work?” <verse eid="EZK 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 15:6"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: “As the vine-tree among trees of the forest, || That I have given to the fire for fuel, || So I have given the inhabitants of Jerusalem. <verse eid="EZK 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 15:7"/>And I have set My face against them, || They have gone forth from the fire, || And the fire consumes them, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My setting My face against them. <verse eid="EZK 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 15:8"/>And I have made the land a desolation, || Because they have committed a trespass,” || A declaration of Lord YHWH!<verse eid="EZK 15:8"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="EZK 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 16:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 16:2"/>“Son of man, cause Jerusalem to know her abominations, and you have said, <verse eid="EZK 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 16:3"/>Thus said Lord YHWH to Jerusalem: Your birth and your nativity || [Are] of the land of the Canaanite, || Your father the Amorite, and your mother a Hittite. <verse eid="EZK 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 16:4"/>As for your nativity, in the day you were born, || Your navel has not been cut, || And you were not washed in water for ease, || And you have not been salted at all, || And you have not been swaddled at all. <verse eid="EZK 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 16:5"/>No eye has had pity on you, to do any of these to you, || To have compassion on you, || And you are cast on the face of the field, || With loathing of your soul || In the day you were born! <verse eid="EZK 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 16:6"/>And I pass over by you, || And I see you trodden down in your blood, || And I say to you in your blood, Live! Indeed, I say to you in your blood, Live! <verse eid="EZK 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 16:7"/>I have made you a myriad as the shoot of the field, || And you are multiplied, and are great, || And come in with an excellent adornment, || Breasts have been formed, and your hair has grown—And you, naked and bare! <verse eid="EZK 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 16:8"/>And I pass over by you, and I see you, || And behold, your time [is] a time of loves, || And I spread My skirt over you, || And I cover your nakedness, || And I swear to you, and come into a covenant with you, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || And you become Mine. <verse eid="EZK 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 16:9"/>And I wash you with water, || And I wash away your blood from off you, || And I anoint you with oil. <verse eid="EZK 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 16:10"/>And I clothe you with embroidery, || And I shoe you with tachash [skin], || And I gird you with fine linen, || And I cover you with figured silk. <verse eid="EZK 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 16:11"/>And I adorn you with adornments, || And I give bracelets for your hands, || And a chain for your neck. <verse eid="EZK 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 16:12"/>And I give a ring for your nose, || And rings for your ears, || And a crown of beauty on your head. <verse eid="EZK 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 16:13"/>And you put on gold and silver, || And your clothing [is] fine linen, || And figured silk and embroidery, || You have eaten fine flour, and honey, and oil, || And you are very, very beautiful, || And go prosperously to the kingdom. <verse eid="EZK 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 16:14"/>And your name goes forth among nations, || Because of your beauty—for it [is] complete, || In My honor that I have set on you, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 16:15"/>And you trust in your beauty, || And go whoring because of your renown, || And pour out your whoredoms on everyone passing by—to him [that would have] it. <verse eid="EZK 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 16:16"/>And you take from your garments, || And make spotted high-places for yourself, || And go whoring on them, || They are not coming in—nor will it be! <verse eid="EZK 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 16:17"/>And you take your beautiful vessels || Of My gold and My silver that I gave to you, || And make images of a male for yourself, || And go whoring with them, <verse eid="EZK 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 16:18"/>And you take the garments of your embroidery, || And cover them, || And you have set My oil and My incense before them. <verse eid="EZK 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 16:19"/>And My bread, that I gave to you, || Fine flour, and oil, and honey, that I caused you to eat. You have even set it before them, || For a refreshing fragrance—thus it is, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 16:20"/>And you take your sons and your daughters whom you have born to Me, || And sacrifice them to them for food. Is it a little thing because of your whoredoms, <verse eid="EZK 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 16:21"/>that you slaughter My sons, || And give them up in causing them to pass over to them? <verse eid="EZK 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 16:22"/>And with all your abominations and your whoredoms, || You have not remembered the days of your youth, || When you were naked and bare, || You were trodden down in your blood! <verse eid="EZK 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 16:23"/>And it comes to pass, after all your wickedness || (Woe, woe, to you—a declaration of Lord YHWH), <verse eid="EZK 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 16:24"/>That you build an arch for yourself, || And make a high place for yourself in every broad place. <verse eid="EZK 16:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 16:25"/>At every head of the way you have built your high place, || And you make your beauty abominable, || And open wide your feet to everyone passing by, || And multiply your whoredoms, <verse eid="EZK 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 16:26"/>And go whoring to sons of Egypt, || Your neighbors—great of appetite! And you multiply your whoredoms, || To provoke Me to anger. <verse eid="EZK 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 16:27"/>And behold, I have stretched out My hand against you, || And I diminish your portion, || And give you to the desire of those hating you, || The daughters of the Philistines, || Who are ashamed of your wicked way. <verse eid="EZK 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 16:28"/>And you go whoring to sons of Asshur, || Without your being satisfied, || And you go whoring with them, || And also—you have not been satisfied. <verse eid="EZK 16:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 16:29"/>And you multiply your whoredoms || On the land of Canaan—toward Chaldea, || And even with this you have not been satisfied. <verse eid="EZK 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 16:30"/>How weak [is] your heart, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || In your doing all these, || The work of a domineering, whorish woman. <verse eid="EZK 16:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 16:31"/>In your building your arch at the head of every way, || You have made your high place in every broad place, || And have not been as a whore deriding a wage. <verse eid="EZK 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 16:32"/>The wife who commits adultery—Under her husband—receives strangers. <verse eid="EZK 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EZK 16:33"/>They give a gift to all whores, || And you have given your gifts to all your lovers, || And bribe them to come in to you, || From all around—in your whoredoms. <verse eid="EZK 16:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EZK 16:34"/>And you are opposite from [other] women in your whoredoms, || That none go whoring after you; And in your giving a wage, || And a wage has not been given to you; Therefore you are the opposite. <verse eid="EZK 16:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EZK 16:35"/>Therefore, O whore, hear a word of YHWH! <verse eid="EZK 16:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EZK 16:36"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Because of your bronze being poured forth, || And your nakedness is revealed in your whoredoms near your lovers, || And near all the idols of your abominations, || And according to the blood of your sons, || Whom you have given to them; <verse eid="EZK 16:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EZK 16:37"/>Therefore, behold, I am assembling all your lovers, || To whom you have been sweet, || And all whom you have loved, || Besides all whom you have hated; And I have assembled them by you all around, || And have revealed your nakedness to them, || And they have seen all your nakedness. <verse eid="EZK 16:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EZK 16:38"/>And I have judged you—judgments of adultresses, || And of women shedding blood, || And have given you blood, fury, and jealousy. <verse eid="EZK 16:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EZK 16:39"/>And I have given you into their hand, || And they have thrown down your arch, || And they have broken down your high places, || And they have stripped you of your garments, || And they have taken your beautiful vessels, || And they have left you naked and bare. <verse eid="EZK 16:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EZK 16:40"/>And have caused an assembly to come up against you, || And stoned you with stones, || And thrust you through with their swords, <verse eid="EZK 16:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="EZK 16:41"/>And burned your houses with fire, || And done judgments in you before the eyes of many women, || And I have caused you to cease from going whoring, || And also, you no longer give a wage. <verse eid="EZK 16:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="EZK 16:42"/>And I have caused My fury against you to rest, || And My jealousy has turned aside from you, || And I have been quiet, and I am not angry anymore. <verse eid="EZK 16:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="EZK 16:43"/>Because you have not remembered the days of your youth, || And give trouble to Me in all these, || Therefore I also—behold—I put your way on [your own] head, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || And you will not have done—have done this wickedness above all your abominations. <verse eid="EZK 16:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="EZK 16:44"/>Behold, everyone using the allegory against you, || Uses [this] allegory concerning [you], saying, || As the mother—her daughter! <verse eid="EZK 16:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="EZK 16:45"/>You [are] your mother’s daughter, || Loathing her husband and her sons, || And you [are] your sisters’ sister, || Who loathed their husbands and their sons, || Your mother [is] a Hittite, and your father an Amorite. <verse eid="EZK 16:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="EZK 16:46"/>And your older sister [is] Samaria, she and her daughters, || Who is dwelling at your left hand, || And your younger sister, who is dwelling on your right hand, [is] Sodom and her daughters. <verse eid="EZK 16:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="EZK 16:47"/>And you have not walked in their ways, || And done according to their abominations, || It has been loathed as a little thing, || Indeed, you do more corruptly than they in all your ways. <verse eid="EZK 16:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="EZK 16:48"/>[As] I live—a declaration of Lord YHWH, || Your sister Sodom has not done—she and her daughters—As you have done—you and your daughters. <verse eid="EZK 16:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="EZK 16:49"/>Behold, this has been the iniquity of your sister Sodom, || Arrogancy, fullness of bread, and quiet ease, || Have been to her and to her daughters, || And the hand of the afflicted and needy || She has not strengthened. <verse eid="EZK 16:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="EZK 16:50"/>And they are haughty and do abomination before Me, || And I turn them aside when I have seen. <verse eid="EZK 16:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="EZK 16:51"/>And Samaria has not sinned even half of your sins, || But you multiply your abominations more than they, || And justify your sisters by all your abominations that you have done. <verse eid="EZK 16:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="EZK 16:52"/>You also—bear your shame, || That you have adjudged for your sisters, || Because of your sins that you have done more abominably than they, || They are more righteous than you, || And you, also, be ashamed and bear your shame, || In your justifying your sisters. <verse eid="EZK 16:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="EZK 16:53"/>And I have turned back [to] their captivity, || The captivity of Sodom and her daughters, || And the captivity of Samaria and her daughters, || And the captivity of your captives in their midst, <verse eid="EZK 16:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="EZK 16:54"/>So that you bear your shame, || And have been ashamed of all that you have done, || In your comforting them. <verse eid="EZK 16:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="EZK 16:55"/>And your sisters, Sodom and her daughters, || Return to their former state, || And Samaria and her daughters return to their former state, || And you and your daughters return to your former state. <verse eid="EZK 16:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="EZK 16:56"/>And your sister Sodom has not been for a report in your mouth, || In the day of your arrogancy, <verse eid="EZK 16:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="EZK 16:57"/>Before your wickedness is revealed, || As [at] the time of the reproach of the daughters of Aram, || And of all her neighbors, the daughters of the Philistines, || Who are despising you all around. <verse eid="EZK 16:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="EZK 16:58"/>Your wicked plans and your abominations, || You have borne them, a declaration of YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 16:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="EZK 16:59"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: I have dealt with you as you have done, || In that you have despised an oath—to break covenant. <verse eid="EZK 16:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="EZK 16:60"/>And I have remembered My covenant with you, || In the days of your youth, || And I have established a perpetual covenant for you. <verse eid="EZK 16:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="EZK 16:61"/>And you have remembered your ways, || And you have been ashamed, || In your receiving your sisters—Your older with your younger, || And I have given them to you for daughters, || And not by your covenant. <verse eid="EZK 16:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="EZK 16:62"/>And I have established My covenant with you, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 16:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="EZK 16:63"/>So that you remember, || And you have been ashamed, || And there is not an opening of the mouth to you anymore because of your shame, || In My receiving atonement for you, || For all that you have done, || A declaration of Lord YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 16:63"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="EZK 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 17:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 17:2"/>“Son of man, put forth a riddle, and use an allegory to the house of Israel, <verse eid="EZK 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 17:3"/>and you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH: The great eagle, great-winged, long-pinioned, || Full of feathers, that has diverse colors, || Has come to Lebanon, || And he takes the foliage of the cedar, <verse eid="EZK 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 17:4"/>He has cropped the top of its tender twigs, || And he brings it to the land of Canaan. He has placed it in a city of merchants. <verse eid="EZK 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 17:5"/>And he takes of the seed of the land, || And puts it in a field of seed, || He took [it] by many waters, || He has set it in a conspicuous place. <verse eid="EZK 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 17:6"/>And it springs up, and becomes a spreading vine, humble of stature, || To turn its thin shoots toward itself, || And its roots are under it, || And it becomes a vine, and makes boughs, || And sends forth beautiful branches. <verse eid="EZK 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 17:7"/>And there is another great eagle, || Great-winged, and abounding with feathers, || And behold, this vine has bent its roots toward him, || And it has sent out its thin shoots toward him, || To water it from the furrows of its planting, <verse eid="EZK 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 17:8"/>On a good field, by many waters, it is planted, to make branches, and to bear fruit, to be for a good vine. <verse eid="EZK 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 17:9"/>Say, Thus said Lord YHWH: It prospers—does he not draw out its roots, || And cut off its fruit, and it is withered? [In] all the leaves of its springing it withers, || And not by great strength, or by numerous people, || To lift it up by its roots. <verse eid="EZK 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 17:10"/>And behold, the planted thing—does it prosper? When the east wind comes against it, does it not utterly wither? On the furrows of its springing it withers.” <verse eid="EZK 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 17:11"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 17:12"/>“Now say to the house of rebellion, || Have you not known what these [are]? Say, Behold, the king of Babylon has come to Jerusalem, || And he takes its king, and its princes, || And brings them to himself to Babylon. <verse eid="EZK 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 17:13"/>And he takes of the seed of the kingdom, || And makes a covenant with him, || And brings him into an oath, || And he has taken the mighty of the land, <verse eid="EZK 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 17:14"/>That the kingdom may be humble, || That it may not lift itself up, || To keep his covenant—that it may stand. <verse eid="EZK 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 17:15"/>And he rebels against him, || To send his messengers to Egypt, || To give to him horses, and many people, || Does he prosper? Does he who is doing these things escape? And has he broken covenant and escaped? <verse eid="EZK 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 17:16"/>[As] I live—a declaration of Lord YHWH, || Does he not—in the place of the king who is causing him to reign, || Whose oath he has despised, || And whose covenant he has broken—die with him in the midst of Babylon? <verse eid="EZK 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 17:17"/>And not with a great force, and with a numerous assembly, || Does Pharaoh maintain him in battle, || By pouring out a mound, and in building a fortification, || To cut off many souls. <verse eid="EZK 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 17:18"/>And he despised the oath—to break covenant, || And behold, he has given his hand, || And all these he has done—he does not escape. <verse eid="EZK 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 17:19"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: [As] I live—My oath that he has despised, || And My covenant that he has broken, || Have I not put it on his head? <verse eid="EZK 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 17:20"/>And I have spread out My snare for him, || And he has been caught in My net, || And I have brought him to Babylon, || And judged him there [for the] trespass || That he has trespassed against Me. <verse eid="EZK 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 17:21"/>And all his fugitives, with all his bands, || Fall by sword, and those remaining, || They are spread out to every wind, || And you have known that I, YHWH, have spoken. <verse eid="EZK 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 17:22"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: I have taken of the foliage of the high cedar, || And I have set [it], || I crop a tender one from the top of its tender shoots, || And I have planted [it] on a high and lofty mountain. <verse eid="EZK 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 17:23"/>In a mountain—the high place of Israel, I plant it, || And it has borne boughs, and yielded fruit, || And become a good cedar, || And every bird of every [kind of] wing has dwelt under it, || They dwell in the shade of its thin shoots. <verse eid="EZK 17:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 17:24"/>And all trees of the field have known || That I, YHWH, have made the high tree low, || I have set the low tree on high, || I have dried up the moist tree, || And I have caused the dry tree to flourish, || I, YHWH, have spoken, and have done [it]!”<verse eid="EZK 17:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="EZK 18"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 18:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 18:2"/>“What [is it] to you [that] you are using this allegory || Concerning the ground of Israel, saying, || Fathers eat unripe fruit, || And the sons’ teeth are blunted? <verse eid="EZK 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 18:3"/>[As] I live,” a declaration of Lord YHWH, “You no longer have the use of this allegory in Israel. <verse eid="EZK 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 18:4"/>Behold, all the souls are Mine, || As the soul of the father, || So also the soul of the son—they are Mine, || The soul that is sinning—it dies. <verse eid="EZK 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 18:5"/>And a man, when he is righteous, || And has done judgment and righteousness, <verse eid="EZK 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 18:6"/>He has not eaten on the mountains, || And has not lifted up his eyes || To idols of the house of Israel, || And did not defile his neighbor’s wife, || And did not come near to a separated woman, <verse eid="EZK 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 18:7"/>He does not oppress a man, || He returns his pledge to the debtor, || He does not take away plunder, || He gives his bread to the hungry, || And covers the naked with a garment, <verse eid="EZK 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 18:8"/>He does not give in usury, and does not take increase, || He turns back his hand from perversity, || He does true judgment between man and man. <verse eid="EZK 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 18:9"/>He walks in My statutes, || And he has kept My judgments—to deal truly, || He [is] righteous—he surely lives,” || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 18:10"/>“And he has begotten a son, || A burglar—a shedder of blood, || And he has made a brother of one of these, <verse eid="EZK 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 18:11"/>And he has not done all those, || For he has even eaten on the mountains, || And he has defiled his neighbor’s wife, <verse eid="EZK 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 18:12"/>He has oppressed the afflicted and needy, || He has taken away plunder violently, || He does not return a pledge, || And he has lifted up his eyes to the idols, || He has done abomination! <verse eid="EZK 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 18:13"/>He has given in usury, and taken increase, || And he lives? He does not live, || He has done all these abominations, || He surely dies, his blood is on him. <verse eid="EZK 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 18:14"/>And—behold, he has begotten a son, || And he sees all the sins of his father, || That he has done, and he fears, || And does not do like them, <verse eid="EZK 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 18:15"/>He has not eaten on the mountains, || And he has not lifted up his eyes || To idols of the house of Israel, || He has not defiled his neighbor’s wife, <verse eid="EZK 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 18:16"/>He has not oppressed a man, || He has not bound a pledge, || And he has not taken away plunder, || He has given his bread to the hungry, || And he covered the naked with a garment, <verse eid="EZK 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 18:17"/>He has turned back his hand from the afflicted, || He has not taken usury and increase, || He has done My judgments, || He has walked in My statutes, || He does not die for the iniquity of his father, || He surely lives. <verse eid="EZK 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 18:18"/>His father—because he used oppression, || Violently plundered a brother, || And did that which [is] not good in the midst of his people, || And behold, he is dying in his iniquity. <verse eid="EZK 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 18:19"/>And you have said, Why has the son not borne of the iniquity of the father? And the son has done judgment and righteousness, || He has kept all My statutes, || And he does them, he surely lives. <verse eid="EZK 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 18:20"/>The soul that sins—it dies. A son does not bear of the iniquity of the father, || And a father does not bear of the iniquity of the son, || The righteousness of the righteous is on him, || And the wickedness of the wicked is on him. <verse eid="EZK 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 18:21"/>And the wicked—when he turns back || From all his sins that he has done, || And he has kept all My statutes, || And has done judgment and righteousness, || He surely lives, he does not die. <verse eid="EZK 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 18:22"/>All his transgressions that he has done || Are not remembered to him, || In his righteousness that he has done he lives. <verse eid="EZK 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 18:23"/>Do I take pleasure [or] delight in the death of the wicked?” A declaration of Lord YHWH, “Is it not in his turning back from his way—And he has lived? <verse eid="EZK 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 18:24"/>And in the turning back of the righteous from his righteousness, || And he has done perversity, || According to all the abominations || That the wicked has done, || Does he then live? All his righteous deeds that he has done are not remembered, || For his trespass that he has trespassed, || And for his sin that he has sinned, || For them he dies. <verse eid="EZK 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 18:25"/>And you have said, The way of the Lord is not pondered. Now hear, O house of Israel, || My way—is it not pondered? Are not your ways unpondered? <verse eid="EZK 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 18:26"/>In the turning back of the righteous from his righteousness, || And he has done perversity, || And he is dying by them, || He dies for his perversity that he has done. <verse eid="EZK 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 18:27"/>And in the turning back of the wicked || From his wickedness that he has done, || And he does judgment and righteousness, || He keeps his soul alive. <verse eid="EZK 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 18:28"/>And he sees and turns back, || From all his transgressions that he has done, || He surely lives, he does not die, <verse eid="EZK 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 18:29"/>And the house of Israel has said, The way of the Lord is not pondered, || My ways—are they not pondered? O house of Israel—are not your ways unpondered? <verse eid="EZK 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 18:30"/>Therefore, I judge each according to his ways, || O house of Israel,” || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || “Turn back, indeed, turn yourselves back, || From all your transgressions, || And iniquity is not for a stumbling-block to you, <verse eid="EZK 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 18:31"/>Cast away all your transgressions from over you, || By which you have transgressed, || And make a new heart and a new spirit for yourselves, || And why do you die, || O house of Israel? <verse eid="EZK 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 18:32"/>For I have no pleasure in the death of the dying,” || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || “Therefore turn back and live!”<verse eid="EZK 18:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="EZK 19"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 19:1"/>“And you, lift up a lamentation to princes of Israel, <verse eid="EZK 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 19:2"/>and you have said: What [is] your mother? A lioness, || She has crouched down among lions, || She has multiplied her whelps in the midst of young lions. <verse eid="EZK 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 19:3"/>And she brings up one of her whelps, || He has been a young lion, || And he learns to tear prey, || He has devoured man. <verse eid="EZK 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 19:4"/>And nations hear of him, || He has been caught in their pit, || And they bring him to the land of Egypt in chains. <verse eid="EZK 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 19:5"/>And as she waited she sees that her hope has perished, || And she takes one of her whelps, || She has made him a young lion. <verse eid="EZK 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 19:6"/>And he goes up and down in the midst of lions, || He has been a young lion, || And he learns to tear prey, || He has devoured man. <verse eid="EZK 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 19:7"/>And he knows his forsaken habitations, || And he has laid waste [to] their cities, || And the land and its fullness is desolate, || Because of the voice of his roaring. <verse eid="EZK 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 19:8"/>And surrounding nations set against him from the provinces. And they spread out their net for him, || He has been caught in their pit. <verse eid="EZK 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 19:9"/>And they put him in prison—in chains, || And they bring him to the king of Babylon, || They bring him into bulwarks, || So that his voice is not heard || On mountains of Israel anymore. <verse eid="EZK 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 19:10"/>Your mother, like the vine in your blood, || Is being planted by waters, || She was bearing fruit and full of boughs, || Because of many waters. <verse eid="EZK 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 19:11"/>And she has strong rods for scepters of rulers, || And she is high in stature above—between thick branches, || And it appears in its height || In the multitude of its thin shoots. <verse eid="EZK 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 19:12"/>And she is plucked up in fury, || She has been cast to the earth, || And the east wind has dried up her fruit, || [The] rod of her strength has been broken and withered, || Fire has consumed it. <verse eid="EZK 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 19:13"/>And now she is planted in a wilderness, || In a dry and thirsty land. <verse eid="EZK 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 19:14"/>And fire goes forth from a rod of her boughs, || It has devoured her fruit, || And she has no rod of strength—a scepter to rule, || A lamentation—and she has become for a lamentation!”<verse eid="EZK 19:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="EZK 20"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 20:1"/>And it comes to pass, in the seventh year, in the fifth [month], on the tenth of the month, men from [the] elderly of Israel have come in to seek YHWH, and they sit before me; <verse eid="EZK 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 20:2"/>and there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 20:3"/>“Son of man, speak to the elderly of Israel, and you have said to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: Are you coming in to seek Me? [As] I live—I am not sought by you—a declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 20:4"/>Do you judge them? Do you judge, son of man? Cause them to know the abominations of their fathers, <verse eid="EZK 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 20:5"/>and you have said to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: In the day of My fixing on Israel, || I lift up My hand, || To the seed of the house of Jacob, || And am known to them in the land of Egypt, || And I lift up My hand to them, || Saying, I [am] your God YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 20:6"/>In that day I lifted up My hand to them, || To bring them forth from the land of Egypt, || To a land that I spied out for them, || Flowing with milk and honey, || It [is] a beauty to all the lands, <verse eid="EZK 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 20:7"/>And I say to them, Let each cast away the detestable things of his eyes, || And do not be defiled with the idols of Egypt, || I [am] your God YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 20:8"/>And they rebel against Me, || And have not been willing to listen to Me, || Each has not cast away the detestable things of their eyes, || And have not forsaken the idols of Egypt, || And I speak—to pour out My fury on them, || To complete My anger against them, || In the midst of the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EZK 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 20:9"/>And I do [it] for My Name’s sake, || Not to defile [it] before the eyes of the nations, || In whose midst they [are in], || Before whose eyes I became known to them, || To bring them out from the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EZK 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 20:10"/>And I bring them out of the land of Egypt, || And I bring them into the wilderness, <verse eid="EZK 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 20:11"/>And I give My statutes to them, || And I caused them to know My judgments, || Which the man who does—lives by them. <verse eid="EZK 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 20:12"/>And I have also given My Sabbaths to them, || To be for a sign between Me and them, || To know that I [am] YHWH who is sanctifying them. <verse eid="EZK 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 20:13"/>And the house of Israel rebels against Me in the wilderness, || They have not walked in My statutes, || And they have despised My judgments, || Which the man who does—lives by them. And they have greatly defiled My Sabbaths, || And I speak—to pour out My fury on them in the wilderness, to consume them. <verse eid="EZK 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 20:14"/>And I do [it] for My Name’s sake, || Not to defile [it] before the eyes of the nations, || Before whose eyes I brought them forth. <verse eid="EZK 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 20:15"/>And also, I have lifted up My hand to them in the wilderness, || Not to bring them into the land that I had given, || Flowing with milk and honey, || It [is] a beauty to all the lands, <verse eid="EZK 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 20:16"/>Because they kicked against My judgments, || And they have not walked in My statutes, || And they have defiled My Sabbaths, || For their heart is going after their idols. <verse eid="EZK 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 20:17"/>And My eye has pity on them—against destroying them, || And I have not made an end of them in the wilderness. <verse eid="EZK 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 20:18"/>And I say to their sons in the wilderness: Do not walk in the statutes of your fathers, || And do not observe their judgments, || And do not defile yourselves with their idols. <verse eid="EZK 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 20:19"/>I [am] your God YHWH, walk in My statutes, || And observe My judgments, and do them, <verse eid="EZK 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 20:20"/>And sanctify My Sabbaths, || And they have been for a sign between Me and you, || To know that I [am] your God YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 20:21"/>And the sons rebel against Me, || They have not walked in My statutes, || And they have not observed My judgments—to do them, || Which the man who does—lives by them. They have defiled My Sabbaths, || And I speak—to pour out My fury on them, || To complete My anger against them in the wilderness. <verse eid="EZK 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 20:22"/>And I have turned back My hand, || And I do [it] for My Name’s sake, || Not to defile [it] before the eyes of the nations, || Before whose eyes I brought them out. <verse eid="EZK 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 20:23"/>I also, I have lifted up My hand to them in the wilderness, || To scatter them among nations, || And to spread them through lands. <verse eid="EZK 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 20:24"/>Because they have not done My judgments, || And they have despised My statutes, || And they have defiled My Sabbaths, || And their eyes have been after [the] idols of their fathers. <verse eid="EZK 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 20:25"/>And I also, I have given statutes to them [that are] not good, || And judgments by which they do not live. <verse eid="EZK 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 20:26"/>And I defile them by their own gifts, || By causing every opener of a womb to pass away, || So that I make them desolate, || So that they know that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 20:27"/>Therefore, speak to the house of Israel, son of man, and you have said to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: Still in this your fathers have reviled Me, || In their committing a trespass against Me. <verse eid="EZK 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 20:28"/>And I bring them into the land, || That I lifted up My hand to give to them, || And they see every high hill, and every thick tree, || And they sacrifice their sacrifices there, || And give the provocation of their offering there, || And make their refreshing fragrance there, || And they pour out their drink-offerings there. <verse eid="EZK 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 20:29"/>And I say to them: What [is] the high place to where you are going in?” And its name is called “High Place” to this day. <verse eid="EZK 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 20:30"/>“Therefore, say to the house of Israel, Thus said Lord YHWH: Are you defiling yourselves in the way of your fathers? And do you go whoring after their detestable things? <verse eid="EZK 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 20:31"/>And in the offering of your gifts, || In causing your sons to pass through fire, || You are defiled by all your idols to this day, || And I am sought by you, O house of Israel? [As] I live—a declaration of Lord YHWH, I am not sought by you. <verse eid="EZK 20:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 20:32"/>And that which is going up on your mind, || It is not at all—in that you are saying: We will be as the nations, as the families of the lands, || To serve wood and stone. <verse eid="EZK 20:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EZK 20:33"/>[As] I live—a declaration of Lord YHWH, || Do I not, with a strong hand, || And with an outstretched arm, || And with poured out fury—rule over you? <verse eid="EZK 20:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EZK 20:34"/>And I have brought you forth from the peoples, || And assembled you from the lands || In which you have been scattered, || With a strong hand and with an outstretched arm, || And with poured out fury. <verse eid="EZK 20:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EZK 20:35"/>And I have brought you into the wilderness of the peoples, || And have been judged with you there face to face. <verse eid="EZK 20:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EZK 20:36"/>As I was judged with your fathers, || In the wilderness of the land of Egypt, || So I am judged with you, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 20:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EZK 20:37"/>And I have caused you to pass under the rod, || And brought you into the bond of the covenant, <verse eid="EZK 20:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EZK 20:38"/>And cleared out the rebels from you, || And those transgressing against Me, || I bring them out from the land of their sojournings, || And they do not come to the land of Israel, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 20:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EZK 20:39"/>And you, O house of Israel, thus said Lord YHWH: Each go, serve his idols, || And afterward, if you are not listening to Me [anyway], || But you do not defile My holy Name anymore by your gifts, and by your idols. <verse eid="EZK 20:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EZK 20:40"/>For on My holy mountain, || On the mountain of the height of Israel, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || All the house of Israel serves Me there, || All of it, in the land—I accept them there, || And I seek your raised-offerings there, || And with the first-fruit of your gifts, || With all your holy things. <verse eid="EZK 20:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="EZK 20:41"/>With refreshing fragrance I accept you, || In My bringing you out from the peoples, || And I have assembled you from the lands || In which you have been scattered, || And I have been sanctified in you || Before the eyes of the nations. <verse eid="EZK 20:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="EZK 20:42"/>And you have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My bringing you to the ground of Israel, || To the land that I lifted up My hand || To give it to your fathers, <verse eid="EZK 20:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="EZK 20:43"/>And you have remembered your ways there, || And all your doings, || In which you have been defiled, || And you have been loathsome in your own faces, || For all your evils that you have done. <verse eid="EZK 20:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="EZK 20:44"/>And you have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My dealing with you for My Name’s sake, || Not according to your evil ways, || And according to your corrupt doings, O house of Israel, || A declaration of Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 20:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="EZK 20:45"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 20:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="EZK 20:46"/>“Son of man, set your face the way of Teman, and prophesy to the south, and prophesy to the forest of the field—the south; <verse eid="EZK 20:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="EZK 20:47"/>and you have said to the forest of the south, Hear a word of YHWH! Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am kindling a fire in you, || And it has devoured every moist tree in you, and every dry tree, || The glowing flames are not quenched, || And all faces from south to north have been burned by it. <verse eid="EZK 20:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="EZK 20:48"/>And all flesh has seen, that I, YHWH, have kindled it—it is not quenched.” <verse eid="EZK 20:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="EZK 20:49"/>And I say, “Aah! Lord YHWH, || They are saying of me, || Is he not using allegories?”<verse eid="EZK 20:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="EZK 21"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 21:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 21:2"/>“Son of man, set your face toward Jerusalem, and prophesy to the holy places, and prophesy to the ground of Israel; <verse eid="EZK 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 21:3"/>and you have said to the ground of Israel, Thus said YHWH: Behold, I [am] against you, || And have brought out My sword from its scabbard, || And have cut off righteous and wicked from you. <verse eid="EZK 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 21:4"/>Because that I have cut off righteous and wicked from you, || Therefore My sword goes out from its scabbard, || To all flesh, from south to north. <verse eid="EZK 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 21:5"/>And all flesh has known that I, YHWH, || Have brought out My sword from its scabbard, || It does not turn back anymore. <verse eid="EZK 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 21:6"/>And you, son of man, sigh with breaking of loins, indeed, sigh before their eyes with bitterness, <verse eid="EZK 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 21:7"/>and it has come to pass, when they say to you, Why are you sighing? That you have said: Because of the report, for it is coming, || And every heart has melted, || And all hands have been feeble, || And every spirit is weak, || And all knees go [as] waters, || Behold, it is coming, indeed, it has been, || A declaration of Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 21:8"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 21:9"/>“Son of man, prophesy, and you have said, Thus said YHWH: Say, A sword, a sword is sharpened, and also polished. <verse eid="EZK 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 21:10"/>It is sharpened so as to slaughter a slaughter. It is polished so as to have brightness, || Or do we rejoice? It is despising the scepter of My son [as] every tree. <verse eid="EZK 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 21:11"/>And He gives it for polishing, || For laying hold of by the hand. It is sharpened—the sword—and polished, || To give it into the hand of a slayer. <verse eid="EZK 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 21:12"/>Cry and howl, son of man, || For it has been among My people, || It [is] among all the princes of Israel, || My people have been cast to the sword. Therefore strike on your thigh, <verse eid="EZK 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 21:13"/>Because [it is] a trier, || And what if it is even despising the scepter? It will not be, a declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 21:14"/>And you, son of man, prophesy, || And strike hand on hand, || And the sword is bent a third time, || The sword of the wounded! It [is] the sword of the wounded—the great one, || That is entering the inner chamber to them. <verse eid="EZK 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 21:15"/>To melt the heart, and to multiply the ruins, || I have set the point of a sword by all their gates. Aah! It is made for brightness, || Wrapped up for slaughter. <verse eid="EZK 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 21:16"/>Take possession of the right, place yourself at the left, || To where your face is appointed. <verse eid="EZK 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 21:17"/>And I also, I strike My hand on My hand, || And have caused My fury to rest; I, YHWH, have spoken.” <verse eid="EZK 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 21:18"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 21:19"/>“And you, son of man, appoint two ways for yourself, for the coming in of the sword of the king of Babylon; they come forth from one land, both of them. And create a station; create [it] at the top of the way of the city. <verse eid="EZK 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 21:20"/>Appoint a way for the coming of the sword, || To Rabbath of the sons of Ammon, || And to Judah, in fortified Jerusalem. <verse eid="EZK 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 21:21"/>For the king of Babylon has stood at the head of the way, || At the top of the two ways, to use divination, || He has moved lightly with the arrows, || He has inquired of the teraphim, || He has looked on the liver. <verse eid="EZK 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 21:22"/>The divination [for] Jerusalem has been at his right, || To place battering-rams, || To open the mouth with slaughter, || To lift up a voice with shouting, || To place battering-rams against the gates, || To pour out a mound, to build a fortification. <verse eid="EZK 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 21:23"/>And it has been to them as a false divination in their eyes, || Who have sworn oaths to them, || But he is causing iniquity to be remembered [so they] are caught. <verse eid="EZK 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 21:24"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Because of your causing your iniquity to be remembered, || In your transgressions being revealed, || For your sins being seen, in all your doings, || Because of your being remembered, || You are caught by the hand. <verse eid="EZK 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 21:25"/>And you, wounded, wicked one, || Prince of Israel, whose day has come, || In the time of the iniquity of the end, <verse eid="EZK 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 21:26"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Turn aside the turban, and carry away the crown, || This—not this—make high the low, || And make low the high. <verse eid="EZK 21:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 21:27"/>An overturn, overturn, overturn, I make it, || Also this has not been until the coming of Him, || Whose [is] the judgment, and I have given it. <verse eid="EZK 21:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 21:28"/>And you, son of man, prophesy, and you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH concerning the sons of Ammon, and concerning their reproach, and you have said: A sword, a sword, open for slaughter, || Polished to the utmost for brightness! <verse eid="EZK 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 21:29"/>In seeing a vain thing for you, || In divining a lie for you, || To put you on the necks of the wounded of the wicked, whose day has come, || In the time of the iniquity of the end. <verse eid="EZK 21:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 21:30"/>Turn [it] back to its scabbard; I judge you || In the place where you were produced, || In the land of your birth. <verse eid="EZK 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 21:31"/>And I have poured My indignation on you, || I blow against you with [the] fire of My wrath, || And have given you into the hand of brutish men—craftsmen of destruction. <verse eid="EZK 21:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 21:32"/>You are fuel for the fire, || Your blood is in the midst of the land, || You are not remembered, || For I, YHWH, have spoken!”<verse eid="EZK 21:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="EZK 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 22:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 22:2"/>“And you, son of man, do you judge? Do you judge the city of blood? Then you have caused it to know all its abominations, <verse eid="EZK 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 22:3"/>and you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH: The city is shedding blood in its midst, || For the coming in of its time, || And it has made idols on it for defilement. <verse eid="EZK 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 22:4"/>You have been guilty by your blood that you have shed, || And you have been defiled by your idols that you have made, || And you cause your days to draw near, || And have come to your years, || Therefore I have given you [for] a reproach to nations, || And a derision to all the lands. <verse eid="EZK 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 22:5"/>The near and the far-off from you scoff at you, || O defiled of name—abounding in trouble. <verse eid="EZK 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 22:6"/>Behold, princes of Israel—each according to his arm || Have been in you to shed blood. <verse eid="EZK 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 22:7"/>They have made light of father and mother in you, || They dealt oppressively to a sojourner in your midst, || They oppressed fatherless and widow in you. <verse eid="EZK 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 22:8"/>You have despised My holy things, || And you have defiled My Sabbaths. <verse eid="EZK 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 22:9"/>Men of slander have been in you to shed blood, || And they have eaten on the mountains in you, || They have done wickedness in your midst. <verse eid="EZK 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 22:10"/>One has uncovered the nakedness of a father in you, || They humbled the menstruous woman in you. <verse eid="EZK 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 22:11"/>And each has done abomination with the wife of his neighbor, || And each has defiled his daughter-in-law through wickedness, || And each has humbled his sister, his father’s daughter, in you. <verse eid="EZK 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 22:12"/>They have taken a bribe to shed blood in you, || You have taken usury and increase, || And cut off your neighbor by oppression, || And you have forgotten Me, || A declaration of Lord YHWH! <verse eid="EZK 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 22:13"/>And behold, I have struck My hand, || Because of your dishonest gain that you have gained, || And for your blood that has been in your midst. <verse eid="EZK 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 22:14"/>Does your heart stand—are your hands strong, || For the days that I am dealing with you? I, YHWH, have spoken and have done [it]. <verse eid="EZK 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 22:15"/>And I have scattered you among nations, || And have spread you out among lands, || And consumed your uncleanness out of you. <verse eid="EZK 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 22:16"/>And you have been defiled in yourself || Before the eyes of nations, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 22:17"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 22:18"/>“Son of man, the house of Israel has been for dross to Me, || All of them [are] bronze, and tin, and iron, and lead, || In the midst of a furnace—silver has been dross, <verse eid="EZK 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 22:19"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Because you have all become dross, || Therefore, behold, I am gathering you into the midst of Jerusalem, <verse eid="EZK 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 22:20"/>A gathering of silver, and bronze, and iron, and lead, and tin, || Into the midst of a furnace—to blow fire on it, to melt it, || So I gather in My anger and in My fury, || And I have let rest, and have melted you. <verse eid="EZK 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 22:21"/>And I have heaped you up, || And blown on you in the fire of My wrath, || And you have been melted in its midst. <verse eid="EZK 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 22:22"/>As the melting of silver in the midst of a furnace, || So you are melted in its midst, || And you have known that I, YHWH, have poured out My fury on you.” <verse eid="EZK 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 22:23"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 22:24"/>“Son of man, say to it, You [are] a land, || It [is] not cleansed nor rained on in a day of indignation. <verse eid="EZK 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 22:25"/>A conspiracy of its prophets [is] in its midst, || As a roaring lion tearing prey; They have devoured the soul, || They have taken wealth and glory, || Its widows have multiplied in its midst. <verse eid="EZK 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 22:26"/>Its priests have wronged My law, || And they defile My holy things, || They have not made separation between holy and common, || And they have not made known [the difference] between the unclean and the clean, || And they have hidden their eyes from My Sabbaths, || And I am pierced in their midst. <verse eid="EZK 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 22:27"/>Its princes [are] as wolves in its midst, || Tearing prey, to shed blood, to destroy souls, || For the sake of gaining dishonest gain. <verse eid="EZK 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 22:28"/>And its prophets have coated with chalk for them, || Seeing a vain thing, and divining a lie for them, || Saying, Thus said Lord YHWH, || And YHWH has not spoken. <verse eid="EZK 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 22:29"/>The people of the land have used oppression, || And have taken plunder away violently, || And have oppressed humble and needy, || And oppressed the sojourner without judgment. <verse eid="EZK 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 22:30"/>And I seek from them a man making a wall, || And standing in the breach before Me, || In behalf of the land—not to destroy it, || And I have found none. <verse eid="EZK 22:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 22:31"/>And I pour out My indignation on them, || I have consumed them by [the] fire of My wrath, || I have put their way on their own head, || A declaration of Lord YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 22:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="EZK 23"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 23:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, “Son of man, <verse eid="EZK 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 23:2"/>Two women were daughters of one mother, <verse eid="EZK 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 23:3"/>And they go whoring in Egypt, || They have gone whoring in their youth, || There they have bruised their breasts, || And there they have dealt with the loves of their virginity. <verse eid="EZK 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 23:4"/>And their names [are] Aholah the older, || And Aholibah her sister, || And they are Mine, and bear sons and daughters. As for their names—Samaria [is] Aholah, || And Jerusalem [is] Aholibah. <verse eid="EZK 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 23:5"/>And Aholah goes whoring under Me, and she lusts on her lovers, on the neighboring Assyrians, <verse eid="EZK 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 23:6"/>Clothed with blue—governors and prefects, || All of them desirable young men, || Horsemen, riding on horses, <verse eid="EZK 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 23:7"/>And she gives her whoredoms on them, || The choice of the sons of Asshur, || All of them—even all on whom she lusted, || She has been defiled by all their idols. <verse eid="EZK 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 23:8"/>And she has not forsaken her whoredoms out of Egypt, || For with her they lay in her youth, || And they dealt with the loves of her virginity, || And they pour out their whoredoms on her. <verse eid="EZK 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 23:9"/>Therefore I have given her into the hand of her lovers, || Into the hand of sons of Asshur on whom she lusted. <verse eid="EZK 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 23:10"/>They have uncovered her nakedness, || They have taken her sons and her daughters, || And they have slain her by sword, || And she is a name for women, || And they have done judgments with her. <verse eid="EZK 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 23:11"/>And her sister Aholibah sees, || And she makes her unhealthy love more corrupt than she, || And her whoredoms than the whoredoms of her sister. <verse eid="EZK 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 23:12"/>She has lusted on sons of Asshur, || Governors and prefects, || Neighboring ones—clothed in perfection, || Horsemen, riding on horses, || All of them desirable young men. <verse eid="EZK 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 23:13"/>And I see that she has been defiled, || One way [is] to them both. <verse eid="EZK 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 23:14"/>And she adds to her whoredoms, || And she sees men carved on the wall, || Pictures of Chaldeans, carved with vermillion, <verse eid="EZK 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 23:15"/>Girded with a girdle on their loins, || Dyed attire spread out on their heads, || The appearance of rulers—all of them, || The likeness of sons of Babylon, || Chaldea is the land of their birth. <verse eid="EZK 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 23:16"/>And she lusts on them at the sight of her eyes, || And sends messengers to them, to Chaldea. <verse eid="EZK 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 23:17"/>And sons of Babylon come in to her, || To the bed of loves, || And they defile her with their whoredoms, || And she is defiled with them, || And her soul is alienated from them. <verse eid="EZK 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 23:18"/>And she reveals her whoredoms, || And she reveals her nakedness, || And My soul is alienated from off her, || As My soul was alienated from off her sister. <verse eid="EZK 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 23:19"/>And she multiplies her whoredoms, || To remember the days of her youth, || When she went whoring in the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EZK 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 23:20"/>And she lusts on their lovers, || Whose flesh [is] the flesh of donkeys, || And the emission of horses—their emission. <verse eid="EZK 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 23:21"/>You look after the wickedness of your youth, || In dealing out of Egypt your loves, || For the sake of the breasts of your youth. <verse eid="EZK 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 23:22"/>Therefore, O Aholibah, thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am stirring up your lovers against you, || From whom your soul has been alienated, || And have brought them in against you from all around. <verse eid="EZK 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 23:23"/>Sons of Babylon, and of all Chaldea, Pekod, and Shoa, and Koa, || All the sons of Asshur with them, || Desirable young men, governors and prefects, || All of them—rulers and proclaimed ones, || All of them riding on horses. <verse eid="EZK 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 23:24"/>And they have come in against you, || With arms, rider, and wheel, || And with an assembly of peoples; Buckler, and shield, and helmet, || They set against you all around, || And I have set judgment before them, || They have judged you in their judgments. <verse eid="EZK 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 23:25"/>And I have set My jealousy against you, || And they have dealt with you in fury, || They turn aside your nose and your ears, || And your posterity falls by sword, || They take away your sons and your daughters, || And your posterity is devoured by fire. <verse eid="EZK 23:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 23:26"/>And they have stripped you of your garments, || And have taken your beautiful jewels. <verse eid="EZK 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 23:27"/>And I have caused your wickedness to cease from you, || And your whoredoms out of the land of Egypt, || And you do not lift up your eyes to them, || And you do not remember Egypt again. <verse eid="EZK 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 23:28"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am giving you into a hand that you have hated, || Into a hand from which you were alienated. <verse eid="EZK 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 23:29"/>And they have dealt with you in hatred, || And they have taken all your labor, || And they have left you naked and bare, || And the nakedness of your whoredoms has been revealed, || And the wickedness of your whoredoms. <verse eid="EZK 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 23:30"/>To do these things to you, || In your going whoring after nations, || Because you have been defiled with their idols, <verse eid="EZK 23:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 23:31"/>You have walked in the way of your sister, || And I have given her cup into your hand. <verse eid="EZK 23:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 23:32"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: You drink the cup of your sister, || The deep and the wide one || (You are for laughter and for scorn), || Abundant to contain. <verse eid="EZK 23:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EZK 23:33"/>You are filled with drunkenness and sorrow, || A cup of astonishment and desolation, || The cup of your sister Samaria. <verse eid="EZK 23:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EZK 23:34"/>And you have drunk it, and have drained [it], || And you gnaw its earthen ware, || And you pluck off your own breasts, || For I have spoken, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, <verse eid="EZK 23:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EZK 23:35"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Because you have forgotten Me, || And you cast Me behind your back, || Even you also bear your wickedness and your whoredoms.” <verse eid="EZK 23:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EZK 23:36"/>And YHWH says to me, “Son of man, || Do you judge Aholah and Aholibah? Then declare their abominations to them. <verse eid="EZK 23:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EZK 23:37"/>For they have committed adultery, || And blood [is] in their hands, || They committed adultery with their idols, || And also their sons whom they bore to Me, || They caused to pass over to them for food. <verse eid="EZK 23:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EZK 23:38"/>Again, they have done this to Me, || They defiled My sanctuary in that day, || And they have defiled My Sabbaths. <verse eid="EZK 23:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EZK 23:39"/>And in their slaughtering their sons to their idols || They also come into My sanctuary in that day to defile it, || And behold, thus they have done in the midst of My house, <verse eid="EZK 23:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EZK 23:40"/>And also that they send to men coming from afar, || To whom a messenger is sent, || And behold, they have come in for whom you have washed, || Painted your eyes, and put on adornment. <verse eid="EZK 23:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="EZK 23:41"/>And you have sat on a couch of honor, || And a table arrayed before it, || And placed My incense and My oil on it. <verse eid="EZK 23:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="EZK 23:42"/>And the voice of a multitude at ease [is] with her, || And Sabeans from the wilderness are brought in to men of the common people, || And they put bracelets on their hands, || And a beautiful crown on their heads. <verse eid="EZK 23:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="EZK 23:43"/>And I say of the worn-out one in adulteries, || Now they commit her whoredoms—she also! <verse eid="EZK 23:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="EZK 23:44"/>And they come in to her, || As the coming in to a whorish woman, || So they have come in to Aholah, || And to Aholibah—the wicked women. <verse eid="EZK 23:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="EZK 23:45"/>As for righteous men, they judge them with the judgment of adulteresses, || And the judgment of women shedding blood, || For they [are] adulteresses, || And blood [is] in their hands. <verse eid="EZK 23:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="EZK 23:46"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: Bring up an assembly against them, || And give them to trembling and to spoiling. <verse eid="EZK 23:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="EZK 23:47"/>And they have cast the stone of the assembly at them, || And cut them with their swords, || They slay their sons and their daughters, || And they burn their houses with fire. <verse eid="EZK 23:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="EZK 23:48"/>And I have caused wickedness to cease from the land, || And all the women have been instructed, || And they do not do according to your wickedness. <verse eid="EZK 23:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="EZK 23:49"/>And they have put your wickedness on you, || And you bear the sins of your idols, || And you have known that I [am] Lord YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 23:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="EZK 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 24:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, in the ninth year, in the tenth month, on the tenth of the month, saying, <verse eid="EZK 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 24:2"/>“Son of man, write! Write the name of the day for yourself, this very day; the king of Babylon has leaned toward Jerusalem in this very day. <verse eid="EZK 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 24:3"/>And use an allegory toward the house of rebellion, and you have said to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: To set on the pot, to set [it] on, and also to pour water into it, <verse eid="EZK 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 24:4"/>To gather its pieces to it, every good piece, || Thigh and shoulder, to fill in the choice of the bones. <verse eid="EZK 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 24:5"/>To take the choice of the flock, || And also to pile the bones under it, || Boil it thoroughly, indeed, cook its bones in its midst. <verse eid="EZK 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 24:6"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Woe [to] the city of blood, || A pot whose scum [is] in it, || And its scum has not come out of it, || By piece of it, by piece of it bring it out, a lot has not fallen on it. <verse eid="EZK 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 24:7"/>For her blood has been in her midst, || She has set it on a clear place of a rock, || She has not poured it on the earth, || To cover it over with dust. <verse eid="EZK 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 24:8"/>To cause fury to come up to take vengeance, || I have put her blood on a clear place of a rock—not to be covered. <verse eid="EZK 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 24:9"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Woe [to] the city of blood, indeed, I make the pile great. <verse eid="EZK 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 24:10"/>Make the wood abundant, || Kindle the fire, consume the flesh, || And make the compound, || And let the bones be burned. <verse eid="EZK 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 24:11"/>And cause it to stand empty on its coals, || So that its bronze is hot and burning, || Its uncleanness has been melted in its midst, || Its scum is consumed. <verse eid="EZK 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 24:12"/>She has wearied herself [with] sorrows, || And the abundance of her scum does not go out of her, || Her scum [is] in the fire. <verse eid="EZK 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 24:13"/>Wickedness [is] in your uncleanness, || Because I have cleansed you, || And you have not been cleansed, || You are not cleansed from your uncleanness again, || Until I have caused My fury to rest on you. <verse eid="EZK 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 24:14"/>I, YHWH, have spoken, || It has come, and I have done [it], || I do not free, nor do I spare, nor do I regret, || According to your ways, and according to your acts, || They have judged you, || A declaration of Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 24:15"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 24:16"/>“Son of man, behold, I am taking the desire of your eyes from you by a stroke, and you do not mourn, nor weep, nor let your tear come. <verse eid="EZK 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 24:17"/>Cease to groan [and] make no mourning [for] the dead, bind your headdress on yourself, and put your shoes on your feet, and you do not cover over the upper lip, and you do not eat [the] bread of men.” <verse eid="EZK 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 24:18"/>And I speak to the people in the morning, and my wife dies in the evening, and I do in the morning as I have been commanded. <verse eid="EZK 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 24:19"/>And the people say to me, “Do you not declare to us what these [are] to us, that you are doing?” <verse eid="EZK 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 24:20"/>And I say to them, “A word of YHWH has been to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 24:21"/>Say to the house of Israel, Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am defiling My sanctuary, || The excellence of your strength, || The desire of your eyes, and the pitied of your soul, || And your sons and your daughters whom you have left, fall by sword. <verse eid="EZK 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 24:22"/>And you have done as I have done, || You have not covered over the upper lip, || And you do not eat [the] bread of men. <verse eid="EZK 24:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 24:23"/>And your headdresses [are] on your heads, || And your shoes [are] on your feet, || You do not mourn nor do you weep, || And you have wasted away for your iniquities, || And you have howled to one another. <verse eid="EZK 24:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 24:24"/>And Ezekiel has been for a type to you; according to all that he has done you do. In its coming in—you have known that I [am] Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 24:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 24:25"/>“And you, son of man, is it not in the day of My taking from them their strength, the joy of their beauty, the desire of their eyes, and the song of their soul—their sons and their daughters? <verse eid="EZK 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 24:26"/>In that day the escaped one comes to you to cause the ears to hear. <verse eid="EZK 24:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 24:27"/>In that day your mouth is opened with the escaped and you speak, and are not silent anymore, and you have been for a type to them, and they have known that I [am] YHWH.”<verse eid="EZK 24:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="EZK 25"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 25:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 25:2"/>“Son of man, set your face toward the sons of Ammon, and prophesy against them; <verse eid="EZK 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 25:3"/>and you have said to the sons of Ammon: Hear a word of Lord YHWH! Thus said Lord YHWH: Because of your saying, Aha, to My sanctuary, || Because it has been defiled, || And to the ground of Israel, || Because it has been desolate, || And to the house of Judah, || Because they have gone into a removal: <verse eid="EZK 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 25:4"/>Therefore, behold, I am giving you to sons of the east for a possession, || And they set their towers in you, || And have placed their dwelling places in you. They eat your fruit, and they drink your milk, <verse eid="EZK 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 25:5"/>And I have given Rabbah for a habitation of camels, || And the sons of Ammon for the crouching of a flock, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 25:6"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: Because of your clapping the hand, || And of your stamping with the foot, || And you rejoice with all your despite in soul || Against the ground of Israel, <verse eid="EZK 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 25:7"/>Therefore, behold, I have stretched out My hand against you, || And have given you for a portion to nations, || And I have cut you off from the peoples, || And caused you to perish from the lands; I destroy you, and you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 25:8"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Because of the saying of Moab and Seir: Behold, the house of Judah [is] as all the nations; <verse eid="EZK 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 25:9"/>Therefore, behold, I am opening the shoulder of Moab—From the cities—from his cities—from his frontier, || The beauty of the land, Beth-Jeshimoth, Ba‘al-Meon, and Kiriathaim, <verse eid="EZK 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 25:10"/>To the sons of the east, with the sons of Ammon, || And I have given it for a possession, || So that the sons of Ammon are not remembered among nations. <verse eid="EZK 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 25:11"/>And I do judgments in Moab, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 25:12"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Because of the doings of Edom, || In taking vengeance on the house of Judah, || Indeed, they are very guilty, || And they have taken vengeance on them. <verse eid="EZK 25:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 25:13"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: I have stretched out My hand against Edom, || And I have cut off man and beast from it, || And given it up—a ruin, from Teman even to Dedan, || They fall by sword. <verse eid="EZK 25:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 25:14"/>And I have given My vengeance on Edom, || By the hand of My people Israel, || And they have done in Edom, || According to My anger, and according to My fury, || And they have known My vengeance, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 25:15"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Because of the doings of the Philistines in vengeance, || And they take vengeance with despite in soul, || Destruction [with] continuous enmity, <verse eid="EZK 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 25:16"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am stretching out My hand against the Philistines, || And I have cut off the Cherethim, || And destroyed the remnant of the haven of the sea, <verse eid="EZK 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 25:17"/>And done great vengeance on them with furious reproofs, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My giving out My vengeance on them!”<verse eid="EZK 25:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="EZK 26"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 26:1"/>And it comes to pass, in the eleventh year, on the first of the month, there has been a word of YHWH to me, saying, “Son of man, <verse eid="EZK 26:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 26:2"/>Because that Tyre has said of Jerusalem: Aha, she has been broken, || The doors of the peoples, || She has turned around to me, || I am filled—she has been laid waste, <verse eid="EZK 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 26:3"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against you, O Tyre, || And have caused many nations to come up against you, || As the sea causes its billows to come up. <verse eid="EZK 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 26:4"/>And they have destroyed the walls of Tyre, || And they have broken down her towers, || And I have scraped her dust from her, || And made her for a clear place of a rock. <verse eid="EZK 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 26:5"/>She is a spreading place of nets in the midst of the sea, || For I have spoken,” || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || “And she has been for a spoil to nations. <verse eid="EZK 26:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 26:6"/>And her daughters who [are] in the field, are slain by sword, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH,” <verse eid="EZK 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 26:7"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: “Behold, I am bringing Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon to Tyre, || From the north—a king of kings, || With horse, and with chariot, and with horsemen, || Even an assembly, and a numerous people. <verse eid="EZK 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 26:8"/>He slays your daughters in the field by sword, || And he has made a fort against you, || And has poured out a mound against you, || And has raised a buckler against you. <verse eid="EZK 26:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 26:9"/>And he places a battering-ram before him against your walls, || And he breaks your towers with his weapons. <verse eid="EZK 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 26:10"/>From the abundance of his horses their dust cover you, || From the noise of horseman, and wheel, and rider, || Your walls shake, in his coming into your gates, || As the coming into a city that has been broken-up. <verse eid="EZK 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 26:11"/>He treads all your out-places with [the] hooves of his horses, || He slays your people by sword, || And the pillars of your strength come down to the earth. <verse eid="EZK 26:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 26:12"/>And they have spoiled your wealth, || And they have plundered your merchandise, || And they have thrown down your walls, || And they break down your desirable houses, || And your stones, and your wood, and your dust, || They place in the midst of the waters. <verse eid="EZK 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 26:13"/>And I have caused the noise of your songs to cease, || And the voice of your harps is heard no more. <verse eid="EZK 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 26:14"/>And I have given you up for a clear place of a rock, || You are a spreading-place of nets, || You are not built up anymore, || For I, YHWH, have spoken,” || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 26:15"/>Thus said Lord YHWH to Tyre: “Do not—from the noise of your fall, || In the groaning of the wounded, || In the slaying of the slaughter in your midst—The islands shake? <verse eid="EZK 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 26:16"/>And all princes of the sea have come down from off their thrones, || And they have turned their robes aside, || And strip off their embroidered garments, || They put on trembling, || They sit on the earth, || And they have trembled every moment, || And they have been astonished at you, <verse eid="EZK 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 26:17"/>And have lifted up a lamentation for you, || And said to you: How you have perished, || That are inhabited from the seas, || The praised city, that was strong in the sea, || She and her inhabitants, || Who put their terror on all her inhabitants! <verse eid="EZK 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 26:18"/>Now the islands tremble [on the] day of your fall; The islands that [are] in the sea have been troubled at your outgoing.” <verse eid="EZK 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 26:19"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: “In My making you a city dried up, || Like cities that have not been inhabited, || In bringing up the deep against you, || Then the great waters have covered you. <verse eid="EZK 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 26:20"/>And I have caused you to go down, || With those going down to the pit, || To the people of old, || And I have caused you to dwell || In the lower parts of the earth—in ancient ruins, || With those going down to the pit, || So that you are not inhabited, || And I have given beauty in the land of the living. <verse eid="EZK 26:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 26:21"/>I make you a terror, and you are not, || And you are sought, and are not found anymore—for all time,” || A declaration of Lord YHWH!<verse eid="EZK 26:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="EZK 27"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 27:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 27:2"/>“And you, son of man, lift up a lamentation concerning Tyre, and you have said to Tyre: <verse eid="EZK 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 27:3"/>O dweller on the entrances of the sea, || Merchant of the peoples to many islands, Thus said Lord YHWH: O Tyre, you have said, || I [am] the perfection of beauty. <verse eid="EZK 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 27:4"/>Your borders [are] in the heart of the seas, || Your builders have perfected your beauty. <verse eid="EZK 27:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 27:5"/>They have built of firs from Senir all your double-boarded ships for you, || They have taken of cedars from Lebanon to make a mast for you, <verse eid="EZK 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 27:6"/>They made your oars of oaks from Bashan, || They have made your bench of ivory, || A branch of Ashurim from islands of Chittim. <verse eid="EZK 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 27:7"/>Your sail has been of fine linen with embroidery from Egypt, || To be for your ensign, || Your covering has been of blue and purple from islands of Elishah. <verse eid="EZK 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 27:8"/>Inhabitants of Sidon and Arvad have been rowers for you, || Your wise men, O Tyre, have been in you, || They [are] your pilots. <verse eid="EZK 27:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 27:9"/>The elderly of Gebal and its wise men have been in you, || Strengthening your breach; All ships of the sea and their mariners, || Have been in you, to trade your merchandise. <verse eid="EZK 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 27:10"/>Persia and Lud and Phut || Have been in your forces—your men of war. They hung up shield and helmet in you, || They have given out your honor. <verse eid="EZK 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 27:11"/>The sons of Arvad, and your force, || [Are] on your walls all around, || And short swordsmen have been in your towers, || They have hung up their shields on your walls all around, || They have perfected your beauty. <verse eid="EZK 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 27:12"/>Tarshish [is] your merchant, || Because of the abundance of all wealth, || They have given silver, iron, tin, and lead [for] your wares. <verse eid="EZK 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 27:13"/>Javan, Tubal, and Meshech—they [are] your merchants, || They have given [the] soul of man, and vessels of bronze, [for] your merchandise. <verse eid="EZK 27:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 27:14"/>Those of the house of Togarmah, || They have given horses, and riding steeds, and mules [for] your wares. <verse eid="EZK 27:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 27:15"/>Sons of Dedan [are] your merchants, || Many islands [are] the market of your hand, || They sent back horns of ivory and ebony [for] your reward. <verse eid="EZK 27:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 27:16"/>Aram [is] your merchant, || Because of the abundance of your works, || They have given emerald, purple, and embroidery, || And fine linen, and coral, and agate for your wares. <verse eid="EZK 27:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 27:17"/>Judah and the land of Israel—they [are] your merchants, || They have given wheat of Minnith, and Pannag, || And honey, and oil, and balm [for] your merchandise. <verse eid="EZK 27:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 27:18"/>Damascus [is] your merchant, || For the abundance of your works, || Because of the abundance of all wealth, || For wine of Helbon, and white wool. <verse eid="EZK 27:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 27:19"/>Dan and Javan go about with your wares, || They have given shining iron, cassia, and cane, || It has been in your merchandise. <verse eid="EZK 27:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 27:20"/>Dedan [is] your merchant, || For clothes of freedom for riding. <verse eid="EZK 27:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 27:21"/>Arabia, and all princes of Kedar, || They [are] the traders of your hand, || For lambs, and rams, and male goats, || In these your merchants. <verse eid="EZK 27:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 27:22"/>Merchants of Sheba and Raamah—they [are] your merchants, || They have given the chief of all spices, || And every precious stone, and gold [for] your wares. <verse eid="EZK 27:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 27:23"/>Haran, and Canneh, and Eden, merchants of Sheba, Asshur—Chilmad—[are] your merchants, <verse eid="EZK 27:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 27:24"/>They [are] your merchants for perfect things, || For wrappings of blue, and embroidery, || And for treasuries of rich apparel, || With cords bound and girded, for your merchandise, <verse eid="EZK 27:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 27:25"/>Ships of Tarshish are journeying [with] your merchandise for you, || And you are filled and honored greatly, || In the heart of the seas. <verse eid="EZK 27:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 27:26"/>Those rowing you have brought you into great waters, || The east wind has broken you in the heart of the seas. <verse eid="EZK 27:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 27:27"/>Your wealth and your wares, || Your merchandise, your mariners, || And your pilots, strengtheners of your breach, || And the traders of your merchandise, || And all your men of war, who [are] in you, || And in all your assembly that [is] in your midst, || Fall into the heart of the seas in the day of your fall, <verse eid="EZK 27:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 27:28"/>At the voice of the cry of your pilots the outskirts shake. <verse eid="EZK 27:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 27:29"/>And all handling an oar come down from their ships, || Mariners [and] all the pilots of the sea stand on the land, <verse eid="EZK 27:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 27:30"/>And have sounded with their voice for you, || And cry bitterly, and cause dust to go up on their heads, || They roll themselves in ashes; <verse eid="EZK 27:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 27:31"/>And they have made themselves bald for you, || And they have girded on sackcloth, || And they have wept for you, || In bitterness of soul—a bitter mourning. <verse eid="EZK 27:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 27:32"/>And their sons have lifted up a lamentation for you, || And they have lamented over you, Who [is] as Tyre? As the cut-off one in the midst of the sea? <verse eid="EZK 27:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EZK 27:33"/>With the outgoing of your wares from the seas, || You have filled many peoples, || With the abundance of your riches, and your merchandise, || You have enriched [the] kings of earth. <verse eid="EZK 27:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EZK 27:34"/>At the time of [your] being broken by the seas in the depths of the waters, || Your merchandise and all your assembly have fallen in your midst. <verse eid="EZK 27:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EZK 27:35"/>All inhabitants of the islands have been astonished at you, || And their kings have been severely afraid, || They have been troubled in countenance. <verse eid="EZK 27:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EZK 27:36"/>Merchants among the peoples have shrieked for you, || You have been terrors, and you are not—for all time!”<verse eid="EZK 27:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="EZK 28"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 28:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 28:2"/>“Son of man, say to the leader of Tyre, Thus said Lord YHWH: Because your heart has been high, || And you say: I [am] a god, || I have inhabited the habitation of God, || In the heart of the seas, || And you [are] man, and not God, || And you give out your heart as the heart of God, <verse eid="EZK 28:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 28:3"/>Behold, you [are] wiser than Daniel, || No hidden thing have they concealed from you. <verse eid="EZK 28:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 28:4"/>By your wisdom and by your understanding || You have made wealth for yourself, || And make gold and silver in your treasuries. <verse eid="EZK 28:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 28:5"/>By the abundance of your wisdom, || Through your merchandise, || You have multiplied your wealth, || And your heart is high through your wealth. <verse eid="EZK 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 28:6"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Because of your giving out your heart as the heart of God, <verse eid="EZK 28:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 28:7"/>Therefore, behold, I am bringing in strangers against you, || The terrible of the nations, || And they have drawn out their swords || Against the beauty of your wisdom, || And they have pierced your brightness. <verse eid="EZK 28:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 28:8"/>They bring you down to destruction, || You die by the deaths of the wounded, in the heart of the seas. <verse eid="EZK 28:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 28:9"/>Do you really say, I [am] God, || Before him who is slaying you? And you [are] man, and not God, || In the hand of him who is piercing you. <verse eid="EZK 28:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 28:10"/>You die the deaths of the uncircumcised, || By the hand of strangers, for I have spoken,” || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 28:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 28:11"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 28:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 28:12"/>“Son of man, lift up a lamentation for the king of Tyre, || And you have said to him, Thus said Lord YHWH: You are sealing up a measurement, || Full of wisdom, and perfect in beauty. <verse eid="EZK 28:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 28:13"/>You have been in Eden, the garden of God, || Every precious stone [was] your covering, || Ruby, topaz, and diamond, beryl, onyx, and jasper, || Sapphire, emerald, and carbuncle, and gold, || The workmanship of your tambourines and of your pipes, || In you in the day of your being produced, have been created; <verse eid="EZK 28:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 28:14"/>And I established you as the anointed, covering cherub, || You have been in [the] holy mountain of God, || You have walked up and down in [the] midst of [the] stones of fire. <verse eid="EZK 28:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 28:15"/>You [were] perfect in your ways, || From [the] day of your being created, || Until perversity was found in you. <verse eid="EZK 28:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 28:16"/>By [the] abundance of your merchandise || They have filled your midst with violence, || And you sin, || And I thrust you from [the] mountain of God, || And I destroy you, O covering cherub, || From [the] midst of [the] stones of fire. <verse eid="EZK 28:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 28:17"/>Your heart has been high because of your beauty, || You have corrupted your wisdom because of your brightness, || I have cast you to earth, || I have set you before kings, to look on you, <verse eid="EZK 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 28:18"/>From [the] abundance of your iniquity, || By [the] perversity of your merchandise, || You have defiled your sanctuaries, || And I bring forth fire from your midst, || It has devoured you, || And I make you become ashes on the earth, || In [the] eyes of all beholding you. <verse eid="EZK 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 28:19"/>All knowing you among the peoples || Have been astonished at you, || You have been terrors, and you are not—for all time.” <verse eid="EZK 28:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 28:20"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 28:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 28:21"/>“Son of man, set your face toward Sidon, and prophesy concerning it; <verse eid="EZK 28:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 28:22"/>and you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against you, O Sidon, || And I have been honored in your midst, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My doing judgments in her, || And I have been sanctified in her. <verse eid="EZK 28:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 28:23"/>And I have sent pestilence into her, || And blood into her out-places, || The wounded has been judged in her midst, || By the sword on her all around, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 28:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 28:24"/>And there is no more pricking brier and paining thorn || For the house of Israel, || Of all around them—despising them, || And they have known that I [am] Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 28:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 28:25"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: In My gathering the house of Israel, || Out of the peoples among whom they were scattered, || I have been sanctified in them, || Before the eyes of the nations, || And they have dwelt on their ground, || That I gave to My servant, to Jacob, <verse eid="EZK 28:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 28:26"/>And they have dwelt confidently on it, || And built houses, and planted vineyards, || And dwelt confidently—in My doing judgments, || On all those despising them all around, || And they have known that I [am] their God YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 28:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="EZK 29"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 29:1"/>In the tenth year, in the tenth [month], on the twelfth of the month, a word of YHWH has been to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 29:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 29:2"/>“Son of man, set your face against Pharaoh king of Egypt, and prophesy concerning him, and concerning Egypt—all of it. <verse eid="EZK 29:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 29:3"/>Speak, and you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against you, || Pharaoh king of Egypt! The great dragon that is crouching in the midst of his floods, || Who has said, My flood [is] my own, || And I have made it [for] myself. <verse eid="EZK 29:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 29:4"/>And I have put hooks in your jaws, || And I have caused the fish of your floods to cleave to your scales, || And I have caused you to come up from the midst of your floods, || And every fish of your floods cleaves to your scales. <verse eid="EZK 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 29:5"/>And I have left you in the wilderness, || You and every fish of your floods, || You fall on the face of the field, || You are not gathered nor assembled, || I have given you for food to the beast of the earth and to the bird of the heavens. <verse eid="EZK 29:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 29:6"/>And all inhabitants of Egypt have known || That I [am] YHWH, || Because of their being a staff of reed to the house of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 29:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 29:7"/>In their taking hold of you by your hand, || You crush and have torn every shoulder of theirs, || And in their leaning on you you are broken, || And have caused all their thighs to stand. <verse eid="EZK 29:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 29:8"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am bringing in a sword against you, || And have cut off man and beast from you. <verse eid="EZK 29:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 29:9"/>And the land of Egypt has been for a desolation and a ruin, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH, || Because he said: The flood [is] mine, and I made [it]. <verse eid="EZK 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 29:10"/>Therefore, behold, I [am] against you, and against your floods, || And have given the land of Egypt for ruins, || A dry place, a desolation, from Migdol to Syene, || And to the border of Cush. <verse eid="EZK 29:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 29:11"/>A foot of man does not pass over into it, || Indeed, the foot of beast does not pass into it, || Nor is it inhabited forty years. <verse eid="EZK 29:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 29:12"/>And I have made the land of Egypt a desolation, || In the midst of desolate lands, || And its cities, in the midst of cities [that are] laid waste, || Are a desolation [for] forty years, || And I have scattered the Egyptians among nations, || And I have dispersed them through lands. <verse eid="EZK 29:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 29:13"/>But thus said Lord YHWH: At the end of forty years I gather the Egyptians || Out of the peoples to where they have been scattered, <verse eid="EZK 29:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 29:14"/>And I have turned back [to] the captivity of Egypt, || And I have brought them back || [To] the land of Pathros, to the land of their birth, || And they have been a low kingdom there. <verse eid="EZK 29:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 29:15"/>It is lowest of the kingdoms, || And it does not lift itself up above the nations anymore, || And I have made them few, || So as not to rule among nations. <verse eid="EZK 29:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 29:16"/>And it is no longer for confidence to the house of Israel, || Bringing iniquity to remembrance, || By their turning after them, || And they have known that I [am] Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 29:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 29:17"/>And it comes to pass, in the twenty-seventh year, in the first [month], on the first of the month, a word of YHWH has been to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 29:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 29:18"/>“Son of man, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, || Has caused his force to serve a great service against Tyre, || Every head [is] bald—every shoulder peeled, || And neither he, nor his force, had reward out of Tyre, || For the service that he served against it. <verse eid="EZK 29:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 29:19"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am giving the land of Egypt to Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, || And he has taken away its store, || And has taken its spoil, and taken its prey, || And it has been a reward to his force. <verse eid="EZK 29:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 29:20"/>I have given to him his wage for which he labored—The land of Egypt, in that they worked for Me, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 29:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 29:21"/>In that day I cause a horn to shoot up for the house of Israel, || And I give an opening to your mouth in their midst, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 29:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="EZK 30"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 30:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 30:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 30:2"/>“Son of man, prophesy, and you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH: Howl, Aah! For the day! <verse eid="EZK 30:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 30:3"/>For a day [is] near, a day [is] near to YHWH! It is a time of cloud [over] the nations. <verse eid="EZK 30:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 30:4"/>And a sword has come into Egypt, || And there has been great pain in Cush, || In the falling of the wounded in Egypt, || And they have taken its store, || And its foundations have been broken down. <verse eid="EZK 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 30:5"/>Cush, and Phut, and Lud, and all the mixture, and Chub, || And the sons of the land of the covenant fall by sword with them, <verse eid="EZK 30:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 30:6"/>Thus said YHWH: And those supporting Egypt have fallen, || And the arrogance of her strength has come down, || From Migdol to Syene, they fall by sword in her, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 30:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 30:7"/>And they have been desolated in the midst of desolate lands, || And its cities are in the midst of cities [that are] laid waste. <verse eid="EZK 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 30:8"/>And they have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My giving fire against Egypt, || And all her helpers have been broken. <verse eid="EZK 30:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 30:9"/>In that day messengers go forth from before Me in ships, || To trouble confident Cush, || And there has been great pain among them, || As the day of Egypt, for behold, it has come. <verse eid="EZK 30:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 30:10"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: I have caused the multitude of Egypt to cease, || By the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, <verse eid="EZK 30:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 30:11"/>He and his people with him—the terrible of nations, || Are brought in to destroy the land, || And they have drawn their swords against Egypt, || And have filled the land [with] the wounded. <verse eid="EZK 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 30:12"/>And I have made floods a dry place, || And I have sold the land into the hand of evildoers, || And I have made the land desolate, || And its fullness, by the hand of strangers, || I, YHWH, have spoken. <verse eid="EZK 30:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 30:13"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: And I have destroyed idols, || And caused vain things to cease from Noph, || And there is no longer a prince of the land of Egypt, || And I give fear in the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EZK 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 30:14"/>And I have made Pathros desolate, || And I have given fire against Zoan, || And I have done judgments in No, <verse eid="EZK 30:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 30:15"/>And I have poured out My fury on Sin, the stronghold of Egypt, || And I have cut off the multitude of No. <verse eid="EZK 30:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 30:16"/>And I have given fire against Egypt, || Sin is greatly pained, and No is to be broken, || And Noph has daily distresses. <verse eid="EZK 30:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 30:17"/>The youths of Aven and Pi-Beseth fall by sword, || And these go into captivity. <verse eid="EZK 30:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 30:18"/>And the day has been dark in Tehaphnehes, || In My breaking the yokes of Egypt there, || And the excellence of her strength has ceased in her, || Her! A cloud covers her, || And her daughters go into captivity. <verse eid="EZK 30:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 30:19"/>And I have done judgments in Egypt, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 30:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 30:20"/>And it comes to pass, in the eleventh year, in the first [month], on the seventh of the month, a word of YHWH has been to me, saying, “Son of man, <verse eid="EZK 30:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 30:21"/>I have broken the arm of Pharaoh, king of Egypt, || And behold, it has not been bound up to give healing, || To put a bandage to bind it, || To strengthen it—to lay hold on the sword. <verse eid="EZK 30:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 30:22"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against Pharaoh, king of Egypt, || And I have broken his arms, || The strong one and the broken one, || And have caused the sword to fall out of his hand, <verse eid="EZK 30:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 30:23"/>And I have scattered the Egyptians among nations, || And have spread them through lands, <verse eid="EZK 30:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 30:24"/>And I have strengthened the arms of the king of Babylon, || And have given My sword into his hand, || And I have broken the arms of Pharaoh, || And he has groaned the groans of a pierced one—before him. <verse eid="EZK 30:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 30:25"/>And I have strengthened the arms of the king of Babylon, || And the arms of Pharaoh fall down, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My giving My sword into the hand of the king of Babylon, || And he has stretched it out toward the land of Egypt. <verse eid="EZK 30:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 30:26"/>And I have scattered the Egyptians among nations, || And I have spread them through lands, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 30:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="EZK 31"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 31:1"/>And it comes to pass, in the eleventh year, in the third [month], on the first of the month, a word of YHWH has been to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 31:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 31:2"/>“Son of man, say to Pharaoh king of Egypt, and to his multitude: To whom have you been like in your greatness? <verse eid="EZK 31:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 31:3"/>Behold, Asshur, a cedar in Lebanon, || Beautiful in branch, and shading bough, and high in stature, || And its foliage has been between thickets. <verse eid="EZK 31:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 31:4"/>Waters have made it great, || The deep has exalted him with its flowings, || Going around its planting, || And it has sent forth its conduits to all trees of the field. <verse eid="EZK 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 31:5"/>Therefore his stature has been higher than all trees of the field, || And his boughs are multiplied, and his branches are long, || Because of many waters in his shooting forth. <verse eid="EZK 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 31:6"/>Every bird of the heavens has made a nest in his boughs, || And every beast of the field has brought forth under his branches, || And all great nations dwell in his shade. <verse eid="EZK 31:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 31:7"/>And he is beautiful in his greatness, || In the length of his thin shoots, || For his root has been by great waters. <verse eid="EZK 31:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 31:8"/>Cedars have not hid him in the garden of God, || Firs have not been like to his boughs, || And plane-trees have not been as his branches, || No tree in the garden of God has been like to him in his beauty, <verse eid="EZK 31:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 31:9"/>I have made him beautiful in the multitude of his thin shoots, || And all trees of Eden that [are] in the garden of God envy him. <verse eid="EZK 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 31:10"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Because that you have been high in stature, || And he yields his foliage between thickets, || And his heart is high in his haughtiness, <verse eid="EZK 31:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 31:11"/>I give him into the hand of a god of nations, || He deals severely with him, || In his wickedness I have cast him out. <verse eid="EZK 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 31:12"/>And strangers cut him off, || The terrible of nations, and they leave him, || His thin shoots have fallen on the mountains and in all valleys, || And his boughs are broken at all streams of the land, || And all peoples of the land go down from his shade, and they leave him. <verse eid="EZK 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 31:13"/>Every bird of the heavens dwells on his ruin, || And all beasts of the field have been on his boughs, <verse eid="EZK 31:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 31:14"/>In order that none of the trees of the waters || May become haughty because of their stature, || Nor give their foliage between thickets, || Nor any drinking waters stand up to them in their haughtiness, || For all of them are given up to death, || To the lower earth, || In the midst of the sons of men, || To those going down to the pit. <verse eid="EZK 31:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 31:15"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: I have caused mourning in the day of his going down to Sheol, || I have covered the deep over him, and diminish its flowings, || And many waters are restrained, || And I make Lebanon black for him, || And all trees of the field [have been] a covering for him. <verse eid="EZK 31:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 31:16"/>I have caused nations to shake at the sound of his fall, || In My causing him to go down to Sheol, || With those going down to the pit, || And all trees of Eden are comforted in the lower earth, || The choice and good of Lebanon—All drinking waters. <verse eid="EZK 31:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 31:17"/>Those with him have also gone down to Sheol, || To the pierced of the sword, || And—his arm—they dwelt in his shade in the midst of nations. <verse eid="EZK 31:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 31:18"/>To whom have you been thus like, || In glory and in greatness among the trees of Eden? And you have been brought down with the trees of Eden, || To the lower earth, || You lie in the midst of the uncircumcised, || With the pierced of the sword. This [is] Pharaoh, and all his multitude, || A declaration of Lord YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 31:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 31"/>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="EZK 32"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 32:1"/>And it comes to pass, in the twelfth year, in the twelfth month, on the first of the month, a word of YHWH has been to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 32:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 32:2"/>“Son of man, lift up a lamentation for Pharaoh king of Egypt, and you have said to him: You have been like a young lion of nations, || And you [are] as a dragon in the seas, || And you come forth with your flowings, || And trouble the waters with your feet, || And you foul their flowings. <verse eid="EZK 32:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 32:3"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: And I have spread out My net for you, || With an assembly of many peoples, || And they have brought you up in My net. <verse eid="EZK 32:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 32:4"/>And I have left you in the land, || I cast you out on the face of the field, || And I have caused every bird of the heavens to dwell on you, || And have satisfied every beast of the earth with you. <verse eid="EZK 32:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 32:5"/>And I have put your flesh on the mountains, || And filled the valleys [with] your heap, <verse eid="EZK 32:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 32:6"/>And watered the land with your flowing, || From your blood—to the mountains, || And streams are filled with you. <verse eid="EZK 32:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 32:7"/>And in quenching you I have covered the heavens, || And have made their stars black, || I cover the sun with a cloud, || And the moon does not cause its light to shine. <verse eid="EZK 32:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 32:8"/>I make all luminaries of light in the heavens black over you, || And I have given darkness over your land, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, <verse eid="EZK 32:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 32:9"/>And I have distressed the heart of many peoples, || In My bringing in your destruction among nations, || To lands that you have not known. <verse eid="EZK 32:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 32:10"/>And I have made many peoples astonished at you, || And their kings are afraid because of you with trembling, || In My brandishing My sword before their faces, || And they have trembled every moment, || Each for his life—in the day of your fall. <verse eid="EZK 32:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 32:11"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: A sword of the king of Babylon enters you, <verse eid="EZK 32:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 32:12"/>I cause your multitude to fall by swords of the mighty, || The terrible of nations—all of them, || And they have spoiled the excellence of Egypt, || And all her multitude has been destroyed. <verse eid="EZK 32:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 32:13"/>And I have destroyed all her beasts, || From beside many waters, || And a foot of man does not trouble them anymore, || Indeed, the hooves of beasts do not trouble them. <verse eid="EZK 32:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 32:14"/>Then I cause their waters to sink, || And I cause their rivers to go as oil, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 32:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 32:15"/>In My making the land of Egypt a desolation, || And the land has been desolated of its fullness, || In My striking all the inhabitants in it, || Then they have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 32:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 32:16"/>It [is] a lamentation, and they have lamented her, || Daughters of the nations lament her, || For Egypt, and for all her multitude, they lament her, || A declaration of Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 32:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 32:17"/>And it comes to pass, in the twelfth year, on the fifteenth of the month, a word of YHWH has been to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 32:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 32:18"/>“Son of man, || Wail for the multitude of Egypt, || And cause it to go down, || It, and the daughters of majestic nations, || To the lower parts of the earth, || With those going down to the pit. <verse eid="EZK 32:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 32:19"/>Whom have you surpassed in beauty? Go down, and be laid with [the] uncircumcised. <verse eid="EZK 32:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 32:20"/>They fall in the midst of the pierced of the sword, || She has been given [to] the sword, || They drew her out, and all her multitude. <verse eid="EZK 32:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 32:21"/>The gods of the mighty speak to him out of the midst of Sheol, || With his helpers—they have gone down, || They have lain with the uncircumcised, || The pierced of the sword. <verse eid="EZK 32:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 32:22"/>There [is] Asshur, and all her assembly, || His graves [are] around him, || All of them [are] wounded, who are falling by sword, <verse eid="EZK 32:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 32:23"/>Whose graves are appointed in the sides of the pit, || And her assembly is around her grave, || All of them wounded, falling by sword, || Because they gave terror in the land of the living. <verse eid="EZK 32:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 32:24"/>There [is] Elam, and all her multitude, || Around her grave, || All of them wounded, who are falling by sword, || Who have gone down uncircumcised to the lower parts of the earth, || Because they gave their terror in the land of the living, || And they bear their shame with those going down to the pit. <verse eid="EZK 32:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 32:25"/>They have appointed a bed for her in the midst of the wounded, || With all her multitude, || Her graves [are] around them, || All of them uncircumcised, pierced of the sword, || For their terror was given in the land of the living, || And they bear their shame with those going down to the pit, || He has been set in the midst of the pierced. <verse eid="EZK 32:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 32:26"/>There [is] Meshech, Tubal, and all her multitude, || Her graves [are] around them, || All of them uncircumcised, pierced by the sword, || For they gave their terror in the land of the living, <verse eid="EZK 32:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 32:27"/>And they do not lie with the mighty, || Who are falling of the uncircumcised, || Who have gone down to Sheol with their weapons of war, || And they put their swords under their heads, || And their iniquities are on their bones, || For the terror of the mighty [is] in the land of the living. <verse eid="EZK 32:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 32:28"/>And you are broken in the midst of the uncircumcised, || And lie with the pierced of the sword. <verse eid="EZK 32:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 32:29"/>There [is] Edom, her kings, and all her princes, || Who have been given up in their might, || With the pierced of the sword, || They lie with the uncircumcised, || And with those going down to the pit. <verse eid="EZK 32:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 32:30"/>There [are] princes of the north, || All of them, and every Zidonian, || Who have gone down with the pierced in their terror, || They are ashamed of their might, || And they lie uncircumcised with the pierced of the sword, || And they bear their shame with those going down to the pit. <verse eid="EZK 32:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 32:31"/>Then Pharaoh sees, || And he has been comforted for all his multitude, || The pierced of the sword—Pharaoh and all his force, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 32:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 32:32"/>For I have given his terror in the land of the living, || And he has been laid down in [the] midst of [the] uncircumcised, || With [the] pierced of [the] sword—Pharaoh, and all his multitude, || A declaration of Lord YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 32:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 32"/>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="EZK 33"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 33:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 33:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 33:2"/>“Son of man, speak to the sons of your people, and you have said to them: When I bring a sword on a land, || And the people of the land have taken one man out of their borders, || And made him their watchman, <verse eid="EZK 33:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 33:3"/>And he has seen the sword coming against the land, || And has blown with a horn, and has warned the people, <verse eid="EZK 33:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 33:4"/>And the hearer has heard the voice of the horn, and he has not taken warning, || And the sword comes in, and takes him away, || His blood is on his [own] head. <verse eid="EZK 33:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 33:5"/>The voice of the horn he heard, || And he has not taken warning, his blood is on him, || And he who took warning has delivered his soul. <verse eid="EZK 33:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 33:6"/>And the watchman, when he sees the sword coming in, || And he has not blown with a horn, || And the people have not been warned, || And a sword comes in, || And takes away a soul from them, || He is taken away in his iniquity, || And I require his blood from the hand of the watchman. <verse eid="EZK 33:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 33:7"/>And you, son of man, || I gave you [as] a watchman for the house of Israel, || And you have heard a word from My mouth, || And you have warned them from Me. <verse eid="EZK 33:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 33:8"/>In My saying to the wicked, O wicked one—you surely die, || And you have not spoken to warn the wicked from his way, || He—the wicked—dies in his iniquity, || And I require his blood from your hand. <verse eid="EZK 33:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 33:9"/>And you, when you have warned the wicked of his way, to turn back from it, || And he has not turned back from his way, || He dies in his iniquity, || And you have delivered your soul. <verse eid="EZK 33:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 33:10"/>And you, son of man, say to the house of Israel: You have spoken correctly, saying, || Surely our transgressions and our sins [are] on us, || And we are wasting away in them, || How, then, do we live? <verse eid="EZK 33:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 33:11"/>Say to them, [As] I live—a declaration of Lord YHWH, || I do not delight in the death of the wicked, || But in the turning of the wicked from his way, and he has lived. Turn back, turn back, from your evil ways! Indeed, why do you die, O house of Israel? <verse eid="EZK 33:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 33:12"/>And you, son of man, say to the sons of your people: The righteousness of the righteous does not deliver him in the day of his transgression, || And the wickedness of the wicked, || He does not stumble for it in the day of his turning from his wickedness, || And the righteous is not able to live in it in the day of his sinning. <verse eid="EZK 33:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 33:13"/>In My saying of the righteous: He surely lives, || And—he has trusted on his righteousness, || And he has done perversity, || All his righteous acts are not remembered, || And for his perversity that he has done, || He dies for it. <verse eid="EZK 33:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 33:14"/>And in My saying to the wicked: You surely die, || And—he has turned back from his sin, || And has done judgment and righteousness, <verse eid="EZK 33:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 33:15"/>(The wicked restores a pledge, he repays [for] plunder), || He has walked in the statutes of life, || So as not to do perversity, || He surely lives—he does not die. <verse eid="EZK 33:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 33:16"/>All his sin—his sins that he has sinned—are not remembered against him, || He has done judgment and righteousness, || He surely lives. <verse eid="EZK 33:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 33:17"/>And the sons of your people have said: The way of the Lord is not pondered, || As for them—their way is not pondered. <verse eid="EZK 33:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 33:18"/>In the turning back of the righteous from his righteousness, || And he has done perversity—he dies for it. <verse eid="EZK 33:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 33:19"/>And in the turning back of the wicked from his wickedness, || And he has done judgment and righteousness—he lives by them. <verse eid="EZK 33:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 33:20"/>And you have said, The way of the Lord is not pondered; I judge each of you according to his ways, O house of Israel.” <verse eid="EZK 33:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 33:21"/>And it comes to pass, in the twelfth year—in the tenth [month], in the fifth of the month—of our removal, one who is escaped from Jerusalem comes to me, saying, “The city has been struck.” <verse eid="EZK 33:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 33:22"/>And the hand of YHWH has been to me in the evening, before the coming in of the escaped one, and He opens my mouth until [his] coming to me in the morning, and my mouth is opened, and I have not been silent again. <verse eid="EZK 33:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 33:23"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 33:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 33:24"/>“Son of man, the inhabitants of these ruins on the ground of Israel are speaking, saying, Abraham has been alone—and he possesses the land, and we [are] many—the land has been given to us for a possession. <verse eid="EZK 33:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 33:25"/>Therefore say to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: You eat with the blood, || And you lift up your eyes to your idols, || And you shed blood, || Should you then inherit the land? <verse eid="EZK 33:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 33:26"/>You have stood on your sword, || You have done abomination, || You have each defiled the wife of his neighbor, || Should you then possess the land? <verse eid="EZK 33:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 33:27"/>Thus you say to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: [As] I live—do they who [are] in the ruins not fall by the sword? And they who [are] on the face of the field, || I have given for food to the beast, || And they who are in strongholds and in caves die by pestilence. <verse eid="EZK 33:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 33:28"/>And I have made the land a desolation and an astonishment, || And the excellence of its strength has ceased, || And mountains of Israel have been desolated, || Without anyone passing through. <verse eid="EZK 33:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 33:29"/>And they have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My making the land a desolation and an astonishment, || For all their abominations that they have done. <verse eid="EZK 33:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 33:30"/>And you, son of man, || The sons of your people who are speaking about you, || By the walls, and in openings of the houses, || Have spoken with one another, each with his brother, || Saying, Please come in, || And hear what the word [is] that comes out from YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 33:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 33:31"/>And they come in to you as the coming in of a people, || And they sit before you—My people, || And have heard your words, and they do not do them, || For they are making unhealthy loves with their mouth, || Their heart is going after their dishonest gain. <verse eid="EZK 33:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 33:32"/>And behold, you [are] as a singer of unhealthy loves to them, || A beautiful voice, and playing well on an instrument, || And they have heard your words, and they are not doing them. <verse eid="EZK 33:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EZK 33:33"/>And in its coming in—behold, it has come, || And they have known that a prophet has been in their midst!”<verse eid="EZK 33:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 33"/>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="EZK 34"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 34:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 34:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 34:2"/>“Son of man, prophesy concerning shepherds of Israel, prophesy, and you have said to them, Thus said Lord YHWH to the shepherds: Woe [to] the shepherds of Israel, || Who have been feeding themselves! Do the shepherds not feed the flock? <verse eid="EZK 34:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 34:3"/>You eat the fat, and you put on the wool, || You slaughter the fed one, || You do not feed the flock. <verse eid="EZK 34:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 34:4"/>You have not strengthened the weak, || And you have not healed the sick one, || And you have not bound up the broken, || And have not brought back the driven away, || And you have not sought the lost, || And you have ruled them with might and with rigor. <verse eid="EZK 34:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 34:5"/>And they are scattered from want of a shepherd, || And are for food to every beast of the field, || Indeed, they are scattered. <verse eid="EZK 34:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 34:6"/>My flock goes astray on all the mountains, || And on every high hill, || And My flock has been scattered on [the] whole face of the earth, || And there is none inquiring, and none seeking. <verse eid="EZK 34:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 34:7"/>Therefore, shepherds, hear a word of YHWH: <verse eid="EZK 34:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 34:8"/>[As] I live—a declaration of Lord YHWH, || If not, because of My flock being for a prey, || Indeed, My flock is for food to every beast of the field, || Because there is no shepherd, || And My shepherds have not sought My flock, || And the shepherds feed themselves, || And they have not fed My flock. <verse eid="EZK 34:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 34:9"/>Therefore, O shepherds, hear a word of YHWH! <verse eid="EZK 34:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 34:10"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against the shepherds, || And have required My flock from their hand, || And caused them to cease from feeding the flock, || And the shepherds feed themselves no more, || And I have delivered My flock from their mouth, || And they are not for food to them. <verse eid="EZK 34:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 34:11"/>For thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I—even I, have required My flock, || And I have sought it out. <verse eid="EZK 34:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 34:12"/>As a shepherd’s searching of his drove, || In the day of his being in the midst of his scattered flock, so I seek My flock, || And have delivered them out of all places, || To where they have been scattered, || In a day of cloud and thick darkness. <verse eid="EZK 34:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 34:13"/>And I have brought them out from the peoples, || And have gathered them from the lands, || And brought them to their own ground, || And have fed them on mountains of Israel, || By streams, and by all dwellings of the land. <verse eid="EZK 34:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 34:14"/>I feed them with good pasture, || And their habitation is on mountains of the high place of Israel, || There they lie down in a good habitation, || And they enjoy fat pastures on mountains of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 34:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 34:15"/>I feed My flock, and cause them to lie down, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 34:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 34:16"/>I seek the lost, and bring back the driven away, || And I bind up the broken, and I strengthen the sick, || And I destroy the fat and the strong, || I feed it with judgment. <verse eid="EZK 34:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 34:17"/>And you, My flock, thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am judging between sheep and sheep, || Between rams and male goats. <verse eid="EZK 34:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 34:18"/>Is it a little thing for you—[that] you enjoy the good pasture, || And tread down the remnant of your pasture with your feet, || And drink a depth of waters, || And trample the remainder with your feet, <verse eid="EZK 34:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 34:19"/>And My flock consumes the trodden thing of your feet, || And drinks the trampled thing of your feet? <verse eid="EZK 34:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 34:20"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH to them: Behold, I—even I, have judged between fat sheep and lean sheep. <verse eid="EZK 34:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 34:21"/>Because you thrust away with side and with shoulder, || And push all the diseased with your horns, || Until you have scattered them to the out-place, <verse eid="EZK 34:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 34:22"/>Therefore I have given safety to My flock, || And they are not for prey anymore, || And I have judged between sheep and sheep. <verse eid="EZK 34:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 34:23"/>And have raised up one shepherd over them, || And he has fed them—My servant David, || He feeds them, and he is their shepherd, <verse eid="EZK 34:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 34:24"/>And I, YHWH, I am their God, || And My servant David [is] prince in their midst, || I, YHWH, have spoken. <verse eid="EZK 34:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 34:25"/>And I have made a covenant of peace with them, || And caused evil beasts to cease out of the land, || And they have dwelt confidently in a wilderness, || And they have slept in forests. <verse eid="EZK 34:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 34:26"/>And I have given them, and the outskirts of My hill, a blessing, || And caused the shower to come down in its season, || They are showers of blessing. <verse eid="EZK 34:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 34:27"/>And the tree of the field has given its fruit, || And the land gives her increase, || And they have been confident on their land, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My breaking the bands of their yoke, || And I have delivered them from the hand of those laying service on them. <verse eid="EZK 34:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 34:28"/>And they are no longer a prey to nations, || And the beast of the earth does not devour them, || And they have dwelt confidently, || And there is none troubling. <verse eid="EZK 34:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 34:29"/>And I have raised a plantation of renown for them, || And they are no longer consumed by hunger in the land, || And they no longer bear the shame of the nations. <verse eid="EZK 34:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 34:30"/>And they have known that I, YHWH, their God, [am] with them, || And they—the house of Israel—My people, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 34:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 34:31"/>And you, My flock, the flock of My pasture, || You [are] men [and] I [am] your God, || A declaration of Lord YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 34:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 34"/>
  <chapter number="35" style="c" sid="EZK 35"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 35:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 35:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 35:2"/>“Son of man, set your face against Mount Seir, and prophesy against it, <verse eid="EZK 35:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 35:3"/>and you have said to it, Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against you, O Mount Seir, || And have stretched out My hand against you, || And made you a desolation and an astonishment. <verse eid="EZK 35:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 35:4"/>I make your cities a ruin, and you are a desolation, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 35:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 35:5"/>Because of your having continuous enmity, || And you saw the sons of Israel, || By the hands of the sword, || In the time of their calamity, || In the time of the iniquity of the end: <verse eid="EZK 35:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 35:6"/>Therefore, [as] I live—a declaration of Lord YHWH, || Surely I appoint you for blood, || And blood pursues you, || If you have not hated blood, || Blood also pursues you. <verse eid="EZK 35:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 35:7"/>And I have given Mount Seir for a desolation and an astonishment, || And have cut off from it him who is passing over and him who is returning, <verse eid="EZK 35:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 35:8"/>And filled his mountains with his wounded, || Your hills, and your valleys, and all your streams, || The pierced of the sword fall into them. <verse eid="EZK 35:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 35:9"/>I make you continuous desolations, || And your cities do not return, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 35:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 35:10"/>Because of your saying: The two nations and the two lands are mine, and we have possessed it, || And YHWH has been there; <verse eid="EZK 35:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 35:11"/>Therefore, [as] I live—a declaration of Lord YHWH, || And I have done according to your anger, || And according to your envy, || With which you have worked, || Because of your hatred against them, || And I have been known among them when I judge you. <verse eid="EZK 35:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 35:12"/>And you have known that I [am] YHWH, || I have heard all your despisings that you have spoken || Against mountains of Israel, saying, || A desolation—they were given to us for food. <verse eid="EZK 35:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 35:13"/>And you magnify yourselves against Me with your mouth, || And have made your words abundant against Me; I have heard. <verse eid="EZK 35:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 35:14"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: According to the rejoicing of the whole land, || I make a desolation of you. <verse eid="EZK 35:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 35:15"/>According to your joy at the inheritance of the house of Israel because of desolation, || So I do to you—you are a desolation, || O Mount Seir, and all Edom—all of it, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 35:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 35"/>
  <chapter number="36" style="c" sid="EZK 36"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 36:1"/>“And you, son of man, prophesy to mountains of Israel, and you have said, O mountains of Israel, hear a word of YHWH! <verse eid="EZK 36:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 36:2"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Because the enemy said against you, Aha! The high places of old have also become our possession, <verse eid="EZK 36:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 36:3"/>therefore, prophesy, and you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH: Because, even because, of desolating, || And of swallowing you up from all around, || For your being a possession to the remnant of the nations, || And you are taken up on the tip of the tongue, || And [are] an evil report to the people. <verse eid="EZK 36:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 36:4"/>Therefore, O mountains of Israel, || Hear a word of Lord YHWH! Thus said Lord YHWH, to mountains, and to hills, || To streams, and to valleys, || And to ruins that [are] desolate, || And to cities that are forsaken, || That have been for a prey, || And for a scorn, to the remnant of the surrounding nations, <verse eid="EZK 36:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 36:5"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Have I not, in the fire of My jealousy, || Spoken against the remnant of the nations, || And against Edom—all of it, || Who gave My land to themselves for a possession, || With the joy of the whole heart—with despite of soul, || For the sake of casting it out for a prey? <verse eid="EZK 36:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 36:6"/>Therefore, prophesy concerning the ground of Israel, || And you have said to mountains, and to hills, || To streams, and to valleys, || Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I, in My jealousy and in My fury, have spoken, || Because you have borne the shame of nations. <verse eid="EZK 36:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 36:7"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: I have lifted up My hand, || Do the nations who [are] surrounding you not bear their own shame? <verse eid="EZK 36:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 36:8"/>And you, O mountains of Israel, || You give out your branch, || And you bear your fruits for My people Israel, || For they have drawn near to come. <verse eid="EZK 36:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 36:9"/>For behold, I [am] for you, and have turned to you, || And you have been tilled and sown. <verse eid="EZK 36:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 36:10"/>And I have multiplied men on you, || All the house of Israel—all of it, || And the cities have been inhabited, || And the ruins are built. <verse eid="EZK 36:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 36:11"/>And I have multiplied man and beast on you, || And they have multiplied and been fruitful, || And I have caused you to dwell according to your former states, || And I have done better than at your beginnings, || And you have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 36:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 36:12"/>And I have caused man to walk over you—My people Israel, || And they possess you, and you have been their inheritance, || And you no longer add to bereave them. <verse eid="EZK 36:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 36:13"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Because they are saying to you, You [are] a devourer of men, || And you have been a bereaver of your nations, <verse eid="EZK 36:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 36:14"/>Therefore, you no longer devour man, || And you do not cause your nations to stumble anymore, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 36:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 36:15"/>And I do not proclaim the shame of the nations to you anymore, || And you no longer bear the reproach of peoples, || And your nations do not stumble anymore, || A declaration of Lord YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 36:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 36:16"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 36:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 36:17"/>“Son of man, || The house of Israel are dwelling on their land, || And they defile it by their way and by their doings, || Their way has been as the uncleanness of a separated one before Me. <verse eid="EZK 36:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 36:18"/>And I pour out My fury on them || For the blood that they shed on the land, || And they have defiled it with their idols. <verse eid="EZK 36:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 36:19"/>And I scatter them among nations, || And they are spread through lands, || According to their way, and according to their doings, || I have judged them. <verse eid="EZK 36:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 36:20"/>And one goes to the nations to where they have gone, || And they defile My holy Name by saying to them, || These [are] the people of YHWH, || And they have gone forth from His land. <verse eid="EZK 36:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 36:21"/>And I have pity on My holy Name, || That the house of Israel has defiled || Among the nations to where they have gone in. <verse eid="EZK 36:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 36:22"/>Therefore, say to the house of Israel, Thus said Lord YHWH: I am not working for your sake, || O house of Israel, but for My holy Name || That you have defiled || Among the nations to where you have gone in. <verse eid="EZK 36:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 36:23"/>And I have sanctified My great Name, || That is profaned among the nations, || That you have defiled in your midst, || And the nations have known that I [am] YHWH, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || In My being sanctified in you before your eyes. <verse eid="EZK 36:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 36:24"/>And I have taken you out of the nations, || And have gathered you out of all the lands, || And I have brought you into your land, <verse eid="EZK 36:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 36:25"/>And I have sprinkled clean water over you, || And you have been clean; I cleanse you from all your uncleannesses, || And from all your idols. <verse eid="EZK 36:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 36:26"/>And I have given a new heart to you, || And I give a new spirit in your midst, || And I have turned aside the heart of stone out of your flesh, || And I have given a heart of flesh to you. <verse eid="EZK 36:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 36:27"/>And I give My Spirit in your midst, || And I have done this, so that you walk in My statutes, || And you keep My judgments, and have done them. <verse eid="EZK 36:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 36:28"/>And you have dwelt in the land that I have given to your fathers, || And you have been to Me for a people, || And I am to you for God. <verse eid="EZK 36:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 36:29"/>And I have saved you from all your uncleannesses, || And I have called to the grain, and multiplied it, || And I have put no famine on you. <verse eid="EZK 36:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 36:30"/>And I have multiplied the fruit of the tree, || And the increase of the field, || So that you do not receive a reproach of famine among nations anymore. <verse eid="EZK 36:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 36:31"/>And you have remembered your ways that [are] evil, || And your doings that [are] not good, || And have been loathsome in your own faces, || For your iniquities, and for your abominations. <verse eid="EZK 36:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 36:32"/>I am not working for your sake, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || Be it known to you, || Be ashamed and confounded, because of your ways, || O house of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 36:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EZK 36:33"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: In the day of My cleansing you from all your iniquities, || I have caused the cities to be inhabited, || And the ruins have been built, <verse eid="EZK 36:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EZK 36:34"/>And the desolate land is tilled, || Instead of which it was a desolation before the eyes of everyone passing by, <verse eid="EZK 36:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EZK 36:35"/>And they have said: This land, that was desolated, || Has been as the Garden of Eden, || And the cities—the dried up, || And the desolated, and the broken down, || [And the] fortified have remained. <verse eid="EZK 36:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EZK 36:36"/>And the nations who are left around you have known || That I, YHWH, have built the thrown down, || I have planted the desolated: I, YHWH, have spoken, and I have done [it]. <verse eid="EZK 36:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EZK 36:37"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Yet this I am inquired of by the house of Israel to do for them: I multiply them as a flock of men, <verse eid="EZK 36:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EZK 36:38"/>As a flock of holy ones, as a flock of Jerusalem, || In her appointed times, || So the dried up cities are full of flocks of man, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 36:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 36"/>
  <chapter number="37" style="c" sid="EZK 37"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 37:1"/>There has been a hand of YHWH on me, and He takes me forth in [the] Spirit of YHWH, and places me in the midst of the valley, and it is full of bones, <verse eid="EZK 37:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 37:2"/>and He causes me to pass over by them, all around, and behold, very many [are] on the face of the valley, and behold—very dry. <verse eid="EZK 37:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 37:3"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, do these bones live?” And I say, “O Lord YHWH, You have known.” <verse eid="EZK 37:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 37:4"/>And He says to me, “Prophesy concerning these bones, and you have said to them, O dry bones, hear a word of YHWH! <verse eid="EZK 37:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 37:5"/>Thus said Lord YHWH to these bones: Behold, I am bringing a spirit into you, and you have lived, <verse eid="EZK 37:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 37:6"/>and I have given sinews on you, and cause flesh to come up on you, and covered you over with skin, and given a spirit in you, and you have lived, and you have known that I [am] YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 37:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 37:7"/>And I have prophesied as I have been commanded, and there is a noise as I am prophesying, and behold, a rushing, and the bones draw near, bone to its bone. <verse eid="EZK 37:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 37:8"/>And I beheld, and behold, sinews [are] on them, and flesh has come up, and skin covers them over above—and there is no spirit in them. <verse eid="EZK 37:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 37:9"/>And He says to me: “Prophesy to the Spirit, prophesy, son of man, and you have said to the Spirit, Thus said Lord YHWH: Come in from the four winds, O Spirit, and breathe on these slain, and they live.” <verse eid="EZK 37:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 37:10"/>And I have prophesied as He commanded me, and the Spirit comes into them, and they live, and stand on their feet—a very, very great force. <verse eid="EZK 37:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 37:11"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, these bones are the whole house of Israel; behold, they are saying, Our bones have dried up, || And our hope has perished, || We have been cut off by ourselves. <verse eid="EZK 37:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 37:12"/>Therefore, prophesy, and you have said to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am opening your graves, || And have brought you up out of your graves, O My people, || And brought you into the land of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 37:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 37:13"/>And you have known that I [am] YHWH, || In My opening your graves, || And in My bringing you up out of your graves, O My people. <verse eid="EZK 37:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 37:14"/>And I have given My Spirit in you, and you have lived, || And I have caused you to rest on your land, || And you have known that I, YHWH, have spoken, and I have done [it], || A declaration of YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 37:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 37:15"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 37:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 37:16"/>“And you, son of man, take one stick for yourself, and write on it, || For Judah, and for the sons of Israel, his companions; and take another stick, and write on it, || For Joseph, the stick of Ephraim, and all the house of Israel, his companions, <verse eid="EZK 37:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 37:17"/>and bring them near to one another, to you, for one stick, and they have become one in your hand. <verse eid="EZK 37:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 37:18"/>And when sons of your people speak to you, saying, Do you not declare to us what these [are] to you? <verse eid="EZK 37:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 37:19"/>Speak to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am taking the stick of Joseph, that [is] in the hand of Ephraim, and the tribes of Israel his companions, and have given them to him, with the stick of Judah, and have made them become one stick, and they have been one in My hand. <verse eid="EZK 37:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 37:20"/>And the sticks on which you write have been in your hand before your eyes, <verse eid="EZK 37:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 37:21"/>and speak to them, Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I am taking the sons of Israel, || From among the nations to where they have gone, || And have gathered them from all around, || And I have brought them into their land. <verse eid="EZK 37:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 37:22"/>And I have made them become one nation in the land, on mountains of Israel, || And one king is to them all for king, || And they are no longer as two nations, || Nor are they divided anymore into two kingdoms again. <verse eid="EZK 37:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 37:23"/>Nor are they defiled anymore with their idols, || And with their abominations, || And with any of their transgressions, || And I have saved them out of all their dwellings, || In which they have sinned, || And I have cleansed them, || And they have been to Me for a people, || And I am to them for God. <verse eid="EZK 37:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 37:24"/>And My servant David [is] king over them, || And they all have one shepherd, || And they go in My judgments, || And they keep My statutes, and have done them. <verse eid="EZK 37:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 37:25"/>And they have dwelt on the land that I gave to My servant, to Jacob, || In which your fathers have dwelt, || And they have dwelt on it, they and their sons, || And their son’s sons—for all time, || And My servant David [is] their prince for all time. <verse eid="EZK 37:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 37:26"/>And I have made a covenant of peace with them, || It is a perpetual covenant with them, || And I have placed them, and multiplied them, || And placed My sanctuary in their midst for all time. <verse eid="EZK 37:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 37:27"/>And My dwelling place has been over them, || And I have been to them for God, || And they have been to Me for a people. <verse eid="EZK 37:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 37:28"/>And the nations have known that I, YHWH, am sanctifying Israel, || In My sanctuary being in their midst for all time!”<verse eid="EZK 37:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 37"/>
  <chapter number="38" style="c" sid="EZK 38"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 38:1"/>And there is a word of YHWH to me, saying, <verse eid="EZK 38:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 38:2"/>“Son of man, set your face toward Gog, of the land of Magog, chief prince of <char style="bd">[[</char><char style="it">or</char> prince of Rosh,<char style="bd">]]</char> Meshech and Tubal, and prophesy concerning him, <verse eid="EZK 38:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 38:3"/>and you have said, Thus says Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against you, O Gog, || Chief prince of <char style="bd">[[</char><char style="it">or</char> prince of Rosh,<char style="bd">]]</char> Meshech and Tubal, <verse eid="EZK 38:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 38:4"/>And I have turned you back, || And I have put hooks in your jaws, || And have brought you out, and all your force, || Horses and horsemen, || All of them clothed in perfection, || A numerous assembly, [with] buckler and shield, || All of them handling swords. <verse eid="EZK 38:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 38:5"/>Persia, Cush, and Phut, with them, || All of them [with] shield and helmet. <verse eid="EZK 38:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 38:6"/>Gomer and all its bands, || The house of Togarmah [from] the sides of the north, || And all its bands, many peoples with you, <verse eid="EZK 38:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 38:7"/>Be prepared, indeed, prepare yourself, || You and all your assemblies who are assembled to you, || And you have been for a watch for them. <verse eid="EZK 38:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 38:8"/>After many days you are appointed, || In the latter end of the years you come into a land brought back from sword—Gathered out of many peoples, || On mountains of Israel, || That have been for a continuous ruin, || And it has been brought out from the peoples, || And all of them have dwelt safely. <verse eid="EZK 38:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 38:9"/>And you have gone up—you come in as desolation, || You are as a cloud to cover the land, || You and all your bands, and many peoples with you. <verse eid="EZK 38:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 38:10"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: And it has come to pass in that day, || Things come up on your heart, || And you have thought an evil thought, <verse eid="EZK 38:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 38:11"/>And you have said: I go up over a land of open places, || I go to those at rest, dwelling confidently, || All of them are dwelling without walls, || And they have no bar and doors— <verse eid="EZK 38:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 38:12"/>To take a spoil, and to take a prey, || To turn back your hand on inhabited ruins, || And on a people gathered out of nations, || Making livestock and substance, || Dwelling on a high part of the land. <verse eid="EZK 38:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 38:13"/>Sheba, and Dedan, and merchants of Tarshish, || And all its young lions say to you, || Are you coming to take spoil? Have you assembled your assembly to take prey? To carry away silver and gold? To take away livestock and substance? To take a great spoil? <verse eid="EZK 38:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 38:14"/>Therefore, prophesy, son of man, and you have said to Gog, Thus said Lord YHWH: In that day, in the dwelling of My people Israel safely, || Do you not know? <verse eid="EZK 38:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 38:15"/>And you have come in out of your place, || From the sides of the north, || You and many peoples with you, || Riding on horses—all of them, || A great assembly, and a numerous force. <verse eid="EZK 38:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 38:16"/>And you have come up against My people Israel, || As a cloud to cover the land, || It is in the latter end of the days, || And I have brought you in against My land, || In order that the nations may know Me, || In My being sanctified in you before their eyes, O Gog. <verse eid="EZK 38:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 38:17"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: Are you he of whom I spoke in former days, || By the hand of My servants, prophets of Israel, || Who were prophesying [for] years in those days, || To bring you in against them? <verse eid="EZK 38:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 38:18"/>And it has come to pass in that day, || In the day of the coming in of Gog against the land of Israel, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || My fury comes up in My face, <verse eid="EZK 38:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 38:19"/>And in My zeal, in the fire of My wrath, || I have spoken: Is there not a great rushing on the land of Israel in that day? <verse eid="EZK 38:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 38:20"/>And rushed from My presence have fishes of the sea, || And the bird of the heavens, || And the beast of the field, || And every creeping thing that is creeping on the ground, || And all men who [are] on the face of the ground, || And the mountains have been thrown down, || And the ascents have fallen, || And every wall falls to the earth. <verse eid="EZK 38:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 38:21"/>And I have called for a sword against him throughout all My mountains, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || The sword of each is against his brother. <verse eid="EZK 38:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 38:22"/>And I have judged him with pestilence and with blood, || And an overflowing rain and hailstones, || I rain fire and brimstone on him, and on his bands, || And on many peoples who [are] with him. <verse eid="EZK 38:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 38:23"/>And I have magnified Myself, and sanctified Myself, || And I have been known before the eyes of many nations, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 38:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 38"/>
  <chapter number="39" style="c" sid="EZK 39"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 39:1"/>“And you, son of man, prophesy concerning Gog, and you have said, Thus said Lord YHWH: Behold, I [am] against you, O Gog, || Chief prince of <char style="bd">[[</char><char style="it">or</char> prince of Rosh,<char style="bd">]]</char> Meshech and Tubal, <verse eid="EZK 39:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 39:2"/>And have turned you back, and enticed you, || And caused you to come up from the sides of the north, || And brought you in against mountains of Israel, <verse eid="EZK 39:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 39:3"/>And have struck your bow out of your left hand, || Indeed, I cause your arrows to fall out of your right. <verse eid="EZK 39:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 39:4"/>You fall on mountains of Israel, || You, and all your bands, and the peoples who [are] with you, || To ravenous bird—a bird of every wing, || And [to] a beast of the field, I have given you for food. <verse eid="EZK 39:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 39:5"/>You fall on the face of the field, for I have spoken, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 39:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 39:6"/>And I have sent a fire against Magog, || And against the confident inhabitants of the islands, || And they have known that I [am] YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 39:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 39:7"/>And I make My holy Name known in the midst of My people Israel, || And I do not defile My holy Name anymore, || And the nations have known that I, YHWH, the Holy One, [am] in Israel. <verse eid="EZK 39:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 39:8"/>Behold, it has come, and it has been done, || A declaration of Lord YHWH, || It [is] the day of which I spoke. <verse eid="EZK 39:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 39:9"/>And those dwelling [in the] cities of Israel have gone out, || And they have burned and kindled [a fire], || With armor, and shield, and buckler, || With bow, and with arrows, || And with hand weapon, and with javelin, || And they have caused a fire to burn seven years with them, <verse eid="EZK 39:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 39:10"/>And they do not take wood out of the field, || Nor do they hew out of the forests, || For they cause the fire to burn with armor, || And they have spoiled their spoilers, || And they have plundered their plunderers, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 39:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 39:11"/>And it has come to pass in that day, I give a place to Gog there—a grave in Israel, the valley of those passing by, east of the sea, and it is stopping those passing by, and they have buried there Gog, and all his multitude, and have cried, O valley of the multitude of Gog! <verse eid="EZK 39:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 39:12"/>And the house of Israel has buried them—in order to cleanse the land—seven months. <verse eid="EZK 39:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 39:13"/>Indeed, all the people of the land have buried them, and it has been to them for a name—the day of My being honored—a declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 39:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 39:14"/>And they separate men for continual employment, with those passing through, passing on through the land, burying those who are left on the face of the earth, to cleanse it. At the end of seven months they search. <verse eid="EZK 39:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 39:15"/>And those passing by have passed through the land, and seen a bone of man, and one has constructed a sign near it until those burying have buried it in the valley of the multitude of Gog. <verse eid="EZK 39:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 39:16"/>And also the name of the city [is] The Multitude; and they have cleansed the land. <verse eid="EZK 39:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 39:17"/>And you, son of man, thus said Lord YHWH: Say to the bird—every wing, and to every beast of the field: Be assembled and come in, || Be gathered from all around, || For My sacrifice that I am sacrificing for you, || A great sacrifice on mountains of Israel, || And you have eaten flesh, and drunk blood. <verse eid="EZK 39:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 39:18"/>You eat [the] flesh of [the] mighty, || And you drink [the] blood of [the] princes of the earth, || Of rams, of lambs, and of male goats, || Of calves, fatlings of Bashan—all of them. <verse eid="EZK 39:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 39:19"/>And you have eaten fat to satiety, || And you have drunk blood—to drunkenness, || Of My sacrifice that I sacrificed for you. <verse eid="EZK 39:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 39:20"/>And you have been satisfied at My table with horse and rider, || Mighty man, and every man of war, || A declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 39:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 39:21"/>And I have given My glory among nations, || And all the nations have seen My judgment that I have done, || And My hand that I have laid on them. <verse eid="EZK 39:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 39:22"/>And the house of Israel has known that I [am] their God YHWH, || From that day and from now on. <verse eid="EZK 39:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 39:23"/>And the nations have known || That the house of Israel was removed for their iniquity, || Because they have trespassed against Me, || And I hide My face from them, || And give them into the hand of their adversaries, || And they fall by sword—all of them. <verse eid="EZK 39:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 39:24"/>According to their uncleanness, || And according to their transgressions, I have done with them, || And I hide My face from them. <verse eid="EZK 39:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 39:25"/>Therefore, thus said Lord YHWH: Now I bring back the captivity of Jacob, || And I have pitied all the house of Israel, || And have been zealous for My holy Name. <verse eid="EZK 39:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 39:26"/>And they have forgotten their shame, || And all their trespass that they trespassed against Me, || In their dwelling on their land confidently and none troubling. <verse eid="EZK 39:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 39:27"/>In My bringing them back from the peoples, || I have assembled them from the lands of their enemies, || And I have been sanctified in them before the eyes of the many nations, <verse eid="EZK 39:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 39:28"/>And they have known that I [am] their God YHWH, || In My removing them to the nations, || And I have gathered them to their land, || And I leave none of them there anymore. <verse eid="EZK 39:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 39:29"/>And I do not hide My face from them anymore, || In that I have poured out My Spirit on the house of Israel, || A declaration of Lord YHWH!”<verse eid="EZK 39:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 39"/>
  <chapter number="40" style="c" sid="EZK 40"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 40:1"/>In the twenty-fifth year of our removal, in the beginning of the year, on the tenth of the month, in the fourteenth year after which the city was struck, on this very same day a hand of YHWH has been on me, and He brings me in there; <verse eid="EZK 40:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 40:2"/>in visions of God He has brought me into the land of Israel, and causes me to rest on a very high mountain, and on it [is] as the frame of a city from the south. <verse eid="EZK 40:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 40:3"/>And He brings me in there, and behold, a man, his appearance as the appearance of bronze, and a thread of flax in his hand, and a measuring-reed, and he is standing at the gate, <verse eid="EZK 40:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 40:4"/>and the man speaks to me: “Son of man, see with your eyes, || And hear with your ears, || And set your heart to all that I am showing you, || For in order to show [it] you, || You have been brought in here, || Declare all that you are seeing to the house of Israel.” <verse eid="EZK 40:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 40:5"/>And behold, a wall all around on the outside of the house, and a measuring-reed in the hand of the man, six cubits by a cubit and a handbreadth, and he measures the breadth of the building—one reed, and the height—one reed. <verse eid="EZK 40:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 40:6"/>And he comes to the gate whose front [is] eastward, and he goes up by its steps, and he measures the threshold of the gate—one reed broad, even one threshold—one reed broad, <verse eid="EZK 40:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 40:7"/>and the little chamber—one reed long and one reed broad, and between the little chambers—five cubits, and the threshold of the gate, from the side of the porch of the gate from within—one reed. <verse eid="EZK 40:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 40:8"/>And he measures the porch of the gate from within—one reed, <verse eid="EZK 40:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 40:9"/>and he measures the porch of the gate—eight cubits, and its posts—two cubits, and the porch of the gates from within, <verse eid="EZK 40:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 40:10"/>and the little chambers of the gate eastward, three on this side and three on that side; the three of them—one measure, and the posts—one measure, on this side and on that side. <verse eid="EZK 40:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 40:11"/>And he measures the breadth of the opening of the gate—ten cubits, the length of the gate—thirteen cubits; <verse eid="EZK 40:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 40:12"/>and a border before the little chambers—one cubit, and one cubit [is] the border on this side, and the little chamber—six cubits on this side, and six cubits on that side. <verse eid="EZK 40:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 40:13"/>And he measures the gate from the roof of the [one] little chamber to the roof of another; the breadth—twenty-five cubits, opening opposite opening. <verse eid="EZK 40:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 40:14"/>And he makes the posts of sixty cubits, even to the post of the court, the gate all around; <verse eid="EZK 40:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 40:15"/>and by the front of the gate of the entrance, by the front of the porch of the inner gate—fifty cubits; <verse eid="EZK 40:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 40:16"/>and narrow windows [are] in the little chambers, and in their posts on the inside of the gate all around—and so to the arches—and windows all around on the inside, and palm-trees [are] on the post. <verse eid="EZK 40:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 40:17"/>And he brings me into the outer court, and behold, chambers and a pavement made for the court all around—thirty chambers on the pavement— <verse eid="EZK 40:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 40:18"/>and the pavement to the side of the gates, corresponding to the length of the gates, [is] the lower pavement; <verse eid="EZK 40:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 40:19"/>and he measures the breadth from before the lower gate, to the front of the inner court, on the outside—one hundred cubits, eastward and northward. <verse eid="EZK 40:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 40:20"/>As for the gate of the outer court whose front [is] northward, he has measured its length and its breadth; <verse eid="EZK 40:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 40:21"/>and its little chambers, three on this side and three on that side, and its posts and its arches have been according to the measure of the first gate, its length [is] fifty cubits, and breadth [is] twenty-five by the cubit; <verse eid="EZK 40:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 40:22"/>and its windows, and its arches, and its palm-trees [are] according to the measure of the gate whose face [is] eastward, and they go up on it by seven steps, and its arches [are] before them. <verse eid="EZK 40:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 40:23"/>And the gate of the inner court [is] opposite the gate at the north and at the east; and he measures from gate to gate—one hundred cubits. <verse eid="EZK 40:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 40:24"/>And he causes me to go southward, and behold, a gate southward, and he has measured its posts and its arches according to these measurements; <verse eid="EZK 40:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 40:25"/>and windows [are] in it and in its arches all around, like these windows, the length—fifty cubits, and the breadth—twenty-five cubits; <verse eid="EZK 40:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 40:26"/>and seven steps [are] its ascent, and its arches [are] before them, and palm-trees [are] in it, one on this side and one on that side, on its posts; <verse eid="EZK 40:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 40:27"/>and the gate of the inner court [is] southward, and he measures from gate to gate southward, one hundred cubits. <verse eid="EZK 40:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 40:28"/>And he brings me into the inner court by the south gate, and he measures the south gate according to these measurements; <verse eid="EZK 40:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 40:29"/>and its little chambers, and its posts, and its arches [are] according to these measurements, and windows [are] in it and in its arches all around; the length—fifty cubits, and the breadth—twenty-five cubits. <verse eid="EZK 40:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 40:30"/>As for the arches all around, the length—twenty-five cubits, and the breadth—five cubits; <verse eid="EZK 40:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 40:31"/>and its arches [are] toward the outer court, and palm-trees [are] on its posts, and eight steps [are] its ascent. <verse eid="EZK 40:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 40:32"/>And he brings me into the inner court eastward, and he measures the gate according to these measurements; <verse eid="EZK 40:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EZK 40:33"/>and its little chambers, and its posts, and its arches [are] according to these measurements: and windows [are] in it and in its arches all around, the length—fifty cubits, and the breadth—twenty-five cubits; <verse eid="EZK 40:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EZK 40:34"/>and its arches [are] toward the outer court, and palm-trees [are] toward its posts, on this side and on that side, and eight steps [are] its ascent. <verse eid="EZK 40:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EZK 40:35"/>And he brings me into the north gate, and has measured according to these measurements; <verse eid="EZK 40:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="EZK 40:36"/>its little chambers, its posts, and its arches; and windows [are] in it all around: the length—fifty cubits, and the breadth—twenty-five cubits; <verse eid="EZK 40:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="EZK 40:37"/>and its posts [are] toward the outer court, and palm-trees [are] on its posts, on this side and on that side, and eight steps [are] its ascent. <verse eid="EZK 40:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="EZK 40:38"/>And the chamber and its opening [is] by the posts of the gates, there they purge the burnt-offering. <verse eid="EZK 40:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="EZK 40:39"/>And in the porch of the gate [are] two tables on this side and two tables on that side, to slaughter on them the burnt-offering, and the sin-offering, and the guilt-offering; <verse eid="EZK 40:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="EZK 40:40"/>and at the side without, at the going up to the opening of the north gate, [are] two tables; and at the other side that [is] at the porch of the gate, [are] two tables; <verse eid="EZK 40:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="EZK 40:41"/>four tables [are] on this side and four tables on that side, at the side of the gate, eight tables on which they slaughter. <verse eid="EZK 40:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="EZK 40:42"/>And the four tables for burnt-offering [are] of hewn stone: the length—one cubit and a half, and the breadth—one cubit and a half, and the height—one cubit; they place on them the instruments with which they slaughter the burnt-offering and the sacrifice. <verse eid="EZK 40:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="EZK 40:43"/>And the boundaries [are] one handbreadth, prepared within all around: and the flesh of the offering [is] on the tables. <verse eid="EZK 40:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="EZK 40:44"/>And on the outside of the inner gate [are] chambers of the singers, in the inner court, that [are] at the side of the north gate, and their fronts [are] southward, one at the side of the east gate [with] front northward. <verse eid="EZK 40:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="EZK 40:45"/>And he speaks to me: “This chamber, whose front [is] southward, [is] for priests keeping charge of the house; <verse eid="EZK 40:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="EZK 40:46"/>and the chamber, whose front [is] northward, [is] for priests keeping charge of the altar: they [are] sons of Zadok, who are drawing near of the sons of Levi to YHWH, to serve Him.” <verse eid="EZK 40:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="EZK 40:47"/>And he measures the court: the length—one hundred cubits, and the breadth—one hundred cubits, square, and the altar [is] before the house. <verse eid="EZK 40:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="EZK 40:48"/>And he brings me to the porch of the house, and he measures the post of the porch—five cubits on this side and five cubits on that side, and the breadth of the gate—three cubits on this side and three cubits on that side; <verse eid="EZK 40:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="EZK 40:49"/>the length of the porch—twenty cubits, and the breadth—eleven <char style="bd">[[</char><char style="it">or</char> twelve<char style="bd">]]</char> cubits; and they go up to it by the <char style="bd">[[</char>ten<char style="bd">]]</char> steps. And pillars [are] by the posts, one on this side and one on that side.<verse eid="EZK 40:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 40"/>
  <chapter number="41" style="c" sid="EZK 41"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 41:1"/>And he brings me into the temple, and he measures the posts, six cubits the breadth on this side and six cubits the breadth on that side—the breadth of the tent. <verse eid="EZK 41:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 41:2"/>And the breadth of the opening [is] ten cubits; and the sides of the opening [are] five cubits on this side and five cubits on that side; and he measures its length—forty cubits, and the breadth—twenty cubits. <verse eid="EZK 41:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 41:3"/>And he has gone inward, and measures the post of the opening—two cubits, and the opening—six cubits, and the breadth of the opening—seven cubits. <verse eid="EZK 41:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 41:4"/>And he measures its length—twenty cubits, and the breadth—twenty cubits, to the front of the temple, and he says to me, “This [is] the Holy of Holies.” <verse eid="EZK 41:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 41:5"/>And he measures the wall of the house—six cubits, and the breadth of the side-chamber—four cubits, all around the house. <verse eid="EZK 41:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 41:6"/>And the side-chambers [are] side-chamber by side-chamber, thirty-three times; and they are entering into the wall—which the house has for the side-chambers all around—to be taken hold of, and they are not taken hold of by the wall of the house. <verse eid="EZK 41:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 41:7"/>And it has become wider when one has turned even higher toward the side-chambers, for the encompassment of the house [is] even higher all around the house: therefore the breadth of the house [goes] upwards, and so the lower [story] goes up to the higher by the middle. <verse eid="EZK 41:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 41:8"/>And I have looked at the height all around the house: the foundations of the side-chambers [are] the fullness of the reed, six cubits by the joining. <verse eid="EZK 41:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 41:9"/>The breadth of that wall, of the side-chamber, at the outside, [is] five cubits; and the space remaining of the side-chambers—that of the house, <verse eid="EZK 41:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 41:10"/>and between the chambers—[is] a breadth of twenty cubits around the house, all around. <verse eid="EZK 41:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 41:11"/>And the opening of the side-chamber [is] to the remaining [space], one opening northward and one opening southward, and the breadth of the remaining space [is] five cubits all around. <verse eid="EZK 41:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 41:12"/>As for the building that [is] at the front of the separate place [at] the corner westward, the breadth [is] seventy cubits, and the wall of the building [is] five cubits broad all around, and its length—ninety cubits. <verse eid="EZK 41:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 41:13"/>And he has measured the house, the length [is] one hundred cubits; and the separate place, and the building, and its walls, the length [is] one hundred cubits; <verse eid="EZK 41:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 41:14"/>and the breadth of the front of the house, and of the separate place eastward—one hundred cubits. <verse eid="EZK 41:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 41:15"/>And he has measured the length of the building to the front of the separate place that [is] at its back part, and its galleries on this side and on that side—one hundred cubits. And the inner temple and the porches of the court, <verse eid="EZK 41:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 41:16"/>the thresholds, and the narrow windows, and the galleries around the three of them, opposite the threshold, [were] paneled with wood all around—and the ground to the windows, and the windows were covered, <verse eid="EZK 41:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 41:17"/>over above the opening, and to the inner-house, and at the outside, and by all the wall all around inside and outside [by] measurements. <verse eid="EZK 41:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 41:18"/>And it is made [with] cherubim and palm-trees, and a palm-tree [is] between cherub and cherub, and two faces [are] on the cherub; <verse eid="EZK 41:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 41:19"/>and the face of a man toward the palm-tree on this side and the face of a young lion toward the palm-tree on that side; it is made to all the house all around. <verse eid="EZK 41:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 41:20"/>From the earth to above the opening the cherubim and the palm-trees [were] made, and [on] the wall of the temple. <verse eid="EZK 41:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 41:21"/>The doorpost of the temple [is] square, and of the front of the sanctuary, the appearance [is] as that appearance. <verse eid="EZK 41:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 41:22"/>Of the altar, the wood [is] three cubits in height, and its length—two cubits; and its corners [are] to it, and its length, and its walls [are] of wood, and he speaks to me, “This [is] the table that [is] before YHWH.” <verse eid="EZK 41:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 41:23"/>And the temple and the sanctuary had two doors; <verse eid="EZK 41:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 41:24"/>and the doors had two panels, two turning panels: two on one door, and two panels on the other. <verse eid="EZK 41:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 41:25"/>And made on them, on the doors of the temple, [are] cherubim and palm-trees as are made on the walls, and a thickness of wood [is] at the front of the porch on the outside. <verse eid="EZK 41:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 41:26"/>And narrow windows and palm-trees [are] on this side and on that side, at the sides of the porch, and the side-chambers of the house, and the thick places.<verse eid="EZK 41:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 41"/>
  <chapter number="42" style="c" sid="EZK 42"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 42:1"/>And he brings me forth to the outer court, the way northward, and he brings me into the chamber that [is] opposite the separate place, and that [is] opposite the building at the north. <verse eid="EZK 42:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 42:2"/>At the front of the length [is] one hundred cubits [at] the north opening, and the breadth—fifty cubits. <verse eid="EZK 42:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 42:3"/>Opposite the twenty [cubits] that are of the inner court, and opposite the pavement that [is] of the outer court, [is] gallery [with] face toward gallery, in the three [stories]. <verse eid="EZK 42:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 42:4"/>And at the front of the chambers [is] a walk of ten cubits in breadth to the inner part, a way of one cubit, and their openings [are] at the north. <verse eid="EZK 42:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 42:5"/>And the upper chambers [are] short, for the galleries contain more than these, than the lower, and than the middle one, of the building; <verse eid="EZK 42:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 42:6"/>for they [are] threefold, and they have no pillars as the pillars of the court, therefore it has been kept back—more than the lower and than the middle one—from the ground. <verse eid="EZK 42:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 42:7"/>As for the wall that [is] at the outside, alongside the chambers, the way of the outer-court at the front of the chambers, its length [is] fifty cubits; <verse eid="EZK 42:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 42:8"/>for the length of the chambers that [are] in the outer court [is] fifty cubits, and of those on the front of the temple—one hundred cubits. <verse eid="EZK 42:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 42:9"/>And under these chambers [is] the entrance from the east, in one’s going into them from the outer court. <verse eid="EZK 42:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 42:10"/>In the breadth of the wall of the court eastward, to the front of the separate place, and to the front of the building, [are] chambers. <verse eid="EZK 42:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 42:11"/>And the way before them [is] as the appearance of the chambers that [are] northward, according to their length so [is] their breadth, and all their outlets, and according to their fashions, and according to their openings. <verse eid="EZK 42:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 42:12"/>And according to the openings of the chambers that [are] southward [is] an opening at the head of the way, the way directly in the front of the wall eastward in entering them. <verse eid="EZK 42:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 42:13"/>And he says to me, “The north chambers, the south chambers, that [are] at the front of the separate place, they [are] holy chambers, where the priests (who [are] near to YHWH) eat the most holy things, there they place the most holy things, and the present, and the sin-offering, and the guilt-offering, for the place [is] holy. <verse eid="EZK 42:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 42:14"/>In the priests’ going in, they do not come out from the sanctuary to the outer court, and there they place their garments with which they minister, for they [are] holy, and have put on other garments, and have drawn near to that which [is] for the people.” <verse eid="EZK 42:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 42:15"/>And he has finished the measurements of the inner house, and has brought me forth the way of the gate whose front [is] eastward, and he has measured it all around. <verse eid="EZK 42:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 42:16"/>He has measured the east side with the measuring-reed, five hundred reeds, with the measuring-reed all around. <verse eid="EZK 42:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 42:17"/>He has measured the north side, five hundred reeds, with the measuring reed all around. <verse eid="EZK 42:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 42:18"/>The south side he has measured, five hundred reeds, with the measuring-reed. <verse eid="EZK 42:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 42:19"/>He has turned around to the west side, he has measured five hundred reeds with the measuring-reed. <verse eid="EZK 42:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 42:20"/>At the four sides he has measured it; it had a wall all around, the length—five hundred, and the breadth—five hundred, to separate between the holy and the profane place.<verse eid="EZK 42:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 42"/>
  <chapter number="43" style="c" sid="EZK 43"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 43:1"/>And he causes me to go to the gate, the gate that is looking eastward. <verse eid="EZK 43:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 43:2"/>And behold, the glory of the God of Israel has come from the way of the east, and His voice [is] as the noise of many waters, and the earth has shone from His glory. <verse eid="EZK 43:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 43:3"/>And according to the appearance [is] the appearance that I saw, as the appearance that I saw in my coming in to destroy the city, and the appearances [are] as the appearance that I saw at the river Chebar, and I fall on my face. <verse eid="EZK 43:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 43:4"/>And the glory of YHWH has come into the house, the way of the gate whose face [is] eastward. <verse eid="EZK 43:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 43:5"/>And [the] Spirit takes me up, and brings me into the inner court, and behold, the glory of YHWH has filled the house. <verse eid="EZK 43:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 43:6"/>And I hear one speaking to me from the house, and a man has been standing near me, <verse eid="EZK 43:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 43:7"/>and He says to me: “Son of man, the place of My throne, || And the place of the soles of My feet, || Where I dwell in the midst of the sons of Israel for all time, || The house of Israel defiles My holy Name no longer, || They, and their kings, by their whoredom, || And by the carcasses of their kings—their high places. <verse eid="EZK 43:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 43:8"/>In their putting their threshold with My threshold, || And their doorpost near My doorpost, || And the wall between Me and them, || And they have defiled My holy Name, || By their abominations that they have done, || And I consume them in My anger. <verse eid="EZK 43:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 43:9"/>Now they put their whoredom far off, || And the carcasses of their kings—from Me, || And I have dwelt in their midst for all time. <verse eid="EZK 43:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 43:10"/>You, son of man, || Show the house of Israel the house, || And they are ashamed of their iniquities, || And they have measured the measurement. <verse eid="EZK 43:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 43:11"/>And since they have been ashamed of all that they have done, || The form of the house, and its measurement, || And its outlets, and its inlets, and all its forms, || And all its statutes, even all its forms, || And all its laws—cause them to know, || And write [it] before their eyes, || And they observe all its forms, || And all its statutes, and have done them. <verse eid="EZK 43:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 43:12"/>This [is] a law of the house: on the top of the mountain, all its border all around [is] most holy; behold, this [is] a law of the house. <verse eid="EZK 43:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 43:13"/>And these [are] measurements of the altar by cubits: the cubit [is] a cubit and a handbreadth, and the center [is] a cubit, and the breadth a cubit; and its border on its edge around [is] one span, and this [is] the upper part of the altar. <verse eid="EZK 43:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 43:14"/>And from the center of the ground to the lower border [is] two cubits, and the breadth—one cubit, and from the lesser border to the greater border—four cubits, and the breadth a cubit. <verse eid="EZK 43:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 43:15"/>And the altar [is] four cubits, and from the altar and upward [are] four horns. <verse eid="EZK 43:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 43:16"/>And the altar [is] twelve long by twelve broad, square in its four sides. <verse eid="EZK 43:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 43:17"/>And the border [is] fourteen long by fourteen broad, at its four sides, and the border around it [is] half a cubit, and the center of it [is] a cubit around, and its steps are looking eastward.” <verse eid="EZK 43:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 43:18"/>And He says to me, “Son of man, thus said Lord YHWH: These [are] statutes of the altar in the day of its being made to cause burnt-offering to go up on it, and to sprinkle blood on it. <verse eid="EZK 43:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 43:19"/>And you have given to the priests, the Levites—who [are] of the seed of Zadok, who are near to Me, a declaration of Lord YHWH, to serve Me—a calf from the herd, for a sin-offering. <verse eid="EZK 43:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 43:20"/>And you have taken of its blood, and have put it on its four horns, and on the four corners of its border, and on the border all around, and have cleansed it, and purified it. <verse eid="EZK 43:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 43:21"/>And you have taken the bullock of the sin-offering, and have burned it in the appointed place of the house at the outside of the sanctuary. <verse eid="EZK 43:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 43:22"/>And on the second day you bring a kid of the goats near, a perfect one, for a sin-offering, and they have cleansed the altar, as they cleansed [it] for the bullock. <verse eid="EZK 43:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 43:23"/>In your finishing cleansing, you bring a calf near, a son of the herd, a perfect one, and a ram out of the flock, a perfect one. <verse eid="EZK 43:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 43:24"/>And you have brought them near before YHWH, and the priests have cast salt on them, and have caused them to go up, a burnt-offering to YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 43:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 43:25"/>[For] seven days you prepare a goat daily for a sin-offering; and they also prepare a bullock, a son of the herd, and a ram out of the flock—perfect ones. <verse eid="EZK 43:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 43:26"/>[For] seven days they purify the altar, and have cleansed it, and filled their hand. <verse eid="EZK 43:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 43:27"/>And the days are completed, and it has come to pass on the eighth day, and from now on, the priests prepare your burnt-offerings and your peace-offerings on the altar, and I have accepted you—a declaration of Lord YHWH.”<verse eid="EZK 43:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 43"/>
  <chapter number="44" style="c" sid="EZK 44"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 44:1"/>And he causes me to turn back the way of the gate of the outer sanctuary that is looking eastward, and it is shut. <verse eid="EZK 44:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 44:2"/>And YHWH says to me, “This gate is shut, it is not opened, and none go in by it, for YHWH, God of Israel, has come in by it, and it has been shut. <verse eid="EZK 44:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 44:3"/>The prince, who [is] prince, he sits by it to eat bread before YHWH, he comes in by the way of the porch of the gate, and by its way he goes out.” <verse eid="EZK 44:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 44:4"/>And he brings me in the way of the north gate to the front of the house, and I look, and behold, the glory of YHWH has filled the house of YHWH, and I fall on my face. <verse eid="EZK 44:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 44:5"/>And YHWH says to me, “Son of man, set your heart, and see with your eyes, and hear with your ears, all that I am speaking with you, all of the statutes of the house of YHWH, and all of its laws; and you have set your heart to the entrance of the house, with all the outlets of the sanctuary, <verse eid="EZK 44:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 44:6"/>and have said to [the] rebellion, to the house of Israel, Thus said Lord YHWH: Enough from you—of all your abominations, O house of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 44:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 44:7"/>In your bringing in sons of a stranger, uncircumcised of heart, and uncircumcised of flesh, to be in My sanctuary, to defile it, even My house, in your bringing near My bread, fat, and blood, and they break My covenant by all your abominations, <verse eid="EZK 44:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 44:8"/>and you have not kept [the] charge of My holy things, and you set [others] for keeping My charge in My sanctuary for you. <verse eid="EZK 44:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 44:9"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: No son of a stranger, uncircumcised of heart, and uncircumcised of flesh, comes into My sanctuary, even any son of a stranger, who [is] in the midst of the sons of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 44:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 44:10"/>And the Levites who have gone far off from Me, in the wandering of Israel when they went astray from Me after their idols, and they have borne their iniquity. <verse eid="EZK 44:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 44:11"/>And they have been servants in My sanctuary, overseers at the gates of the house, and servants at the house; they slay the burnt-offering and the sacrifice for the people, and they stand before them to serve them. <verse eid="EZK 44:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 44:12"/>Because that they serve them before their idols, and have been for a stumbling-block of iniquity to the house of Israel, therefore I have lifted up My hand against them—a declaration of Lord YHWH—and they have borne their iniquity. <verse eid="EZK 44:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 44:13"/>And they do not draw near to Me to act as My priest, and to draw near to any of My holy things, to the Holy of Holies, and they have borne their shame and their abominations that they have done, <verse eid="EZK 44:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 44:14"/>and I made them keepers of the charge of the house, for all its service and for all that is done in it. <verse eid="EZK 44:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 44:15"/>And the priests, the Levites, sons of Zadok, who have kept the charge of My sanctuary in the wandering of the sons of Israel from off Me, they draw near to Me to serve Me, and have stood before Me, to bring fat and blood near to Me—a declaration of Lord YHWH: <verse eid="EZK 44:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 44:16"/>they come into My sanctuary, and they draw near to My table to serve Me, and they have kept My charge. <verse eid="EZK 44:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 44:17"/>And it has come to pass, in their going into the gates of the inner court, they put on linen garments; and no wool comes up on them in their ministering in the gates of the inner court and within. <verse eid="EZK 44:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 44:18"/>Linen headdresses are on their head, and linen trousers are on their loins, they are not restrained with sweat. <verse eid="EZK 44:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 44:19"/>And in their going forth to the outer court—to the outer court to the people—they strip off their garments, in which they are ministering, and have placed them in the holy chambers, and have put on other garments; and they do not sanctify the people in their own garments. <verse eid="EZK 44:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 44:20"/>And they do not shave their head, and they do not send forth the lock; they certainly trim their heads. <verse eid="EZK 44:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 44:21"/>And no priest drinks wine in their coming into the inner court. <verse eid="EZK 44:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 44:22"/>And they do not take a widow or divorced woman to themselves for wives, but they take virgins of the seed of the house of Israel, and the widow who is widow of a priest. <verse eid="EZK 44:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 44:23"/>And they direct My people between holy and common, and they cause them to discern between unclean and clean. <verse eid="EZK 44:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 44:24"/>And concerning controversy, they stand up for judgment; they judge it with My judgments; and they keep My law and My statutes in all My appointed places; and they sanctify My Sabbaths. <verse eid="EZK 44:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 44:25"/>And he does not come near to any dead man to be defiled, but if for father, and for mother, and for son, and for daughter, for brother, for sister who has not been to a man, they may defile themselves. <verse eid="EZK 44:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 44:26"/>And after his cleansing, they number seven days to him. <verse eid="EZK 44:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 44:27"/>And in the day of his coming into the sanctuary, into the inner court, to minister in the sanctuary, he brings his sin-offering near—a declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 44:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 44:28"/>And it has been for an inheritance to them; I [am] their inheritance, and you do not give a possession to them in Israel; I [am] their possession. <verse eid="EZK 44:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 44:29"/>The present, and the sin-offering, and the guilt-offering, they eat, and every devoted thing in Israel is theirs. <verse eid="EZK 44:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 44:30"/>And the first of all the first-fruits of all, and every raised-offering of all, of all your raised-offerings, are the priests’; and you give the first of your dough to the priest, to cause a blessing to rest on your house. <verse eid="EZK 44:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 44:31"/>The priests do not eat any carcass or torn thing, from the bird or from the beast.”<verse eid="EZK 44:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 44"/>
  <chapter number="45" style="c" sid="EZK 45"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 45:1"/>“And in your causing the land to fall into inheritance, you lift up a raised-offering to YHWH, a holy [portion] of the land: the length—twenty-five thousand [is] the length, and the breadth—ten thousand; it [is] holy in all its surrounding border. <verse eid="EZK 45:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 45:2"/>There is of this for the sanctuary five hundred by five hundred, square, around; and fifty cubits of outskirt [is] around it. <verse eid="EZK 45:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 45:3"/>And by this measure you measure: the length—twenty-five thousand, and the breadth—ten thousand: and the sanctuary is in it, the Holy of Holies. <verse eid="EZK 45:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 45:4"/>It [is] the holy [portion] of the land; it is for priests, servants of the sanctuary, who are drawing near to serve YHWH; and it has been a place for their houses, and a holy place for the sanctuary. <verse eid="EZK 45:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 45:5"/>And of the twenty-five thousand of length, and of the ten thousand of breadth, there is to the Levites, servants of the house, for them—for a possession—twenty chambers. <verse eid="EZK 45:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 45:6"/>And of the possession of the city you set [an area] of five thousand breadth, and twenty-five thousand length, alongside the raised-offering of the holy [portion]; it is for all the house of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 45:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 45:7"/>And for the prince: on this side and on that side of the raised-offering of the holy place, and of the possession of the city, at the front of the raised-offering of the holy place, and at the front of the possession of the city, from the west corner westward, and from the east corner eastward—and the length [is] corresponding to one of the portions from the west border to the east border— <verse eid="EZK 45:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 45:8"/>of the land there is for a possession to him in Israel, and My princes do not oppress My people anymore, and they give the land to the house of Israel according to their tribes.” <verse eid="EZK 45:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 45:9"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: “Enough from you—princes of Israel; turn violence and spoil aside, and do judgment and righteousness; lift up your exactions from off My people—a declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 45:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 45:10"/>You must have just balances, and a just ephah, and a just bath. <verse eid="EZK 45:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 45:11"/>The ephah and the bath is of one measure, for the bath to carry a tenth of the homer, and the ephah a tenth of the homer: its measurement is according to the homer. <verse eid="EZK 45:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 45:12"/>And the shekel [is] twenty gerah: twenty shekels, twenty-five shekels, fifteen shekels—is your maneh. <verse eid="EZK 45:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 45:13"/>This [is] the raised-offering that you lift up; a sixth part of the ephah of a homer of wheat, also you have given a sixth part of the ephah of a homer of barley, <verse eid="EZK 45:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 45:14"/>and the portion of oil, the bath of oil, a tenth part of the bath out of the cor, a homer of ten baths—for ten baths [are] a homer; <verse eid="EZK 45:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 45:15"/>and one lamb out of the flock, out of two hundred, out of the watered country of Israel, for a present, and for a burnt-offering, and for peace-offerings, to make atonement by them—a declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 45:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 45:16"/>All the people of the land are at this raised-offering for the prince in Israel. <verse eid="EZK 45:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 45:17"/>And on the prince are the burnt-offerings, and the present, and the drink-offering, in celebrations, and in new moons, and in Sabbaths, in all appointed times of the house of Israel: he makes the sin-offering, and the present, and the burnt-offering, and the peace-offerings, to make atonement for the house of Israel.” <verse eid="EZK 45:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 45:18"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: “In the first [month], on the first of the month, you take a bullock, a son of the herd, a perfect one, and have cleansed the sanctuary: <verse eid="EZK 45:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 45:19"/>and the priest has taken from the blood of the sin offering, and has put [it] on the doorpost of the house, and on the four corners of the border of the altar, and on the post of the gate of the inner court. <verse eid="EZK 45:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 45:20"/>And so you do on the seventh of the month, because of each erring one, and because of the simple one—and you have purified the house. <verse eid="EZK 45:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 45:21"/>In the first [month], on the fourteenth day of the month, you have the Passover, a celebration of seven days, unleavened bread is eaten. <verse eid="EZK 45:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 45:22"/>And the prince has prepared on that day, for himself, and for all the people of the land, a bullock, a sin-offering. <verse eid="EZK 45:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 45:23"/>And [on] the seven days of the celebration he prepares a burnt-offering to YHWH, seven bullocks, and seven rams, perfect ones, daily [for] seven days, and a sin-offering, a kid of the goats, daily. <verse eid="EZK 45:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 45:24"/>And he prepares a present of an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram, and a hin of oil for an ephah. <verse eid="EZK 45:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 45:25"/>In the seventh [month], on the fifteenth day of the month, in the celebration, he does according to these things [for] seven days; as the sin-offering so the burnt-offering, and as the present so also the oil.”<verse eid="EZK 45:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 45"/>
  <chapter number="46" style="c" sid="EZK 46"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 46:1"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: “The gate of the inner court that is looking eastward is shut [during] the six days of work, and on the day of rest it is opened, and in the day of the new moon it is opened; <verse eid="EZK 46:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 46:2"/>and the prince has come in the way of the porch of the gate from the outside, and he has stood by the post of the gate, and the priests have made his burnt-offering, and his peace-offerings, and he has bowed himself by the opening of the gate, and has gone forth, and the gate is not shut until the evening. <verse eid="EZK 46:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 46:3"/>And the people of the land have bowed themselves at the opening of that gate, on Sabbaths, and on new moons, before YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 46:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 46:4"/>And the burnt-offering that the prince brings near to YHWH on the day of rest [is] six lambs, perfect ones, and a ram, a perfect one. <verse eid="EZK 46:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 46:5"/>And the present [is] an ephah for a ram, and for the lambs a present, the gift of his hand, and a hin of oil for an ephah. <verse eid="EZK 46:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 46:6"/>And on the day of the new moon—a bullock, a son of the herd, a perfect one, and six lambs and a ram; they are perfect. <verse eid="EZK 46:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 46:7"/>And with an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram, he prepares a present, and for the lambs as his hand attains, and a hin of oil for an ephah. <verse eid="EZK 46:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 46:8"/>And in the coming in of the prince, he comes in the way of the porch of the gate, and by its way he goes out. <verse eid="EZK 46:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 46:9"/>And in the coming in of the people of the land before YHWH at appointed times, he who has come in the way of the north gate to bow himself, goes out the way of the south gate, and he who has come in the way of the south gate, goes out by the way of the north gate: he does not turn back the way of the gate by which he came in, but he goes out opposite it. <verse eid="EZK 46:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 46:10"/>And in their coming in the prince in their midst comes in, and in their going out he goes out. <verse eid="EZK 46:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 46:11"/>And in celebrations, and in appointed times, the present is an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram, and for lambs the gift of his hand, and a hin of oil for an ephah. <verse eid="EZK 46:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 46:12"/>And when the prince makes a free-will burnt-offering, or free-will peace-offerings, to YHWH, then he has opened the gate that is looking eastward for himself, and has made his burnt-offering and his peace-offerings as he does in the day of rest, and he has gone out, and has shut the gate after his going out. <verse eid="EZK 46:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 46:13"/>And you make a daily burnt-offering of a lamb, son of a year, a perfect one, to YHWH; you make it morning by morning. <verse eid="EZK 46:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 46:14"/>And you make a present with it morning by morning, a sixth part of the ephah, and a third part of the hin of oil, to temper with the fine flour, a present to YHWH, by a continuous statute—continually; <verse eid="EZK 46:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 46:15"/>and they prepare the lamb, and the present, and the oil, morning by morning—a continual burnt-offering.” <verse eid="EZK 46:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 46:16"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: “When the prince gives a gift to any of his sons, it [is] his inheritance, it [is] for his sons; it [is] their possession by inheritance. <verse eid="EZK 46:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 46:17"/>And when he gives a gift out of his inheritance to one of his servants, then it has been his until the year of freedom, and it has turned back to the prince, only the inheritance of his sons is theirs. <verse eid="EZK 46:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 46:18"/>And the prince does not take from the people’s inheritance to oppress them—from their possession; he causes his sons to inherit out of his own possession, so that My people are not each scattered from his possession.” <verse eid="EZK 46:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 46:19"/>And he brings me in through the entrance that [is] by the side of the gate, to the holy chambers, to the priests, that are looking northward, and behold, there [is] a place in their two sides westward. <verse eid="EZK 46:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 46:20"/>And he says to me, “This [is] the place where the priests boil the guilt-offering and the sin-offering, where they bake the present, so as not to bring [it] out to the outer court, to sanctify the people.” <verse eid="EZK 46:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 46:21"/>And he brings me out to the outer court, and causes me to pass over to the four corners of the court, and behold, a court in a corner of the court, [moreover] a court in [every] corner of the corner. <verse eid="EZK 46:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 46:22"/>In the four corners of the court [are] enclosed courts, forty long and thirty broad, [with] one measure for the four corners. <verse eid="EZK 46:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 46:23"/>And a row [is] all around in them—around the four of them—and made with boilers under the rows all around. <verse eid="EZK 46:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 46:24"/>And he says to me, “These [are] the houses of those boiling where the servants of the house boil the sacrifice of the people.”<verse eid="EZK 46:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 46"/>
  <chapter number="47" style="c" sid="EZK 47"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 47:1"/>And he causes me to turn back to the opening of the house; and behold, water is coming forth from under the threshold of the house eastward, for the front of the house [is] eastward, and the water is coming down from beneath, from the right side of the house, from south of the altar. <verse eid="EZK 47:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 47:2"/>And he causes me to go out the way of the gate northward, and causes me to turn around the way outside, to the gate that [is] outside, the way that is looking eastward, and behold, water is coming forth from the right side. <verse eid="EZK 47:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 47:3"/>In the going out of the man eastward—and a line in his hand—then he measures one thousand by the cubit, and he causes me to pass over into the waters—waters [to my] ankles. <verse eid="EZK 47:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 47:4"/>And he measures one thousand, and causes me to pass over into the waters—waters [to my] knees. And he measures one thousand, and causes me to pass over—waters [to my] loins. <verse eid="EZK 47:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 47:5"/>And he measures one thousand—a stream that I am not able to pass over; for the waters have risen—waters to swim in—a stream that is not passed over. <verse eid="EZK 47:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 47:6"/>And he says to me, “Have you seen, son of man?” And he leads me, and brings me back to the edge of the stream. <verse eid="EZK 47:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 47:7"/>In my turning back, then, behold, at the edge of the stream [are] very many trees, on this side and on that side. <verse eid="EZK 47:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 47:8"/>And he says to me, “These waters are going forth to the east circuit, and have gone down to the desert, and have entered the sea; they are brought forth to the sea, and the waters have been healed. <verse eid="EZK 47:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 47:9"/>And it has come to pass, every living creature that teems, wherever the streams come, lives: and there has been great abundance of fish, for these waters have come there, and they are healed; and everything to where the stream comes has lived. <verse eid="EZK 47:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 47:10"/>And it has come to pass, fishers stand by it, from En-Gedi even to En-Eglaim; they are a spreading place for the nets; their fish are of the same kind as the fish of the Great Sea—very many. <verse eid="EZK 47:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 47:11"/>Its miry and its marshy places—they are not healed; they have been given up to salt. <verse eid="EZK 47:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 47:12"/>And there comes up by the stream, on its edge, on this side and on that side, every [kind of] fruit-tree whose leaf does not fade, and its fruit is not consumed, it yields first-fruits according to its months, because its waters are coming forth from the sanctuary; and its fruits have been for food, and its leaf for medicine.” <verse eid="EZK 47:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 47:13"/>Thus said Lord YHWH: “This [is] the border whereby you inherit the land, according to the twelve tribes of Israel; Joseph [has two] portions. <verse eid="EZK 47:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 47:14"/>And you have inherited it, one as well as another, in that I have lifted up My hand to give it to your fathers; and this land has fallen to you in inheritance. <verse eid="EZK 47:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 47:15"/>And this [is] the border of the land at the north quarter; from the Great Sea, the way of Hethlon, at the coming in to Zedad: <verse eid="EZK 47:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 47:16"/>Hamath, Berothah, Sibraim, that [is] between the border of Damascus and the border of Hamath; Hazar-Hatticon, that [is] at the coast of Havran. <verse eid="EZK 47:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 47:17"/>And the border from the sea has been Hazar-Enan, the border of Damascus, and Zaphon at the north, and the border of Hamath: and [this is] the north quarter. <verse eid="EZK 47:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 47:18"/>And the east quarter [is] from between Havran, and Damascus, and Gilead, and the land of Israel, [to] the Jordan; you measure from the border on the Eastern Sea: and [this is] the east quarter. <verse eid="EZK 47:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 47:19"/>And the south quarter southward [is] from Tamar to the waters of Meriboth-Kadesh, the stream to the Great Sea: and [this is] the south quarter southward. <verse eid="EZK 47:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 47:20"/>And the west quarter [is] the Great Sea, from the border until opposite the coming in to Hamath: this [is] the west quarter. <verse eid="EZK 47:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 47:21"/>And you have divided this land to yourselves, according to the tribes of Israel; <verse eid="EZK 47:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 47:22"/>and it has come to pass, you separate it for an inheritance to yourselves, and to the sojourners who are sojourning in your midst, who have begotten sons in your midst, and they have been to you as native, with the sons of Israel; they are separated with you for an inheritance in the midst of the tribes of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 47:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 47:23"/>And it has come to pass, in the tribe with which the sojourner sojourns, there you give his inheritance,” a declaration of Lord YHWH.<verse eid="EZK 47:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 47"/>
  <chapter number="48" style="c" sid="EZK 48"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EZK 48:1"/>“And these [are] the names of the tribes: from the north end to the side of the way of Hethlon, at the coming in to Hamath, Hazar-Enan, the border of Damascus northward, in the direction of Hamath, and they have been his—east side to west, Dan, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EZK 48:2"/>and by the border of Dan, from the east side to the west side, Asher, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EZK 48:3"/>and by the border of Asher, from the east side even to the west side, Naphtali, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EZK 48:4"/>and by the border of Naphtali, from the east side to the west side, Manasseh, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EZK 48:5"/>and by the border of Manasseh, from the east side to the west side, Ephraim, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EZK 48:6"/>and by the border of Ephraim, from the east side even to the west side, Reuben, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EZK 48:7"/>and by the border of Reuben, from the east side to the west side, Judah, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EZK 48:8"/>and by the border of Judah, from the east side to the west side is the raised-offering that you lift up, twenty-five thousand [cubits] broad and long, as one of the parts, from the east side to the west side: and the sanctuary has been in its midst. <verse eid="EZK 48:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EZK 48:9"/>The raised-offering that you lift up to YHWH [is] twenty-five thousand long and ten thousand broad. <verse eid="EZK 48:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EZK 48:10"/>And of these is the holy raised-offering for the priests, northward twenty-five thousand, and westward ten thousand [in] breadth, and eastward ten thousand [in] breadth, and southward twenty-five thousand [in] length: and the sanctuary of YHWH has been in its midst. <verse eid="EZK 48:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EZK 48:11"/>For the priests who are sanctified of the sons of Zadok, who have kept My charge, who did not err in the erring of the sons of Israel, as the Levites erred, <verse eid="EZK 48:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EZK 48:12"/>even the raised-offering has been for them, out of the raised-offering of the land, most holy, by the border of the Levites. <verse eid="EZK 48:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EZK 48:13"/>And [to] the Levites alongside the border of the priests [are] twenty-five thousand [in] length, and ten thousand [in] breadth, all the length [is] twenty-five thousand, and the breadth ten thousand. <verse eid="EZK 48:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EZK 48:14"/>And they do not sell of it, nor exchange, nor cause the first-fruit of the land to pass away: for [it is] holy to YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 48:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EZK 48:15"/>And the five thousand that is left in the breadth, on the front of the twenty-five thousand, is common—for the city, for dwelling, and for outskirt, and the city has been in its midst. <verse eid="EZK 48:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EZK 48:16"/>And these [are] its measurements: the north side—four thousand and five hundred, and the south side—four thousand and five hundred, and on the east side—four thousand and five hundred, and the west side—four thousand and five hundred. <verse eid="EZK 48:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EZK 48:17"/>And the outskirt of the city has been northward—two hundred and fifty, and southward—two hundred and fifty, and eastward—two hundred and fifty, and westward—two hundred and fifty. <verse eid="EZK 48:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EZK 48:18"/>And the remainder in length alongside the raised-offering of the holy [portion is] ten thousand eastward, and ten thousand westward, and it has been alongside the raised-offering of the holy [portion], and its increase has been for food for those serving the city, <verse eid="EZK 48:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EZK 48:19"/>even [to] him who is serving the city, they serve it out of all the tribes of Israel. <verse eid="EZK 48:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EZK 48:20"/>All the raised-offering [is] twenty-five thousand by twenty-five thousand square—you lift up the raised-offering of the holy [portion] with the possession of the city. <verse eid="EZK 48:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EZK 48:21"/>And the remainder [is] for the prince, on this side and on that side of the raised-offering of the holy [portion], and of the possession of the city, on the front of the twenty-five thousand of the raised-offering to the east border, and westward, on the front of the twenty-five thousand on the west border, alongside the portions of the prince; and the raised-offering of the holy [portion], and the sanctuary of the house, has been in its midst. <verse eid="EZK 48:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EZK 48:22"/>And from the possession of the Levites, from the possession of the city, in the midst of that which is for the prince, between the border of Judah and the border of Benjamin, there is for the prince. <verse eid="EZK 48:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EZK 48:23"/>As for the rest of the tribes, from the east side to the west side, Benjamin, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EZK 48:24"/>and by the border of Benjamin, from the east side to the west side, Simeon, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EZK 48:25"/>and by the border of Simeon, from the east side to the west side, Issachar, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EZK 48:26"/>and by the border of Issachar, from the east side to the west side, Zebulun, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EZK 48:27"/>and by the border of Zebulun, from the east side to the west side, Gad, one [portion]; <verse eid="EZK 48:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EZK 48:28"/>and by the border of Gad, at the south side southward, the border has been from Tamar [to] the waters of Meriboth-Kadesh, the stream by the Great Sea. <verse eid="EZK 48:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EZK 48:29"/>This [is] the land that you separate by inheritance to the tribes of Israel, and these [are] their divisions,” a declaration of Lord YHWH. <verse eid="EZK 48:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EZK 48:30"/>“And these [are] the outgoings of the city: on the north side, four thousand and five hundred measures; <verse eid="EZK 48:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EZK 48:31"/>and the gates of the city [are] according to the names of the tribes of Israel; three gates northward—one gate of Reuben, one gate of Judah, one gate of Levi. <verse eid="EZK 48:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EZK 48:32"/>And on the east side, four thousand and five hundred, and three gates—one gate of Joseph, one gate of Benjamin, one gate of Dan. <verse eid="EZK 48:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EZK 48:33"/>And the south side, four thousand and five hundred, and three gates—one gate of Simeon, one gate of Issachar, one gate of Zebulun. <verse eid="EZK 48:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="EZK 48:34"/>The west side, four thousand and five hundred, [with] their three gates—one gate of Gad, one gate of Asher, one gate of Naphtali. <verse eid="EZK 48:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="EZK 48:35"/>[It is] eighteen thousand around, and the renown of the city [is] from the day YHWH [is] there.”<verse eid="EZK 48:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EZK 48"/>
</usx>
