<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JHN" style="id">- Literal Standard Version</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">John</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Gospel of John</para>
  <para style="toc2">John</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jhn</para>
  <para style="mt">John</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JHN 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 1:1"/>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God; <verse eid="JHN 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 1:2"/>this One was in the beginning with God; <verse eid="JHN 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 1:3"/>all things happened through Him, and without Him not even one thing happened that has happened. <verse eid="JHN 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 1:4"/>In Him was life, and the life was the light of men, <verse eid="JHN 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 1:5"/>and the light shined in the darkness, and the darkness did not perceive it. <verse eid="JHN 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 1:6"/>There came a man—having been sent from God—whose name [is] John, <verse eid="JHN 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 1:7"/>this one came for testimony, that he might testify about the Light, that all might believe through him; <verse eid="JHN 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 1:8"/>that one was not the Light, but—that he might testify about the Light. <verse eid="JHN 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 1:9"/>He was the true Light, which enlightens every man, coming into the world; <verse eid="JHN 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 1:10"/>He was in the world, and the world was made through Him, and the world did not know Him: <verse eid="JHN 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 1:11"/>He came to [His] own, and [His] own did not receive Him; <verse eid="JHN 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 1:12"/>but as many as received Him, to them He gave authority to become sons of God—to those believing in His Name, <verse eid="JHN 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 1:13"/>who were begotten, not of blood, nor of will of flesh, nor of will of man, but of God. <verse eid="JHN 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 1:14"/>And the Word became flesh, and dwelt among us, and we beheld His glory, glory as of [the] only begotten of [the] Father, full of grace and truth. <verse eid="JHN 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 1:15"/>John testifies concerning Him, and has cried, saying, “This was He of whom I said, He who is coming after me has come before me, for He was before me.” <verse eid="JHN 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 1:16"/>And we all received out of His fullness, and grace for grace; <verse eid="JHN 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 1:17"/>for the Law was given through Moses, the grace and the truth came through Jesus Christ. <verse eid="JHN 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 1:18"/>No one has ever seen God; the only begotten God who is on the bosom of the Father—He has expounded [Him]. <verse eid="JHN 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 1:19"/>And this is the testimony of John when the Jews sent priests and Levites out of Jerusalem, that they might question him, “Who are you?” <verse eid="JHN 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 1:20"/>And he confessed and did not deny, and confessed, “I am not the Christ.” <verse eid="JHN 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 1:21"/>And they questioned him, “What then? Are you Elijah?” And he says, “I am not.” “Are you the prophet?” And he answered, “No.” <verse eid="JHN 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 1:22"/>Then they said to him, “Who are you, that we may give an answer to those sending us? What do you say concerning yourself?” <verse eid="JHN 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 1:23"/>He said, “I [am] a voice of one crying in the wilderness: Make straight the way of the LORD, as Isaiah the prophet said.” <verse eid="JHN 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 1:24"/>And those sent were of the Pharisees, <verse eid="JHN 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 1:25"/>and they questioned him and said to him, “Why, then, do you immerse, if you are not the Christ, nor Elijah, nor the prophet?” <verse eid="JHN 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 1:26"/>John answered them, saying, “I immerse in water, but in the midst of you has stood He whom you have not known, it is this One who is coming after me, who has been before me, <verse eid="JHN 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 1:27"/>of whom I am not worthy that I may loose the strap of His sandal.” <verse eid="JHN 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 1:28"/>These things came to pass in Bethabara, beyond the Jordan, where John was immersing. <verse eid="JHN 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 1:29"/>On the next day John sees Jesus coming to him and says, “Behold, the Lamb of God, who is taking away the sin of the world; <verse eid="JHN 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 1:30"/>this is He concerning whom I said, After me comes a Man who has come before me, because He was before me: <verse eid="JHN 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 1:31"/>and I did not know Him, but that He might be revealed to Israel, because of this I came immersing in water.” <verse eid="JHN 1:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 1:32"/>And John testified, saying, “I have seen the Spirit coming down out of Heaven as a dove, and [that] One remained on Him; <verse eid="JHN 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 1:33"/>and I did not know Him, but He who sent me to immerse in water, He said to me, On whomsoever you may see the Spirit coming down, and remaining on Him, this is He who is immersing in the Holy Spirit; <verse eid="JHN 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 1:34"/>and I have seen, and have testified, that this is the Son of God.” <verse eid="JHN 1:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 1:35"/>On the next day, again, John was standing, and two of his disciples, <verse eid="JHN 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 1:36"/>and having looked on Jesus walking, he says, “Behold, the Lamb of God”; <verse eid="JHN 1:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 1:37"/>and the two disciples heard him speaking, and they followed Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 1:38"/>And Jesus having turned, and having beheld them following, says to them, “What do you seek?” And they said to Him, “Rabbi” (which is, being interpreted, Teacher), “where do You remain?” <verse eid="JHN 1:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 1:39"/>He says to them, “Come and see”; they came and saw where He remains, and they remained with Him that day and the hour was about the tenth. <verse eid="JHN 1:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 1:40"/>Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, was one of the two who heard from John, and followed Him; <verse eid="JHN 1:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 1:41"/>this one first finds his own brother Simon and says to him, “We have found the Messiah,” (which is, being interpreted, Anointed One), <verse eid="JHN 1:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 1:42"/>and he brought him to Jesus: and having looked on him, Jesus says, “You are Simon, the son of Jonas, you will be called Cephas,” (which is interpreted, A rock). <verse eid="JHN 1:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 1:43"/>On the next day He willed to go forth to Galilee, and He finds Philip and says to him, “Follow Me.” <verse eid="JHN 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 1:44"/>And Philip was from Bethsaida, of the city of Andrew and Peter; <verse eid="JHN 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 1:45"/>Philip finds Nathanael and says to him, “Him of whom Moses wrote in the Law, and the Prophets, we have found, Jesus the Son of Joseph, who [is] from Nazareth!” <verse eid="JHN 1:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 1:46"/>And Nathanael said to him, “Is any good thing able to be out of Nazareth?” Philip said to him, “Come and see.” <verse eid="JHN 1:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 1:47"/>Jesus saw Nathanael coming to Him, and He says concerning him, “Behold, truly an Israelite, in whom is no guile”; <verse eid="JHN 1:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 1:48"/>Nathanael says to Him, “From where do You know me?” Jesus answered and said to him, “Before Philip’s calling you, being under the fig tree, I saw you.” <verse eid="JHN 1:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 1:49"/>Nathanael answered and says to Him, “Rabbi, You are the Son of God, You are the King of Israel.” <verse eid="JHN 1:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 1:50"/>Jesus answered and said to him, “Because I said to you, I saw you under the fig tree, you believe; you will see greater things than these”; <verse eid="JHN 1:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 1:51"/>and He says to him, “Truly, truly, I say to you, from now on you will see Heaven opened, and the messengers of God going up and coming down on the Son of Man.”<verse eid="JHN 1:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JHN 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 2:1"/>And [on] the third day a wedding happened in Cana of Galilee, and the mother of Jesus was there, <verse eid="JHN 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 2:2"/>and also Jesus was called, and His disciples, to the wedding; <verse eid="JHN 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 2:3"/>and wine having failed, the mother of Jesus says to Him, “They have no wine”; <verse eid="JHN 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 2:4"/>Jesus says to her, “What [is that] to Me and to you, woman? My hour is not yet come.” <verse eid="JHN 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 2:5"/>His mother says to the servants, “Whatever He may say to you—do.” <verse eid="JHN 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 2:6"/>And there were six water-jugs of stone there, placed according to the purifying of the Jews, holding each two or three measures. <verse eid="JHN 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 2:7"/>Jesus says to them, “Fill the water-jugs with water”; and they filled them—to the brim; <verse eid="JHN 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 2:8"/>and He says to them, “Draw out, now, and carry to the headwaiter”; and they bore. <verse eid="JHN 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 2:9"/>And as the headwaiter tasted the water become wine, and did not know where it is from (but the servants knew, who have drawn the water), the headwaiter calls the bridegroom, <verse eid="JHN 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 2:10"/>and says to him, “Every man, at first, sets forth the good wine; and when they may have drunk freely, then the inferior; you kept the good wine until now.” <verse eid="JHN 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 2:11"/>This [is the] beginning of the signs Jesus did in Cana of Galilee, and revealed His glory, and His disciples believed in Him; <verse eid="JHN 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 2:12"/>after this He went down to Capernaum, He, and His mother, and His brothers, and His disciples; and they did not remain there many days. <verse eid="JHN 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 2:13"/>And the Passover of the Jews was near, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem, <verse eid="JHN 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 2:14"/>and He found in the temple those selling oxen, and sheep, and doves, and the money-changers sitting, <verse eid="JHN 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 2:15"/>and having made a whip of small cords, He put all forth out of the temple, also the sheep, and the oxen; and He poured out the coins of the money-changers, and He overthrew the tables, <verse eid="JHN 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 2:16"/>and He said to those selling the doves, “Take these things from here; do not make the house of My Father a house of merchandise.” <verse eid="JHN 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 2:17"/>And His disciples remembered that it is written: “The zeal of Your house ate Me up”; <verse eid="JHN 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 2:18"/>the Jews then answered and said to Him, “What sign do You show to us—that You do these things?” <verse eid="JHN 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 2:19"/>Jesus answered and said to them, “Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up.” <verse eid="JHN 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 2:20"/>The Jews, therefore, said, “This temple was built [in] forty-six years, and will You raise it up in three days?” <verse eid="JHN 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 2:21"/>But He spoke concerning the temple of His body; <verse eid="JHN 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 2:22"/>when, then, He was raised out of the dead, His disciples remembered that He said this to them, and they believed the Writing, and the word that Jesus said. <verse eid="JHN 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 2:23"/>And as He was in Jerusalem, in the Passover, in the celebration, many believed in His Name, beholding His signs that He was doing; <verse eid="JHN 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 2:24"/>and Jesus Himself was not trusting Himself to them, because of His knowing all [men], <verse eid="JHN 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 2:25"/>and because He had no need that any should testify concerning man, for He Himself was knowing what was in man.<verse eid="JHN 2:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JHN 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 3:1"/>And there was a man of the Pharisees, his name Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews; <verse eid="JHN 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 3:2"/>this one came to Him by night and said to Him, “Rabbi, we have known that You have come from God—a teacher, for no one is able to do these signs that You do, if God may not be with him.” <verse eid="JHN 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 3:3"/>Jesus answered and said to him, “Truly, truly, I say to you, if anyone may not be born from above, he is not able to see the Kingdom of God”; <verse eid="JHN 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 3:4"/>Nicodemus says to Him, “How is a man able to be born, being old? Is he able to enter into the womb of his mother a second time, and to be born?” <verse eid="JHN 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 3:5"/>Jesus answered, “Truly, truly, I say to you, if anyone may not be born of water and the Spirit, he is not able to enter into the Kingdom of God; <verse eid="JHN 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 3:6"/>that which has been born of the flesh is flesh, and that which has been born of the Spirit is spirit. <verse eid="JHN 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 3:7"/>You may not wonder that I said to you, It is required for you to be born from above; <verse eid="JHN 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 3:8"/>the Spirit blows where [that] One wills, and you hear [that] One’s voice, but you have not known from where [that] One comes, and to where [that] One goes; thus is everyone who has been born of the Spirit.” <verse eid="JHN 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 3:9"/>Nicodemus answered and said to Him, “How are these things able to happen?” <verse eid="JHN 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 3:10"/>Jesus answered and said to him, “You are the teacher of Israel and you do not know these things? <verse eid="JHN 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 3:11"/>Truly, truly, I say to you, what We have known We speak, and what We have seen We testify, and you do not receive Our testimony; <verse eid="JHN 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 3:12"/>if I spoke to you of the earthly things, and you do not believe, how, if I will speak to you of the heavenly things, will you believe? <verse eid="JHN 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 3:13"/>And no one has gone up to Heaven, except He who came down out of Heaven—the Son of Man who is in Heaven. <verse eid="JHN 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 3:14"/>And as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, so it is necessary for the Son of Man to be lifted up, <verse eid="JHN 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 3:15"/>that everyone who is believing in Him may not perish, but may have continuous life, <verse eid="JHN 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 3:16"/>for God so loved the world that He gave the only begotten Son, that everyone who is believing in Him may not perish, but may have continuous life. <verse eid="JHN 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 3:17"/>For God did not send His Son into the world that He may judge the world, but that the world may be saved through Him; <verse eid="JHN 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 3:18"/>he who is believing in Him is not judged, but he who is not believing has been judged already, because he has not believed in the Name of the only begotten Son of God. <verse eid="JHN 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 3:19"/>And this is the judgment, that the light has come into the world, and men loved the darkness rather than the light, for their works were evil; <verse eid="JHN 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 3:20"/>for everyone who is doing wicked things hates the light, and does not come into the light, that his works may not be detected; <verse eid="JHN 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 3:21"/>but he who is doing the truth comes into the light, that his works may be revealed, that in God they are having been worked.” <verse eid="JHN 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 3:22"/>After these things Jesus and His disciples came into the land of Judea, and there He tarried with them, and was immersing; <verse eid="JHN 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 3:23"/>and John was also immersing in Aenon, near to Salem, because there were many waters there, and they were coming and were being immersed— <verse eid="JHN 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 3:24"/>for John was not yet cast into the prison— <verse eid="JHN 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 3:25"/>there arose then a question from the disciples of John with [some] Jews about purifying, <verse eid="JHN 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 3:26"/>and they came to John and said to him, “Rabbi, He who was with you beyond the Jordan, to whom you testified, behold, this One is immersing, and all are coming to Him.” <verse eid="JHN 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 3:27"/>John answered and said, “A man is not able to receive anything if it may not have been given him from Heaven; <verse eid="JHN 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 3:28"/>you yourselves testify to me that I said, I am not the Christ, but that I am having been sent before Him; <verse eid="JHN 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 3:29"/>He who is having the bride is bridegroom, and the friend of the bridegroom, who is standing and hearing Him, rejoices with joy because of the voice of the bridegroom; this, then, my joy has been fulfilled. <verse eid="JHN 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 3:30"/>It is necessary [for] Him to increase, and me to become less; <verse eid="JHN 3:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 3:31"/>He who is coming from above is above all; he who is from the earth, from the earth he is, and from the earth he speaks; He who is coming from Heaven is above all. <verse eid="JHN 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 3:32"/>And what He has seen and heard—this He testifies, and none receives His testimony; <verse eid="JHN 3:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 3:33"/>he who is receiving His testimony sealed that God is true; <verse eid="JHN 3:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 3:34"/>for He whom God sent, He speaks the sayings of God; for God does not give the Spirit by measure; <verse eid="JHN 3:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 3:35"/>the Father loves the Son, and has given all things into His hand; <verse eid="JHN 3:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 3:36"/>he who is believing in the Son has continuous life; and he who is not believing the Son will not see life, but the wrath of God remains on him.”<verse eid="JHN 3:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JHN 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 4:1"/>When therefore the LORD knew that the Pharisees heard that Jesus makes and immerses more disciples than John, <verse eid="JHN 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 4:2"/>(though indeed Jesus Himself was not immersing, but His disciples), <verse eid="JHN 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 4:3"/>He left Judea and went away again to Galilee, <verse eid="JHN 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 4:4"/>and it was necessary [for] Him to go through Samaria. <verse eid="JHN 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 4:5"/>He comes, therefore, to a city of Samaria, called Sychar, near to the place that Jacob gave to his son Joseph; <verse eid="JHN 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 4:6"/>and there was there a well of Jacob. Jesus therefore having been weary from the journeying, was thus sitting on the well; it was as it were the sixth hour; <verse eid="JHN 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 4:7"/>there comes a woman out of Samaria to draw water. Jesus says to her, “Give Me to drink”; <verse eid="JHN 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 4:8"/>for His disciples were gone away into the city that they may buy food; <verse eid="JHN 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 4:9"/>the Samaritan woman therefore says to Him, “How do You, being a Jew, ask drink from me, being a Samaritan woman?” For Jews have no dealing with Samaritans. <verse eid="JHN 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 4:10"/>Jesus answered and said to her, “If you had known the gift of God, and who it is who is saying to you, Give Me to drink, you would have asked Him, and He would have given you living water.” <verse eid="JHN 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 4:11"/>The woman says to Him, “Lord, You do not even have a vessel to draw with, and the well is deep; from where, then, have You the living water? <verse eid="JHN 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 4:12"/>Are You greater than our father Jacob, who gave us the well, and himself drank out of it, and his sons, and his livestock?” <verse eid="JHN 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 4:13"/>Jesus answered and said to her, “Everyone who is drinking of this water will thirst again; <verse eid="JHN 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 4:14"/>but whoever may drink of the water that I will give him, may not thirst—throughout the age; and the water that I will give him will become in him a well of water, springing up to continuous life.” <verse eid="JHN 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 4:15"/>The woman says to Him, “Lord, give me this water, that I may not thirst, nor come here to draw.” <verse eid="JHN 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 4:16"/>Jesus says to her, “Go, call your husband, and come here”; <verse eid="JHN 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 4:17"/>the woman answered and said, “I do not have a husband.” Jesus says to her, “Well did you say—I do not have a husband; <verse eid="JHN 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 4:18"/>for you have had five husbands, and now, he whom you have is not your husband; you have said this correctly.” <verse eid="JHN 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 4:19"/>The woman says to Him, “Lord, I perceive that You are a prophet; <verse eid="JHN 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 4:20"/>our fathers worshiped in this mountain, and You say that in Jerusalem is the place where it is required to worship.” <verse eid="JHN 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 4:21"/>Jesus says to her, “Woman, believe Me, that there comes an hour when neither in this mountain, nor in Jerusalem, will you worship the Father; <verse eid="JHN 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 4:22"/>you worship what you have not known; we worship what we have known, because salvation is of the Jews; <verse eid="JHN 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 4:23"/>but there comes an hour, and it now is, when the true worshipers will worship the Father in spirit and truth, for the Father also seeks such to worship Him; <verse eid="JHN 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 4:24"/>God [is] Spirit, and those worshiping Him should worship in spirit and truth.” <verse eid="JHN 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 4:25"/>The woman says to Him, “I have known that Messiah comes, who is called Christ, when that One may come, He will tell us all things”; <verse eid="JHN 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 4:26"/>Jesus says to her, “I who am speaking to you am [He].” <verse eid="JHN 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 4:27"/>And on this came His disciples, and were wondering that He was speaking with a woman, no one, however, said, “What do You seek?” Or “Why do You speak with her?” <verse eid="JHN 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 4:28"/>The woman then left her water-jug and went away into the city, and says to the men, <verse eid="JHN 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 4:29"/>“Come, see a Man who told me all things—as many as I did; is this the Christ?” <verse eid="JHN 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 4:30"/>They went forth therefore out of the city, and were coming to Him. <verse eid="JHN 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 4:31"/>And in the meanwhile His disciples were asking Him, saying, “Rabbi, eat”; <verse eid="JHN 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 4:32"/>and He said to them, “I have food to eat that you have not known.” <verse eid="JHN 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 4:33"/>The disciples then said to one another, “Did anyone bring Him anything to eat?” <verse eid="JHN 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 4:34"/>Jesus says to them, “My food is that I may do the will of Him who sent Me, and may finish His work; <verse eid="JHN 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 4:35"/>do not say that it is yet four months, and the harvest comes; behold, I say to you, lift up your eyes, and see the fields, that they are white to harvest already. <verse eid="JHN 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 4:36"/>And he who is reaping receives a reward, and gathers fruit to continuous life, that both he who is sowing and he who is reaping may rejoice together; <verse eid="JHN 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 4:37"/>for in this the saying is the true one, that one is the sower and another the reaper. <verse eid="JHN 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 4:38"/>I sent you to reap on that which you have not labored; others labored, and you have entered into their labor.” <verse eid="JHN 4:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 4:39"/>And many from that city believed in Him, of the Samaritans, because of the word of the woman testifying, “He told me all things—as many as I did.” <verse eid="JHN 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 4:40"/>When, then, the Samaritans came to Him, they were asking Him to remain with them, and He remained there two days; <verse eid="JHN 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 4:41"/>and many more believed because of His word, <verse eid="JHN 4:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 4:42"/>and said to the woman, “We no longer believe because of your speaking; for we ourselves have heard and known that this is truly the Savior of the world—the Christ.” <verse eid="JHN 4:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 4:43"/>And after the two days He went forth from there, and went away to Galilee, <verse eid="JHN 4:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 4:44"/>for Jesus Himself testified that a prophet will not have honor in his own country; <verse eid="JHN 4:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 4:45"/>when then, He came to Galilee, the Galileans received Him, having seen all things that He did in Jerusalem in the celebration—for they also went to the celebration. <verse eid="JHN 4:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 4:46"/>Jesus came, therefore, again to Cana of Galilee, where He made the water wine, and there was a certain attendant, whose son was ailing in Capernaum, <verse eid="JHN 4:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 4:47"/>he, having heard that Jesus comes out of Judea to Galilee, went away to Him, and was asking Him that He may come down and may heal his son, for he was about to die. <verse eid="JHN 4:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 4:48"/>Jesus then said to him, “If you may not see signs and wonders, you will not believe.” <verse eid="JHN 4:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 4:49"/>The attendant says to Him, “Lord, come down before my child dies”; <verse eid="JHN 4:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 4:50"/>Jesus says to him, “Be going on; your son lives.” And the man believed the word that Jesus said to him, and was going on, <verse eid="JHN 4:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 4:51"/>and he now going down, his servants met him, and told, saying, “Your child lives”; <verse eid="JHN 4:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 4:52"/>he inquired then of them the hour in which he became better, and they said to him, “Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him”; <verse eid="JHN 4:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 4:53"/>then the father knew that [it was] in that hour in which Jesus said to him, “Your son lives,” and he himself believed, and his whole house; <verse eid="JHN 4:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 4:54"/>this again [was] a second sign Jesus did, having come out of Judea to Galilee.<verse eid="JHN 4:54"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JHN 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 5:1"/>After these things there was a celebration of the Jews, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem, <verse eid="JHN 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 5:2"/>and there is in Jerusalem by the sheep-[gate] a pool that is called in Hebrew Bethesda, having five porches, <verse eid="JHN 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 5:3"/>in these were lying a great multitude of the ailing, blind, lame, withered, <char style="bd">[[</char>waiting for the moving of the water, <verse eid="JHN 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 5:4"/>for a messenger at a set time was going down in the pool, and was troubling the water, the first then having gone in after the troubling of the water, became whole of whatever sickness he was held.<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="JHN 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 5:5"/>And there was a certain man there being in ailment thirty-eight years, <verse eid="JHN 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 5:6"/>him Jesus having seen lying, and having known that he is already a long time, He says to him, “Do you wish to become whole?” <verse eid="JHN 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 5:7"/>The ailing man answered Him, “Lord, I have no man, that, when the water may be troubled, he may put me into the pool, and while I am coming, another goes down before me.” <verse eid="JHN 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 5:8"/>Jesus says to him, “Rise, take up your pallet, and be walking”; <verse eid="JHN 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 5:9"/>and immediately the man became whole, and he took up his pallet, and was walking, and it was a Sabbath on that day, <verse eid="JHN 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 5:10"/>the Jews then said to him that has been healed, “It is a Sabbath; it is not lawful to you to take up the pallet.” <verse eid="JHN 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 5:11"/>He answered them, “He who made me whole—that One said to me, Take up your pallet, and be walking”; <verse eid="JHN 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 5:12"/>they questioned him, then, “Who is the Man who is saying to you, Take up your bed and be walking?” <verse eid="JHN 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 5:13"/>But he that was healed had not known who He is, for Jesus moved away, a multitude being in the place. <verse eid="JHN 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 5:14"/>After these things, Jesus finds him in the temple and said to him, “Behold, you have become whole; sin no more, lest something worse may happen to you.” <verse eid="JHN 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 5:15"/>The man went away, and told the Jews that it is Jesus who made him whole, <verse eid="JHN 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 5:16"/>and because of this were the Jews persecuting Jesus, and seeking to kill Him, because these things He was doing on a Sabbath. <verse eid="JHN 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 5:17"/>And Jesus answered them, “My Father works until now, and I work”; <verse eid="JHN 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 5:18"/>because of this, then, were the Jews seeking the more to kill Him, because not only was He breaking the Sabbath, but He also called God His own Father, making Himself equal to God. <verse eid="JHN 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 5:19"/>Jesus therefore responded and said to them, “Truly, truly, I say to you, the Son is not able to do anything of Himself, if He may not see the Father doing anything; for whatever things He may do, these also the Son does in like manner; <verse eid="JHN 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 5:20"/>for the Father cherishes the Son, and shows to Him all things that He Himself does; and greater works than these He will show Him, that you may wonder. <verse eid="JHN 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 5:21"/>For as the Father raises the dead, and makes alive, so also the Son makes alive whom He wills; <verse eid="JHN 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 5:22"/>for neither does the Father judge anyone, but all the judgment He has given to the Son, <verse eid="JHN 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 5:23"/>that all may honor the Son according as they honor the Father; he who is not honoring the Son, does not honor the Father who sent Him. <verse eid="JHN 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 5:24"/>Truly, truly, I say to you, he who is hearing My word, and is believing Him who sent Me, has continuous life, and he does not come into judgment, but has passed out of death into life. <verse eid="JHN 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 5:25"/>Truly, truly, I say to you, [that] there comes an hour, and it now is, when the dead will hear the voice of the Son of God, and those having heard will live; <verse eid="JHN 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 5:26"/>for as the Father has life in Himself, so He gave also to the Son to have life in Himself, <verse eid="JHN 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 5:27"/>and authority He gave Him also to do judgment, because He is Son of Man. <verse eid="JHN 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 5:28"/>Do not wonder at this, because there comes an hour in which all those in the tombs will hear His voice, <verse eid="JHN 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 5:29"/>and they will come forth; those who did good things to a resurrection of life, and those who practiced evil things to a resurrection of judgment. <verse eid="JHN 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 5:30"/>I am not able of Myself to do anything; according as I hear I judge, and My judgment is righteous, because I do not seek My own will, but the will of the Father who sent Me. <verse eid="JHN 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 5:31"/>If I testify concerning Myself, My testimony is not true; <verse eid="JHN 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 5:32"/>there is another who is testifying concerning Me, and I have known that the testimony that He testifies concerning Me is true; <verse eid="JHN 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 5:33"/>you have sent to John, and he has testified to the truth. <verse eid="JHN 5:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 5:34"/>But I do not receive testimony from man, but these things I say that you may be saved; <verse eid="JHN 5:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 5:35"/>he was the burning and shining lamp, and you willed to be glad, for an hour, in his light. <verse eid="JHN 5:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 5:36"/>But I have the testimony greater than John’s, for the works that the Father gave Me, that I might finish them, the works themselves that I do, they testify concerning Me, that the Father has sent Me. <verse eid="JHN 5:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 5:37"/>And the Father who sent Me has testified Himself concerning Me; you have neither heard His voice at any time, nor have you seen His appearance; <verse eid="JHN 5:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 5:38"/>and you do not have His word remaining in you, because you do not believe Him whom He sent. <verse eid="JHN 5:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 5:39"/>You search the Writings, because you think in them to have continuous life, and these are they that are testifying concerning Me; <verse eid="JHN 5:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 5:40"/>and you do not will to come to Me, that you may have life; <verse eid="JHN 5:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 5:41"/>I do not receive glory from man, <verse eid="JHN 5:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 5:42"/>but I have known you, that you do not have the love of God in yourselves. <verse eid="JHN 5:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 5:43"/>I have come in the Name of My Father, and you do not receive Me; if another may come in his own name, him you will receive; <verse eid="JHN 5:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 5:44"/>how are you able—you—to believe, receiving glory from one another, and the glory that [is] from God alone you do not seek? <verse eid="JHN 5:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 5:45"/>Do not think that I will accuse you to the Father; there is [one] who is accusing you, Moses—in whom you have hoped; <verse eid="JHN 5:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 5:46"/>for if you were believing Moses, you would have been believing Me, for he wrote concerning Me; <verse eid="JHN 5:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 5:47"/>but if you do not believe his writings, how will you believe My sayings?”<verse eid="JHN 5:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JHN 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 6:1"/>After these things Jesus went away beyond the Sea of Galilee (of Tiberias), <verse eid="JHN 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 6:2"/>and there was following Him a great multitude, because they were seeing His signs that He was doing on the ailing; <verse eid="JHN 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 6:3"/>and Jesus went up to the mountain, and He was sitting with His disciples there, <verse eid="JHN 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 6:4"/>and the Passover was near, the celebration of the Jews. <verse eid="JHN 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 6:5"/>Jesus then having lifted up [His] eyes and having seen that a great multitude comes to Him, says to Philip, “From where will we buy loaves, that these may eat?” <verse eid="JHN 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 6:6"/>And this He said, trying him, for He Himself had known what He was about to do. <verse eid="JHN 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 6:7"/>Philip answered Him, “Two hundred denarii worth of loaves are not sufficient to them, that each of them may receive some little”; <verse eid="JHN 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 6:8"/>one of His disciples—Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter—says to Him, <verse eid="JHN 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 6:9"/>“There is one little boy here who has five barley loaves and two fishes, but these—what are they to so many?” <verse eid="JHN 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 6:10"/>And Jesus said, “Make the men to sit down”; and there was much grass in the place, the men then sat down, in number, as it were, five thousand, <verse eid="JHN 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 6:11"/>and Jesus took the loaves, and having given thanks He distributed [them] to the disciples, and the disciples to those reclining, in like manner, also of the little fishes as much as they wished. <verse eid="JHN 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 6:12"/>And when they were filled, He says to His disciples, “Gather together the broken pieces that are left over, that nothing may be lost”; <verse eid="JHN 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 6:13"/>they gathered together, therefore, and filled twelve hand-baskets with broken pieces, from the five barley loaves that were over to those having eaten. <verse eid="JHN 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 6:14"/>The men, then, having seen the sign that Jesus did, said, “This is truly the Prophet who is coming into the world”; <verse eid="JHN 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 6:15"/>Jesus, therefore, having known that they are about to come, and to seize Him by force that they may make Him king, retired again to the mountain Himself alone. <verse eid="JHN 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 6:16"/>And when evening came, His disciples went down to the sea, <verse eid="JHN 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 6:17"/>and having entered into the boat, they were going over the sea to Capernaum, and darkness had already come, and Jesus had not come to them, <verse eid="JHN 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 6:18"/>the sea also—a great wind blowing—was being raised, <verse eid="JHN 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 6:19"/>having pushed onward, therefore, about twenty-five or thirty stadia, they behold Jesus walking on the sea, and coming near to the boat, and they were afraid; <verse eid="JHN 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 6:20"/>and He says to them, “I AM; do not be afraid”; <verse eid="JHN 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 6:21"/>they were willing then to receive Him into the boat, and immediately the boat came to the land to which they were going. <verse eid="JHN 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 6:22"/>On the next day, the multitude that was standing on the other side of the sea, having seen that there was no other little boat there except one—that into which His disciples entered—and that Jesus did not go in with His disciples into the little boat, but His disciples went away alone <verse eid="JHN 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 6:23"/>(and other little boats came from Tiberias, near the place where they ate the bread, the LORD having given thanks), <verse eid="JHN 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 6:24"/>when therefore the multitude saw that Jesus is not there, nor His disciples, they also entered into the boats themselves, and came to Capernaum seeking Jesus; <verse eid="JHN 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 6:25"/>and having found Him on the other side of the sea, they said to Him, “Rabbi, when have You come here?” <verse eid="JHN 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 6:26"/>Jesus answered them and said, “Truly, truly, I say to you, you seek Me, not because you saw signs, but because you ate of the loaves, and were satisfied; <verse eid="JHN 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 6:27"/>do not work for the food that is perishing, but for the food that is remaining to continuous life, which the Son of Man will give to you, for the Father sealed Him—[even] God.” <verse eid="JHN 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 6:28"/>Therefore they said to Him, “What may we do that we may work the works of God?” <verse eid="JHN 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 6:29"/>Jesus answered and said to them, “This is the work of God, that you may believe in Him whom He sent.” <verse eid="JHN 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 6:30"/>Therefore they said to Him, “What sign, then, do You do, that we may see and may believe You? What do You work? <verse eid="JHN 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 6:31"/>Our fathers ate the manna in the wilderness, according as it is having been written: He gave them bread out of Heaven to eat.” <verse eid="JHN 6:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 6:32"/>Jesus, therefore, said to them, “Truly, truly, I say to you, Moses did not give you the bread out of Heaven, but My Father gives you the true bread out of Heaven; <verse eid="JHN 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 6:33"/>for the bread of God is Him coming down out of Heaven, and giving life to the world.” <verse eid="JHN 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 6:34"/>Therefore they said to Him, “Lord, always give us this bread.” <verse eid="JHN 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 6:35"/>And Jesus said to them, “I AM the bread of life; he who is coming to Me may not hunger, and he who is believing in Me may not thirst—at any time; <verse eid="JHN 6:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 6:36"/>but I said to you that you also have seen Me, and you do not believe; <verse eid="JHN 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 6:37"/>all that the Father gives to Me will come to Me; and him who is coming to Me, I will never cast outside, <verse eid="JHN 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 6:38"/>because I have come down out of Heaven, not that I may do My will, but the will of Him who sent Me. <verse eid="JHN 6:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 6:39"/>And this is the will of the Father who sent Me, that all that He has given to Me, I may lose none of it, but may raise it up in the last day; <verse eid="JHN 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 6:40"/>and this is the will of Him who sent Me, that everyone who is beholding the Son, and is believing in Him, may have continuous life, and I will raise him up in the last day.” <verse eid="JHN 6:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 6:41"/>The Jews, therefore, were murmuring at Him, because He said, “I AM the bread that came down out of Heaven”; <verse eid="JHN 6:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 6:42"/>and they said, “Is this not Jesus, the Son of Joseph, whose father and mother we have known? How then does this One say, I have come down out of Heaven?” <verse eid="JHN 6:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 6:43"/>Jesus answered, therefore, and said to them, “Do not murmur with one another; <verse eid="JHN 6:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 6:44"/>no one is able to come to Me if the Father who sent Me may not draw him, and I will raise him up in the last day; <verse eid="JHN 6:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 6:45"/>it is having been written in the Prophets: And they will all be taught of God; everyone, therefore, who heard from the Father, and learned, comes to Me; <verse eid="JHN 6:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 6:46"/>not that anyone has seen the Father, except He who is from God, He has seen the Father. <verse eid="JHN 6:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 6:47"/>Truly, truly, I say to you, he who is believing in Me has continuous life; <verse eid="JHN 6:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 6:48"/>I AM the bread of life; <verse eid="JHN 6:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 6:49"/>your fathers ate the manna in the wilderness and they died; <verse eid="JHN 6:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 6:50"/>this is the bread that is coming down out of Heaven, that anyone may eat of it, and not die. <verse eid="JHN 6:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 6:51"/>I AM the living bread that came down out of Heaven; if anyone may eat of this bread he will live—throughout the age; and the bread also that I will give is My flesh, that I will give for the life of the world.” <verse eid="JHN 6:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 6:52"/>The Jews, therefore, were striving with one another, saying, “How is this One able to give us [His] flesh to eat?” <verse eid="JHN 6:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 6:53"/>Jesus, therefore, said to them, “Truly, truly, I say to you, if you may not eat the flesh of the Son of Man, and may not drink His blood, you have no life in yourselves; <verse eid="JHN 6:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 6:54"/>he who is eating My flesh, and is drinking My blood, has continuous life, and I will raise him up in the last day; <verse eid="JHN 6:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 6:55"/>for My flesh is truly food, and My blood is truly drink; <verse eid="JHN 6:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JHN 6:56"/>he who is eating My flesh, and is drinking My blood, remains in Me, and I in him. <verse eid="JHN 6:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JHN 6:57"/>According as the living Father sent Me, and I live because of the Father, he also who is eating Me, even that one will live because of Me; <verse eid="JHN 6:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="JHN 6:58"/>this is the bread that came down out of Heaven; not as your fathers ate the manna, and died; he who is eating this bread will live—throughout the age.” <verse eid="JHN 6:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JHN 6:59"/>He said these things in a synagogue, teaching in Capernaum; <verse eid="JHN 6:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="JHN 6:60"/>many, therefore, of His disciples having heard, said, “This word is hard; who is able to hear it?” <verse eid="JHN 6:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="JHN 6:61"/>And Jesus having known in Himself that His disciples are murmuring about this, said to them, “Does this stumble you? <verse eid="JHN 6:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="JHN 6:62"/>If then you may behold the Son of Man going up where He was before? <verse eid="JHN 6:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="JHN 6:63"/>It is the Spirit that is giving life; the flesh does not profit anything; the sayings that I speak to you are spirit, and they are life; <verse eid="JHN 6:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="JHN 6:64"/>but there are certain of you who do not believe”; for Jesus had known from the beginning who they are who are not believing, and who is he who will deliver Him up, <verse eid="JHN 6:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="JHN 6:65"/>and He said, “Because of this I have said to you, No one is able to come to Me if it may not have been given him from My Father.” <verse eid="JHN 6:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="JHN 6:66"/>From this [time] many of His disciples went away backward, and were no longer walking with Him, <verse eid="JHN 6:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="JHN 6:67"/>Jesus, therefore, said to the Twelve, “Do you also wish to go away?” <verse eid="JHN 6:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="JHN 6:68"/>Simon Peter, therefore, answered Him, “Lord, to whom will we go? You have sayings of continuous life; <verse eid="JHN 6:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="JHN 6:69"/>and we have believed, and we have known, that You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.” <verse eid="JHN 6:69"/><verse number="70" style="v" sid="JHN 6:70"/>Jesus answered them, “Did I not choose you—the Twelve? And of you—one is a devil.” <verse eid="JHN 6:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="JHN 6:71"/>And He spoke of Judas, [son] of Simon Iscariot, for he was about to deliver Him up, being one of the Twelve.<verse eid="JHN 6:71"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JHN 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 7:1"/>And Jesus was walking after these things in Galilee, for He did not wish to walk in Judea, because the Jews were seeking to kill Him, <verse eid="JHN 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 7:2"/>and the celebration of the Jews was near—that of Shelters— <verse eid="JHN 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 7:3"/>His brothers, therefore, said to Him, “Depart from here, and go away to Judea, that Your disciples may also behold Your works that You do; <verse eid="JHN 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 7:4"/>for no one does anything in secret, and himself seeks to be in public; if you do these things—reveal Yourself to the world”; <verse eid="JHN 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 7:5"/>for not even His brothers were believing in Him. <verse eid="JHN 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 7:6"/>Jesus, therefore, says to them, “My time is not yet present, but your time is always ready; <verse eid="JHN 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 7:7"/>the world is not able to hate you, but it hates Me, because I testify concerning it that its works are evil. <verse eid="JHN 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 7:8"/>You—go up to this celebration; I do not yet go up to this celebration, because My time has not yet been fulfilled”; <verse eid="JHN 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 7:9"/>and saying these things to them, He remained in Galilee. <verse eid="JHN 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 7:10"/>And when His brothers went up, then also He Himself went up to the celebration, not openly, but as in secret; <verse eid="JHN 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 7:11"/>the Jews, therefore, were seeking Him in the celebration, and said, “Where is that One?” <verse eid="JHN 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 7:12"/>And there was much murmuring about Him among the multitudes, some indeed said, “He is good”; and others said, “No, but He leads the multitude astray”; <verse eid="JHN 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 7:13"/>no one, however, was speaking freely about Him, through fear of the Jews. <verse eid="JHN 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 7:14"/>And it being now the middle of the celebration, Jesus went up to the temple, and He was teaching, <verse eid="JHN 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 7:15"/>and the Jews were wondering, saying, “How has this One known letters—having not learned?” <verse eid="JHN 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 7:16"/>Jesus answered them and said, “My teaching is not Mine, but His who sent Me; <verse eid="JHN 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 7:17"/>if anyone may will to do His will, he will know concerning the teaching, whether it is of God, or—[if] I speak from Myself. <verse eid="JHN 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 7:18"/>He who is speaking from himself seeks his own glory, but he who is seeking the glory of him who sent him, this one is true, and unrighteousness is not in him; <verse eid="JHN 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 7:19"/>has not Moses given you the Law? And none of you does the Law; why do you seek to kill Me?” <verse eid="JHN 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 7:20"/>The multitude answered and said, “You have a demon, who seeks to kill You?” <verse eid="JHN 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 7:21"/>Jesus answered and said to them, “I did one work, and you all wonder, <verse eid="JHN 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 7:22"/>because of this, Moses has given you the circumcision—not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers—and on a Sabbath you circumcise a man; <verse eid="JHN 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 7:23"/>if a man receives circumcision on a Sabbath that the Law of Moses may not be broken, are you angry with Me that I made a man all whole on a Sabbath? <verse eid="JHN 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 7:24"/>Do not judge according to appearance, but the righteous judgment judge.” <verse eid="JHN 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 7:25"/>Certain, therefore, of the Jerusalemites said, “Is this not He whom they are seeking to kill? <verse eid="JHN 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 7:26"/>And behold, He speaks freely, and they say nothing to Him; did the rulers truly know that this is the Christ? <verse eid="JHN 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 7:27"/>But this One—we have known where He is from; and the Christ, when He comes, no one knows where He is from.” <verse eid="JHN 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 7:28"/>Jesus cried, therefore, in the temple, teaching and saying, “You have both known Me, and you have known from where I am; and I have not come of Myself, but He who sent Me is true, whom you have not known; <verse eid="JHN 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 7:29"/>and I have known Him, because I am from Him, and He sent Me.” <verse eid="JHN 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 7:30"/>They were seeking, therefore, to seize Him, and no one laid the hand on Him, because His hour had not yet come, <verse eid="JHN 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 7:31"/>and many out of the multitude believed in Him and said, “The Christ—when He may come—will He do more signs than these that this One did?” <verse eid="JHN 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 7:32"/>The Pharisees heard the multitude murmuring these things concerning Him, and the Pharisees and the chief priests sent officers that they may take Him; <verse eid="JHN 7:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 7:33"/>Jesus, therefore, said to them, “Yet a short time I am with you, and I go away to Him who sent Me; <verse eid="JHN 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 7:34"/>you will seek Me, and you will not find; and where I am, you are not able to come.” <verse eid="JHN 7:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 7:35"/>The Jews, therefore, said among themselves, “To where is this One about to go that we will not find Him? Is He about to go to the dispersion of the Greeks, and to teach the Greeks? <verse eid="JHN 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 7:36"/>What is this word that He said, You will seek Me, and you will not find? And, Where I am, you are not able to come?” <verse eid="JHN 7:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 7:37"/>And in the last, the great day of the celebration, Jesus stood and cried, saying, “If anyone thirsts, let him come to Me and drink; <verse eid="JHN 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 7:38"/>he who is believing in Me, according as the Writing said, Rivers of living water will flow out of his belly”; <verse eid="JHN 7:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 7:39"/>and this He said of the Spirit, which those believing in Him were about to receive; for not yet was the Holy Spirit, because Jesus was not yet glorified. <verse eid="JHN 7:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 7:40"/>Many, therefore, out of the multitude, having heard the word, said, “This is truly the Prophet”; <verse eid="JHN 7:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 7:41"/>others said, “This is the Christ”; and others said, “Why, does the Christ come out of Galilee? <verse eid="JHN 7:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 7:42"/>Did the Writing not say that out of the seed of David, and from Beth-Lehem—the village where David was—the Christ comes?” <verse eid="JHN 7:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 7:43"/>A division, therefore, arose among the multitude because of Him. <verse eid="JHN 7:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 7:44"/>And certain of them were willing to seize Him, but no one laid hands on Him; <verse eid="JHN 7:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 7:45"/>the officers came, therefore, to the chief priests and Pharisees, and they said to them, “Why did you not bring Him?” <verse eid="JHN 7:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 7:46"/>The officers answered, “Never so spoke man—as this Man.” <verse eid="JHN 7:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 7:47"/>The Pharisees, therefore, answered them, “Have you also been led astray? <verse eid="JHN 7:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 7:48"/>Did anyone out of the rulers believe in Him? Or out of the Pharisees? <verse eid="JHN 7:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 7:49"/>But this multitude, that is not knowing the Law, is accursed.” <verse eid="JHN 7:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 7:50"/>Nicodemus says to them—he who came by night to Him—being one of them, <verse eid="JHN 7:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 7:51"/>“Does our law judge the Man, if it may not hear from Him first, and know what He does?” <verse eid="JHN 7:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 7:52"/>They answered and said to him, “Are you also out of Galilee? Search and see that a prophet has not risen out of Galilee”; <char style="bd">[[</char> <verse eid="JHN 7:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 7:53"/>and each one went on to his house, but Jesus went on to the Mount of Olives.<verse eid="JHN 7:53"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JHN 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 8:1"/>And at dawn He came again to the temple [courts], <verse eid="JHN 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 8:2"/>and all the people were coming to Him, and having sat down, He was teaching them; <verse eid="JHN 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 8:3"/>and the scribes and the Pharisees bring to Him a woman having been taken in adultery, and having set her in the midst, <verse eid="JHN 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 8:4"/>they say to Him, “Teacher, this woman was taken in the very crime [of] committing adultery, <verse eid="JHN 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 8:5"/>and in the Law, Moses commanded us that such be stoned; You, therefore, what do You say?” <verse eid="JHN 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 8:6"/>And this they said, trying Him, that they might have to accuse Him. And Jesus, having stooped down, with the finger He was writing on the ground, <verse eid="JHN 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 8:7"/>and when they continued asking Him, having bent Himself back, He said to them, “The sinless of you—let him cast the first stone at her”; <verse eid="JHN 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 8:8"/>and again having stooped down, He was writing on the ground, <verse eid="JHN 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 8:9"/>and they having heard, and being convicted by the conscience, were going forth one by one, having begun from the elders—to the last; and Jesus was left alone, and the woman standing in the midst. <verse eid="JHN 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 8:10"/>And Jesus having bent Himself back, and having seen no one but the woman, said to her, “Woman, where are those—your accusers? Did no one pass sentence on you?” <verse eid="JHN 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 8:11"/>And she said, “No one, Lord”; and Jesus said to her, “Neither do I pass sentence on you; be going on, and sin no more.”<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="JHN 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 8:12"/>Again, therefore, Jesus spoke to them, saying, “I AM the light of the world; he who is following Me will not walk in the darkness, but he will have the light of life.” <verse eid="JHN 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 8:13"/>The Pharisees, therefore, said to Him, “You testify of Yourself, Your testimony is not true”; <verse eid="JHN 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 8:14"/>Jesus answered and said to them, “And if I testify of Myself—My testimony is true, because I have known from where I came, and to where I go, and you have not known from where I come, or to where I go. <verse eid="JHN 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 8:15"/>You judge according to the flesh; I do not judge anyone, <verse eid="JHN 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 8:16"/>and even if I do judge My judgment is true, because I am not alone, but I and the Father who sent Me; <verse eid="JHN 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 8:17"/>and also in your law it has been written that the testimony of two men is true; <verse eid="JHN 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 8:18"/>I am [One] who is testifying of Myself, and the Father who sent Me testifies of Me.” <verse eid="JHN 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 8:19"/>They said, therefore, to Him, “Where is Your father?” Jesus answered, “You have neither known Me nor My Father: if you had known Me, you had also known My Father.” <verse eid="JHN 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 8:20"/>Jesus spoke these sayings in the treasury, teaching in the temple, and no one seized Him, because His hour had not yet come; <verse eid="JHN 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 8:21"/>therefore Jesus said again to them, “I go away, and you will seek Me, and you will die in your sin; to where I go away, you are not able to come.” <verse eid="JHN 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 8:22"/>The Jews, therefore, said, “Will He kill Himself, because He says, To where I go away, you are not able to come?” <verse eid="JHN 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 8:23"/>And He said to them, “You are from beneath, I am from above; you are of this world, I am not of this world; <verse eid="JHN 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 8:24"/>I said, therefore, to you, that you will die in your sins, for if you may not believe that I AM, you will die in your sins.” <verse eid="JHN 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 8:25"/>They said, therefore, to Him, “You—who are You?” And Jesus said to them, “Even what I spoke of to you at the beginning; <verse eid="JHN 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 8:26"/>many things I have to speak concerning you and to judge, but He who sent Me is true, and I—what things I heard from Him—these I say to the world.” <verse eid="JHN 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 8:27"/>They did not know that He spoke to them of the Father; <verse eid="JHN 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 8:28"/>Jesus, therefore, said to them, “When you may lift up the Son of Man then you will know that I AM; and I do nothing of Myself, but according as My Father taught Me, these things I speak; <verse eid="JHN 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 8:29"/>and He who sent Me is with Me; the Father did not leave Me alone, because I always do the things pleasing to Him.” <verse eid="JHN 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 8:30"/>As He is speaking these things, many believed in Him; <verse eid="JHN 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 8:31"/>Jesus, therefore, said to the Jews who believed in Him, “If you may remain in My word, you are truly My disciples, <verse eid="JHN 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 8:32"/>and you will know the truth, and the truth will make you free.” <verse eid="JHN 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 8:33"/>They answered Him, “We are seed of Abraham; and we have been servants to no one at any time; how do You say—You will become free?” <verse eid="JHN 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 8:34"/>Jesus answered them, “Truly, truly, I say to you, everyone who is committing sin, is a servant of sin, <verse eid="JHN 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 8:35"/>and the servant does not remain in the house—throughout the age, the Son remains—throughout the age; <verse eid="JHN 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 8:36"/>if then the Son may make you free, in reality you will be free. <verse eid="JHN 8:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 8:37"/>I have known that you are seed of Abraham, but you seek to kill Me, because My word has no place in you; <verse eid="JHN 8:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 8:38"/>I speak that which I have seen with My Father, and you, therefore, do that which you have seen with your father.” <verse eid="JHN 8:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 8:39"/>They answered and said to Him, “Our father is Abraham”; Jesus says to them, “If you were children of Abraham, the works of Abraham you were doing; <verse eid="JHN 8:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 8:40"/>and now, you seek to kill Me—a Man who has spoken to you the truth I heard from God; Abraham did not do this; <verse eid="JHN 8:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 8:41"/>you do the works of your father.” They said, therefore, to Him, “We have not been born of whoredom; we have one Father—God”; <verse eid="JHN 8:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 8:42"/>Jesus then said to them, “If God were your father, you were loving Me, for I came forth from God, and am come; for neither have I come of Myself, but He sent Me; <verse eid="JHN 8:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 8:43"/>why do you not know My speech? Because you are not able to hear My word. <verse eid="JHN 8:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 8:44"/>You are of a father—the Devil, and the desires of your father you will to do; he was a manslayer from the beginning, and he has not stood in the truth, because there is no truth in him; when one may speak the falsehood, he speaks of his own, because he is a liar—also his father. <verse eid="JHN 8:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 8:45"/>And because I say the truth, you do not believe Me. <verse eid="JHN 8:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 8:46"/>Who of you convicts Me of sin? And if I speak truth, why do you not believe Me? <verse eid="JHN 8:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 8:47"/>He who is of God, he hears the sayings of God; because of this you do not hear, because you are not of God.” <verse eid="JHN 8:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 8:48"/>The Jews, therefore, answered and said to Him, “Do we not say well, that You are a Samaritan, and have a demon?” <verse eid="JHN 8:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 8:49"/>Jesus answered, “I do not have a demon, but I honor My Father, and you dishonor Me; <verse eid="JHN 8:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 8:50"/>and I do not seek My own glory; there is [One] who is seeking and is judging; <verse eid="JHN 8:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 8:51"/>truly, truly, I say to you, if anyone may keep My word, he may not see death—throughout the age.” <verse eid="JHN 8:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 8:52"/>The Jews, therefore, said to Him, “Now we have known that You have a demon; Abraham died, and the prophets, and You say, If anyone may keep My word, he will not taste of death—throughout the age! <verse eid="JHN 8:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 8:53"/>Are You greater than our father Abraham, who died? And the prophets died; whom do You make Yourself?” <verse eid="JHN 8:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 8:54"/>Jesus answered, “If I glorify Myself, My glory is nothing; it is My Father who is glorifying Me, of whom you say that He is your God; <verse eid="JHN 8:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 8:55"/>and you have not known Him, and I have known Him, and if I say that I have not known Him, I will be like you—speaking falsely; but I have known Him, and I keep His word; <verse eid="JHN 8:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JHN 8:56"/>your father Abraham was glad that he might see My day; and he saw, and rejoiced.” <verse eid="JHN 8:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JHN 8:57"/>The Jews, therefore, said to Him, “You are not yet fifty years old, and You have seen Abraham?” <verse eid="JHN 8:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="JHN 8:58"/>Jesus said to them, “Truly, truly, I say to you, before Abraham’s coming—I AM”; <verse eid="JHN 8:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JHN 8:59"/>they took up, therefore, stones that they may cast at Him, but Jesus hid Himself, and went forth out of the temple, going through the midst of them, and so passed by.<verse eid="JHN 8:59"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JHN 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 9:1"/>And passing by, He saw a man blind from birth, <verse eid="JHN 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 9:2"/>and His disciples asked Him, saying, “Rabbi, who sinned, this one or his parents, that he should be born blind?” <verse eid="JHN 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 9:3"/>Jesus answered, “Neither this one sinned nor his parents, but that the works of God may be revealed in him; <verse eid="JHN 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 9:4"/>it is necessary for Me to be working the works of Him who sent Me while it is day; night comes when no one is able to work: <verse eid="JHN 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 9:5"/>when I am in the world, I AM [the] light of the world.” <verse eid="JHN 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 9:6"/>Saying these things, He spat on the ground, and made clay of the spittle, and rubbed the clay on the eyes of the blind man, and said to him, <verse eid="JHN 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 9:7"/>“Go away, wash at the pool of Siloam,” which is, interpreted, Sent. He went away, therefore, and washed, and came seeing; <verse eid="JHN 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 9:8"/>the neighbors, therefore, and those seeing him before, that he was blind, said, “Is this not he who is sitting and begging?” <verse eid="JHN 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 9:9"/>Others said, “This is he”; and others, “He is like to him”; he himself said, “I am [he].” <verse eid="JHN 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 9:10"/>They said, therefore, to him, “How were your eyes opened?” <verse eid="JHN 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 9:11"/>He answered and said, “A man called Jesus made clay, and rubbed my eyes, and said to me, Go away to the pool of Siloam, and wash; and having gone away and having washed, I received sight”; <verse eid="JHN 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 9:12"/>they said, therefore, to him, “Where is that One?” He says, “I have not known.” <verse eid="JHN 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 9:13"/>They bring him who once [was] blind to the Pharisees, <verse eid="JHN 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 9:14"/>and it was a Sabbath when Jesus made the clay, and opened his eyes. <verse eid="JHN 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 9:15"/>Again, therefore, the Pharisees also were asking him how he received sight, and he said to them, “He put clay on my eyes, and I washed—and I see.” <verse eid="JHN 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 9:16"/>Certain of the Pharisees therefore said, “This Man is not from God, because He does not keep the Sabbath”; others said, “How is a man—a sinful one—able to do such signs?” And there was a division among them. <verse eid="JHN 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 9:17"/>They said to the blind man again, “You—what do you say of Him—that He opened your eyes?” <verse eid="JHN 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 9:18"/>And he said, “He is a prophet.” The Jews, therefore, did not believe concerning him that he was blind and received sight, until they called the parents of him who received sight, <verse eid="JHN 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 9:19"/>and they asked them, saying, “Is [this] your son, of whom you say that he was born blind? How then does he now see?” <verse eid="JHN 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 9:20"/>His parents answered them and said, “We have known that this is our son, and that he was born blind; <verse eid="JHN 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 9:21"/>and how he now sees, we have not known; or who opened his eyes, we have not known; he is of age, ask him; he himself will speak concerning himself.” <verse eid="JHN 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 9:22"/>His parents said these things, because they were afraid of the Jews, for the Jews had already agreed together, that if anyone may confess Him—Christ, he may be put out of the synagogue; <verse eid="JHN 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 9:23"/>because of this his parents said, “He is of age, ask him.” <verse eid="JHN 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 9:24"/>They called, therefore, the man who was blind a second time, and they said to him, “Give glory to God, we have known that this Man is a sinner”; <verse eid="JHN 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 9:25"/>he answered, therefore, and said, “If He is a sinner—I have not known, one thing I have known, that, being blind, now I see.” <verse eid="JHN 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 9:26"/>And they said to him again, “What did He do to you? How did He open your eyes?” <verse eid="JHN 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 9:27"/>He answered them, “I told you already, and you did not hear; why do you wish to hear [it] again? Do you also wish to become His disciples?” <verse eid="JHN 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 9:28"/>They reviled him, therefore, and said, “You are His disciple, and we are Moses’ disciples; <verse eid="JHN 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 9:29"/>we have known that God has spoken to Moses, but this One—we have not known where He is from.” <verse eid="JHN 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 9:30"/>The man answered and said to them, “Why, in this is a wonderful thing, that you have not known where He is from, and He opened my eyes! <verse eid="JHN 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 9:31"/>And we have known that God does not hear sinners, but if anyone may be a worshiper of God, and may do His will, He hears him; <verse eid="JHN 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 9:32"/>from the age it was not heard that anyone opened eyes of one who has been born blind; <verse eid="JHN 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 9:33"/>if this One were not from God, He were not able to do anything.” <verse eid="JHN 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 9:34"/>They answered and said to him, “In sins you were born altogether, and you teach us?” And they cast him forth outside. <verse eid="JHN 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 9:35"/>Jesus heard that they cast him forth outside, and having found him, He said to him, “Do you believe in the Son of God?” <verse eid="JHN 9:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 9:36"/>He answered and said, “Who is He, Lord, that I may believe in Him?” <verse eid="JHN 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 9:37"/>And Jesus said to him, “You have both seen Him, and He who is speaking with you is He”; <verse eid="JHN 9:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 9:38"/>and he said, “I believe, Lord,” and worshiped Him. <verse eid="JHN 9:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 9:39"/>And Jesus said, “I came to this world for judgment, that those not seeing may see, and those seeing may become blind.” <verse eid="JHN 9:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 9:40"/>And those of the Pharisees who were with Him heard these things, and they said to Him, “Are we also blind?” <verse eid="JHN 9:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 9:41"/>Jesus said to them, “If you were blind, you were not having had sin, but now you say—We see, therefore your sin remains.”<verse eid="JHN 9:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JHN 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 10:1"/>“Truly, truly, I say to you, he who is not entering through the door to the fold of the sheep, but is going up from another side, that one is a thief and a robber; <verse eid="JHN 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 10:2"/>and he who is entering through the door is shepherd of the sheep; <verse eid="JHN 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 10:3"/>the doorkeeper opens to this one, and the sheep hear his voice, and his own sheep he calls by name, and leads them forth; <verse eid="JHN 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 10:4"/>and when he may put forth his own sheep, he goes on before them, and the sheep follow him, because they have known his voice; <verse eid="JHN 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 10:5"/>and they will not follow a stranger, but will flee from him, because they have not known the voice of strangers.” <verse eid="JHN 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 10:6"/>Jesus spoke this allegory to them, and they did not know what the things were that He was speaking to them; <verse eid="JHN 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 10:7"/>Jesus therefore said again to them, “Truly, truly, I say to you, I AM the door of the sheep; <verse eid="JHN 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 10:8"/>all, as many as came before Me, are thieves and robbers, but the sheep did not hear them; <verse eid="JHN 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 10:9"/>I AM the door, if anyone may come in through Me, he will be saved, and he will come in, and go out, and find pasture. <verse eid="JHN 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 10:10"/>The thief does not come, except that he may steal, and kill, and destroy; I came that they may have life, and may have [it] abundantly. <verse eid="JHN 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 10:11"/>I AM the good shepherd; the good shepherd lays His life down for the sheep; <verse eid="JHN 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 10:12"/>and the hired worker, and not being a shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, beholds the wolf coming, and leaves the sheep, and flees; and the wolf snatches them, and scatters the sheep; <verse eid="JHN 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 10:13"/>and the hired worker flees because he is a hired worker, and is not caring for the sheep. <verse eid="JHN 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 10:14"/>I AM the good shepherd, and I know My [sheep], and am known by Mine, <verse eid="JHN 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 10:15"/>according as the Father knows Me, and I know the Father, and My life I lay down for the sheep, <verse eid="JHN 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 10:16"/>and other sheep I have that are not of this fold, these also it is necessary for Me to bring, and My voice they will hear, and there will become one flock—one shepherd. <verse eid="JHN 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 10:17"/>Because of this the Father loves Me, because I lay down My life, that again I may take it; <verse eid="JHN 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 10:18"/>no one takes it from Me, but I lay it down of Myself; authority I have to lay it down, and authority I have again to take it; this command I received from My Father.” <verse eid="JHN 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 10:19"/>Therefore, again, there came a division among the Jews, because of these words, <verse eid="JHN 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 10:20"/>and many of them said, “He has a demon, and is mad, why do you hear Him?” <verse eid="JHN 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 10:21"/>Others said, “These sayings are not those of a demoniac; is a demon able to open blind men’s eyes?” <verse eid="JHN 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 10:22"/>And the Dedication in Jerusalem came, and it was winter, <verse eid="JHN 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 10:23"/>and Jesus was walking in the temple, in the porch of Solomon, <verse eid="JHN 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 10:24"/>the Jews, therefore, came around Him and said to Him, “Until when do You hold our soul in suspense? If You are the Christ, tell us freely.” <verse eid="JHN 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 10:25"/>Jesus answered them, “I told you, and you do not believe; the works that I do in the Name of My Father, these testify concerning Me; <verse eid="JHN 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 10:26"/>but you do not believe, for you are not of My sheep, <verse eid="JHN 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 10:27"/>according as I said to you: My sheep hear My voice, and I know them, and they follow Me, <verse eid="JHN 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 10:28"/>and I give continuous life to them, and they will not perish—throughout the age, and no one will snatch them out of My hand; <verse eid="JHN 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 10:29"/>My Father, who has given to Me, is greater than all, and no one is able to snatch out of the hand of My Father; <verse eid="JHN 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 10:30"/>I and the Father are one.” <verse eid="JHN 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 10:31"/>Therefore, again, the Jews took up stones that they may stone Him; <verse eid="JHN 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 10:32"/>Jesus answered them, “I showed you many good works from My Father; because of which work of them do you stone Me?” <verse eid="JHN 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 10:33"/>The Jews answered Him, saying, “We do not stone You for a good work, but for slander, and because You, being a man, make Yourself God.” <verse eid="JHN 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 10:34"/>Jesus answered them, “Is it not having been written in your law: I said, you are gods? <verse eid="JHN 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 10:35"/>If He called them gods to whom the word of God came (and the Writing is not able to be broken), <verse eid="JHN 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 10:36"/>of Him whom the Father sanctified and sent into the world, do you say—You slander, because I said, I am [the] Son of God? <verse eid="JHN 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 10:37"/>If I do not do the works of My Father, do not believe Me; <verse eid="JHN 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 10:38"/>and if I do, even if you may not believe Me, believe the works, that you may know and may believe that the Father [is] in Me, and I in Him.” <verse eid="JHN 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 10:39"/>Therefore they were seeking again to seize Him, and He went forth out of their hand, <verse eid="JHN 10:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 10:40"/>and went away again to the other side of the Jordan, to the place where John was at first immersing, and remained there, <verse eid="JHN 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 10:41"/>and many came to Him and said, “John, indeed, did no sign, and all things, as many as John said about this One were true”; <verse eid="JHN 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 10:42"/>and many believed in Him there.<verse eid="JHN 10:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JHN 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 11:1"/>And there was a certain one ailing, Lazarus, from Bethany, of the village of Mary and Martha her sister— <verse eid="JHN 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 11:2"/>and it was Mary who anointed the LORD with ointment, and wiped His feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was ailing— <verse eid="JHN 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 11:3"/>therefore the sisters sent to Him, saying, “Lord, behold, he whom You cherish is ailing”; <verse eid="JHN 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 11:4"/>and Jesus having heard, said, “This ailment is not to death, but for the glory of God, that the Son of God may be glorified through it.” <verse eid="JHN 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 11:5"/>And Jesus was loving Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus, <verse eid="JHN 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 11:6"/>when, therefore, He heard that he is ailing, then indeed He remained in the place in which He was two days, <verse eid="JHN 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 11:7"/>then after this, He says to the disciples, “We may go to Judea again”; <verse eid="JHN 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 11:8"/>the disciples say to Him, “Rabbi, the Jews were just seeking to stone You, and again You go there?” <verse eid="JHN 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 11:9"/>Jesus answered, “Are there not twelve hours in the day? If anyone may walk in the day, he does not stumble, because he sees the light of this world; <verse eid="JHN 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 11:10"/>and if anyone may walk in the night, he stumbles, because the light is not in him.” <verse eid="JHN 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 11:11"/>He said these things, and after this He says to them, “Our friend Lazarus has fallen asleep, but I go on that I may awake him”; <verse eid="JHN 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 11:12"/>therefore His disciples said, “Lord, if he has fallen asleep, he will be saved”; <verse eid="JHN 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 11:13"/>but Jesus had spoken about his death, but they thought that He speaks about the repose of sleep. <verse eid="JHN 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 11:14"/>Then, therefore, Jesus said to them freely, “Lazarus has died; <verse eid="JHN 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 11:15"/>and I rejoice, for your sake (that you may believe), that I was not there; but we may go to him”; <verse eid="JHN 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 11:16"/>therefore Thomas, who is called Didymus, said to the fellow-disciples, “We may go—we also, that we may die with Him,” <verse eid="JHN 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 11:17"/>Jesus, therefore, having come, found him having already been four days in the tomb. <verse eid="JHN 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 11:18"/>And Bethany was near to Jerusalem, about fifteen stadia off, <verse eid="JHN 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 11:19"/>and many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary, that they might comfort them concerning their brother; <verse eid="JHN 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 11:20"/>Martha, therefore, when she heard that Jesus comes, met Him, and Mary kept sitting in the house. <verse eid="JHN 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 11:21"/>Martha, therefore, said to Jesus, “Lord, if You had been here, my brother had not died; <verse eid="JHN 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 11:22"/>but even now, I have known that whatever You may ask of God, God will give to You”; <verse eid="JHN 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 11:23"/>Jesus says to her, “Your brother will rise again.” <verse eid="JHN 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 11:24"/>Martha says to Him, “I have known that he will rise again in the resurrection in the last day”; <verse eid="JHN 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 11:25"/>Jesus said to her, “I AM the resurrection, and the life; he who is believing in Me, even if he may die, will live; <verse eid="JHN 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 11:26"/>and everyone who is living and believing in Me will not die—throughout the age; <verse eid="JHN 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 11:27"/>do you believe this?” She says to Him, “Yes, Lord, I have believed that You are the Christ, the Son of God, who is coming into the world.” <verse eid="JHN 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 11:28"/>And having said these things, she went away, and called Mary her sister privately, saying, “The Teacher is present, and calls you”; <verse eid="JHN 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 11:29"/>she, when she heard, rises up quickly, and comes to Him; <verse eid="JHN 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 11:30"/>and Jesus had not yet come into the village, but was in the place where Martha met Him; <verse eid="JHN 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 11:31"/>the Jews, therefore, who were with her in the house, and were comforting her, having seen Mary that she rose up quickly and went forth, followed her, saying, “She goes away to the tomb, that she may weep there.” <verse eid="JHN 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 11:32"/>Mary, therefore, when she came where Jesus was, having seen Him, fell at His feet, saying to Him, “Lord, if You had been here, my brother had not died”; <verse eid="JHN 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 11:33"/>Jesus, therefore, when He saw her weeping, and the Jews who came with her weeping, groaned in the spirit, and troubled Himself, and He said, <verse eid="JHN 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 11:34"/>“Where have you laid him?” They say to Him, “Lord, come and see”; <verse eid="JHN 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 11:35"/>Jesus wept. <verse eid="JHN 11:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 11:36"/>The Jews, therefore, said, “Behold, how He was cherishing him!” <verse eid="JHN 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 11:37"/>And certain of them said, “Was not this One, who opened the eyes of the blind man, also able to cause that this one might not have died?” <verse eid="JHN 11:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 11:38"/>Jesus, therefore, again groaning in Himself, comes to the tomb, and it was a cave, and a stone was lying on it, <verse eid="JHN 11:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 11:39"/>Jesus says, “Take away the stone”; the sister of him who has died—Martha—says to Him, “Lord, he already stinks, for he is four days dead”; <verse eid="JHN 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 11:40"/>Jesus says to her, “Did I not say to you that if you may believe, you will see the glory of God?” <verse eid="JHN 11:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 11:41"/>Therefore they took away the stone where the dead was laid, and Jesus lifted His eyes upwards, and said, “Father, I thank You that You heard Me; <verse eid="JHN 11:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 11:42"/>and I knew that You always hear Me, but because of the multitude that is standing by, I said [it], that they may believe that You sent Me.” <verse eid="JHN 11:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 11:43"/>And saying these things, He cried out with a loud voice, “Lazarus, come forth!” <verse eid="JHN 11:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 11:44"/>And he who died came forth, feet and hands being bound with grave-clothes, and his face was bound around with a napkin; Jesus says to them, “Loose him, and permit to go.” <verse eid="JHN 11:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 11:45"/>Many, therefore, of the Jews who came to Mary, and beheld what Jesus did, believed in Him; <verse eid="JHN 11:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 11:46"/>but certain of them went away to the Pharisees, and told them what Jesus did; <verse eid="JHN 11:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 11:47"/>the chief priests, therefore, and the Pharisees, gathered together [the] Sanhedrin and said, “What may we do? Because this Man does many signs? <verse eid="JHN 11:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 11:48"/>If we may leave Him alone thus, all will believe in Him; and the Romans will come, and will take away both our place and nation.” <verse eid="JHN 11:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 11:49"/>And a certain one of them, Caiaphas, being chief priest of that year, said to them, “You have not known anything, <verse eid="JHN 11:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 11:50"/>nor reason that it is good for us that one man may die for the people, and not the whole nation perish.” <verse eid="JHN 11:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 11:51"/>And he did not say this of himself, but being chief priest of that year, he prophesied that Jesus was about to die for the nation, <verse eid="JHN 11:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 11:52"/>and not for the nation only, but that also the children of God, who have been scattered abroad, He may gather together into one. <verse eid="JHN 11:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 11:53"/>From that day, therefore, they took counsel together that they may kill Him; <verse eid="JHN 11:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 11:54"/>Jesus, therefore, was no longer freely walking among the Jews, but went away from there into the region near the wilderness, to a city called Ephraim, and there He tarried with His disciples. <verse eid="JHN 11:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 11:55"/>And the Passover of the Jews was near, and many went up to Jerusalem out of the country before the Passover, that they might purify themselves; <verse eid="JHN 11:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JHN 11:56"/>therefore they were seeking Jesus and said with one another, standing in the temple, “What appears to you—that He may not come to the celebration?” <verse eid="JHN 11:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JHN 11:57"/>And both the chief priests and the Pharisees had given a command, that if anyone may know where He is, he may show [it], so that they may seize Him.<verse eid="JHN 11:57"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JHN 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 12:1"/>Jesus, therefore, six days before the Passover, came to Bethany, where Lazarus was, who had died, whom He raised out of the dead; <verse eid="JHN 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 12:2"/>they made, therefore, a dinner to Him there, and Martha was ministering, and Lazarus was one of those reclining together with Him; <verse eid="JHN 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 12:3"/>Mary, therefore, having taken a pound of ointment of spikenard, of great price, anointed the feet of Jesus and wiped His feet with her hair, and the house was filled from the fragrance of the ointment. <verse eid="JHN 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 12:4"/>Therefore one of His disciples—Judas Iscariot, of Simon, who is about to deliver Him up—says, <verse eid="JHN 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 12:5"/>“Why was this ointment not sold for three hundred denarii, and given to the poor?” <verse eid="JHN 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 12:6"/>And he said this, not because he was caring for the poor, but because he was a thief, and had the bag, and what things were put in he was carrying. <verse eid="JHN 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 12:7"/>Jesus, therefore, said, “Permit her; she has kept it for the day of My embalming, <verse eid="JHN 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 12:8"/>for you always have the poor with yourselves, and you do not always have Me.” <verse eid="JHN 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 12:9"/>Therefore, a great multitude of the Jews knew that He is there, and they came, not only because of Jesus, but that they may also see Lazarus, whom He raised out of the dead; <verse eid="JHN 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 12:10"/>and the chief priests took counsel, that they may also kill Lazarus, <verse eid="JHN 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 12:11"/>because on account of him many of the Jews were going away, and were believing in Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 12:12"/>On the next day, a great multitude that came to the celebration, having heard that Jesus comes to Jerusalem, <verse eid="JHN 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 12:13"/>took the branches of the palms, and went forth to meet Him, and were crying, “Hosanna! Blessed [is] He who is coming in the Name of the LORD—the King of Israel”; <verse eid="JHN 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 12:14"/>and Jesus having found a young donkey sat on it, according as it is written, <verse eid="JHN 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 12:15"/>“Do not fear, daughter of Zion, behold, your King comes, sitting on a colt of a donkey.” <verse eid="JHN 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 12:16"/>And His disciples did not know these things at first, but when Jesus was glorified, then they remembered that these things were having been written about Him, and these things they did to Him. <verse eid="JHN 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 12:17"/>The multitude, therefore, who are with Him, were testifying that He called Lazarus out of the tomb, and raised him out of the dead; <verse eid="JHN 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 12:18"/>because of this the multitude also met Him, because they heard of His having done this sign, <verse eid="JHN 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 12:19"/>therefore the Pharisees said among themselves, “You see that you do not gain anything, behold, the world went after Him.” <verse eid="JHN 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 12:20"/>And there were certain Greeks out of those coming up that they may worship in the celebration, <verse eid="JHN 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 12:21"/>these then came near to Philip, who [is] from Bethsaida of Galilee, and were asking him, saying, “Lord, we wish to see Jesus”; <verse eid="JHN 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 12:22"/>Philip comes and tells Andrew, and again Andrew and Philip tell Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 12:23"/>And Jesus responded to them, saying, “The hour has come that the Son of Man may be glorified; <verse eid="JHN 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 12:24"/>truly, truly, I say to you, if the grain of the wheat, having fallen to the earth, may not die, itself remains alone; and if it may die, it bears much fruit; <verse eid="JHN 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 12:25"/>he who is cherishing his life will lose it, and he who is hating his life in this world will keep it to continuous life; <verse eid="JHN 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 12:26"/>if anyone may minister to Me, let him follow Me, and where I am, there My servant will be also; and if anyone may minister to Me—the Father will honor him. <verse eid="JHN 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 12:27"/>Now My soul has been troubled; and what will I say—Father, save Me from this hour? But because of this I came to this hour; <verse eid="JHN 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 12:28"/>Father, glorify Your Name.” Therefore there came a voice out of Heaven, “I both glorified, and again I will glorify [it]”; <verse eid="JHN 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 12:29"/>the multitude, therefore, having stood and heard, were saying that there has been thunder; others said, “A messenger has spoken to Him.” <verse eid="JHN 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 12:30"/>Jesus answered and said, “This voice has not come because of Me, but because of you; <verse eid="JHN 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 12:31"/>now is a judgment of this world, now will the ruler of this world be cast forth; <verse eid="JHN 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 12:32"/>and I, if I may be lifted up from the earth, will draw all men to Myself.” <verse eid="JHN 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 12:33"/>And this He said signifying by what death He was about to die; <verse eid="JHN 12:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 12:34"/>the multitude answered Him, “We heard that the Christ remains out of the Law—throughout the age; and how do You say that it is required that the Son of Man be lifted up? Who is this—the Son of Man?” <verse eid="JHN 12:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 12:35"/>Therefore Jesus said to them, “Yet a short time is the light with you; walk while you have the light, that darkness may not overtake you; and he who is walking in the darkness has not known where he goes; <verse eid="JHN 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 12:36"/>while you have the light, believe in the light, that you may become sons of light.” Jesus spoke these things, and having gone away, He was hid from them, <verse eid="JHN 12:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 12:37"/>yet He, having done so many signs before them, they were not believing in Him, <verse eid="JHN 12:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 12:38"/>that the word of Isaiah the prophet might be fulfilled, which he said, “LORD, who gave credence to our report? And the arm of the LORD—to whom was it revealed?” <verse eid="JHN 12:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 12:39"/>Because of this they were not able to believe, that again Isaiah said, <verse eid="JHN 12:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 12:40"/>“He has blinded their eyes, and hardened their heart, that they might not see with the eyes, and understand with the heart, and turn, and I might heal them”; <verse eid="JHN 12:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 12:41"/>Isaiah said these things when he saw His glory, and spoke of Him. <verse eid="JHN 12:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 12:42"/>Still, however, out of the rulers many also believed in Him, but because of the Pharisees they were not confessing, that they might not be put out of the synagogue, <verse eid="JHN 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 12:43"/>for they loved the glory of men more than the glory of God. <verse eid="JHN 12:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 12:44"/>And Jesus cried and said, “He who is believing in Me, does not believe in Me, but in Him who sent Me; <verse eid="JHN 12:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 12:45"/>and He who is beholding Me, beholds Him who sent Me; <verse eid="JHN 12:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 12:46"/>I—light to the world—have come, that everyone who is believing in Me may not remain in the darkness; <verse eid="JHN 12:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 12:47"/>and if anyone may hear My sayings, and not believe, I do not judge him, for I did not come that I might judge the world, but that I might save the world. <verse eid="JHN 12:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 12:48"/>He who is rejecting Me, and not receiving My sayings, has one who is judging him, the word that I spoke, that will judge him in the last day, <verse eid="JHN 12:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 12:49"/>because I did not speak from Myself, but the Father who sent Me, He gave Me a command, what I may say, and what I may speak, <verse eid="JHN 12:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 12:50"/>and I have known that His command is continuous life; what, therefore, I speak, according as the Father has said to Me, so I speak.”<verse eid="JHN 12:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JHN 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 13:1"/>And before the Celebration of the Passover, Jesus knowing that His hour has come, that He may depart out of this world to the Father, having loved His own who [are] in the world—to the end He loved them. <verse eid="JHN 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 13:2"/>And dinner having come, the Devil already having put [it] into the heart of Judas of Simon, Iscariot, that he may deliver Him up, <verse eid="JHN 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 13:3"/>Jesus knowing that all things the Father has given to Him—into [His] hands, and that He came forth from God, and He goes to God, <verse eid="JHN 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 13:4"/>rises from the dinner, and lays down His garments, and having taken a towel, He girded Himself; <verse eid="JHN 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 13:5"/>afterward He puts water into the basin, and began to wash the feet of His disciples, and to wipe with the towel with which He was being girded. <verse eid="JHN 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 13:6"/>He comes, therefore, to Simon Peter, and that one says to Him, “Lord, You—do You wash my feet?” <verse eid="JHN 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 13:7"/>Jesus answered and said to him, “That which I do you have not known now, but you will know after these things”; <verse eid="JHN 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 13:8"/>Peter says to Him, “You may not wash my feet—throughout the age.” Jesus answered him, “If I may not wash you, you have no part with Me”; <verse eid="JHN 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 13:9"/>Simon Peter says to Him, “Lord, not my feet only, but also the hands and the head.” <verse eid="JHN 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 13:10"/>Jesus says to him, “He who has been bathed has no need except to wash his feet, but he is clean altogether; and you are clean, but not all”; <verse eid="JHN 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 13:11"/>for He knew him who is delivering Him up; because of this He said, “You are not all clean.” <verse eid="JHN 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 13:12"/>When, therefore, He washed their feet, and took His garments, having reclined again, He said to them, “Do you know what I have done to you? <verse eid="JHN 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 13:13"/>You call Me the Teacher and the LORD, and you say well, for I am; <verse eid="JHN 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 13:14"/>if then I washed your feet—the LORD and the Teacher—you also ought to wash one another’s feet. <verse eid="JHN 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 13:15"/>For I gave to you an example, that, according as I did to you, you also may do; <verse eid="JHN 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 13:16"/>truly, truly, I say to you, a servant is not greater than his lord, nor an apostle greater than he who sent him; <verse eid="JHN 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 13:17"/>if you have known these things, you are blessed if you may do them; <verse eid="JHN 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 13:18"/>I do not speak concerning you all; I have known whom I chose for Myself; but that the Writing may be fulfilled: He who is eating the bread with Me, lifted up his heel against Me. <verse eid="JHN 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 13:19"/>From this time I tell you, before its coming to pass, that, when it may come to pass, you may believe that I AM; <verse eid="JHN 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 13:20"/>truly, truly, I say to you, he who is receiving whomsoever I may send, receives Me; and he who is receiving Me, receives Him who sent Me.” <verse eid="JHN 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 13:21"/>Having said these things, Jesus was troubled in the spirit, and testified and said, “Truly, truly, I say to you that one of you will deliver Me up”; <verse eid="JHN 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 13:22"/>the disciples were looking, therefore, at one another, doubting concerning of whom He speaks. <verse eid="JHN 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 13:23"/>And there was one of His disciples reclining in the bosom of Jesus, whom Jesus was loving; <verse eid="JHN 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 13:24"/>Simon Peter, then, beckons to this one, to inquire who he may be concerning whom He speaks, <verse eid="JHN 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 13:25"/>and that one having leaned back on the breast of Jesus, responds to Him, “Lord, who is it?” <verse eid="JHN 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 13:26"/>Jesus answers, “It is that one to whom I, having dipped the morsel, will give it”; and having dipped the morsel, He gives [it] to Judas of Simon, Iscariot. <verse eid="JHN 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 13:27"/>And after the morsel, then Satan entered into that one. Jesus, therefore, says to him, “What you do—do quickly”; <verse eid="JHN 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 13:28"/>and none of those reclining to eat knew for what intent He said this to him, <verse eid="JHN 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 13:29"/>for certain [of them] were thinking, since Judas had the bag, that Jesus says to him, “Buy what we have need of for the celebration”; or that he may give something to the poor; <verse eid="JHN 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 13:30"/>having received, therefore, the morsel, that one immediately went forth, and it was night. <verse eid="JHN 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 13:31"/>When, therefore, he went forth, Jesus says, “Now was the Son of Man glorified, and God was glorified in Him; <verse eid="JHN 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 13:32"/>if God was glorified in Him, God will also glorify Him in Himself; indeed, He will immediately glorify Him. <verse eid="JHN 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 13:33"/>Little children, yet a little [while] am I with you; you will seek Me, and according as I said to the Jews, I also say to you now: To where I go away, you are not able to come. <verse eid="JHN 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 13:34"/>A new command I give to you, that you love one another; according as I loved you, that you also love one another; <verse eid="JHN 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 13:35"/>in this will all know that you are My disciples, if you may have love one to another.” <verse eid="JHN 13:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 13:36"/>Simon Peter says to Him, “Lord, to where do You go away?” Jesus answered him, “To where I go away, you are not able now to follow Me, but afterward you will follow Me.” <verse eid="JHN 13:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 13:37"/>Peter says to Him, “Lord, why am I not able to follow You now? I will lay down my life for You”; <verse eid="JHN 13:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 13:38"/>Jesus answered him, “You will lay down your life for Me? Truly, truly, I say to you, a rooster will not crow until you may deny Me three times.”<verse eid="JHN 13:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JHN 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 14:1"/>“Do not let your heart be troubled, believe in God, believe also in Me; <verse eid="JHN 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 14:2"/>in the house of My Father are many rooms; and if not, I would have told you; I go on to prepare a place for you; <verse eid="JHN 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 14:3"/>and if I go on and prepare a place for you, I come again, and will receive you to Myself, that where I am you also may be; <verse eid="JHN 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 14:4"/>and to where I go away you have known, and the way you have known.” <verse eid="JHN 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 14:5"/>Thomas says to Him, “Lord, we have not known to where You go away, and how are we able to know the way?” <verse eid="JHN 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 14:6"/>Jesus says to him, “I AM the way, and the truth, and the life, no one comes to the Father, if not through Me; <verse eid="JHN 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 14:7"/>if you had known Me, you would also have known My Father, and from this time you have known Him, and have seen Him.” <verse eid="JHN 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 14:8"/>Philip says to Him, “Lord, show to us the Father, and it is enough for us”; <verse eid="JHN 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 14:9"/>Jesus says to him, “Such [a] long time am I with you, and you have not known Me, Philip? He who has seen Me has seen the Father; and how do you say, Show to us the Father? <verse eid="JHN 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 14:10"/>Do you not believe that I [am] in the Father, and the Father is in Me? The sayings that I speak to you, I do not speak from Myself, and the Father who is abiding in Me does the works Himself; <verse eid="JHN 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 14:11"/>believe Me, that I [am] in the Father, and the Father in Me; and if not, because of the works themselves, believe Me. <verse eid="JHN 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 14:12"/>Truly, truly, I say to you, he who is believing in Me, the works that I do—that one will also do, and greater than these he will do, because I go on to My Father; <verse eid="JHN 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 14:13"/>and whatever you may ask in My Name, I will do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son; <verse eid="JHN 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 14:14"/>if you ask anything in My Name I will do [it]. <verse eid="JHN 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 14:15"/>If you love Me, keep My commands, <verse eid="JHN 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 14:16"/>and I will ask the Father, and He will give to you another Comforter, that He may remain with you throughout the age: <verse eid="JHN 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 14:17"/>the Spirit of truth, whom the world is not able to receive, because it does not see nor know [this] One, and you know [this] One, because [this] One remains with you, and will be in you. <verse eid="JHN 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 14:18"/>I will not leave you bereaved, I come to you; <verse eid="JHN 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 14:19"/>yet a little [while] and the world beholds Me no more, and you behold Me, because I live, and you will live; <verse eid="JHN 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 14:20"/>in that day you will know that I [am] in My Father, and you in Me, and I in you; <verse eid="JHN 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 14:21"/>he who is having My commands, and is keeping them, that one it is who is loving Me, and he who is loving Me will be loved by My Father, and I will love him, and will manifest Myself to him.” <verse eid="JHN 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 14:22"/>Judas says to Him (not the Iscariot), “Lord, what has come to pass, that You are about to manifest Yourself to us, and not to the world?” <verse eid="JHN 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 14:23"/>Jesus answered and said to him, “If anyone may love Me, he will keep My word, and My Father will love him, and We will come to him, and We will make [an] abode with him; <verse eid="JHN 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 14:24"/>he who is not loving Me does not keep My words; and the word that you hear is not Mine, but the Father’s who sent Me. <verse eid="JHN 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 14:25"/>These things I have spoken to you, remaining with you, <verse eid="JHN 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 14:26"/>and the Comforter, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in My Name, He will teach you all things, and remind you of all things that I said to you. <verse eid="JHN 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 14:27"/>Peace I leave to you; My peace I give to you. Not according as the world gives do I give to you. Do not let your heart be troubled, nor let it be afraid. <verse eid="JHN 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 14:28"/>You heard that I said to you, I go away, and I come to you. If you loved Me, you would have rejoiced that I said, I go on to the Father, because My Father is greater than I. <verse eid="JHN 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 14:29"/>And now I have said [it] to you before it comes to pass, that when it may come to pass, you may believe. <verse eid="JHN 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 14:30"/>I will no longer talk much with you, for the ruler of this world comes, and he has nothing in Me; <verse eid="JHN 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 14:31"/>but that the world may know that I love the Father, and according as the Father gave Me command, so I do; arise, we may go from here.”<verse eid="JHN 14:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JHN 15"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 15:1"/>“I AM the true vine, and My Father is the vinedresser; <verse eid="JHN 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 15:2"/>every branch not bearing fruit in Me, He takes it away, and everyone bearing fruit, He cleanses by pruning it, that it may bear more fruit; <verse eid="JHN 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 15:3"/>you are already clean, because of the word that I have spoken to you; <verse eid="JHN 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 15:4"/>remain in Me, and I in you, as the branch is not able to bear fruit of itself, if it may not remain in the vine, so neither you, if you may not remain in Me. <verse eid="JHN 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 15:5"/>I AM the vine, you the branches; he who is remaining in Me, and I in him, this one bears much fruit, because apart from Me you are not able to do anything; <verse eid="JHN 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 15:6"/>if anyone may not remain in Me, he was cast forth outside as the branch, and was withered, and they gather them, and cast into fire, and they are burned; <verse eid="JHN 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 15:7"/>if you may remain in Me, and My sayings may remain in you, whatever you may wish you will ask, and it will be done to you. <verse eid="JHN 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 15:8"/>In this was My Father glorified, that you may bear much fruit, and you will become My disciples. <verse eid="JHN 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 15:9"/>According as the Father loved Me, I also loved you, remain in My love; <verse eid="JHN 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 15:10"/>if you may keep My commands, you will remain in My love, according as I have kept the commands of My Father, and remain in His love; <verse eid="JHN 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 15:11"/>these things I have spoken to you, that My joy in you may remain, and your joy may be full. <verse eid="JHN 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 15:12"/>This is My command, that you love one another, according as I loved you; <verse eid="JHN 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 15:13"/>greater love has no one than this, that anyone may lay down his life for his friends; <verse eid="JHN 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 15:14"/>you are My friends if you may do whatever I command you; <verse eid="JHN 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 15:15"/>I no longer call you servants, because the servant has not known what his lord does, and I have called you friends, because all things that I heard from My Father, I made known to you. <verse eid="JHN 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 15:16"/>You did not choose Me, but I chose you, and appointed you, that you might go away, and might bear fruit, and your fruit might remain, that whatever you may ask of the Father in My Name, He may give you. <verse eid="JHN 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 15:17"/>These things I command you, that you love one another; <verse eid="JHN 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 15:18"/>if the world hates you, you know that it has hated Me before you; <verse eid="JHN 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 15:19"/>if you were of the world, the world would have been cherishing its own, but because you are not of the world, but I chose [you] out of the world—because of this the world hates you. <verse eid="JHN 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 15:20"/>Remember the word that I said to you: A servant is not greater than his lord; if they persecuted Me, they will also persecute you; if they kept My word, they will also keep yours; <verse eid="JHN 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 15:21"/>but all these things will they do to you, because of My Name, because they have not known Him who sent Me; <verse eid="JHN 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 15:22"/>if I had not come and spoken to them, they were not having sin; but now they have no pretext for their sin. <verse eid="JHN 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 15:23"/>He who is hating Me, hates My Father also; <verse eid="JHN 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 15:24"/>if I did not do among them the works that no other has done, they were not having sin, and now they have both seen and hated both Me and My Father; <verse eid="JHN 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 15:25"/>but—that the word may be fulfilled that was written in their law—They hated Me without a cause. <verse eid="JHN 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 15:26"/>And when the Comforter may come, whom I will send to you from the Father—the Spirit of truth, who comes forth from the Father, He will testify of Me; <verse eid="JHN 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 15:27"/>and you also testify, because you are with Me from the beginning.”<verse eid="JHN 15:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JHN 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 16:1"/>“These things I have spoken to you, that you may not be stumbled. <verse eid="JHN 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 16:2"/>They will put you out of the synagogues, but an hour comes that everyone who has killed you may think to offer service to God; <verse eid="JHN 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 16:3"/>and these things they will do to you, because they did not know the Father, nor Me. <verse eid="JHN 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 16:4"/>But these things I have spoken to you, that when the hour may come, you may remember them, that I said [them] to you, and I did not say these things to you from the beginning, because I was with you; <verse eid="JHN 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 16:5"/>and now I go away to Him who sent Me, and none of you asks Me, To where do you go? <verse eid="JHN 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 16:6"/>But because I have said to you these things, the sorrow has filled your heart. <verse eid="JHN 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 16:7"/>But I tell you the truth; it is better for you that I go away, for if I may not go away, the Comforter will not come to you, and if I go on, I will send Him to you; <verse eid="JHN 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 16:8"/>and having come, He will convict the world concerning sin, and concerning righteousness, and concerning judgment; <verse eid="JHN 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 16:9"/>concerning sin indeed, because they do not believe in Me; <verse eid="JHN 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 16:10"/>and concerning righteousness, because I go away to My Father, and you behold Me no more; <verse eid="JHN 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 16:11"/>and concerning judgment, because the ruler of this world has been judged. <verse eid="JHN 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 16:12"/>I have yet many things to say to you, but you are not able to bear [them] now; <verse eid="JHN 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 16:13"/>and when He may come—the Spirit of truth—He will guide you to all the truth, for He will not speak from Himself, but as many things as He will hear He will speak, and the coming things He will tell you; <verse eid="JHN 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 16:14"/>He will glorify Me, because He will take of Mine, and will tell to you. <verse eid="JHN 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 16:15"/>All things, as many as the Father has, are Mine; because of this I said that He will take of Mine, and will tell to you; <verse eid="JHN 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 16:16"/>a little while, and you do not behold Me, and again a little while, and you will see Me, because I go away to the Father.” <verse eid="JHN 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 16:17"/>Therefore [some] of His disciples said to one another, “What is this that He says to us, A little while, and you do not behold Me, and again a little while, and you will see Me, and, Because I go away to the Father?” <verse eid="JHN 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 16:18"/>They said then, “What is this He says—the little while? We have not known what He says.” <verse eid="JHN 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 16:19"/>Jesus, therefore, knew that they were wishing to ask Him, and He said to them, “Concerning this do you seek with one another, because I said, A little while, and you do not behold Me, and again a little while, and you will see Me? <verse eid="JHN 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 16:20"/>Truly, truly, I say to you that you will weep and lament, and the world will rejoice; and you will be sorrowful, but your sorrow will become joy. <verse eid="JHN 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 16:21"/>The woman, when she may bear, has sorrow, because her hour came, and when she may bear the child, she no longer remembers the anguish, because of the joy that a man was born into the world. <verse eid="JHN 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 16:22"/>And you, therefore, now indeed have sorrow; and again I will see you, and your heart will rejoice, and no one takes your joy from you, <verse eid="JHN 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 16:23"/>and in that day you will question nothing of Me; truly, truly, I say to you, as many things as you may ask of the Father in My Name, He will give you; <verse eid="JHN 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 16:24"/>until now you asked nothing in My Name; ask, and you will receive, that your joy may be full. <verse eid="JHN 16:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 16:25"/>I have spoken these things in allegories to you, but there comes an hour when I will no longer speak to you in allegories, but will tell you freely of the Father. <verse eid="JHN 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 16:26"/>In that day you will make request in My Name, and I do not say to you that I will ask the Father for you, <verse eid="JHN 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 16:27"/>for the Father Himself cherishes you, because you have cherished Me, and you have believed that I came forth from God; <verse eid="JHN 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 16:28"/>I came forth from the Father, and have come into the world; again I leave the world, and go on to the Father.” <verse eid="JHN 16:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 16:29"/>His disciples say to Him, “Behold, now You speak freely, and You do not speak allegory; <verse eid="JHN 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 16:30"/>now we have known that You have known all things, and have no need that anyone questions You; in this we believe that You came forth from God.” <verse eid="JHN 16:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 16:31"/>Jesus answered them, “Now do you believe? Behold, there comes an hour, <verse eid="JHN 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 16:32"/>and now it has come, that you may be scattered, each to his own things, and you may leave Me alone, and I am not alone, because the Father is with Me; <verse eid="JHN 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 16:33"/>these things I have spoken to you, that in Me you may have peace, in the world you will have tribulation, but take courage—I have overcome the world.”<verse eid="JHN 16:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JHN 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 17:1"/>These things Jesus spoke, and lifted up His eyes to the sky, and said, “Father, the hour has come, glorify Your Son, that Your Son may also glorify You, <verse eid="JHN 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 17:2"/>according as You gave to Him authority over all flesh, that—all that You have given to Him—He may give to them continuous life; <verse eid="JHN 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 17:3"/>and this is the continuous life, that they may know You, the only true God, and Him whom You sent—Jesus Christ; <verse eid="JHN 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 17:4"/>I glorified You on the earth, having completed the work that You have given Me, that I should do. <verse eid="JHN 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 17:5"/>And now, glorify Me, You Father, with Yourself, with the glory that I had with You before the world was; <verse eid="JHN 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 17:6"/>I revealed Your Name to the men whom You have given to Me out of the world; they were Yours, and You have given them to Me, and they have kept Your word; <verse eid="JHN 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 17:7"/>now they have known that all things, as many as You have given to Me, are from You, <verse eid="JHN 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 17:8"/>because the sayings that You have given to Me, I have given to them, and they themselves received, and have known truly, that I came forth from You, and they believed that You sent Me. <verse eid="JHN 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 17:9"/>I ask in regard to them; I do not ask in regard to the world, but in regard to those whom You have given to Me, because they are Yours, <verse eid="JHN 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 17:10"/>and all Mine are Yours, and Yours [are] Mine, and I have been glorified in them; <verse eid="JHN 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 17:11"/>and I am no longer in the world, and these are in the world, and I come to You. Holy Father, keep them in Your Name, whom You have given to Me, that they may be one as We [are one]; <verse eid="JHN 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 17:12"/>when I was with them in the world, I was keeping them in Your Name; I guarded those whom You have given to Me, and none of them were destroyed, except the son of the destruction, that the Writing may be fulfilled. <verse eid="JHN 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 17:13"/>And now I come to You, and these things I speak in the world, that they may have My joy fulfilled in themselves; <verse eid="JHN 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 17:14"/>I have given Your word to them, and the world hated them, because they are not of the world, as I am not of the world; <verse eid="JHN 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 17:15"/>I do not ask that You may take them out of the world, but that You may keep them out of the evil. <verse eid="JHN 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 17:16"/>They are not of the world, as I am not of the world; <verse eid="JHN 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 17:17"/>sanctify them in Your truth, Your word is truth; <verse eid="JHN 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 17:18"/>as You sent Me into the world, I also sent them into the world; <verse eid="JHN 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 17:19"/>and I sanctify Myself for them, that they also may be sanctified in truth themselves. <verse eid="JHN 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 17:20"/>And I do not ask in regard to these alone, but also in regard to those who will be believing in Me through their word, <verse eid="JHN 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 17:21"/>that they all may be one, as You Father [are] in Me, and I in You, that they also may be one in Us, that the world may believe that You sent Me. <verse eid="JHN 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 17:22"/>And I have given to them the glory that You have given to Me, that they may be one as We are one— <verse eid="JHN 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 17:23"/>I in them, and You in Me, that they may be perfected into one, and that the world may know that You sent Me, and loved them as You loved Me. <verse eid="JHN 17:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 17:24"/>Father, those whom You have given to Me, I will that where I am they also may be with Me, that they may behold My glory that You gave to Me, because You loved Me before the foundation of the world. <verse eid="JHN 17:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 17:25"/>Righteous Father, also the world did not know You, and I knew You, and these have known that You sent Me, <verse eid="JHN 17:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 17:26"/>and I made known to them Your Name, and will make known, that the love with which You loved Me may be in them, and I in them.”<verse eid="JHN 17:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JHN 18"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 18:1"/>Having said these things, Jesus went forth with His disciples beyond the Brook of Kidron, where [there] was a garden, into which He entered, Himself and His disciples, <verse eid="JHN 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 18:2"/>and Judas also, who delivered Him up, had known the place, because Jesus assembled there with His disciples many times. <verse eid="JHN 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 18:3"/>Judas, therefore, having taken the band and officers out of the chief priests and Pharisees, comes there with torches and lamps, and weapons; <verse eid="JHN 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 18:4"/>Jesus, therefore, knowing all things that are coming on Him, having gone forth, said to them, “Whom do you seek?” <verse eid="JHN 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 18:5"/>They answered Him, “Jesus the Nazarene”; Jesus says to them, “I AM”; and Judas who delivered Him up was standing with them. <verse eid="JHN 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 18:6"/>When, therefore, He said to them, “I AM,” they went away backward, and fell to the ground. <verse eid="JHN 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 18:7"/>Again, therefore, He questioned them, “Whom do you seek?” And they said, “Jesus the Nazarene”; <verse eid="JHN 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 18:8"/>Jesus answered, “I said to you that I AM; if, then, you seek Me, permit these to go away”; <verse eid="JHN 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 18:9"/>that the word might be fulfilled that He said, “Those whom You have given to Me, I did not lose even one of them.” <verse eid="JHN 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 18:10"/>Simon Peter, therefore, having a sword, drew it, and struck the chief priest’s servant, and cut off his right ear—and the name of the servant was Malchus— <verse eid="JHN 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 18:11"/>Jesus, therefore, said to Peter, “Put the sword into the sheath; the cup that the Father has given to Me, may I not drink it?” <verse eid="JHN 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 18:12"/>The band, therefore, and the captain, and the officers of the Jews, took hold on Jesus, and bound Him, <verse eid="JHN 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 18:13"/>and they led Him away to Annas first, for he was father-in-law of Caiaphas, who was chief priest of that year, <verse eid="JHN 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 18:14"/>and Caiaphas was he who gave counsel to the Jews that it is good for one man to perish for the people. <verse eid="JHN 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 18:15"/>And following Jesus was Simon Peter, and the other disciple, and that disciple was known to the chief priest, and he entered with Jesus into the hall of the chief priest, <verse eid="JHN 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 18:16"/>and Peter was standing at the door outside, therefore the other disciple who was known to the chief priest went forth, and he spoke to the doorkeeper, and he brought in Peter. <verse eid="JHN 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 18:17"/>Then the maid, the doorkeeper, says to Peter, “Are you also of the disciples of this Man?” He says, “I am not”; <verse eid="JHN 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 18:18"/>and the servants and the officers were standing, having made a fire of coals, because it was cold, and they were warming themselves, and Peter was standing with them, and warming himself. <verse eid="JHN 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 18:19"/>The chief priests, therefore, questioned Jesus concerning His disciples, and concerning His teaching; <verse eid="JHN 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 18:20"/>Jesus answered him, “I spoke freely to the world, I always taught in a synagogue, and in the temple, where the Jews always come together; and I spoke nothing in secret; <verse eid="JHN 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 18:21"/>why do you question Me? Question those having heard what I spoke to them; behold, these have known what I said.” <verse eid="JHN 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 18:22"/>And He having said these things, one of the officers standing by gave Jesus a slap, saying, “Thus do You answer the chief priest?” <verse eid="JHN 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 18:23"/>Jesus answered him, “If I spoke ill, testify concerning the ill; and if well, why do you strike Me?” <verse eid="JHN 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 18:24"/>Annas then sent Him bound to Caiaphas the chief priest. <verse eid="JHN 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 18:25"/>And Simon Peter was standing and warming himself, then they said to him, “Are you also of His disciples?” He denied and said, “I am not.” <verse eid="JHN 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 18:26"/>One of the servants of the chief priest, being a relative of him whose ear Peter cut off, says, “Did I not see you in the garden with Him?” <verse eid="JHN 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 18:27"/>Again, therefore, Peter denied, and immediately a rooster crowed. <verse eid="JHN 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 18:28"/>They led, therefore, Jesus from Caiaphas into the Praetorium, and it was early, and they themselves did not enter into the Praetorium, that they might not be defiled, but that they might eat the Passover; <verse eid="JHN 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 18:29"/>Pilate, therefore, went forth to them and said, “What accusation do you bring against this Man?” <verse eid="JHN 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 18:30"/>They answered and said to him, “If He were not doing evil, we had not delivered Him to you.” <verse eid="JHN 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 18:31"/>Pilate, therefore, said to them, “Take Him—you—and judge Him according to your law”; the Jews, therefore, said to him, “It is not lawful to us to put anyone to death”; <verse eid="JHN 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 18:32"/>that the word of Jesus might be fulfilled which He said, signifying by what death He was about to die. <verse eid="JHN 18:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 18:33"/>Pilate, therefore, entered into the Praetorium again, and called Jesus, and said to Him, “You are the King of the Jews?” <verse eid="JHN 18:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 18:34"/>Jesus answered him, “Do you say this from yourself? Or did others say it to you about Me?” <verse eid="JHN 18:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 18:35"/>Pilate answered, “Am I a Jew? Your nation and the chief priests delivered You up to me; what did You do?” <verse eid="JHN 18:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 18:36"/>Jesus answered, “My kingdom is not of this world; if My kingdom were of this world, My officers had struggled that I might not be delivered up to Jews; but now My kingdom is not from here.” <verse eid="JHN 18:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 18:37"/>Pilate, therefore, said to Him, “Are You then a king?” Jesus answered, “You say [it], because I am a king; I have been born for this, and I have come into the world for this, that I may testify to the truth; everyone who is of the truth, hears My voice.” <verse eid="JHN 18:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 18:38"/>Pilate says to Him, “What is truth?” And having said this, again he went forth to the Jews and says to them, “I find no fault in Him; <verse eid="JHN 18:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 18:39"/>and you have a custom that I will release to you one in the Passover; do you determine, therefore, [that] I will release to you the King of the Jews?” <verse eid="JHN 18:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 18:40"/>Therefore they all cried out again, saying, “Not this One—but Barabbas”; and Barabbas was a robber.<verse eid="JHN 18:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JHN 19"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 19:1"/>Then, therefore, Pilate took Jesus and scourged [Him], <verse eid="JHN 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 19:2"/>and the soldiers having plaited a garland of thorns, placed [it] on His head, and they cast a purple garment around Him, <verse eid="JHN 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 19:3"/>and said, “Hail! The King of the Jews”; and they were giving Him slaps. <verse eid="JHN 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 19:4"/>Pilate, therefore, again went forth outside and says to them, “Behold, I bring Him to you outside, that you may know that I find no fault in Him”; <verse eid="JHN 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 19:5"/>Jesus, therefore, came forth outside, bearing the thorny garland and the purple garment; and he says to them, “Behold, the Man!” <verse eid="JHN 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 19:6"/>When, therefore, the chief priests and the officers saw Him, they cried out, saying, “Crucify! Crucify!” Pilate says to them, “Take Him yourselves and crucify, for I find no fault in Him”; <verse eid="JHN 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 19:7"/>the Jews answered him, “We have a law, and according to our law He ought to die, for He made Himself Son of God.” <verse eid="JHN 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 19:8"/>When, therefore, Pilate heard this word, he was more afraid, <verse eid="JHN 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 19:9"/>and entered again into the Praetorium and says to Jesus, “Where are You from?” And Jesus gave him no answer. <verse eid="JHN 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 19:10"/>Pilate, therefore, says to Him, “Do You not speak to me? Have You not known that I have authority to crucify You, and I have authority to release You?” <verse eid="JHN 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 19:11"/>Jesus answered, “You would have no authority against Me if it were not having been given you from above; because of this, he who is delivering Me up to you has greater sin.” <verse eid="JHN 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 19:12"/>From this [time] Pilate was seeking to release Him, and the Jews were crying out, saying, “If you may release this One, you are not a friend of Caesar; everyone making himself a king speaks against Caesar.” <verse eid="JHN 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 19:13"/>Pilate, therefore, having heard this word, brought Jesus outside—and he sat down on the judgment seat—to a place called, “Pavement,” and in Hebrew, Gabbatha; <verse eid="JHN 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 19:14"/>and it was the Preparation of the Passover, and as it were the sixth hour, and he says to the Jews, “Behold, your King!” <verse eid="JHN 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 19:15"/>And they cried out, “Take away! Take away! Crucify Him!” Pilate says to them, “Will I crucify your King?” The chief priests answered, “We have no king except Caesar.” <verse eid="JHN 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 19:16"/>Then, therefore, he delivered Him up to them, that He may be crucified, and they took Jesus and led [Him] away, <verse eid="JHN 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 19:17"/>and carrying His cross, He went forth to the [place] called “Place of [the] Skull,” which is called in Hebrew, Golgotha— <verse eid="JHN 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 19:18"/>where they crucified Him, and with Him two others, on this side and on that side, but Jesus in the middle. <verse eid="JHN 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 19:19"/>And Pilate also wrote a title, and put [it] on the cross, and it was written: “JESUS THE NAZARENE, THE KING OF THE JEWS”; <verse eid="JHN 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 19:20"/>therefore many of the Jews read this title, because the place was near to the city where Jesus was crucified, and it was having been written in Hebrew, in Greek, in Latin. <verse eid="JHN 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 19:21"/>The chief priests of the Jews therefore said to Pilate, “Do not write, The King of the Jews, but that this One said, I am King of the Jews”; <verse eid="JHN 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 19:22"/>Pilate answered, “What I have written, I have written.” <verse eid="JHN 19:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 19:23"/>The soldiers, therefore, when they crucified Jesus, took His garments, and made four parts, to each soldier a part, also the coat, and the coat was seamless, from the top woven throughout; <verse eid="JHN 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 19:24"/>they said, therefore, to one another, “We may not tear it, but cast a lot for it, whose it will be”; that the Writing might be fulfilled, that is saying, “They divided My garments to themselves, and they cast a lot for My clothing”; the soldiers, therefore, indeed, did these things. <verse eid="JHN 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 19:25"/>And there stood by the cross of Jesus His mother, and His mother’s sister, Mary of Cleopas, and Mary the Magdalene; <verse eid="JHN 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 19:26"/>Jesus, therefore, having seen [His] mother, and the disciple standing by, whom He was loving, He says to His mother, “Woman, behold, your son”; <verse eid="JHN 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 19:27"/>afterward He says to the disciple, “Behold, your mother”; and from that hour the disciple took her to his own [home]. <verse eid="JHN 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 19:28"/>After this, Jesus knowing that all things have now been accomplished, that the Writing may be fulfilled, says, “I thirst”; <verse eid="JHN 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 19:29"/>a vessel, therefore, was placed full of vinegar, and having filled a sponge with vinegar, and having put [it] around a hyssop stalk, they put [it] to His mouth; <verse eid="JHN 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 19:30"/>when, therefore, Jesus received the vinegar, He said, “It has been accomplished.” And having bowed the head, gave up the spirit. <verse eid="JHN 19:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 19:31"/>The Jews, therefore, that the bodies might not remain on the cross on the Sabbath, since it was the Preparation (for that Sabbath day was a great one), asked of Pilate that their legs may be broken, and they [are] taken away. <verse eid="JHN 19:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 19:32"/>The soldiers, therefore, came, and they indeed broke the legs of the first and of the other who was crucified with Him, <verse eid="JHN 19:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 19:33"/>and having come to Jesus, when they saw Him already having been dead, they did not break His legs; <verse eid="JHN 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 19:34"/>but one of the soldiers pierced His side with a spear, and immediately there came forth blood and water; <verse eid="JHN 19:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 19:35"/>and he who has seen has testified, and his testimony is true, and that one has known that he speaks true things, that you also may believe. <verse eid="JHN 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 19:36"/>For these things came to pass, that the Writing may be fulfilled, “A bone of Him will not be broken”; <verse eid="JHN 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 19:37"/>and again another Writing says, “They will look to Him whom they pierced.” <verse eid="JHN 19:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 19:38"/>And after these things, Joseph of Arimathea—being a disciple of Jesus, but concealed, through the fear of the Jews—asked of Pilate, that he may take away the body of Jesus, and Pilate gave leave; he came, therefore, and took away the body of Jesus, <verse eid="JHN 19:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 19:39"/>and Nicodemus also came—who came to Jesus by night at the first—carrying a mixture of myrrh and aloes, as it were, one hundred pounds. <verse eid="JHN 19:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 19:40"/>Therefore they took the body of Jesus, and bound it with linen clothes with the spices, according as it was the custom of the Jews to prepare for burial; <verse eid="JHN 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 19:41"/>and there was a garden in the place where He was crucified, and a new tomb in the garden, in which no one was yet laid; <verse eid="JHN 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 19:42"/>therefore, because the tomb was near, there they laid Jesus because of the Preparation of the Jews.<verse eid="JHN 19:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JHN 20"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 20:1"/>And on the first [day] of the weeks, Mary the Magdalene comes early (there being yet darkness) to the tomb, and she sees the stone having been taken away out of the tomb; <verse eid="JHN 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 20:2"/>she runs, therefore, and comes to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple whom Jesus was cherishing, and says to them, “They took away the Lord out of the tomb, and we have not known where they laid Him.” <verse eid="JHN 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 20:3"/>Peter, therefore, went forth, and the other disciple, and they were coming to the tomb, <verse eid="JHN 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 20:4"/>and the two were running together, and the other disciple ran forward more quickly than Peter, and came first to the tomb, <verse eid="JHN 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 20:5"/>and having stooped down, sees the linen clothes lying, yet, indeed, he did not enter. <verse eid="JHN 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 20:6"/>Simon Peter, therefore, comes, following him, and he entered into the tomb, and beholds the linen clothes lying [there], <verse eid="JHN 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 20:7"/>and the napkin that was on His head not lying with the linen clothes, but apart, having been folded up, in one place; <verse eid="JHN 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 20:8"/>then, therefore, the other disciple who came first to the tomb entered also, and he saw and believed; <verse eid="JHN 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 20:9"/>for they did not yet know the Writing, that it was necessary for Him to rise again out of the dead. <verse eid="JHN 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 20:10"/>The disciples therefore went away again to their own friends, <verse eid="JHN 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 20:11"/>and Mary was standing near the tomb, weeping outside; as she was weeping, then, she stooped down into the tomb, and beholds two messengers in white, sitting, <verse eid="JHN 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 20:12"/>one at the head and one at the feet, where the body of Jesus had been laid. <verse eid="JHN 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 20:13"/>And they say to her, “Woman, why do you weep?” She says to them, “Because they took away my Lord, and I have not known where they laid Him”; <verse eid="JHN 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 20:14"/>and having said these things, she turned backward, and sees Jesus standing, and she had not known that it is Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 20:15"/>Jesus says to her, “Woman, why do you weep? Whom do you seek?” She, supposing that He is the gardener, says to Him, “Lord, if You carried Him away, tell me where You laid Him, and I will take Him away”; <verse eid="JHN 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 20:16"/>Jesus says to her, “Mary!” Having turned, she says to Him, “Rabboni!” That is to say, “Teacher.” <verse eid="JHN 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 20:17"/>Jesus says to her, “Do not be touching Me, for I have not yet ascended to My Father; and be going on to My brothers, and say to them, I ascend to My Father and your Father, and [to] My God and your God.” <verse eid="JHN 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 20:18"/>Mary the Magdalene comes, reporting to the disciples that she has seen the LORD, and [that] He said these things to her. <verse eid="JHN 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 20:19"/>It being, therefore, evening, on that day, the first [day] of the weeks, and the doors having been shut where the disciples were assembled through fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in the midst, and says to them, “Peace to you”; <verse eid="JHN 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 20:20"/>and having said this, He showed them His hands and side; the disciples, therefore, rejoiced, having seen the LORD. <verse eid="JHN 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 20:21"/>Jesus, therefore, said to them again, “Peace to you; according as the Father has sent Me, I also send you”; <verse eid="JHN 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 20:22"/>having said this, He breathed on [them], and says to them, “Receive the Holy Spirit; <verse eid="JHN 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 20:23"/>if you may forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven them; if you may retain of any, they have been retained.” <verse eid="JHN 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 20:24"/>And Thomas, one of the Twelve, who is called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came; <verse eid="JHN 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 20:25"/>the other disciples, therefore, said to him, “We have seen the Lord!” And he said to them, “If I may not see the mark of the nails in His hands, and may [not] put my finger into the mark of the nails, and may [not] put my hand into His side, I will not believe.” <verse eid="JHN 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 20:26"/>And after eight days, again His disciples were within, and Thomas [was] with them; Jesus comes, the doors having been shut, and He stood in the midst and said, “Peace to you!” <verse eid="JHN 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 20:27"/>Then He says to Thomas, “Bring your finger here, and see My hands, and bring your hand, and put [it] into My side, and do not become unbelieving, but believing.” <verse eid="JHN 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 20:28"/>And Thomas answered and said to Him, “My Lord and my God!” <verse eid="JHN 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 20:29"/>Jesus says to him, “Because you have seen Me, Thomas, you have believed; blessed [are] those having not seen, and having believed.” <verse eid="JHN 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 20:30"/>Many indeed, therefore, other signs Jesus also did before His disciples that are not written in this scroll; <verse eid="JHN 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 20:31"/>and these have been written that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and that believing, you may have life in His Name.<verse eid="JHN 20:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JHN 21"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 21:1"/>After these things Jesus Himself again appeared to the disciples on the Sea of Tiberias, and He revealed Himself thus: <verse eid="JHN 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 21:2"/>Simon Peter, and Thomas who is called Didymus, and Nathanael from Cana of Galilee, and the [sons] of Zebedee, and two of His other disciples were together. <verse eid="JHN 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 21:3"/>Simon Peter says to them, “I go away to fish”; they say to him, “We go—we also—with you”; they went forth and immediately entered into the boat, and on that night they caught nothing. <verse eid="JHN 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 21:4"/>And morning having now come, Jesus stood at the shore, yet indeed the disciples did not know that it is Jesus; <verse eid="JHN 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 21:5"/>Jesus, therefore, says to them, “Boys, do you have any meat?” <verse eid="JHN 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 21:6"/>They answered Him, “No”; and He said to them, “Cast the net at the right side of the boat, and you will find [some]”; they cast, therefore, and no longer were they able to draw it, from the multitude of the fishes. <verse eid="JHN 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 21:7"/>That disciple, therefore, whom Jesus was loving says to Peter, “It is the Lord!” Simon Peter, therefore, having heard that it is the LORD, girded on the outer coat (for he was naked), and cast himself into the sea; <verse eid="JHN 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 21:8"/>and the other disciples came by the little boat, for they were not far from the land, but about two hundred cubits away, dragging the net of the fishes; <verse eid="JHN 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 21:9"/>when, therefore, they came to the land, they behold a fire of coals lying [there], and a fish lying on it, and bread. <verse eid="JHN 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 21:10"/>Jesus says to them, “Bring from the fishes that you caught now”; <verse eid="JHN 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 21:11"/>Simon Peter went up, and drew the net up on the land, full of great fishes—one hundred fifty-three; and though they were so many, the net was not split. <verse eid="JHN 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 21:12"/>Jesus says to them, “Come, dine”; and none of the disciples were venturing to inquire of Him, “Who are You?” Knowing that it is the LORD; <verse eid="JHN 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 21:13"/>Jesus, therefore, comes and takes the bread and gives [it] to them, and the fish in like manner; <verse eid="JHN 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 21:14"/>this [is] now a third time Jesus was revealed to His disciples, having been raised from the dead. <verse eid="JHN 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 21:15"/>When, therefore, they dined, Jesus says to Simon Peter, “Simon, [son] of Jonas, do you love Me more than these?” He says to Him, “Yes, Lord; You have known that I cherish You”; He says to him, “Feed My lambs.” <verse eid="JHN 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 21:16"/>He says to him again, a second time, “Simon, [son] of Jonas, do you love Me?” He says to Him, “Yes, Lord; You have known that I cherish You”; He says to him, “Tend My sheep.” <verse eid="JHN 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 21:17"/>He says to him the third time, “Simon, [son] of Jonas, do you cherish Me?” Peter was grieved that He said to him the third time, “Do you cherish Me?” And he said to Him, “Lord, You have known all things; You know that I cherish You.” Jesus says to him, “Feed My sheep; <verse eid="JHN 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 21:18"/>truly, truly, I say to you, when you were younger, you were girding yourself and were walking to where you willed, but when you may be old, you will stretch forth your hands, and another will gird you, and will carry [you] to where you do not will”; <verse eid="JHN 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 21:19"/>and this He said, signifying by what death he will glorify God; and having said this, He says to him, “Follow Me.” <verse eid="JHN 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 21:20"/>And having turned, Peter sees the disciple whom Jesus was loving following (who also reclined in the dinner on His breast and said, “Lord, who is he who is delivering You up?”) <verse eid="JHN 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 21:21"/>Having seen this one, Peter says to Jesus, “Lord, and what of this one?” <verse eid="JHN 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 21:22"/>Jesus says to him, “If I will him to remain until I come, what [is that] to you? Follow Me.” <verse eid="JHN 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 21:23"/>This word, therefore, went forth to the brothers that this disciple does not die, yet Jesus did not say to him that he does not die, but, “If I will him to remain until I come, what [is that] to you?” <verse eid="JHN 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 21:24"/>This is the disciple who is testifying concerning these things, and he wrote these things, and we have known that his testimony is true. <verse eid="JHN 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 21:25"/>And there are also many other things—as many as Jesus did—which, if they may be written one by one, I think the world itself does not even have place for the scrolls written. Amen.<verse eid="JHN 21:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 21"/>
</usx>
