<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JOS" style="id">- Literal Standard Version</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Book of Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc2">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jos</para>
  <para style="mt">Joshua</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JOS 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 1:1"/>And it comes to pass after the death of Moses, servant of YHWH, that YHWH speaks to Joshua son of Nun, minister of Moses, saying, <verse eid="JOS 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 1:2"/>“My servant Moses is dead, and now, rise, pass over this Jordan, you and all this people, to the land which I am giving to them, to the sons of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 1:3"/>Every place on which the sole of your foot treads, I have given it to you, as I have spoken to Moses. <verse eid="JOS 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 1:4"/>From this wilderness and Lebanon, and to the great river, the Euphrates River, all the land of the Hittites, and to the Great Sea—the going in of the sun—is your border. <verse eid="JOS 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 1:5"/>No man stations himself before you all [the] days of your life; as I have been with Moses, I am with you, I do not fail you, nor forsake you; <verse eid="JOS 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 1:6"/>be strong and courageous, for you cause this people to inherit the land which I have sworn to their fathers to give to them. <verse eid="JOS 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 1:7"/>Only, be strong and very courageous, to observe to do according to all the Law which Moses My servant commanded you; you do not turn aside from it right or left, so that you act wisely in every [place] to where you go; <verse eid="JOS 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 1:8"/>the scroll of this Law does not depart out of your mouth, and you have meditated in it by day and by night, so that you observe to do according to all that is written in it, for then you cause your way to prosper, and then you act wisely. <verse eid="JOS 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 1:9"/>Have I not commanded you? Be strong and courageous; do not be terrified nor frightened, for your God YHWH [is] with you in every [place] to where you go.” <verse eid="JOS 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 1:10"/>And Joshua commands the authorities of the people, saying, <verse eid="JOS 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 1:11"/>“Pass over into the midst of the camp, and command the people, saying, Prepare provision for yourselves, for within three days you are passing over this Jordan, to go in to possess the land which your God YHWH is giving to you to possess it.” <verse eid="JOS 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 1:12"/>And to the Reubenite, and to the Gadite, and to the half of the tribe of Manasseh, Joshua has spoken, saying, <verse eid="JOS 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 1:13"/>“Remember the word which Moses, servant of YHWH, commanded you, saying, Your God YHWH is giving rest to you, and He has given this land to you; <verse eid="JOS 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 1:14"/>your wives, your infants, and your substance, abide in the land which Moses has given to you beyond the Jordan, and you pass over by fifties, before your brothers, all the mighty men of valor, and have helped them, <verse eid="JOS 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 1:15"/>until YHWH gives rest to your brothers as to yourselves, and they have possessed, even they, the land which your God YHWH is giving to them; then you have turned back to the land of your possession, and have possessed it, which Moses, servant of YHWH, has given to you beyond the Jordan, [at] the sun-rising.” <verse eid="JOS 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 1:16"/>And they answer Joshua, saying, “All that you have commanded us we do; and to every [place] to where you send us, we go; <verse eid="JOS 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 1:17"/>according to all that we listened to [from] Moses, so we listen to you; surely your God YHWH is with you as He has been with Moses. <verse eid="JOS 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 1:18"/>Any man who provokes your mouth, and does not hear your words, in all that you command him, is put to death; only, be strong and courageous.”<verse eid="JOS 1:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JOS 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 2:1"/>And Joshua son of Nun silently sends two men, spies, from Shittim, saying, “Go, see the land—and Jericho”; and they go and come into the house of a woman, a harlot, and her name [is] Rahab, and they lie down there. <verse eid="JOS 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 2:2"/>And it is told to the king of Jericho, saying, “Behold, men have come in here tonight, from the sons of Israel, to search the land.” <verse eid="JOS 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 2:3"/>And the king of Jericho sends to Rahab, saying, “Bring out the men who are coming to you, who have come into your house, for they have come to search the entirety of the land.” <verse eid="JOS 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 2:4"/>And the woman takes the two men, and hides them, and says thus: “The men came to me, and I have not known where they [are] from; <verse eid="JOS 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 2:5"/>and it comes to pass—the gate is to [be] shut—in the dark, and the men have gone out; I have not known to where the men have gone; pursue, hurry after them, for you overtake them”; <verse eid="JOS 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 2:6"/>and she has caused them to go up on the roof, and hides them with the flax wood, which is arranged for her on the roof. <verse eid="JOS 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 2:7"/>And the men have pursued after them the way of the Jordan, by the fords, and they have shut the gate afterward when the pursuers have gone out after them. <verse eid="JOS 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 2:8"/>And before they lie down, she has gone up to them on the roof, <verse eid="JOS 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 2:9"/>and she says to the men, “I have known that YHWH has given the land to you, and that your terror has fallen on us, and that all the inhabitants of the land have melted at your presence. <verse eid="JOS 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 2:10"/>For we have heard how YHWH dried up the waters of the Red Sea at your presence, in your going out of Egypt, and that which you have done to the two kings of the Amorite who [are] beyond the Jordan; to Sihon and to Og whom you devoted. <verse eid="JOS 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 2:11"/>And we hear, and our heart melts, and there has not stood anymore spirit in [any] man from your presence, for He, your God YHWH, [is] God in the heavens above and on the earth below. <verse eid="JOS 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 2:12"/>And now, please swear to me by YHWH—because I have done kindness with you—that you have done, even you, kindness with the house of my father, and have given a true token to me, <verse eid="JOS 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 2:13"/>and have kept alive my father, and my mother, and my brothers, and my sisters, and all that they have, and have delivered our souls from death.” <verse eid="JOS 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 2:14"/>And the men say to her, “Our soul to die for yours; if you do not declare this—our matter, then it has been, in YHWH’s giving this land to us, that we have done kindness and truth with you.” <verse eid="JOS 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 2:15"/>And she causes them to go down by a rope through the window, for her house [is] in the side of the wall, and she [is] dwelling in the wall; <verse eid="JOS 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 2:16"/>and she says to them, “Go to the mountain, lest the pursuers come on you; and you have been hidden there three days until the turning back of the pursuers, and afterward you go on your way.” <verse eid="JOS 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 2:17"/>And the men say to her, “We are acquitted of this, your oath, which you have caused us to swear: <verse eid="JOS 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 2:18"/>behold, we are coming into the land, bind this line of scarlet thread to the window by which you have caused us to go down, and gather your father, and your mother, and your brothers, and all the house of your father to you, to the house; <verse eid="JOS 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 2:19"/>and it has been, anyone who goes out from the doors of your house outside, his blood [is] on his head, and we are innocent; and anyone who is with you in the house, his blood [is] on our head, if a hand is on him; <verse eid="JOS 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 2:20"/>and if you declare this—our matter, then we have been acquitted from your oath which you have caused us to swear.” <verse eid="JOS 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 2:21"/>And she says, “According to your words, so it [is]”; and she sends them away, and they go; and she binds the scarlet line to the window. <verse eid="JOS 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 2:22"/>And they go, and come to the mountain, and abide there three days until the pursuers have turned back; and the pursuers seek in all the way, and have not found. <verse eid="JOS 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 2:23"/>And the two men turn back, and come down from the hill, and pass over, and come to Joshua son of Nun, and recount to him all that has come on them; <verse eid="JOS 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 2:24"/>and they say to Joshua, “Surely YHWH has given all the land into our hand; and also, all the inhabitants of the land have melted at our presence.”<verse eid="JOS 2:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JOS 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 3:1"/>And Joshua rises early in the morning, and they journey from Shittim, and come to the Jordan, he and all the sons of Israel, and they lodge there before they pass over. <verse eid="JOS 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 3:2"/>And it comes to pass, at the end of three days, that the authorities pass over into the midst of the camp, <verse eid="JOS 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 3:3"/>and command the people, saying, “When you see the Ark of the Covenant of your God YHWH, and the priests, the Levites, carrying it, then you journey from your place, and have gone after it; <verse eid="JOS 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 3:4"/>only, a distance is between you and it, about two thousand cubits by measure; you do not come near to it, so that you know the way in which you go, for you have not passed over in the way before.” <verse eid="JOS 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 3:5"/>And Joshua says to the people, “Sanctify yourselves, for tomorrow YHWH does wonders in your midst.” <verse eid="JOS 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 3:6"/>And Joshua speaks to the priests, saying, “Take up the Ark of the Covenant, and pass over before the people”; and they take up the Ark of the Covenant, and go before the people. <verse eid="JOS 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 3:7"/>And YHWH says to Joshua, “This day I begin to make you great in the eyes of all Israel, so that they know that as I was with Moses I am with you; <verse eid="JOS 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 3:8"/>and you, command the priests carrying the Ark of the Covenant, saying, When you come to the extremity of the waters of the Jordan, stand in the Jordan.” <verse eid="JOS 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 3:9"/>And Joshua says to the sons of Israel, “Come near here, and hear the words of your God YHWH”; <verse eid="JOS 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 3:10"/>and Joshua says, “By this you know that the living God [is] in your midst, and He certainly dispossesses from before you the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Hivite, and the Perizzite, and the Girgashite, and the Amorite, and the Jebusite: <verse eid="JOS 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 3:11"/>behold, the Ark of the Covenant of the Lord of all the earth is passing over before you into the Jordan; <verse eid="JOS 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 3:12"/>and now, take for yourselves twelve men out of the tribes of Israel, one man—one man for a tribe; <verse eid="JOS 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 3:13"/>and it has been, at the resting of the soles of the feet of the priests carrying the Ark of YHWH, Lord of all the earth, in the waters of the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan are cut off—the waters which are coming down from above—and they stand—one heap.” <verse eid="JOS 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 3:14"/>And it comes to pass, in the journeying of the people from their tents to pass over the Jordan, and of the priests carrying the Ark of the Covenant before the people, <verse eid="JOS 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 3:15"/>and at those carrying the Ark coming to the Jordan, and the feet of the priests carrying the Ark have been dipped in the extremity of the waters (and the Jordan is full over all its banks all the days of harvest)— <verse eid="JOS 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 3:16"/>that the waters stand; those coming down from above have risen—one heap, very far above Adam, the city which [is] at the side of Zaretan; and those going down by the Sea of the Plain (the Salt Sea), have been completely cut off; and the people have passed through opposite Jericho; <verse eid="JOS 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 3:17"/>and the priests carrying the Ark of the Covenant of YHWH stand on dry ground in the midst of the Jordan—established, and all Israel are passing over on dry ground until all the nation has completed to pass over the Jordan.<verse eid="JOS 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JOS 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 4:1"/>And it comes to pass, when all the nation has completed to pass over the Jordan, that YHWH speaks to Joshua, saying, <verse eid="JOS 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 4:2"/>“Take for yourselves twelve men out of the people, one man—one man out of a tribe; <verse eid="JOS 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 4:3"/>and command them, saying, Take up for yourselves from this [place], from the midst of the Jordan, from the established standing-place of the feet of the priests, twelve stones, and you have removed them over with you, and placed them in the lodging-place in which you lodge tonight.” <verse eid="JOS 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 4:4"/>And Joshua calls to the twelve men whom he prepared out of the sons of Israel, one man—one man out of a tribe; <verse eid="JOS 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 4:5"/>and Joshua says to them, “Pass over before the Ark of your God YHWH into the midst of the Jordan, and each of you lift up one stone on his shoulder, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Israel, <verse eid="JOS 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 4:6"/>so that this is a sign in your midst when your children ask hereafter, saying, What [are] these stones to you? <verse eid="JOS 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 4:7"/>That you have said to them, Because the waters of the Jordan were cut off, at the presence of the Ark of the Covenant of YHWH; in its passing over into the Jordan the waters of the Jordan were cut off; and these stones have been for a memorial to the sons of Israel for all time.” <verse eid="JOS 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 4:8"/>And the sons of Israel do so as Joshua commanded, and take up twelve stones out of the midst of the Jordan, as YHWH has spoken to Joshua, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Israel, and remove them over with them to the lodging-place, and place them there, <verse eid="JOS 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 4:9"/>even the twelve stones Joshua has raised up out of the midst of the Jordan, the place of the standing of the feet of the priests carrying the Ark of the Covenant, and they are there to this day. <verse eid="JOS 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 4:10"/>And the priests carrying the Ark are standing in the midst of the Jordan until the completion of the whole thing which YHWH commanded Joshua to speak to the people, according to all that Moses commanded Joshua, and the people hurry and pass over. <verse eid="JOS 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 4:11"/>And it comes to pass, when all the people have completed to pass over, that the Ark of YHWH passes over, and the priests, in the presence of the people; <verse eid="JOS 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 4:12"/>and the sons of Reuben, and the sons of Gad, and the half of the tribe of Manasseh, pass over, by fifties, before the sons of Israel, as Moses had spoken to them; <verse eid="JOS 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 4:13"/>about forty thousand, armed ones of the host, passed over before YHWH for battle, to the plains of Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 4:14"/>On that day YHWH has made Joshua great in the eyes of all Israel, and they fear him, as they feared Moses, all [the] days of his life. <verse eid="JOS 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 4:15"/>And YHWH speaks to Joshua, saying, <verse eid="JOS 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 4:16"/>“Command the priests carrying the Ark of the Testimony, and they come up out of the Jordan.” <verse eid="JOS 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 4:17"/>And Joshua commands the priests, saying, “Come up out of the Jordan.” <verse eid="JOS 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 4:18"/>And it comes to pass, in the coming up of the priests carrying the Ark of the Covenant of YHWH out of the midst of the Jordan—the soles of the feet of the priests have been drawn up into the dry ground—and the waters of the Jordan return to their place, and go over all its banks as before. <verse eid="JOS 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 4:19"/>And the people have come up out of the Jordan on the tenth of the first month, and encamp in Gilgal, in the extremity east of Jericho; <verse eid="JOS 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 4:20"/>and these twelve stones, which they have taken out of the Jordan, Joshua has raised up in Gilgal. <verse eid="JOS 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 4:21"/>And he speaks to the sons of Israel, saying, “When your sons ask their fathers hereafter, saying, What [are] these stones? <verse eid="JOS 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 4:22"/>Then you have caused your sons to know, saying, Israel passed over this Jordan on dry land; <verse eid="JOS 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 4:23"/>because your God YHWH dried up the waters of the Jordan at your presence, until your passing over, as your God YHWH did to the Red Sea which He dried up at our presence until our passing over; <verse eid="JOS 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 4:24"/>so that all the people of the land know the hand of YHWH—that it [is] strong, so that you have feared your God YHWH [for] all the days.”<verse eid="JOS 4:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JOS 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 5:1"/>And it comes to pass, when all the kings of the Amorite which [are] beyond the Jordan, toward the sea, and all the kings of the Canaanite which [are] by the sea, hear how that YHWH has dried up the waters of the Jordan at the presence of the sons of Israel until their passing over, that their heart is melted, and there has not been anymore spirit in them because of the presence of the sons of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 5:2"/>At that time YHWH said to Joshua, “Make knives of flint for yourself, and return, circumcise the sons of Israel a second time”; <verse eid="JOS 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 5:3"/>and Joshua makes knives of flint for himself, and circumcises the sons of Israel at the height of the foreskins. <verse eid="JOS 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 5:4"/>And this [is] the thing [for] which Joshua circumcises [them]: all the people who are coming out of Egypt, who are males, all the men of war have died in the wilderness, in the way, in their coming out of Egypt, <verse eid="JOS 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 5:5"/>for all the people who are coming out were circumcised, and all the people who [are] born in the wilderness, in the way, in their coming out from Egypt, they have not circumcised; <verse eid="JOS 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 5:6"/>for forty years the sons of Israel have gone in the wilderness, until all the nation of the men of war who are coming out of Egypt, who did not listen to the voice of YHWH, to whom YHWH has sworn not to show them the land which YHWH swore to their fathers to give to us, a land flowing with milk and honey, are consumed; <verse eid="JOS 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 5:7"/>and He raised up their sons in their stead, Joshua has circumcised them, for they have been uncircumcised, for they have not circumcised them in the way. <verse eid="JOS 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 5:8"/>And it comes to pass, when all the nation has completed to be circumcised, that they abide in their places in the camp until their recovering; <verse eid="JOS 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 5:9"/>and YHWH says to Joshua, “Today I have rolled the reproach of Egypt from off you”; and [one] calls the name of that place Gilgal to this day. <verse eid="JOS 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 5:10"/>And the sons of Israel encamp in Gilgal, and make the Passover on the fourteenth day of the month, at evening, in the plains of Jericho; <verse eid="JOS 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 5:11"/>and they eat of the old grain of the land on the next day of the Passover, unleavened things and roasted [grain], on this very same day; <verse eid="JOS 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 5:12"/>and the manna ceases on the next day in their eating of the old grain of the land, and there has been no more manna for [the] sons of Israel, and they eat of the increase of the land of Canaan in that year. <verse eid="JOS 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 5:13"/>And it comes to pass in Joshua’s being by Jericho, that he lifts up his eyes, and looks, and behold, [there is] one standing in front of him, and his drawn sword [is] in his hand, and Joshua goes to him, and says to him, “Are you for us or for our adversaries?” <verse eid="JOS 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 5:14"/>And He says, “No, for I [am] Prince of YHWH’s host; now I have come”; and Joshua falls on his face to the earth, and pays respect, and says to Him, “What is my Lord speaking to His servant?” <verse eid="JOS 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 5:15"/>And the Prince of YHWH’s host says to Joshua, “Cast off your shoe from off your foot, for the place on which you are standing is holy”; and Joshua does so.<verse eid="JOS 5:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JOS 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 6:1"/>And Jericho shuts itself up, and is shut up, because of the presence of the sons of Israel—none going out, and none coming in. <verse eid="JOS 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 6:2"/>And YHWH says to Joshua, “See, I have given Jericho and its king into your hand—mighty men of valor, <verse eid="JOS 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 6:3"/>and you have surrounded the city—all the men of battle—going around the city once; thus you do [for] six days; <verse eid="JOS 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 6:4"/>and seven priests carry seven horns of the rams before the Ark, and on the seventh day you go around the city seven times, and the priests blow with the horns, <verse eid="JOS 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 6:5"/>and it has been, in the prolonging of the horn of the ram, in your hearing the voice of the horn, all the people shout [with] a great shout, and the wall of the city has fallen under it, and the people have gone up, each straight before him.” <verse eid="JOS 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 6:6"/>And Joshua son of Nun calls to the priests and says to them, “Carry the Ark of the Covenant, and seven priests carry seven horns of the rams before the Ark of YHWH”; <verse eid="JOS 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 6:7"/>and He said to the people, “Pass over, and go around the city, and he who is armed passes over before the Ark of YHWH.” <verse eid="JOS 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 6:8"/>And it comes to pass, when Joshua speaks to the people, that the seven priests carrying seven horns of the rams before YHWH have passed over and blown with the horns, and the Ark of the Covenant of YHWH is going after them; <verse eid="JOS 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 6:9"/>and he who is armed is going before the priests blowing the horns, and he who is gathering up is going after the Ark, going on and blowing with the horns; <verse eid="JOS 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 6:10"/>and Joshua has commanded the people, saying, “Do not shout, nor cause your voice to be heard, nor does a word go out from your mouth, until the day of my saying to you, Shout! Then you have shouted.” <verse eid="JOS 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 6:11"/>And the Ark of YHWH goes around the city, going around once, and they come into the camp, and lodge in the camp. <verse eid="JOS 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 6:12"/>And Joshua rises early in the morning, and the priests carry the Ark of YHWH, <verse eid="JOS 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 6:13"/>and seven priests carrying seven horns of the rams before the Ark of YHWH are walking, going on, and they have blown with the horns—and he who is armed is going before them, and he who is gathering up is going behind the Ark of YHWH—going on and blowing with the horns. <verse eid="JOS 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 6:14"/>And they go around the city once on the second day, and return to the camp; thus they have done [for] six days. <verse eid="JOS 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 6:15"/>And it comes to pass, on the seventh day, that they rise early, at the ascending of the dawn, and go around the city, according to this manner, seven times; (only on that day have they gone around the city seven times); <verse eid="JOS 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 6:16"/>and it comes to pass, at the seventh time, the priests have blown with the horns, and Joshua says to the people, “Shout! For YHWH has given the city to you; <verse eid="JOS 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 6:17"/>and the city has been devoted, it and all that [is] in it, to YHWH; only Rahab the harlot lives, she and all who [are] with her in the house, for she hid the messengers whom we sent; <verse eid="JOS 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 6:18"/>and surely you have kept from the devoted thing, lest you devote [yourselves], and have taken from the devoted thing, and have made the camp of Israel become a devoted thing, and have troubled it; <verse eid="JOS 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 6:19"/>and all the silver and gold, and vessels of bronze and iron—it [is] holy to YHWH; it comes into the treasury of YHWH.” <verse eid="JOS 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 6:20"/>And the people shout, and blow with the horns, and it comes to pass, when the people hear the voice of the horn, that the people shout [with] a great shout, and the wall falls under it, and the people goes up into the city, each straight before him, and they capture the city; <verse eid="JOS 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 6:21"/>and they devote all that [is] in the city, from man even to woman, from young even to aged, even to ox, and sheep, and donkey, by the mouth of the sword. <verse eid="JOS 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 6:22"/>And Joshua said to the two men who are spying out the land, “Go into the house of the woman, the harlot, and bring out the woman from there, and all whom she has, as you have sworn to her.” <verse eid="JOS 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 6:23"/>And the young men, those spying, go in and bring out Rahab, and her father, and her mother, and her brothers, and all whom she has; indeed, they have brought out all her relatives, and place them at the outside of the camp of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 6:24"/>And they have burned the city with fire, and all that [is] in it; only, the silver and the gold, and the vessels of bronze, and of iron, they have given [to] the treasury of the house of YHWH; <verse eid="JOS 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 6:25"/>and Rahab the harlot, and the house of her father, and all whom she has, Joshua has kept alive; and she dwells in the midst of Israel to this day, for she hid the messengers whom Joshua sent to spy out Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 6:26"/>And Joshua adjures [them] at that time, saying, “Cursed [is] the man before YHWH who raises up and has built this city, [even] Jericho; he lays its foundation in his firstborn, and he sets up its doors in his youngest.” <verse eid="JOS 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 6:27"/>And YHWH is with Joshua, and his fame is in all the land.<verse eid="JOS 6:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JOS 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 7:1"/>And the sons of Israel commit a trespass in the devoted thing, and Achan, son of Carmi, son of Zabdi, son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, takes from the devoted thing, and the anger of YHWH burns against the sons of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 7:2"/>And Joshua sends men from Jericho to Ai, which [is] near Beth-Aven, on the east of Bethel, and speaks to them, saying, “Go up and spy out the land”; and the men go up and spy Ai, <verse eid="JOS 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 7:3"/>and they return to Joshua, and say to him, “Do not let all the people go up; let about two thousand men, or about three thousand men, go up, and they strike Ai; do not cause all the people to labor there; for they [are] few.” <verse eid="JOS 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 7:4"/>So about three thousand men of the people go up from there, and they flee before the men of Ai, <verse eid="JOS 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 7:5"/>and the men of Ai strike about thirty-six men from them, and pursue them before the gate to Shebarim, and they strike them in Morad; and the heart of the people is melted, and becomes water. <verse eid="JOS 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 7:6"/>And Joshua tears his garments, and falls on his face to the earth before the Ark of YHWH until the evening, he and [the] elderly of Israel, and they cause dust to go up on their head. <verse eid="JOS 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 7:7"/>And Joshua says, “Aah! Lord YHWH, why have You caused this people to pass over the Jordan at all, to give us into the hand of the Amorite to destroy us? And oh that we had been willing—and we dwell beyond the Jordan! <verse eid="JOS 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 7:8"/>Oh, Lord, what do I say, after that Israel has turned the neck before its enemies? <verse eid="JOS 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 7:9"/>And the Canaanite and all the inhabitants of the land hear, and have come around against us, and cut off our name from the earth; and what do You do for Your great Name?” <verse eid="JOS 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 7:10"/>And YHWH says to Joshua, “Rise, for you—why this—[that] you [are] falling on your face? <verse eid="JOS 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 7:11"/>Israel has sinned, and they have also transgressed My covenant which I commanded them, and also taken of the devoted thing, and also stolen, and also deceived, and also put [it] among their vessels, <verse eid="JOS 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 7:12"/>and the sons of Israel have not been able to stand before their enemies; they turn the neck before their enemies, for they have become a devoted thing; I do not add to be with you—if you do not destroy the devoted thing from your midst. <verse eid="JOS 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 7:13"/>Rise, sanctify the people, and you have said, Sanctify yourselves for tomorrow; for thus said YHWH, God of Israel: A devoted thing [is] in your midst, O Israel, you are not able to stand before your enemies until your turning aside the devoted thing from your midst; <verse eid="JOS 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 7:14"/>and you have been brought near in the morning by your tribes, and it has been [that] the tribe which YHWH captures draws near by families, and the family which YHWH captures draws near by households, and the household which YHWH captures draws near by men; <verse eid="JOS 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 7:15"/>and it has been, he who is captured with the devoted thing is burned with fire, he and all that he has, because he has transgressed the covenant of YHWH, and because he has done folly in Israel.” <verse eid="JOS 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 7:16"/>And Joshua rises early in the morning, and brings Israel near by its tribes, and the tribe of Judah is captured; <verse eid="JOS 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 7:17"/>and he brings the family of Judah near, and he captures the family of the Zerahite; and he brings the family of the Zerahite near by men, and Zabdi is captured; <verse eid="JOS 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 7:18"/>and he brings his household near by men, and Achan—son of Carmi, son of Zabdi, son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah—is captured. <verse eid="JOS 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 7:19"/>And Joshua says to Achan, “My son, please give glory to YHWH, God of Israel, and give thanks to Him, and now declare to me what you have done—do not hide [it] from me.” <verse eid="JOS 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 7:20"/>And Achan answers Joshua and says, “Truly I have sinned against YHWH, God of Israel, and I have done thus and thus; <verse eid="JOS 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 7:21"/>and I see among the spoil a good robe of Shinar, and two hundred shekels of silver, and one wedge of gold, whose weight [is] fifty shekels, and I desire them, and take them; and behold, they [are] hid in the earth, in the midst of my tent, and the silver [is] under it.” <verse eid="JOS 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 7:22"/>And Joshua sends messengers, and they run to the tent, and behold, it is hidden in his tent, and the silver [is] under it; <verse eid="JOS 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 7:23"/>and they take them out of the midst of the tent, and bring them to Joshua, and to all the sons of Israel, and pour them out before YHWH. <verse eid="JOS 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 7:24"/>And Joshua takes Achan son of Zerah, and the silver, and the robe, and the wedge of gold, and his sons, and his daughters, and his ox, and his donkey, and his flock, and his tent, and all that he has, and all Israel with him, and they brought them up [to] the Valley of Achor. <verse eid="JOS 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 7:25"/>And Joshua says, “Why have you troubled us? YHWH troubles you this day!” And all Israel cast stone at him, and they burn them with fire, and they stone them with stones, <verse eid="JOS 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 7:26"/>and they raise up a great heap of stones over him to this day, and YHWH turns back from the heat of His anger, therefore [one] has called the name of that place “Valley of Achor” until this day.<verse eid="JOS 7:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JOS 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 8:1"/>And YHWH says to Joshua, “Do not fear, nor be frightened, take with you all the people of war, and rise, go up to Ai; see, I have given into your hand the king of Ai, and his people, and his city, and his land, <verse eid="JOS 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 8:2"/>and you have done to Ai and to her king as you have done to Jericho and to her king; only spoil its spoil and its livestock for yourselves; for you set an ambush for the city at its rear.” <verse eid="JOS 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 8:3"/>And Joshua rises, and all the people of war, to go up to Ai, and Joshua chooses thirty thousand men, mighty men of valor, and sends them away by night, <verse eid="JOS 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 8:4"/>and commands them, saying, “See, you are ones lying in wait against the city, at the rear of the city, you do not go very far off from the city, and all of you have been prepared, <verse eid="JOS 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 8:5"/>and I and all the people who [are] with me draw near to the city, and it has come to pass, when they come out to meet us as at the first, and we have fled before them, <verse eid="JOS 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 8:6"/>and they have come out after us until we have drawn them out of the city, for they say, They are fleeing before us as at the first, and we have fled before them, <verse eid="JOS 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 8:7"/>and you rise from the ambush, and have occupied the city, and your God YHWH has given it into your hand; <verse eid="JOS 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 8:8"/>and it has been, when you capture the city, you burn the city with fire, you do according to the word of YHWH, see, I have commanded you.” <verse eid="JOS 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 8:9"/>And Joshua sends them away, and they go to the ambush, and abide between Bethel and Ai, on the west of Ai; and Joshua lodges on that night in the midst of the people. <verse eid="JOS 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 8:10"/>And Joshua rises early in the morning, and inspects the people, and goes up, he and [the] elderly of Israel, before the people to Ai; <verse eid="JOS 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 8:11"/>and all the people of war who [are] with him have gone up, and draw near and come in before the city, and encamp on the north of Ai; and the valley [is] between him and Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 8:12"/>And he takes about five thousand men, and sets them [for] an ambush between Bethel and Ai, on the west of the city; <verse eid="JOS 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 8:13"/>and they set the people, all the camp which [is] on the north of the city, and its rear on the west of the city, and that night Joshua goes on into the midst of the valley. <verse eid="JOS 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 8:14"/>And it comes to pass, when the king of Ai sees [it], that he hurries, and rises early, and the men of the city go out to meet Israel for battle, he and all his people, at the appointed time, at the front of the plain, and he has not known that an ambush [is] against him, on the rear of the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 8:15"/>And Joshua and all Israel [seem] struck before them, and flee the way of the wilderness, <verse eid="JOS 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 8:16"/>and all the people who [are] in the city are called to pursue after them, and they pursue after Joshua, and are drawn away out of the city, <verse eid="JOS 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 8:17"/>and there has not been a man left in Ai and Bethel who has not gone out after Israel, and they leave the city open, and pursue after Israel. <verse eid="JOS 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 8:18"/>And YHWH says to Joshua, “Stretch out with the javelin which [is] in your hand toward Ai, for I give it into your hand”; and Joshua stretches out with the javelin which [is] in his hand toward the city, <verse eid="JOS 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 8:19"/>and the ambush has risen [with] haste, out of its place, and they run at the stretching out of his hand, and go into the city, and capture it, and hurry, and burn the city with fire. <verse eid="JOS 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 8:20"/>And the men of Ai look behind them, and see, and behold, the smoke of the city has gone up to the heavens, and there has not been power in them to flee here and there—and the people who are fleeing to the wilderness have turned against the pursuer— <verse eid="JOS 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 8:21"/>and Joshua and all Israel have seen that the ambush has captured the city, and that the smoke of the city has gone up, and they turn back and strike the men of Ai; <verse eid="JOS 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 8:22"/>and these have come out from the city to meet them, and they are in the midst of Israel, some on this [side], and some on that [side], and they strike them until he has not left a remnant and escaped one to them; <verse eid="JOS 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 8:23"/>and they have caught the king of Ai alive, and bring him near to Joshua. <verse eid="JOS 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 8:24"/>And it comes to pass, at Israel’s finishing to slay all the inhabitants of Ai in the field, in the wilderness in which they pursued them (and all of them fall by the mouth of the sword until their consumption), that all of Israel turns back to Ai, and strikes it by the mouth of the sword; <verse eid="JOS 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 8:25"/>and all who fall during the day, of men and of women, are twelve thousand—all men of Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 8:26"/>And Joshua has not brought back his hand which he stretched out with the javelin until he has devoted all the inhabitants of Ai; <verse eid="JOS 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 8:27"/>only the livestock and the spoil of that city has Israel spoiled for themselves, according to the word of YHWH which He commanded Joshua. <verse eid="JOS 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 8:28"/>And Joshua burns Ai, and makes it a continuous heap—a desolation to this day; <verse eid="JOS 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 8:29"/>and he has hanged the king of Ai on the tree until evening, and at the going in of the sun Joshua has commanded, and they take down his carcass from the tree, and cast it to the opening of the gate of the city, and raise a great heap of stones over it until this day. <verse eid="JOS 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 8:30"/>Then Joshua builds an altar to YHWH, God of Israel, in Mount Ebal, <verse eid="JOS 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 8:31"/>as Moses, servant of YHWH, commanded the sons of Israel, as it is written in the Scroll of the Law of Moses—an altar of whole stones, over which he has not waved iron—and they cause burnt-offerings to go up on it to YHWH, and sacrifice peace-offerings; <verse eid="JOS 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 8:32"/>and he writes there on the stones a copy of the Law of Moses, which he has written in the presence of the sons of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 8:33"/>And all Israel, and its elderly, and authorities, and his judges, are standing on this [side] and on that [side] of the Ark, before the priests, the Levites, carrying the Ark of the Covenant of YHWH, the sojourner as well as the native, half of them in front of Mount Gerizim, and the half of them in front of Mount Ebal, as Moses servant of YHWH had commanded to bless the people of Israel at the first. <verse eid="JOS 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 8:34"/>And afterward he has proclaimed all the words of the Law, the blessing and the reviling, according to all that is written in the Scroll of the Law; <verse eid="JOS 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 8:35"/>there has not been a thing of all that Moses commanded which Joshua has not proclaimed before all the assembly of Israel, and the women, and the infants, and the sojourner who is going in their midst.<verse eid="JOS 8:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JOS 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 9:1"/>And it comes to pass, when all the kings who [are] beyond the Jordan, in the hill-country, and in the low-country, and in every haven of the Great Sea, toward Lebanon, the Hittite, and the Amorite, the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, hear— <verse eid="JOS 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 9:2"/>that they gather themselves together to fight with Joshua, and with Israel—[with] one mouth. <verse eid="JOS 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 9:3"/>And the inhabitants of Gibeon have heard that which Joshua has done to Jericho and to Ai, <verse eid="JOS 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 9:4"/>and they work, even they, with subtlety, and go, and feign to be ambassadors, and take old sacks for their donkeys, and wine-bottles, old, and split, and bound up, <verse eid="JOS 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 9:5"/>and sandals, old and patched, on their feet, and old garments on them, and all the bread of their provision is dry—it was crumbs. <verse eid="JOS 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 9:6"/>And they go to Joshua, to the camp at Gilgal, and say to him, and to the men of Israel, “We have come from a far-off land, and now, make a covenant with us”; <verse eid="JOS 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 9:7"/>and the men of Israel say to the Hivite, “It may be [that] you are dwelling in our midst, so how do we make a covenant with you?” <verse eid="JOS 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 9:8"/>And they say to Joshua, “We [are] your servants.” And Joshua says to them, “Who [are] you? And where do you come from?” <verse eid="JOS 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 9:9"/>And they say to him, “Your servants have come from a very far-off land, for the Name of your God YHWH, for we have heard His fame, and all that He has done in Egypt, <verse eid="JOS 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 9:10"/>and all that He has done to the two kings of the Amorite who [are] beyond the Jordan, to Sihon king of Heshbon, and to Og king of Bashan, who [is] in Ashtaroth. <verse eid="JOS 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 9:11"/>And our elderly, and all the inhabitants of our land speak to us, saying, Take provision in your hand for the way, and go to meet them, and you have said to them: We [are] your servants, and now, make a covenant with us; <verse eid="JOS 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 9:12"/>this bread of ours—we provided ourselves with it hot out of our houses, on the day of our coming out to go to you, and now, behold, it is dry, and has been crumbs; <verse eid="JOS 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 9:13"/>and these [are] the wine-bottles which we filled, new, and behold, they have split; and these, our garments and our sandals, have become old, from the exceeding greatness of the way.” <verse eid="JOS 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 9:14"/>And the men take of their provision, and have not asked the mouth of YHWH; <verse eid="JOS 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 9:15"/>and Joshua makes peace with them, and makes a covenant with them, to keep them alive; and the princes of the congregation swear to them. <verse eid="JOS 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 9:16"/>And it comes to pass, that at the end of three days after they have made a covenant with them, that they hear that they [are] their neighbors—that they are dwelling in their midst. <verse eid="JOS 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 9:17"/>And the sons of Israel journey and come to their cities on the third day—and their cities [are] Gibeon, and Chephirah, and Beeroth, and Kirjath-Jearim— <verse eid="JOS 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 9:18"/>and the sons of Israel have not struck them, for the princes of the congregation have sworn to them by YHWH, God of Israel, and all the congregation murmur against the princes. <verse eid="JOS 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 9:19"/>And all the princes say to all the congregation, “We have sworn to them by YHWH, God of Israel; and now, we are not able to come against them; <verse eid="JOS 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 9:20"/>we do this to them, and have kept them alive, and wrath is not on us, because of the oath which we have sworn to them.” <verse eid="JOS 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 9:21"/>And the princes say to them, “They live, and are hewers of wood and drawers of water for all the congregation, as the princes spoke to them.” <verse eid="JOS 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 9:22"/>And Joshua calls for them, and speaks to them, saying, “Why have you deceived us, saying, We are very far from you, yet you [are] dwelling in our midst? <verse eid="JOS 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 9:23"/>And now you are cursed, and none of you is cut off [from being] a servant, even hewers of wood and drawers of water, for the house of my God.” <verse eid="JOS 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 9:24"/>And they answer Joshua and say, “Because it was certainly declared to your servants that your God YHWH commanded His servant Moses to give all the land to you, and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land from before you; and we fear greatly for ourselves because of you, and we do this thing; <verse eid="JOS 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 9:25"/>and now, behold, we [are] in your hand, as [it is] good, and as [it is] right in your eyes to do to us—do.” <verse eid="JOS 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 9:26"/>And he does to them so, and delivers them from the hand of the sons of Israel, and they have not slain them; <verse eid="JOS 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 9:27"/>and on that day Joshua makes them hewers of wood and drawers of water for the congregation, and for the altar of YHWH, to this day, at the place which He chooses.<verse eid="JOS 9:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JOS 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 10:1"/>And it comes to pass, when Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem hears that Joshua has captured Ai, and devotes it (as he had done to Jericho and to her king so he has done to Ai and to her king), and that the inhabitants of Gibeon have made peace with Israel, and are in their midst— <verse eid="JOS 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 10:2"/>that they are greatly afraid, because Gibeon [is] a great city, as one of the royal cities, and because it [is] greater than Ai, and all its men [are] heroes. <verse eid="JOS 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 10:3"/>And Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem sends to Hoham king of Hebron, and to Piram king of Jarmuth, and to Japhia king of Lachish, and to Debir king of Eglon, saying, <verse eid="JOS 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 10:4"/>“Come up to me, and help me, and we strike Gibeon, for it has made peace with Joshua, and with the sons of Israel.” <verse eid="JOS 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 10:5"/>And five kings of the Amorite (the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, the king of Eglon) are gathered together, and go up, they and all their camps, and encamp against Gibeon, and fight against it. <verse eid="JOS 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 10:6"/>And the men of Gibeon send to Joshua, to the camp at Gilgal, saying, “Do not let your hand cease from your servants; come up to us [with] haste, and give safety to us, and help us; for all the kings of the Amorite, dwelling in the hill-country, have been assembled against us.” <verse eid="JOS 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 10:7"/>And Joshua goes up from Gilgal, he, and all the people of war with him, even all the mighty men of valor. <verse eid="JOS 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 10:8"/>And YHWH says to Joshua, “Do not be afraid of them, for I have given them into your hand, there does not stand a man of them in your presence.” <verse eid="JOS 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 10:9"/>And Joshua comes to them suddenly (all the night he has gone up from Gilgal), <verse eid="JOS 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 10:10"/>and YHWH crushes them before Israel, and strikes them [with] a great striking at Gibeon, and pursues them the way of the ascent of Beth-Horon, and strikes them to Azekah, and to Makkedah. <verse eid="JOS 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 10:11"/>And it comes to pass, in their fleeing from the face of Israel—they [are] in the descent of Beth-Horon—and YHWH has cast great stones on them out of the heavens, to Azekah, and they die; more are they who have died by the hailstones than they whom the sons of Israel have slain by the sword. <verse eid="JOS 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 10:12"/>Then Joshua speaks to YHWH in the day of YHWH’s giving up the Amorites before the sons of Israel, and he says before the eyes of Israel, “Sun—stand still in Gibeon; and moon—in the Valley of Ajalon”; <verse eid="JOS 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 10:13"/>and the sun stands still, and the moon has stood—until the nation takes vengeance [on] its enemies; is it not written on the Scroll of the Upright, “and the sun stands in the midst of the heavens, and has not hurried to go in—as a perfect day?” <verse eid="JOS 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 10:14"/>And there has not been like that day before it or after it, for YHWH’s listening to the voice of a man; for YHWH is fighting for Israel. <verse eid="JOS 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 10:15"/>And Joshua turns back, and all Israel with him, to the camp at Gilgal. <verse eid="JOS 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 10:16"/>And these five kings flee, and are hidden in a cave at Makkedah, <verse eid="JOS 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 10:17"/>and it is declared to Joshua, saying, “The five kings have been found hidden in a cave at Makkedah.” <verse eid="JOS 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 10:18"/>And Joshua says, “Roll great stones to the mouth of the cave, and appoint men over it to watch them; <verse eid="JOS 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 10:19"/>and you, do not stand, pursue after your enemies, and you have struck them from the rear; do not permit them to go into their cities, for your God YHWH has given them into your hand.” <verse eid="JOS 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 10:20"/>And it comes to pass, when Joshua and the sons of Israel finish to strike them [with] a very great striking until they are consumed, and the remnant who have remained of them go into the fortified cities, <verse eid="JOS 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 10:21"/>that all the people return to the camp, to Joshua, [at] Makkedah, in peace; none moved his tongue sharply against the sons of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 10:22"/>And Joshua says, “Open the mouth of the cave, and bring out to me these five kings from the cave”; <verse eid="JOS 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 10:23"/>and they do so, and bring out to him these five kings from the cave: the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, the king of Eglon. <verse eid="JOS 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 10:24"/>And it comes to pass, when they bring out these kings to Joshua, that Joshua calls to every man of Israel, and says to the captains of the men of war, who have gone with him, “Draw near, set your feet on the necks of these kings”; and they draw near, and set their feet on their necks. <verse eid="JOS 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 10:25"/>And Joshua says to them, “Do not fear, nor be frightened; be strong and courageous; for thus does YHWH do to all your enemies with whom you are fighting”; <verse eid="JOS 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 10:26"/>and Joshua strikes them afterward, and puts them to death, and hangs them on five trees; and they are hanging on the trees until the evening. <verse eid="JOS 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 10:27"/>And it comes to pass, at the time of the going in of the sun, Joshua has commanded, and they take them down from off the trees, and cast them into the cave where they had been hid, and put great stones on the mouth of the cave until this very day. <verse eid="JOS 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 10:28"/>And Joshua has captured Makkedah on that day, and he strikes it by the mouth of the sword, and he has devoted its king, them and every person who [is] in it—he has not left a remnant; and he does to the king of Makkedah as he did to the king of Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 10:29"/>And Joshua passes over, and all Israel with him, from Makkedah [to] Libnah, and fights with Libnah; <verse eid="JOS 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 10:30"/>and YHWH also gives it into the hand of Israel, and its king, and [Joshua] strikes it by the mouth of the sword, and every person who [is] in it—he does not leave a remnant in it; and he does to its king as he did to the king of Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 10:31"/>And Joshua passes over, and all Israel with him, from Libnah to Lachish, and encamps against it, and fights against it. <verse eid="JOS 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 10:32"/>And YHWH gives Lachish into the hand of Israel, and [Joshua] captures it on the second day, and strikes it by the mouth of the sword, and every person who [is] in it, according to all that he did to Libnah. <verse eid="JOS 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 10:33"/>Then Horam king of Gezer has come up to help Lachish, and Joshua strikes him and his people, until he has not left a remnant to him. <verse eid="JOS 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 10:34"/>And Joshua passes over, and all Israel with him, from Lachish to Eglon, and they encamp against it, and fight against it, <verse eid="JOS 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 10:35"/>and capture it on that day, and strike it by the mouth of the sword, and every person who [is] in it he has devoted on that day, according to all that he did to Lachish. <verse eid="JOS 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 10:36"/>And Joshua goes up, and all Israel with him, from Eglon to Hebron, and they fight against it, <verse eid="JOS 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 10:37"/>and capture it, and strike it by the mouth of the sword, and its king, and all its cities, and every person who [is] in it—he has not left a remnant—according to all that he did to Eglon—and devotes it, and every person who [is] in it. <verse eid="JOS 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 10:38"/>And Joshua turns back, and all Israel with him, to Debir, and fights against it, <verse eid="JOS 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 10:39"/>and captures it, and its king, and all its cities, and they strike them by the mouth of the sword, and devote every person who [is] in it—he has not left a remnant; as he did to Hebron so he did to Debir, and to its king, and as he did to Libnah, and to its king. <verse eid="JOS 10:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 10:40"/>And Joshua strikes all the land of the hill-country, and of the south, and of the low-country, and of the springs, and all their kings—he has not left a remnant, and he has devoted all that breathe, as YHWH, God of Israel, commanded. <verse eid="JOS 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 10:41"/>And Joshua strikes them from Kadesh-Barnea, even to Gaza, and all the land of Goshen, even to Gibeon; <verse eid="JOS 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 10:42"/>and Joshua has captured all these kings and their land [at] one time, for YHWH, God of Israel, is fighting for Israel. <verse eid="JOS 10:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 10:43"/>And Joshua turns back, and all Israel with him, to the camp at Gilgal.<verse eid="JOS 10:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JOS 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 11:1"/>And it comes to pass, when Jabin king of Hazor hears, that he sends to Jobab king of Madon, and to the king of Shimron, and to the king of Achshaph, <verse eid="JOS 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 11:2"/>and to the kings who [are] on the north in the hill-country, and in the plain south of Chinneroth, and in the low country, and in the elevations of Dor, on the west, <verse eid="JOS 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 11:3"/>[to] the Canaanite on the east, and on the west, and the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Jebusite in the hill-country, and the Hivite under Hermon, in the land of Mizpeh— <verse eid="JOS 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 11:4"/>and they go out, they and all their camps with them, a people numerous, as the sand which [is] on the seashore for multitude, and [with] very many horse and charioteer; <verse eid="JOS 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 11:5"/>and all these kings are met together, and they come and encamp together at the waters of Merom, to fight with Israel. <verse eid="JOS 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 11:6"/>And YHWH says to Joshua, “Do not be afraid of their presence, for about this time tomorrow I am giving all of them slain before Israel; hamstring their horses, and burn their chariots with fire.” <verse eid="JOS 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 11:7"/>And Joshua comes, and all the people of war with him, against them by the waters of Merom, and they suddenly fall on them; <verse eid="JOS 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 11:8"/>and YHWH gives them into the hand of Israel, and they strike them and pursue them to the great Sidon, and to Misrephoth-Maim, and to the Valley of Mizpeh eastward, and they strike them, until he has not left a remnant to them; <verse eid="JOS 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 11:9"/>and Joshua does to them as YHWH commanded to him; he has hamstrung their horses, and burned their chariots with fire. <verse eid="JOS 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 11:10"/>And Joshua turns back at that time, and captures Hazor, and he has struck its king by the sword; for Hazor [was] formerly head of all these kingdoms; <verse eid="JOS 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 11:11"/>and they strike every person who [is] in it by the mouth of the sword; he has devoted—he has not left anyone breathing, and he has burned Hazor with fire; <verse eid="JOS 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 11:12"/>and all the cities of these kings, and all their kings, Joshua has captured, and he strikes them by the mouth of the sword; he devoted them, as Moses, servant of YHWH, commanded. <verse eid="JOS 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 11:13"/>Only, all the cities which are standing by their hill, Israel has not burned them—except Joshua has burned Hazor, only; <verse eid="JOS 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 11:14"/>and all the spoil of these cities, and the livestock, the sons of Israel have spoiled for themselves; only, they have struck every man by the mouth of the sword, until their destroying them; they have not left anyone breathing. <verse eid="JOS 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 11:15"/>As YHWH commanded His servant Moses, so Moses commanded Joshua, and so Joshua has done; he has not turned aside a thing of all that YHWH commanded Moses. <verse eid="JOS 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 11:16"/>And Joshua takes all this land: the hill-country, and all the south, and all the land of Goshen, and the low country, and the plain, even the hill-country of Israel and its low lands, <verse eid="JOS 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 11:17"/>from the Mount of Halak, which is going up [to] Seir, and to Ba‘al-Gad, in the Valley of Lebanon, under Mount Hermon; and he has captured all their kings, and he strikes them, and puts them to death. <verse eid="JOS 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 11:18"/>Joshua has made war with all these kings [for] many days; <verse eid="JOS 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 11:19"/>there has not been a city which made peace with the sons of Israel except the Hivite, inhabitants of Gibeon; they have taken the whole in battle; <verse eid="JOS 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 11:20"/>for it has been from YHWH to strengthen their heart, to meet in battle with Israel, in order to devote them, so that they have no grace, but in order to destroy them, as YHWH commanded Moses. <verse eid="JOS 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 11:21"/>And Joshua comes at that time, and cuts off the Anakim from the hill-country, from Hebron, from Debir, from Anab, and from all the hill-country of Judah, and from all the hill-country of Israel; Joshua has devoted them with their cities. <verse eid="JOS 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 11:22"/>There has not been Anakim left in the land of the sons of Israel; only in Gaza, in Gath, and in Ashdod, were they left. <verse eid="JOS 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 11:23"/>And Joshua takes the whole of the land, according to all that YHWH has spoken to Moses, and Joshua gives it for an inheritance to Israel according to their divisions, by their tribes; and the land has rest from war.<verse eid="JOS 11:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JOS 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 12:1"/>And these [are] kings of the land whom the sons of Israel have struck, and possess their land beyond the Jordan, at the sun-rising, from the Brook of Arnon to Mount Hermon, and all the plain eastward: <verse eid="JOS 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 12:2"/>Sihon, king of the Amorite, who is dwelling in Heshbon, ruling from Aroer which [is] on the border of the Brook of Arnon, and the middle of the brook, and half of Gilead, and to the Brook of Jabok, the border of the sons of Ammon; <verse eid="JOS 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 12:3"/>and the plain to the Sea of Chinneroth eastward, and to the Sea of the Plain (the Salt Sea) eastward, the way to Beth-Jeshimoth, and from the south under the Springs of Pisgah. <verse eid="JOS 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 12:4"/>And the border of Og king of Bashan (of the remnant of the Rephaim), who is dwelling in Ashtaroth and in Edrei, <verse eid="JOS 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 12:5"/>and ruling in Mount Hermon, and in Salcah, and in all Bashan, to the border of the Geshurite, and the Maachathite, and the half of Gilead, the border of Sihon king of Heshbon. <verse eid="JOS 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 12:6"/>Moses, servant of YHWH, and the sons of Israel have struck them, and Moses, servant of YHWH, gives it—a possession to the Reubenite, and to the Gadite, and to the half of the tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 12:7"/>And these [are] kings of the land whom Joshua and the sons of Israel have struck beyond the Jordan westward, from Ba‘al-Gad, in the Valley of Lebanon, and to the Mount of Halak, which is going up to Seir; and Joshua gives it to the tribes of Israel—a possession according to their divisions; <verse eid="JOS 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 12:8"/>in the hill-country, and in the low country, and in the plain, and in the springs, and in the wilderness, and in the south; the Hittite, the Amorite, and the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite: <verse eid="JOS 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 12:9"/>the king of Jericho, one; the king of Ai, which [is] beside Bethel, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 12:10"/>the king of Jerusalem, one; the king of Hebron, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 12:11"/>the king of Jarmuth, one; the king of Lachish, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 12:12"/>the king of Eglon, one; the king of Gezer, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 12:13"/>the king of Debir, one; the king of Geder, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 12:14"/>the king of Hormah, one; the king of Arad, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 12:15"/>the king of Libnah, one; the king of Adullam, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 12:16"/>the king of Mekkedah, one; the king of Beth-El, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 12:17"/>the king of Tappuah, one; the king of Hepher, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 12:18"/>the king of Aphek, one; the king of Lasharon, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 12:19"/>the king of Madon, one; the king of Hazor, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 12:20"/>the king of Shimron-Meron, one; the king of Achshaph, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 12:21"/>the king of Taanach, one; the king of Megiddo, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 12:22"/>the king of Kedesh, one; the king of Jokneam of Carmel, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 12:23"/>the king of Dor, at the elevation of Dor, one; the king of the nations of Gilgal, one; <verse eid="JOS 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 12:24"/>the king of Tirzah, one; all the kings [are] thirty-one.<verse eid="JOS 12:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JOS 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 13:1"/>And Joshua is old, entering into days, and YHWH says to him, “You have become aged, you have entered into days; as for the land, very much has been left to possess. <verse eid="JOS 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 13:2"/>This [is] the land that is left: all the circuits of the Philistines, and all Geshuri, <verse eid="JOS 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 13:3"/>from Sihor which [is] on the front of Egypt, and to the border of Ekron northward (it is reckoned to the Canaanite), five princes of the Philistines, the Gazathite, and the Ashdothite, the Eshkalonite, the Gittite, and the Ekronite, also the Avim; <verse eid="JOS 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 13:4"/>from the south, all the land of the Canaanite, and Mearah, which [is] to the Sidonians, to Aphek, to the border of the Amorite; <verse eid="JOS 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 13:5"/>and the land of the Giblite, and all Lebanon, at the sun-rising, from Ba‘al-Gad under Mount Hermon, to the going in to Hamath: <verse eid="JOS 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 13:6"/>all the inhabitants of the hill-country, from Lebanon to Misrephoth-Maim, all the Sidonians: I dispossess them before the sons of Israel; only, cause it to fall to Israel for an inheritance, as I have commanded you. <verse eid="JOS 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 13:7"/>And now, apportion this land for an inheritance to the nine tribes, and half of the tribe of Manasseh.” <verse eid="JOS 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 13:8"/>With [the other half], the Reubenite and the Gadite have received their inheritance, which Moses has given to them beyond the Jordan eastward, as Moses servant of YHWH has given to them; <verse eid="JOS 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 13:9"/>from Aroer, which [is] on the edge of the Brook of Arnon, and the city which [is] in the midst of the brook, and all the plain of Medeba to Dihon, <verse eid="JOS 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 13:10"/>and all the cities of Sihon king of the Amorite, who reigned in Heshbon, to the border of the sons of Ammon, <verse eid="JOS 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 13:11"/>and Gilead, and the border of the Geshurite, and of the Maachathite, and all Mount Hermon, and all Bashan to Salcah; <verse eid="JOS 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 13:12"/>all the kingdom of Og in Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth and in Edrei; he was left of the remnant of the Rephaim, and Moses strikes them, and dispossesses them; <verse eid="JOS 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 13:13"/>and the sons of Israel did not dispossess the Geshurite, and the Maachathite; and Geshur and Maachath dwell in the midst of Israel to this day. <verse eid="JOS 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 13:14"/>Only, he has not given an inheritance to the tribe of Levi; fire-offerings of YHWH, God of Israel, [are] its inheritance, as He has spoken to it. <verse eid="JOS 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 13:15"/>And Moses gives to the tribe of the sons of Reuben, for their families; <verse eid="JOS 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 13:16"/>and the border is to them from Aroer, which [is] on the edge of the Brook of Arnon, and the city which [is] in the midst of the brook, and all the plain by Medeba, <verse eid="JOS 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 13:17"/>Heshbon, and all its cities which [are] in the plain, Dibon, and Bamoth-Ba‘al, and Beth-Ba‘al-Meon, <verse eid="JOS 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 13:18"/>and Jahazah, and Kedemoth, and Mephaath, <verse eid="JOS 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 13:19"/>and Kirjathaim, and Sibmah, and Zareth-Shahar, on the mountain of the valley, <verse eid="JOS 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 13:20"/>and Beth-Peor, and the Springs of Pisgah, and Beth-Jeshimoth, <verse eid="JOS 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 13:21"/>and all the cities of the plain, and all the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorite, who reigned in Heshbon, whom Moses struck, with the princes of Midian, Evi, and Rekem, and Zur, and Hur, and Reba, princes of Sihon, inhabitants of the land. <verse eid="JOS 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 13:22"/>And the sons of Israel have slain Balaam, son of Beor, the diviner, with the sword, among their wounded ones. <verse eid="JOS 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 13:23"/>And the border of the sons of Reuben is the Jordan, and [its] border; this [is] the inheritance of the sons of Reuben, for their families, the cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 13:24"/>And Moses gives to the tribe of Gad, to the sons of Gad, for their families; <verse eid="JOS 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 13:25"/>and the border to them is Jazer, and all the cities of Gilead, and half of the land of the sons of Ammon, to Aroer which [is] on the front of Rabbah, <verse eid="JOS 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 13:26"/>and from Heshbon to Ramath-Mispeh, and Betonim, and from Mahanaim to the border of Debir, <verse eid="JOS 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 13:27"/>and in the valley, Beth-Aram, and Beth-Nimrah, and Succoth, and Zaphon, the rest of the kingdom of Sihon king of Heshbon, the Jordan and [its] border, to the extremity of the Sea of Chinnereth, beyond the Jordan eastward. <verse eid="JOS 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 13:28"/>This [is] the inheritance of the sons of Gad, for their families, the cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 13:29"/>And Moses gives to the half-tribe of Manasseh; and it is to the half-tribe of the sons of Manasseh, for their families. <verse eid="JOS 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 13:30"/>And their border is from Mahanaim, all Bashan, all the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, and all the small towns of Jair, which [are] in Bashan—sixty cities; <verse eid="JOS 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 13:31"/>and half of Gilead, and Ashteroth, and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan, [are] to the sons of Machir, son of Manasseh, to the half of the sons of Machir, for their families. <verse eid="JOS 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 13:32"/>These [are] they whom Moses caused to inherit in the plains of Moab beyond the Jordan, [by] Jericho, eastward; <verse eid="JOS 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 13:33"/>and Moses did not give an inheritance to the tribe of Levi; YHWH, God of Israel, Himself, [is] their inheritance, as He has spoken to them.<verse eid="JOS 13:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JOS 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 14:1"/>And these [are] they of the sons of Israel who inherited in the land of Canaan, whom Eleazar the priest, and Joshua son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the sons of Israel, caused to inherit; <verse eid="JOS 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 14:2"/>their inheritance [is] by lot, as YHWH commanded by the hand of Moses, for the nine tribes and the half-tribe; <verse eid="JOS 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 14:3"/>for Moses has given the inheritance of two of the tribes, and of half of the tribe, beyond the Jordan, and he has not given an inheritance to the Levites in their midst; <verse eid="JOS 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 14:4"/>for the sons of Joseph have been two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim, and they have not given a portion to the Levites in the land, except cities to dwell in, and their outskirts for their livestock, and for their possessions; <verse eid="JOS 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 14:5"/>as YHWH commanded Moses, so the sons of Israel have done, and they apportion the land. <verse eid="JOS 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 14:6"/>And the sons of Judah come near to Joshua in Gilgal, and Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenezzite says to him, “You have known the word that YHWH has spoken to Moses, the man of God, concerning me and concerning you in Kadesh-Barnea: <verse eid="JOS 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 14:7"/>I [was] a son of forty years in Moses, servant of YHWH, sending me from Kadesh-Barnea, to spy out the land, and I bring him back word as with my heart; <verse eid="JOS 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 14:8"/>and my brothers who have gone up with me have caused the heart of the people to melt, and I have been fully after my God YHWH; <verse eid="JOS 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 14:9"/>and Moses swears in that day, saying, Nevertheless—the land on which your foot has trodden, it is to you for an inheritance, and to your sons—for all time, for you have been fully after my God YHWH. <verse eid="JOS 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 14:10"/>And now, behold, YHWH has kept me alive, as He has spoken, these forty-five years, since YHWH spoke this word to Moses when Israel went in the wilderness; and now, behold, I [am] a son of eighty-five years today; <verse eid="JOS 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 14:11"/>yet today I [am] strong as in the day of Moses’ sending me; as my power [was] then, so [is] my power now, for battle, and to go out, and to come in. <verse eid="JOS 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 14:12"/>And now, give this hill-country to me, of which YHWH spoke in that day, for you heard in that day, for Anakim [are] there, and great, fortified cities; if [it] so be [that] YHWH [is] with me, then I have dispossessed them, as YHWH has spoken.” <verse eid="JOS 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 14:13"/>And Joshua blesses him, and gives Hebron to Caleb son of Jephunneh for an inheritance, <verse eid="JOS 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 14:14"/>therefore Hebron has been to Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenezzite for an inheritance to this day, because that he was fully after YHWH, God of Israel; <verse eid="JOS 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 14:15"/>and the name of Hebron [was] formerly Kirjath-Arba (the man [was] the greatest among the Anakim); and the land has rest from war.<verse eid="JOS 14:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JOS 15"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 15:1"/>And the lot for the tribe of the sons of Judah, for their families, is to the border of Edom; the wilderness of Zin southward, at the extremity of the south; <verse eid="JOS 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 15:2"/>and to them the south border is at the extremity of the Salt Sea, from the bay which is looking southward; <verse eid="JOS 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 15:3"/>and it has gone out to the south to Maaleh-Akrabbim, and passed over to Zin, and gone up on the south to Kadesh-Barnea, and passed over [to] Hezron, and gone up to Adar, and turned around to Karkaa, <verse eid="JOS 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 15:4"/>and passed over [to] Azmon, and gone out [at] the Brook of Egypt, and the outgoings of the border have been at the sea; this is the south border to you. <verse eid="JOS 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 15:5"/>And the east border [is] the Salt Sea, to the extremity of the Jordan, and the border at the north quarter [is] from the bay of the sea, at the extremity of the Jordan; <verse eid="JOS 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 15:6"/>and the border has gone up [to] Beth-Hoglah, and passed over on the north of Beth-Arabah, and the border has gone up [to] the stone of Bohan son of Reuben: <verse eid="JOS 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 15:7"/>and the border has gone up toward Debir from the Valley of Achor, and northward looking to Gilgal, which [is] opposite the ascent of Adummim, which [is] on the south of the brook, and the border has passed over to the waters of En-Shemesh, and its outgoings have been to En-Rogel; <verse eid="JOS 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 15:8"/>and the border has gone up the Valley of the Son of Hinnom, to the side of the Jebusite on the south (it [is] Jerusalem), and the border has gone up to the top of the hill-country which [is] on the front of the Valley of Hinnom westward, which [is] in the extremity of the Valley of the Rephaim northward; <verse eid="JOS 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 15:9"/>and the border has been marked out, from the top of the hill-country to the fountain of the waters of Nephtoah, and has gone out to the cities of Mount Ephron, and the border has been marked out [to] Ba‘alah (it [is] Kirjath-Jearim); <verse eid="JOS 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 15:10"/>and the border has gone around from Ba‘alah westward, to Mount Seir, and passed over to the side of Mount Jearim (it [is] Chesalon), on the north, and gone down [to] Beth-Shemesh, and passed over to Timnah; <verse eid="JOS 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 15:11"/>and the border has gone out to the side of Ekron northward, and the border has been marked out [to] Shicron, and has passed over to Mount Ba‘alah, and gone out [to] Jabneel; and the outgoings of the border have been at the sea. <verse eid="JOS 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 15:12"/>And the west border [is] to the Great Sea, and [its] border; this [is] the border of the sons of Judah all around for their families. <verse eid="JOS 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 15:13"/>And to Caleb son of Jephunneh he has given a portion in the midst of the sons of Judah, according to the command of YHWH to Joshua, [even] the city of Arba, father of Anak—it [is] Hebron. <verse eid="JOS 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 15:14"/>And Caleb is dispossessing there the three sons of Anak: Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai, children of Anak, <verse eid="JOS 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 15:15"/>and he goes up there to the inhabitants of Debir; and the name of Debir [was] formerly Kirjath-Sepher. <verse eid="JOS 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 15:16"/>And Caleb says, “He who strikes Kirjath-Sephar, and has captured it—I have given my daughter Achsah to him for a wife.” <verse eid="JOS 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 15:17"/>And Othniel son of Kenaz, brother of Caleb, captures it, and he gives his daughter Achsah to him for a wife. <verse eid="JOS 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 15:18"/>And it comes to pass, in her coming in, that she persuades him to ask [for] a field from her father, and she comes down off the donkey, and Caleb says to her, “What do you [want]?” <verse eid="JOS 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 15:19"/>And she says, “Give a blessing to me; when you have given me the land of the south, then you have given springs of waters to me”; and he gives the upper springs and the lower springs to her. <verse eid="JOS 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 15:20"/>This [is] the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Judah, for their families. <verse eid="JOS 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 15:21"/>And the cities at the extremity of the tribe of the sons of Judah are to the border of Edom in the south, Kabzeel, and Eder, and Jagur, <verse eid="JOS 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 15:22"/>and Kinah, and Dimonah, and Adadah, <verse eid="JOS 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 15:23"/>and Kedesh, and Hazor, and Ithnan, <verse eid="JOS 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 15:24"/>Ziph, and Telem, and Bealoth, <verse eid="JOS 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 15:25"/>and Hazor, Hadattah, and Kerioth, Hezron (it [is] Hazor), <verse eid="JOS 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 15:26"/>Amam, and Shema, and Moladah, <verse eid="JOS 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 15:27"/>and Hazar-Gaddah, and Heshmon, and Beth-Palet, <verse eid="JOS 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 15:28"/>and Hazar-Shual, and Beer-Sheba, and Bizjothjah, <verse eid="JOS 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 15:29"/>Ba‘alah, and Iim, and Azem, <verse eid="JOS 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 15:30"/>and Eltolad, and Chesil, and Hormah, <verse eid="JOS 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 15:31"/>and Ziklag, and Madmannah, and Sansannah, <verse eid="JOS 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 15:32"/>and Lebaoth, and Shilhim, and Ain, and Rimmon; all the cities [are] twenty-nine, and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 15:33"/>In the low country: Eshtaol, and Zoreah, and Ashnah, <verse eid="JOS 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 15:34"/>and Zanoah, and En-Gannim, Tappuah, and Enam, <verse eid="JOS 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 15:35"/>Jarmuth, and Adullam, Socoh, and Azekah, <verse eid="JOS 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 15:36"/>and Sharaim, and Adithaim, and Gederah, and Gederothaim; fourteen cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 15:37"/>Zenan, and Hadashah, and Migdal-Gad, <verse eid="JOS 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 15:38"/>and Dilean, and Mizpeh, and Joktheel, <verse eid="JOS 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 15:39"/>Lachish, and Bozkath, and Eglon, <verse eid="JOS 15:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 15:40"/>and Cabbon, and Lahmam, and Kithlish, <verse eid="JOS 15:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 15:41"/>and Gederoth, Beth-Dagon, and Naamah, and Makkedah; sixteen cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 15:42"/>Libnah, and Ether, and Ashan, <verse eid="JOS 15:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 15:43"/>and Jiphtah, and Ashnah, and Nezib, <verse eid="JOS 15:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 15:44"/>and Keilah, and Achzib, and Mareshah; nine cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 15:45"/>Ekron and its towns and its villages, <verse eid="JOS 15:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JOS 15:46"/>from Ekron and westward, all that [are] by the side of Ashdod, and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JOS 15:47"/>Ashdod, its towns and its villages, Gaza, its towns and its villages, to the Brook of Egypt, and the Great Sea, and [its] border. <verse eid="JOS 15:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JOS 15:48"/>And in the hill-country: Shamir, and Jattir, and Socoh, <verse eid="JOS 15:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JOS 15:49"/>and Dannah, and Kirjath-Sannah (it [is] Debir), <verse eid="JOS 15:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JOS 15:50"/>and Anab, and Eshtemoh, and Anim, <verse eid="JOS 15:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JOS 15:51"/>and Goshen, and Holon, and Giloh; eleven cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JOS 15:52"/>Arab, and Dumah, and Eshean, <verse eid="JOS 15:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JOS 15:53"/>and Janum, and Beth-Tappuah, and Aphekah, <verse eid="JOS 15:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JOS 15:54"/>and Humtah, and Kirjath-Arba (it [is] Hebron), and Zior; nine cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JOS 15:55"/>Maon, Carmel, and Ziph, and Juttah, <verse eid="JOS 15:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JOS 15:56"/>and Jezreel, and Jokdeam, and Zanoah, <verse eid="JOS 15:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JOS 15:57"/>Cain, Gibeah, and Timnah; ten cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="JOS 15:58"/>Halhul, Beth-Zur, and Gedor, <verse eid="JOS 15:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JOS 15:59"/>and Maarath, and Beth-Anoth, and Eltekon; six cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="JOS 15:60"/>Kirjath-Ba‘al (it [is] Kirjath-Jearim), and Rabbah; two cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="JOS 15:61"/>In the wilderness: Beth-Arabah, Middin, and Secacah, <verse eid="JOS 15:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="JOS 15:62"/>and Nibshan, and the City of Salt, and En-Gedi; six cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 15:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="JOS 15:63"/>As for the Jebusites, inhabitants of Jerusalem, the sons of Judah have not been able to dispossess them, and the Jebusite dwells with the sons of Judah in Jerusalem to this day.<verse eid="JOS 15:63"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JOS 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 16:1"/>And the lot for the sons of Joseph goes out from Jordan [by] Jericho, to the waters of Jericho on the east, to the wilderness going up from Jericho in the hill-country of Beth-El, <verse eid="JOS 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 16:2"/>and has gone out from Beth-El to Luz, and passed over to the border of Archi [to] Ataroth, <verse eid="JOS 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 16:3"/>and gone down westward to the border of Japhleti, to the border of the lower Beth-Horon, and to Gezer, and its outgoings have been at the sea. <verse eid="JOS 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 16:4"/>And the sons of Joseph—Manasseh and Ephraim—inherit. <verse eid="JOS 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 16:5"/>And the border of the sons of Ephraim is by their families; and the border of their inheritance is on the east, Atroth-Addar to the upper Beth-Horon; <verse eid="JOS 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 16:6"/>and the border has gone out at the sea, to Michmethah on the north, and the border has gone around eastward [to] Taanath-Shiloh, and passed over it eastward to Janohah, <verse eid="JOS 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 16:7"/>and gone down from Janohah [to] Ataroth, and to Naarath, and touched against Jericho, and gone out at the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 16:8"/>From Tappuah the border goes westward to the Brook of Kanah, and its outgoings have been at the sea: this [is] the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Ephraim, for their families. <verse eid="JOS 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 16:9"/>And the separate cities of the sons of Ephraim [are] in the midst of the inheritance of the sons of Manasseh, all the cities and their villages; <verse eid="JOS 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 16:10"/>and they have not dispossessed the Canaanite who is dwelling in Gezer, and the Canaanite dwells in the midst of Ephraim to this day, and is for forced labor—serving.<verse eid="JOS 16:10"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JOS 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 17:1"/>And the lot is for the tribe of Manasseh (for he [is] firstborn of Joseph), for Machir firstborn of Manasseh, father of Gilead, for he has been a man of war, and his are Gilead and Bashan. <verse eid="JOS 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 17:2"/>And there is [a lot] for the sons of Manasseh who are left, for their families; for the sons of Abiezer, and for the sons of Helek, and for the sons of Asriel, and for the sons of Shechem, and for the sons of Hepher, and for the sons of Shemida; these [are] the children of Manasseh son of Joseph—the males—by their families. <verse eid="JOS 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 17:3"/>As for Zelophehad, son of Hepher, son of Gilead, son of Machir, son of Manasseh, he has no children except daughters, and these [are] the names of his daughters: Mahlah, and Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah, <verse eid="JOS 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 17:4"/>and they draw near before Eleazar the priest, and before Joshua son of Nun, and before the princes, saying, “YHWH commanded Moses to give an inheritance to us in the midst of our brothers”; and he gives to them, at the command of YHWH, an inheritance in the midst of the brothers of their father. <verse eid="JOS 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 17:5"/>And ten portions fall [to] Manasseh, apart from the land of Gilead and Bashan, which [are] beyond the Jordan; <verse eid="JOS 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 17:6"/>for the daughters of Manasseh have inherited an inheritance in the midst of his sons, and the land of Gilead has been for the sons of Manasseh who are left. <verse eid="JOS 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 17:7"/>And the border of Manasseh is from Asher to Michmethah, which [is] on the front of Shechem, and the border has gone on to the right, to the inhabitants of En-Tappuah. <verse eid="JOS 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 17:8"/>The land of Tappuah has been for Manasseh, and Tappuah to the border of Manasseh for the sons of Ephraim. <verse eid="JOS 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 17:9"/>And the border has come down [to] the Brook of Kanah, southward of the brook; these cities of Ephraim [are] in the midst of the cities of Manasseh, and the border of Manasseh [is] on the north of the brook, and its outgoings are at the sea. <verse eid="JOS 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 17:10"/>Southward [is] for Ephraim and northward for Manasseh, and the sea is his border, and in Asher they meet on the north, and in Issachar on the east. <verse eid="JOS 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 17:11"/>And in Issachar and in Asher, Manasseh has Beth-Shean and its towns, and Ibleam and its towns, and the inhabitants of Dor and its towns, and the inhabitants of En-Dor and its towns, and the inhabitants of Taanach and its towns, and the inhabitants of Megiddo and its towns—three counties. <verse eid="JOS 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 17:12"/>And the sons of Manasseh have not been able to occupy these cities, and the Canaanite is desirous to dwell in this land, <verse eid="JOS 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 17:13"/>and it comes to pass, when the sons of Israel have been strong, that they put the Canaanite to forced labor, and have not utterly dispossessed him. <verse eid="JOS 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 17:14"/>And the sons of Joseph speak with Joshua, saying, “Why have you given an inheritance to me—one lot and one portion, and I [am] a numerous people? YHWH has blessed me until now.” <verse eid="JOS 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 17:15"/>And Joshua says to them, “If you [are] a numerous people, go up to the forest for yourself, then you have created [a place] for yourself there in the land of the Perizzite and of the Rephaim, when Mount Ephraim has been narrow for you.” <verse eid="JOS 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 17:16"/>And the sons of Joseph say, “The mountain is not enough for us, and a chariot of iron [is] with every Canaanite who is dwelling in the land of the valley—to him who [is] in Beth-Shean and its towns, and to him who [is] in the Valley of Jezreel.” <verse eid="JOS 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 17:17"/>And Joshua speaks to the house of Joseph, to Ephraim and to Manasseh, saying, “You [are] a numerous people, and have great power; you do not have [only] one lot, <verse eid="JOS 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 17:18"/>because the mountain is yours; because it [is] a forest—you have created it, and its outgoings have been yours; because you dispossess the Canaanite, though it has chariots of iron—though it [is] strong.”<verse eid="JOS 17:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JOS 18"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 18:1"/>And all the congregation of the sons of Israel is assembled [at] Shiloh, and they cause the Tent of Meeting to dwell there, and the land has been subdued before them. <verse eid="JOS 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 18:2"/>And there are seven tribes left among the sons of Israel who have not shared their inheritance, <verse eid="JOS 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 18:3"/>and Joshua says to the sons of Israel, “Until when are you remiss to go in to possess the land which He, YHWH, God of your fathers, has given to you? <verse eid="JOS 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 18:4"/>Give three men from you for [each] tribe, and I send them, and they rise and go up and down through the land, and describe it according to their inheritance, and come to me, <verse eid="JOS 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 18:5"/>and they have divided it into seven portions—Judah stays by its border on the south, and the house of Joseph stays by their border on the north— <verse eid="JOS 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 18:6"/>and you describe the land [in] seven portions, and have brought [it] to me here, and I have cast a lot for you here before our God YHWH; <verse eid="JOS 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 18:7"/>for there is no portion for the Levites in your midst, for the priesthood of YHWH [is] their inheritance, and Gad, and Reuben, and half of the tribe of Manasseh received their inheritance beyond the Jordan eastward, which Moses, servant of YHWH, gave to them.” <verse eid="JOS 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 18:8"/>And the men rise and go; and Joshua commands those who are going to describe the land, saying, “Go, and walk up and down through the land, and describe it, and return to me, and here I cast a lot for you before YHWH in Shiloh.” <verse eid="JOS 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 18:9"/>And the men go, and pass over through the land, and describe it by cities, in seven portions, on a scroll, and they come to Joshua, to the camp [at] Shiloh. <verse eid="JOS 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 18:10"/>And Joshua casts a lot for them in Shiloh before YHWH, and there Joshua apportions the land to the sons of Israel, according to their divisions. <verse eid="JOS 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 18:11"/>And a lot goes up [for] the tribe of the sons of Benjamin, for their families; and the border of their lot goes out between the sons of Judah and the sons of Joseph. <verse eid="JOS 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 18:12"/>And the border is for them at the north side from the Jordan, and the border has gone up to the side of Jericho on the north, and gone up through the hill-country westward, and its outgoings have been at the wilderness of Beth-Aven; <verse eid="JOS 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 18:13"/>and the border has gone over there to Luz, to the side of Luz (it [is] Beth-El) southward, and the border has gone down [to] Atroth-Addar, by the hill that [is] on the south of the lower Beth-Horon; <verse eid="JOS 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 18:14"/>and the border has been marked out, and has gone around to the corner of the sea southward, from the hill which [is] at the front of Beth-Horon southward, and its outgoings have been to Kirjath-Ba‘al (it [is] Kirjath-Jearim), a city of the sons of Judah: this [is] the west quarter. <verse eid="JOS 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 18:15"/>And the south quarter [is] from the end of Kirjath-Jearim, and the border has gone out westward, and has gone out to the fountain of the waters of Nephtoah; <verse eid="JOS 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 18:16"/>and the border has come down to the extremity of the hill which [is] on the front of the Valley of the Son of Hinnom, which [is] in the Valley of the Rephaim northward, and has gone down the Valley of Hinnom to the side of Jebusi southward, and gone down [to] En-Rogel, <verse eid="JOS 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 18:17"/>and has been marked out on the north, and gone out to En-Shemesh, and gone out to Geliloth, which [is] opposite the ascent of Adummim, and gone down [to] the stone of Bohan son of Reuben, <verse eid="JOS 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 18:18"/>and passed over to the side in front of the Arabah northward, and gone down to Arabah; <verse eid="JOS 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 18:19"/>and the border has passed over to the side of Beth-Hoglah northward, and the outgoings of the border have been to the north bay of the Salt Sea, to the south extremity of the Jordan; this [is] the south border; <verse eid="JOS 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 18:20"/>and the Jordan borders it at the east quarter; this [is] the inheritance of the sons of Benjamin, by its borders all around, for their families. <verse eid="JOS 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 18:21"/>And the cities for the tribe of the sons of Benjamin, for their families, have been Jericho, and Beth-Hoglah, and the Valley of Keziz, <verse eid="JOS 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 18:22"/>and Beth-Arabah, Zemaraim, and Beth-El, <verse eid="JOS 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 18:23"/>and Avim, and Parah, and Ophrah, <verse eid="JOS 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 18:24"/>and Chephar-Haammonai, and Ophni, and Gaba; twelve cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 18:25"/>Gibeon, and Ramah, and Beeroth, <verse eid="JOS 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 18:26"/>and Mizpeh, and Chephirah, and Mozah, <verse eid="JOS 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 18:27"/>and Rekem, and Irpeel, and Taralah, <verse eid="JOS 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 18:28"/>and Zelah, Eleph, and Jebusi (it [is] Jerusalem), Gibeath, Kirjath; fourteen cities and their villages. This [is] the inheritance of the sons of Benjamin, for their families.<verse eid="JOS 18:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JOS 19"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 19:1"/>And the second lot goes out for Simeon, for the tribe of the sons of Simeon, for their families; and their inheritance is in the midst of the inheritance of the sons of Judah, <verse eid="JOS 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 19:2"/>and they have in their inheritance Beer-Sheba, and Sheba, and Moladah, <verse eid="JOS 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 19:3"/>and Hazar-Shual, and Balah, and Azem, <verse eid="JOS 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 19:4"/>and Eltolad, and Bethul, and Hormah, <verse eid="JOS 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 19:5"/>and Ziklag, and Beth-Marcaboth, and Hazar-Susah, <verse eid="JOS 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 19:6"/>and Beth-Lebaoth, and Sharuhen; thirteen cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 19:7"/>Ain, Remmon, and Ether, and Ashan; four cities and their villages; <verse eid="JOS 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 19:8"/>also all the villages which [are] around these cities, to Ba‘alath-Beer, Ramoth of the south. This [is] the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Simeon, for their families; <verse eid="JOS 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 19:9"/>out of the portion of the sons of Judah [is] the inheritance of the sons of Simeon, for the portion of the sons of Judah has been too much for them, and the sons of Simeon inherit in the midst of their inheritance. <verse eid="JOS 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 19:10"/>And the third lot goes up for the sons of Zebulun, for their families; and the border of their inheritance is to Sarid, <verse eid="JOS 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 19:11"/>and their border has gone up toward the sea, and Maralah, and come against Dabbasheth, and come to the brook which [is] on the front of Jokneam, <verse eid="JOS 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 19:12"/>and turned back from Sarid eastward, at the sun-rising, by the border of Chisloth-Tabor, and gone out to Daberath, and gone up to Japhia, <verse eid="JOS 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 19:13"/>and there it has passed over eastward, to the east, to Gittah-Hepher, [to] Ittah-Kazin, and gone out [to] Rimmon-Methoar to Neah; <verse eid="JOS 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 19:14"/>and the border has gone around it, from the north to Hannathon; and its outgoings have been [in] the Valley of Jiphthah-El, <verse eid="JOS 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 19:15"/>and Kattath, and Nahallal, and Shimron, and Idalah, and Beth-Lehem; twelve cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 19:16"/>This [is] the inheritance of the sons of Zebulun, for their families, these cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 19:17"/>The fourth lot has gone out for Issachar, for the sons of Issachar, for their families; <verse eid="JOS 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 19:18"/>and their border is [at] Jezreel, and Chesulloth, and Shunem, <verse eid="JOS 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 19:19"/>and Haphraim, and Shihon, and Anaharath, <verse eid="JOS 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 19:20"/>and Rabbith, and Kishion, and Abez, <verse eid="JOS 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 19:21"/>and Remeth, and En-Gannim, and En-Haddah, and Beth-Pazzez; <verse eid="JOS 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 19:22"/>and the border has touched against Tabor, and Shahazimah, and Beth-Shemesh, and the outgoings of their border have been [at] the Jordan; sixteen cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 19:23"/>This [is] the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Issachar, for their families, the cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 19:24"/>And the fifth lot goes out for the tribe of the sons of Asher, for their families; <verse eid="JOS 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 19:25"/>and their border is Helkath, and Hali, and Beten, and Achshaph, <verse eid="JOS 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 19:26"/>and Alammelech, and Amad, and Misheal; and it touches against Carmel westward, and against Shihor-Libnath; <verse eid="JOS 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 19:27"/>and has turned back, at the sun-rising, [to] Beth-Dagon, and come against Zebulun, and against the Valley of Jiphthah-El toward the north of Beth-Emek, and Neiel, and has gone out to Cabul on the left, <verse eid="JOS 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 19:28"/>and Hebron, and Rehob, and Hammon, and Kanah, to great Sidon; <verse eid="JOS 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 19:29"/>and the border has turned back to Ramah, and to the fortified city Tyre; and the border has turned back to Hosah, and its outgoings are at the sea, from the coast to Achzib, <verse eid="JOS 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 19:30"/>and Ummah, and Aphek, and Rehob; twenty-two cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 19:31"/>This [is] the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Asher, for their families, these cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 19:32"/>The sixth lot has gone out for the sons of Naphtali—for the sons of Naphtali, for their families; <verse eid="JOS 19:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 19:33"/>and their border is from Heleph, from Allon in Zaanannim, and Adami, Nekeb, and Jabneel, to Lakkum, and its outgoings are [at] the Jordan; <verse eid="JOS 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 19:34"/>and the border has turned back westward [to] Aznoth-Tabor, and gone out there to Hukkok, and touched against Zebulun on the south, and it has touched against Asher on the west, and against Judah [at] the Jordan, at the sun-rising; <verse eid="JOS 19:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 19:35"/>and the cities of defense [are] Ziddim, Zer, and Hammath, Rakkath, and Chinnereth, <verse eid="JOS 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 19:36"/>and Adamah, and Ramah, and Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 19:37"/>and Kedesh, and Edrei, and En-Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 19:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 19:38"/>and Iron, and Migdal-El, Horem, and Beth-Anath, and Beth-Shemesh; nineteen cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 19:39"/>This [is] the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Naphtali, for their families, the cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 19:40"/>The seventh lot has gone out for the tribe of the sons of Dan, for their families; <verse eid="JOS 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 19:41"/>and the border of their inheritance is Zorah, and Eshtaol, and Ir-Shemesh, <verse eid="JOS 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 19:42"/>and Shalabbin, and Aijalon, and Jethlah, <verse eid="JOS 19:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 19:43"/>and Elon, and Thimnathah, and Ekron, <verse eid="JOS 19:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 19:44"/>and Eltekeh, and Gibbethon, and Ba‘alath, <verse eid="JOS 19:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 19:45"/>and Jehud, and Bene-Barak, and Gath-Rimmon, <verse eid="JOS 19:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JOS 19:46"/>and Me-Jarkon, and Rakkon, with the border in front of Joppa. <verse eid="JOS 19:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JOS 19:47"/>And the border of the sons of Dan goes out from them, and the sons of Dan go up and fight with Leshem, and capture it, and strike it by the mouth of the sword, and possess it, and dwell in it, and call Leshem, Dan, according to the name of their father Dan. <verse eid="JOS 19:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JOS 19:48"/>This [is] the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Dan, for their families, these cities and their villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JOS 19:49"/>And they finish to give the land in inheritance, by its borders, and the sons of Israel give an inheritance to Joshua son of Nun in their midst; <verse eid="JOS 19:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JOS 19:50"/>by the command of YHWH they have given to him the city which he asked for, Timnath-Serah, in the hill-country of Ephraim, and he builds the city and dwells in it. <verse eid="JOS 19:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JOS 19:51"/>These [are] the inheritances which Eleazar the priest, and Joshua son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the sons of Israel, have caused to inherit by lot, in Shiloh, before YHWH, at the opening of the Tent of Meeting; and they finish to apportion the land.<verse eid="JOS 19:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JOS 20"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 20:1"/>And YHWH speaks to Joshua, saying, <verse eid="JOS 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 20:2"/>“Speak to the sons of Israel, saying, Give cities of refuge for yourselves, as I have spoken to you by the hand of Moses, <verse eid="JOS 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 20:3"/>for the fleeing there of a manslayer striking life through ignorance, without knowledge; and they have been for a refuge to you from the redeemer of blood. <verse eid="JOS 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 20:4"/>When [one] has fled to one of these cities, and has stood [at] the opening of the gate of the city, and has spoken his matter in the ears of [the] elderly of that city, then they have gathered him into the city to them, and have given a place to him, and he has dwelt with them. <verse eid="JOS 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 20:5"/>And when the redeemer of blood pursues after him, then they do not shut up the manslayer into his hand, for he has struck his neighbor without knowledge, and is not hating him until now; <verse eid="JOS 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 20:6"/>and he has dwelt in that city until his standing before the congregation for judgment, until the death of the chief priest who is in those days—then the manslayer turns back and has come to his city, and to his house, to the city from where he fled.” <verse eid="JOS 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 20:7"/>And they sanctify Kedesh in Galilee, in the hill-country of Naphtali, and Shechem in the hill-country of Ephraim, and Kirjath-Arba (it [is] Hebron), in the hill-country of Judah; <verse eid="JOS 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 20:8"/>and beyond the Jordan, [at] Jericho eastward, they have given Bezer in the wilderness, in the plain, out of the tribe of Reuben, and Ramoth in Gilead out of the tribe of Gad, and Golan in Bashan out of the tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 20:9"/>These have been cities of meeting for all the sons of Israel, and for a sojourner who is sojourning in their midst, for the fleeing there of anyone striking life through ignorance, and he does not die by the hand of the redeemer of blood until his standing before the congregation.<verse eid="JOS 20:9"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JOS 21"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 21:1"/>And the heads of the fathers of the Levites draw near to Eleazar the priest, and to Joshua son of Nun, and to the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the sons of Israel, <verse eid="JOS 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 21:2"/>and they speak to them in Shiloh, in the land of Canaan, saying, “YHWH commanded by the hand of Moses to give to us cities to dwell in, and their outskirts for our livestock.” <verse eid="JOS 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 21:3"/>And the sons of Israel give to the Levites, out of their inheritance, at the command of YHWH, these cities and their outskirts: <verse eid="JOS 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 21:4"/>and the lot goes out for the families of the Kohathite, and there are for the sons of Aaron the priest (of the Levites), out of the tribe of Judah, and out of the tribe of Simeon, and out of the tribe of Benjamin, thirteen cities by lot, <verse eid="JOS 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 21:5"/>and for the sons of Kohath who are left, out of the families of the tribe of Ephraim, and out of the tribe of Dan, and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, ten cities by lot. <verse eid="JOS 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 21:6"/>And for the sons of Gershon, out of the families of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, [are] thirteen cities by lot. <verse eid="JOS 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 21:7"/>For the sons of Merari, for their families, out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, [are] twelve cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 21:8"/>And the sons of Israel give these cities and their outskirts to the Levites, as YHWH commanded by the hand of Moses, by lot. <verse eid="JOS 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 21:9"/>And they give out of the tribe of the sons of Judah, and out of the tribe of the sons of Simeon, these cities which are called by name; <verse eid="JOS 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 21:10"/>and they are for the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathite, of the sons of Levi, for the first lot has been theirs; <verse eid="JOS 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 21:11"/>and they give to them the city of Arba father of Anak (it [is] Hebron), in the hill-country of Judah, and its outskirts around it; <verse eid="JOS 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 21:12"/>and they have given the field of the city and its villages to Caleb son of Jephunneh for his possession. <verse eid="JOS 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 21:13"/>And to the sons of Aaron the priest they have given the city of refuge [for] the manslayer, Hebron and its outskirts, and Libnah and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 21:14"/>and Jattir and its outskirts, and Eshtemoa and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 21:15"/>and Holon and its outskirts, and Debir and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 21:16"/>and Ain and its outskirts, and Juttah and its outskirts, Beth-Shemesh and its outskirts; nine cities out of these two tribes. <verse eid="JOS 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 21:17"/>And out of the tribe of Benjamin, Gibeon and its outskirts, Geba and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 21:18"/>Anathoth and its outskirts, and Almon and its outskirts—four cities; <verse eid="JOS 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 21:19"/>all the cities of the sons of Aaron the priests, [are] thirteen cities and their outskirts. <verse eid="JOS 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 21:20"/>And for the families of the sons of Kohath, the Levites, who are left of the sons of Kohath, even the cities of their lot are of the tribe of Ephraim; <verse eid="JOS 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 21:21"/>and they give to them the city of refuge [for] the manslayer, Shechem and its outskirts, in the hill-country of Ephraim, and Gezer and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 21:22"/>and Kibzaim and its outskirts, and Beth-Horon and its outskirts—four cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 21:23"/>And out of the tribe of Dan, Eltekeh and its outskirts, Gibbethon and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 21:24"/>Aijalon and its outskirts, Gath-Rimmon and its outskirts—four cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 21:25"/>And out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Taanach and its outskirts, and Gath-Rimmon and its outskirts—two cities; <verse eid="JOS 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 21:26"/>all the cities [are] ten and their outskirts, for the families of the sons of Kohath who are left. <verse eid="JOS 21:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 21:27"/>And for the sons of Gershon, of the families of the Levites, out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, the city of refuge [for] the manslayer, Golan in Bashan and its outskirts, and Beeshterah and its outskirts—two cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 21:28"/>And out of the tribe of Issachar, Kishon and its outskirts, Dabarath and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 21:29"/>Jarmuth and its outskirts, En-Gannim and its outskirts—four cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 21:30"/>And out of the tribe of Asher, Mishal and its outskirts, Abdon and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 21:31"/>Helkath and its outskirts, and Rehob and its outskirts—four cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 21:32"/>And out of the tribe of Naphtali, the city of refuge [for] the manslayer, Kedesh in Galilee and its outskirts, and Hammoth-Dor and its outskirts, and Kartan and its outskirts—three cities; <verse eid="JOS 21:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 21:33"/>all the cities of the Gershonite, for their families, [are] thirteen cities and their outskirts. <verse eid="JOS 21:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 21:34"/>And for the families of the sons of Merari, the Levites, who are left, [are,] out of the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam and its outskirts, Kartah and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 21:35"/>Dimnah and its outskirts, Nahalal and its outskirts—four cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 21:36"/>And out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer and its outskirts, and Jahazah and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 21:37"/>Kedemoth and its outskirts, and Mephaath and its outskirts—four cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 21:38"/>And out of the tribe of Gad, the city of refuge [for] the manslayer, Ramoth in Gilead and its outskirts, and Mahanaim and its outskirts, <verse eid="JOS 21:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 21:39"/>Heshbon and its outskirts, Jazer and its outskirts—four cities [in] all. <verse eid="JOS 21:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 21:40"/>All the cities for the sons of Merari, for their families, who are left of the families of the Levites—their lot is twelve cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 21:41"/>All the cities of the Levites in the midst of the possession of the sons of Israel [are] forty-eight cities, and their outskirts. <verse eid="JOS 21:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 21:42"/>These cities are each city and its outskirts around it; so to all these cities. <verse eid="JOS 21:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 21:43"/>And YHWH gives to Israel the whole of the land which He has sworn to give to their fathers, and they possess it, and dwell in it; <verse eid="JOS 21:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 21:44"/>and YHWH gives rest to them all around, according to all that which He has sworn to their fathers, and there has not stood a man in their presence of all their enemies, YHWH has given the whole of their enemies into their hand; <verse eid="JOS 21:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 21:45"/>there has not fallen a thing of all the good thing which YHWH spoke to the house of Israel—the whole has come.<verse eid="JOS 21:45"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="JOS 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 22:1"/>Then Joshua calls for the Reubenite, and for the Gadite, and for the half-tribe of Manasseh, <verse eid="JOS 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 22:2"/>and says to them, “You have kept the whole of that which Moses, servant of YHWH, commanded you, and you listen to my voice, to all that I have commanded you; <verse eid="JOS 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 22:3"/>you have not left your brothers these many days to this day, and have kept the charge—the command of your God YHWH. <verse eid="JOS 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 22:4"/>And now, your God YHWH has given rest to your brothers, as He spoke to them; and now, turn, and go for yourselves to your tents, to the land of your possession, which Moses, servant of YHWH, has given to you beyond the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 22:5"/>Only, be very watchful to do the command and the Law which Moses, servant of YHWH, commanded you, to love your God YHWH, and to walk in all His ways, and to keep His commands, and to cleave to Him, and to serve Him, with all your heart, and with all your soul.” <verse eid="JOS 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 22:6"/>And Joshua blesses them, and sends them away, and they go to their tents. <verse eid="JOS 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 22:7"/>And to the half-tribe of Manasseh Moses has given, in Bashan, and to its [other] half Joshua has given with their brothers beyond the Jordan westward; and also when Joshua has sent them away to their tents, then he blesses them, <verse eid="JOS 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 22:8"/>and speaks to them, saying, “Turn back to your tents with great riches, and with very much livestock, with silver, and with gold, and with bronze, and with iron, and with very much raiment; divide the spoil of your enemies with your brothers.” <verse eid="JOS 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 22:9"/>And the sons of Reuben, and the sons of Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, turn back and go from the sons of Israel out of Shiloh, which [is] in the land of Canaan, to go to the land of Gilead, to the land of their possession, in which they have possession, according to the command of YHWH, by the hand of Moses; <verse eid="JOS 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 22:10"/>and they come to the districts of the Jordan, which [are] in the land of Canaan, and the sons of Reuben, and the sons of Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, build an altar there by the Jordan—a great altar in appearance. <verse eid="JOS 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 22:11"/>And the sons of Israel hear, saying, “Behold, the sons of Reuben, and the sons of Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, have built the altar at the frontier of the land of Canaan, in the districts of the Jordan, at the passage of the sons of Israel.” <verse eid="JOS 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 22:12"/>And the sons of Israel hear, and all the congregation of the sons of Israel is assembled at Shiloh, to go up against them to war; <verse eid="JOS 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 22:13"/>and the sons of Israel send to the sons of Reuben, and to the sons of Gad, and to the half-tribe of Manasseh—to the land of Gilead—Phinehas son of Eleazar the priest, <verse eid="JOS 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 22:14"/>and ten princes with him, one prince—one prince for a house of a father, for all the tribes of Israel, and each of them a head of a house of their fathers, for the thousands of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 22:15"/>And they come to the sons of Reuben, and to the sons of Gad, and to the half-tribe of Manasseh, to the land of Gilead, and speak with them, saying, <verse eid="JOS 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 22:16"/>“Thus said all the congregation of YHWH: What [is] this trespass which you have trespassed against the God of Israel, to turn back today from after YHWH, by your building an altar for yourselves, for your rebelling today against YHWH? <verse eid="JOS 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 22:17"/>Is the iniquity of Peor little to us, from which we have not been cleansed until this day—and the plague is in the congregation of YHWH, <verse eid="JOS 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 22:18"/>that you turn back today from after YHWH? And it has been [that] you rebel against YHWH today, and tomorrow He is angry against all the congregation of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 22:19"/>And surely, if the land of your possession is unclean, pass over for yourselves to the land of the possession of YHWH, where the Dwelling Place of YHWH has dwelt, and have possession in our midst; and do not rebel against YHWH, and do not rebel against us, by your building an altar for yourselves, besides the altar of our God YHWH. <verse eid="JOS 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 22:20"/>Did Achan son of Zerah not commit a trespass in the devoted thing, and there was wrath on all the congregation of Israel? And he alone did not expire in his iniquity.” <verse eid="JOS 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 22:21"/>And the sons of Reuben, and the sons of Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, answer and speak with the heads of the thousands of Israel: <verse eid="JOS 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 22:22"/>“The God of gods—YHWH, the God of gods—YHWH, He is knowing, and Israel—he knows, if [we are] in rebellion, and if in trespass against YHWH, do not save us this day! <verse eid="JOS 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 22:23"/>[If we] are building an altar for ourselves to turn back from after YHWH, and if to cause burnt-offering and present to go up on it, and if to make peace-offerings on it—YHWH Himself requires [it]. <verse eid="JOS 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 22:24"/>And nevertheless, we have done it from fear of [this] thing, saying, Hereafter your sons speak to our sons, saying, And what have you to [do with] YHWH God of Israel? <verse eid="JOS 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 22:25"/>For YHWH has put a border between us and you, O sons of Reuben, and sons of Gad—Jordan; you have no portion in YHWH—and your sons have caused our sons to cease, not to fear YHWH. <verse eid="JOS 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 22:26"/>And we say, Now let us prepare to build the altar for ourselves—not for burnt-offering, nor for sacrifice— <verse eid="JOS 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 22:27"/>but it [is] a witness between us and you, and between our generations after us, to do the service of YHWH before Him with our burnt-offerings, and with our sacrifices, and with our peace-offerings, and your sons do not say hereafter to our sons, You have no portion in YHWH. <verse eid="JOS 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 22:28"/>And we say, And it has been, when they say [so] to us, and to our generations hereafter, that we have said, See the pattern of the altar of YHWH, which our fathers made—not for burnt-offering nor for sacrifice—but it [is] a witness between us and you. <verse eid="JOS 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 22:29"/>Far be it from us to rebel against YHWH, and to turn back from after YHWH today, to build an altar for burnt-offering, for present, and for sacrifice, apart from the altar of our God YHWH, which [is] before His Dwelling Place.” <verse eid="JOS 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 22:30"/>And Phinehas the priest, and the princes of the congregation, and the heads of the thousands of Israel, who [are] with him, hear the words which the sons of Reuben, and the sons of Gad, and the sons of Manasseh have spoken, and it is good in their eyes. <verse eid="JOS 22:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 22:31"/>And Phinehas son of Eleazar the priest says to the sons of Reuben, and to the sons of Gad, and to the sons of Manasseh, “Today we have known that YHWH [is] in our midst, because you have not committed this trespass against YHWH—then you have delivered the sons of Israel out of the hand of YHWH.” <verse eid="JOS 22:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 22:32"/>And Phinehas son of Eleazar the priest, and the princes, turn back from the sons of Reuben, and from the sons of Gad, out of the land of Gilead, to the land of Canaan, to the sons of Israel, and bring them back word; <verse eid="JOS 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 22:33"/>and the thing is good in the eyes of the sons of Israel, and the sons of Israel bless God, and have not spoken to go up against them to war, to destroy the land which the sons of Reuben, and the sons of Gad, are dwelling in. <verse eid="JOS 22:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 22:34"/>And the sons of Reuben and the sons of Gad proclaim concerning the altar, that, “[It is] a witness between us that YHWH [is] God.”<verse eid="JOS 22:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="JOS 23"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 23:1"/>And it comes to pass, many days after that YHWH has given rest to Israel from all their surrounding enemies, that Joshua is old, entering into days, <verse eid="JOS 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 23:2"/>and Joshua calls for all Israel, for his elderly, and for his heads, and for his judges, and for his authorities, and says to them, “I have become old; I have entered into days; <verse eid="JOS 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 23:3"/>and you have seen all that your God YHWH has done to all these nations because of you, for your God YHWH [is] He who is fighting for you; <verse eid="JOS 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 23:4"/>see, I have caused these nations who are left to fall to you for an inheritance to your tribes, from the Jordan (and all the nations which I cut off), and the Great Sea [at] the [setting] sun. <verse eid="JOS 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 23:5"/>As for your God YHWH, He thrusts them from your presence, and has dispossessed them from before you, and you have possessed their land, as your God YHWH has spoken to you, <verse eid="JOS 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 23:6"/>and you have been very strong to keep and to do the whole that is written in the Scroll of the Law of Moses, so as not to turn aside from it right or left, <verse eid="JOS 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 23:7"/>so as not to go in among these nations, these who are left with you; and you do not make mention of the name of their gods, nor do you swear, nor do you serve them, nor do you bow yourselves to them; <verse eid="JOS 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 23:8"/>but you cleave to your God YHWH, as you have done until this day. <verse eid="JOS 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 23:9"/>And YHWH is dispossessing great and mighty nations from before you; as for you, none has stood in your presence until this day; <verse eid="JOS 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 23:10"/>one man of you pursues a thousand, for your God YHWH [is] He who is fighting for you, as He has spoken to you; <verse eid="JOS 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 23:11"/>and you have been very watchful for yourselves to love your God YHWH. <verse eid="JOS 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 23:12"/>But—if you turn back at all and have cleaved to the remnant of these nations, these who are left with you, and intermarried with them, and gone in to them, and they to you, <verse eid="JOS 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 23:13"/>certainly know that your God YHWH is not continuing to dispossess these nations from before you, and they have been to you for a trap, and for a snare, and for a scourge, in your sides, and for thorns in your eyes, until you perish from off this good ground which your God YHWH has given to you. <verse eid="JOS 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 23:14"/>And behold, I am going, today, in the way of all the earth, and you have known—with all your heart, and with all your soul—that there has not fallen one thing of all the good things which your God YHWH has spoken concerning you; the whole have come to you; there has not failed of it one thing. <verse eid="JOS 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 23:15"/>And it has been, as there has come on you all the good thing which your God YHWH has spoken to you, so YHWH brings on you the whole of the evil thing, until His destroying you from off this good ground which your God YHWH has given to you; <verse eid="JOS 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 23:16"/>in your transgressing the covenant of your God YHWH which He commanded you, and you have gone and served other gods, and bowed yourselves to them, then the anger of YHWH has burned against you, and you have perished quickly from off the good land which He has given to you.”<verse eid="JOS 23:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="JOS 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 24:1"/>And Joshua gathers all the tribes of Israel to Shechem, and calls for [the] elderly of Israel, and for his heads, and for his judges, and for his authorities, and they station themselves before God. <verse eid="JOS 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 24:2"/>And Joshua says to all the people, “Thus said YHWH, God of Israel: Beyond the River your fathers have dwelt of old—Terah father of Abraham and father of Nachor—and they serve other gods; <verse eid="JOS 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 24:3"/>and I take your father Abraham from beyond the River, and cause him to go through all the land of Canaan, and multiply his seed, and give Isaac to him. <verse eid="JOS 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 24:4"/>And I give Jacob and Esau to Isaac; and I give Mount Seir to Esau, to possess it; and Jacob and his sons have gone down to Egypt. <verse eid="JOS 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 24:5"/>And I send Moses and Aaron, and plague Egypt, as I have done in its midst, and afterward I have brought you out. <verse eid="JOS 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 24:6"/>And I bring out your fathers from Egypt, and you go to the sea, and the Egyptians pursue after your fathers, with chariot and with horsemen, to the Red Sea; <verse eid="JOS 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 24:7"/>and they cry to YHWH, and He sets thick darkness between you and the Egyptians, and brings the sea over him, and covers them, and your eyes see that which I have done in Egypt; and you dwell in a wilderness [for] many days. <verse eid="JOS 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 24:8"/>And I bring you into the land of the Amorite who is dwelling beyond the Jordan, and they fight with you, and I give them into your hand, and you possess their land, and I destroy them out of your presence. <verse eid="JOS 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 24:9"/>And Balak son of Zippor, king of Moab, rises and fights against Israel, and sends and calls for Balaam son of Beor, to revile you, <verse eid="JOS 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 24:10"/>and I have not been willing to listen to Balaam, and he greatly blesses you, and I deliver you out of his hand. <verse eid="JOS 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 24:11"/>And you pass over the Jordan, and come to Jericho, and the possessors of Jericho fight against you—the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Girgashite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite—and I give them into your hand. <verse eid="JOS 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 24:12"/>And I send the hornet before you, and it casts them out from your presence—two kings of the Amorite—not by your sword, nor by your bow. <verse eid="JOS 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 24:13"/>And I give a land to you for which you have not labored, and cities which you have not built, and you dwell in them; you are eating of vineyards and olive-yards which you have not planted. <verse eid="JOS 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 24:14"/>And now, fear YHWH, and serve Him, in perfection and in truth, and turn aside the gods which your fathers served beyond the River, and in Egypt, and serve YHWH; <verse eid="JOS 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 24:15"/>and if [it is] wrong in your eyes to serve YHWH—choose for yourselves today whom you serve—whether the gods whom your fathers served, which [are] beyond the River, or the gods of the Amorite in whose land you are dwelling; but me and my house—we serve YHWH.” <verse eid="JOS 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 24:16"/>And the people answer and say, “Far be it from us to forsake YHWH, to serve other gods; <verse eid="JOS 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 24:17"/>for our God YHWH [is] He who is bringing us and our fathers up out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of servants, and who has done these great signs before our eyes, and keeps us in all the way in which we have gone, and among all the peoples through whose midst we passed; <verse eid="JOS 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 24:18"/>and YHWH casts out the whole of the peoples, even the Amorite inhabiting the land, from our presence; we also serve YHWH, for He [is] our God.” <verse eid="JOS 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 24:19"/>And Joshua says to the people, “You are not able to serve YHWH, for He [is] a most holy God; He [is] a zealous God; He does not bear with your transgression and with your sins. <verse eid="JOS 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 24:20"/>When you forsake YHWH, and have served gods of a stranger, then He has turned back and done harm to you, and consumed you, after that He has done good to you.” <verse eid="JOS 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 24:21"/>And the people say to Joshua, “No, but we serve YHWH!” <verse eid="JOS 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 24:22"/>And Joshua says to the people, “You are witnesses against yourselves, that you have chosen YHWH for yourselves, to serve Him,” and they say, “Witnesses!” <verse eid="JOS 24:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 24:23"/>“And now, turn aside the gods of the stranger which [are] in your midst, and incline your heart to YHWH, God of Israel.” <verse eid="JOS 24:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 24:24"/>And the people say to Joshua, “We serve our God YHWH, and we listen to His voice.” <verse eid="JOS 24:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 24:25"/>And Joshua makes a covenant with the people on that day, and lays a statute and an ordinance on it, in Shechem. <verse eid="JOS 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 24:26"/>And Joshua writes these words in the Scroll of the Law of God, and takes a great stone, and raises it up there under the oak which [is] in the sanctuary of YHWH. <verse eid="JOS 24:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 24:27"/>And Joshua says to all the people, “Behold, this stone is for a witness against us, for it has heard all the sayings of YHWH which He has spoken with us, and it has been for a witness against you, lest you lie against your God.” <verse eid="JOS 24:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 24:28"/>And Joshua sends the people away, each to his inheritance. <verse eid="JOS 24:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 24:29"/>And it comes to pass, after these things, that Joshua son of Nun, servant of YHWH, dies, a son of one hundred and ten years, <verse eid="JOS 24:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 24:30"/>and they bury him in the border of his inheritance, in Timnath-Serah, which [is] in the hill-country of Ephraim, on the north of the hill of Gaash. <verse eid="JOS 24:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 24:31"/>And Israel serves YHWH all [the] days of Joshua, and all [the] days of the elderly who prolonged days after Joshua, and who knew all the work of YHWH which He did to Israel. <verse eid="JOS 24:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 24:32"/>And the bones of Joseph, which the sons of Israel brought up out of Egypt, they buried in Shechem, in the portion of the field which Jacob bought from the sons of Hamor father of Shechem, with one hundred kesitah; and they are for an inheritance to the sons of Joseph. <verse eid="JOS 24:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 24:33"/>And Eleazar son of Aaron died, and they bury him in a hill of his son Phinehas, which was given to him in the hill-country of Ephraim.<verse eid="JOS 24:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 24"/>
</usx>
