<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="LUK" style="id">- Literal Standard Version</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Luke</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Gospel of Luke</para>
  <para style="toc2">Luke</para>
  <para style="toc3">Luk</para>
  <para style="mt">Luke</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="LUK 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 1:1"/>Seeing that many took in hand to set in order a narration of the matters that have been fully assured among us, <verse eid="LUK 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 1:2"/>as they delivered to us, who from the beginning became eyewitnesses, and officers of the word, <verse eid="LUK 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 1:3"/>it seemed good also to me, having followed from the first after all things exactly, to write to you in order, most noble Theophilus, <verse eid="LUK 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 1:4"/>that you may know the certainty of the things wherein you were instructed. <verse eid="LUK 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 1:5"/>There was in the days of Herod, the king of Judea, a certain priest, by name Zacharias, of the division of Abijah, and his wife of the daughters of Aaron, and her name Elizabeth; <verse eid="LUK 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 1:6"/>and they were both righteous before God, going on in all the commands and righteousnesses of the LORD blameless, <verse eid="LUK 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 1:7"/>and they had no child, because that Elizabeth was barren, and both were advanced in their days. <verse eid="LUK 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 1:8"/>And it came to pass, in his acting as priest, in the order of his division before God, <verse eid="LUK 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 1:9"/>according to the custom of the priesthood, his lot was to make incense, having gone into the temple of the LORD, <verse eid="LUK 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 1:10"/>and all the multitude of the people were praying outside, at the hour of the incense. <verse eid="LUK 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 1:11"/>And there appeared to him a messenger of the LORD standing on the right side of the altar of the incense, <verse eid="LUK 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 1:12"/>and Zacharias, having seen, was troubled, and fear fell on him; <verse eid="LUK 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 1:13"/>and the messenger said to him, “Do not fear, Zacharias, for your supplication was heard, and your wife Elizabeth will bear a son to you, and you will call his name John, <verse eid="LUK 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 1:14"/>and there will be joy to you, and gladness, and many will rejoice at his birth, <verse eid="LUK 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 1:15"/>for he will be great before the LORD, and wine and strong drink he may not drink, and he will be full of the Holy Spirit, even from his mother’s womb; <verse eid="LUK 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 1:16"/>and he will turn many of the sons of Israel to the LORD their God, <verse eid="LUK 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 1:17"/>and he will go before Him, in the spirit and power of Elijah, to turn hearts of fathers to children, and disobedient ones to the wisdom of righteous ones, to make ready for the LORD, a people prepared.” <verse eid="LUK 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 1:18"/>And Zacharias said to the messenger, “Whereby will I know this? For I am aged, and my wife is advanced in her days?” <verse eid="LUK 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 1:19"/>And the messenger answering said to him, “I am Gabriel, who has been standing near before God, and I was sent to speak to you, and to proclaim this good news to you, <verse eid="LUK 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 1:20"/>and behold, you will be silent, and not able to speak, until the day that these things will come to pass, because you did not believe my words that will be fulfilled in their season.” <verse eid="LUK 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 1:21"/>And the people were waiting for Zacharias, and wondering at his lingering in the temple, <verse eid="LUK 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 1:22"/>and having come out, he was not able to speak to them, and they perceived that he had seen a vision in the temple, and he was beckoning to them, and remained mute. <verse eid="LUK 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 1:23"/>And it came to pass, when the days of his service were fulfilled, he went away to his house, <verse eid="LUK 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 1:24"/>and after those days, his wife Elizabeth conceived, and hid herself five months, saying, <verse eid="LUK 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 1:25"/>“Thus the LORD has done to me, in days in which He looked on [me], to take away my reproach among men.” <verse eid="LUK 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 1:26"/>And in the sixth month the messenger Gabriel was sent by God, to a city of Galilee, the name of which [is] Nazareth, <verse eid="LUK 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 1:27"/>to a virgin, betrothed to a man, whose name [is] Joseph, of the house of David, and the name of the virgin [is] Mary. <verse eid="LUK 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 1:28"/>And the messenger having come in to her, said, “Greetings, favored one, the LORD [is] with you; blessed [are] you among women”; <verse eid="LUK 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 1:29"/>and she, having seen, was troubled at his word, and was reasoning of what kind this salutation may be. <verse eid="LUK 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 1:30"/>And the messenger said to her, “Do not fear, Mary, for you have found favor with God; <verse eid="LUK 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 1:31"/>and behold, you will conceive in the womb, and will bring forth a Son, and call His Name Jesus; <verse eid="LUK 1:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 1:32"/>He will be great, and He will be called Son of the Highest, and the LORD God will give Him the throne of His father David, <verse eid="LUK 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 1:33"/>and He will reign over the house of Jacob for all ages; and of His kingdom there will be no end.” <verse eid="LUK 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 1:34"/>And Mary said to the messenger, “How will this be, seeing I do not know a husband?” <verse eid="LUK 1:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 1:35"/>And the messenger answering said to her, “The Holy Spirit will come on you, and the power of the Highest will overshadow you, therefore also the holy-begotten thing will be called Son of God; <verse eid="LUK 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 1:36"/>and behold, Elizabeth, your relative, she also has conceived a son in her old age, and this is the sixth month to her who was called barren; <verse eid="LUK 1:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 1:37"/>because nothing will be impossible with God.” <verse eid="LUK 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 1:38"/>And Mary said, “Behold, the maidservant of the LORD; let it be to me according to your saying,” and the messenger went away from her. <verse eid="LUK 1:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 1:39"/>And Mary having arisen in those days, went into the hill-country, with haste, to a city of Judea, <verse eid="LUK 1:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 1:40"/>and entered into the house of Zacharias, and greeted Elizabeth. <verse eid="LUK 1:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 1:41"/>And it came to pass, when Elizabeth heard the salutation of Mary, the baby leapt in her womb; and Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit, <verse eid="LUK 1:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 1:42"/>and spoke out with a loud voice and said, “Blessed [are] you among women, and blessed [is] the Fruit of your womb; <verse eid="LUK 1:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 1:43"/>and from where [is] this to me, that the mother of my Lord might come to me? <verse eid="LUK 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 1:44"/>For behold, when the voice of your salutation came to my ears, the baby in my womb leapt in gladness; <verse eid="LUK 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 1:45"/>and blessed [is] she who believed, for there will be a completion to the things spoken to her from the LORD.” <verse eid="LUK 1:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 1:46"/>And Mary said, “My soul magnifies the LORD, <verse eid="LUK 1:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 1:47"/>And my spirit was glad on God my Savior, <verse eid="LUK 1:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 1:48"/>Because He looked on the lowliness of His maidservant, || For behold, from now on all the generations will call me blessed, <verse eid="LUK 1:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 1:49"/>For He who is mighty did great things to me, || And holy [is] His Name, <verse eid="LUK 1:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 1:50"/>And His kindness [is] to generations of generations, || To those fearing Him; <verse eid="LUK 1:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 1:51"/>He did powerfully with His arm, || He scattered abroad the proud in the thought of their heart, <verse eid="LUK 1:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 1:52"/>He brought down the mighty from thrones, || And He exalted the lowly, <verse eid="LUK 1:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 1:53"/>He filled the hungry with good, || And the rich He sent away empty; <verse eid="LUK 1:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 1:54"/>He has taken hold of His servant Israel, || To remember kindness, <verse eid="LUK 1:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 1:55"/>As He spoke to our fathers, || To Abraham and to his seed—throughout the age.” <verse eid="LUK 1:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 1:56"/>And Mary remained with her about three months, and turned back to her house. <verse eid="LUK 1:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LUK 1:57"/>And to Elizabeth was the time fulfilled for her bringing forth, and she bore a son, <verse eid="LUK 1:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LUK 1:58"/>and the neighbors and her relatives heard that the LORD was making His kindness great with her, and they were rejoicing with her. <verse eid="LUK 1:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="LUK 1:59"/>And it came to pass, on the eighth day, they came to circumcise the child, and they were calling him by the name of his father, Zacharias, <verse eid="LUK 1:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="LUK 1:60"/>and his mother answering said, “No, but he will be called John.” <verse eid="LUK 1:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="LUK 1:61"/>And they said to her, “There is none among your relatives who is called by this name,” <verse eid="LUK 1:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="LUK 1:62"/>and they were making signs to his father, what he would wish him to be called, <verse eid="LUK 1:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="LUK 1:63"/>and having asked for a tablet, he wrote, saying, “John is his name”; and they all wondered; <verse eid="LUK 1:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="LUK 1:64"/>and his mouth was opened immediately, and his tongue, and he was speaking, praising God. <verse eid="LUK 1:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="LUK 1:65"/>And fear came on all those dwelling around them, and in all the hill-country of Judea were all these sayings spoken of, <verse eid="LUK 1:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="LUK 1:66"/>and all who heard laid them up in their hearts, saying, “What then will this child be?” And the hand of the LORD was with him. <verse eid="LUK 1:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="LUK 1:67"/>And his father Zacharias was filled with the Holy Spirit, and prophesied, saying, <verse eid="LUK 1:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="LUK 1:68"/>“Blessed [is] the LORD, the God of Israel, || Because He looked on, || And worked redemption for His people, <verse eid="LUK 1:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="LUK 1:69"/>And raised a horn of salvation to us, || In the house of His servant David, <verse eid="LUK 1:69"/><verse number="70" style="v" sid="LUK 1:70"/>As He spoke by the mouth of His holy prophets, || Which have been from the age; <verse eid="LUK 1:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="LUK 1:71"/>Salvation from our enemies, || And out of the hand of all hating us, <verse eid="LUK 1:71"/><verse number="72" style="v" sid="LUK 1:72"/>To do kindness with our fathers, || And to be mindful of His holy covenant, <verse eid="LUK 1:72"/><verse number="73" style="v" sid="LUK 1:73"/>An oath that He swore to Abraham our father, <verse eid="LUK 1:73"/><verse number="74" style="v" sid="LUK 1:74"/>To give to us, without fear, || Having been delivered out of the hand of our enemies, <verse eid="LUK 1:74"/><verse number="75" style="v" sid="LUK 1:75"/>To serve Him, in holiness and righteousness || Before Him, all the days of our life. <verse eid="LUK 1:75"/><verse number="76" style="v" sid="LUK 1:76"/>And you, child, || Prophet of the Highest will you be called; For you will go before the face of the LORD, || To prepare His ways. <verse eid="LUK 1:76"/><verse number="77" style="v" sid="LUK 1:77"/>To give knowledge of salvation to His people || In forgiveness of their sins, <verse eid="LUK 1:77"/><verse number="78" style="v" sid="LUK 1:78"/>Through the yearnings of our God, || In which the rising from on high looked on us, <verse eid="LUK 1:78"/><verse number="79" style="v" sid="LUK 1:79"/>To give light to those sitting in darkness and death-shade, || To guide our feet to a way of peace.” <verse eid="LUK 1:79"/><verse number="80" style="v" sid="LUK 1:80"/>And the child grew, and was strengthened in spirit, and he was in the deserts until the day of his showing to Israel.<verse eid="LUK 1:80"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="LUK 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 2:1"/>And it came to pass in those days, there went forth a decree from Caesar Augustus that all the world be registered— <verse eid="LUK 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 2:2"/>this census first came to pass when Quirinius was governor of Syria— <verse eid="LUK 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 2:3"/>and all were going to be registered, each to his proper city, <verse eid="LUK 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 2:4"/>and Joseph also went up from Galilee, out of the city of Nazareth, to Judea, to the city of David, that is called Beth-Lehem, because of his being of the house and family of David, <verse eid="LUK 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 2:5"/>to register himself with Mary his betrothed wife, being with Child. <verse eid="LUK 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 2:6"/>And it came to pass, in their being there, the days were fulfilled for her bringing forth, <verse eid="LUK 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 2:7"/>and she brought forth her Son—the firstborn, and wrapped Him up, and laid Him down in the manger, because there was not a place for them in the guest-chamber. <verse eid="LUK 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 2:8"/>And there were shepherds in the same region, lodging in the field and keeping the night-watches over their flock, <verse eid="LUK 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 2:9"/>and behold, a messenger of the LORD stood over them, and the glory of the LORD shone around them, and they feared [with] a great fear. <verse eid="LUK 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 2:10"/>And the messenger said to them, “Do not fear, for behold, I bring you good news of great joy that will be to all the people, <verse eid="LUK 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 2:11"/>because today in the city of David a Savior was born to you, who is Christ the LORD! <verse eid="LUK 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 2:12"/>And this [is] the sign to you: you will find a Baby wrapped up, lying in the manger.” <verse eid="LUK 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 2:13"/>And suddenly there came with the messenger a multitude of the heavenly host, praising God, and saying, <verse eid="LUK 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 2:14"/>“Glory in the highest to God, and on earth peace, among men—good will!” <verse eid="LUK 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 2:15"/>And it came to pass, when the messengers were gone away from them to the heavens, that the men, the shepherds, said to one another, “We may indeed go over to Beth-Lehem and see this thing that has come to pass, that the LORD made known to us!” <verse eid="LUK 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 2:16"/>And they came, having hurried, and found both Mary, and Joseph, and the Baby lying in the manger, <verse eid="LUK 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 2:17"/>and having seen, they made known abroad concerning the saying spoken to them concerning the Child. <verse eid="LUK 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 2:18"/>And all who heard [it] wondered concerning the things spoken to them by the shepherds; <verse eid="LUK 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 2:19"/>and Mary was preserving all these things, pondering [them] in her heart; <verse eid="LUK 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 2:20"/>and the shepherds turned back, glorifying and praising God for all those things they heard and saw, as it was spoken to them. <verse eid="LUK 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 2:21"/>And when eight days were fulfilled to circumcise the Child, then was His Name called Jesus, having been so called by the messenger before His being conceived in the womb. <verse eid="LUK 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 2:22"/>And when the days of their purification were fulfilled, according to the Law of Moses, they brought Him up to Jerusalem, to present to the LORD, <verse eid="LUK 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 2:23"/>as it has been written in the Law of the LORD: “Every male opening a womb will be called holy to the LORD,” <verse eid="LUK 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 2:24"/>and to give a sacrifice, according to that said in the Law of the LORD: “A pair of turtle-doves, or two young pigeons.” <verse eid="LUK 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 2:25"/>And behold, there was a man in Jerusalem whose name [is] Simeon, and this man is righteous and devout, looking for the comforting of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was on him, <verse eid="LUK 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 2:26"/>and it has been divinely told him by the Holy Spirit—not to see death before he may see the Christ of the LORD. <verse eid="LUK 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 2:27"/>And he came in the Spirit into the temple, and in the parents bringing in the child Jesus, for their doing according to the custom of the Law regarding Him, <verse eid="LUK 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 2:28"/>then he took Him in his arms, and blessed God, and he said, <verse eid="LUK 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 2:29"/>“Now You send Your servant away, O LORD, according to Your word, in peace, <verse eid="LUK 2:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 2:30"/>because my eyes saw Your salvation, <verse eid="LUK 2:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 2:31"/>which You prepared before the face of all the peoples, <verse eid="LUK 2:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 2:32"/>a light to the uncovering of nations, and the glory of Your people Israel.” <verse eid="LUK 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 2:33"/>And Joseph and His mother were wondering at the things spoken concerning Him, <verse eid="LUK 2:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 2:34"/>and Simeon blessed them and said to His mother Mary, “Behold, this [One] is set for the falling and rising again of many in Israel, and for a sign spoken against— <verse eid="LUK 2:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 2:35"/>(and also a sword will pass through your own soul)—that the reasonings of many hearts may be revealed.” <verse eid="LUK 2:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 2:36"/>And there was Anna, a prophetess, daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Asher, she was much advanced in days, having lived with a husband seven years from her virginity, <verse eid="LUK 2:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 2:37"/>and she [is] a widow of about eighty-four years, who did not depart from the temple, serving with fasts and supplications, night and day, <verse eid="LUK 2:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 2:38"/>and she, at that hour, having come in, was confessing, likewise, to the LORD, and was speaking concerning Him to all those looking for redemption in Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 2:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 2:39"/>And when they completed all things according to the Law of the LORD, they turned back to Galilee, to their city of Nazareth; <verse eid="LUK 2:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 2:40"/>and the Child grew and was strengthened in spirit, being filled with wisdom, and the grace of God was on Him. <verse eid="LUK 2:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 2:41"/>And His parents were going yearly to Jerusalem, at the Celebration of the Passover, <verse eid="LUK 2:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 2:42"/>and when He became twelve years old, they having gone up to Jerusalem according to the custom of the celebration, <verse eid="LUK 2:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 2:43"/>and having finished the days, in their returning the child Jesus remained behind in Jerusalem, and Joseph and His mother did not know, <verse eid="LUK 2:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 2:44"/>and having supposed Him to be in the company, they went a day’s journey, and were seeking Him among the relatives and among the acquaintances, <verse eid="LUK 2:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 2:45"/>and having not found Him, they turned back to Jerusalem seeking Him. <verse eid="LUK 2:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 2:46"/>And it came to pass, after three days they found Him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the teachers, both hearing them and questioning them, <verse eid="LUK 2:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 2:47"/>and all those hearing Him were astonished at His understanding and answers. <verse eid="LUK 2:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 2:48"/>And having seen Him, they were amazed, and His mother said to Him, “Child, why did You do this to us? Behold, Your father and I, sorrowing, were seeking You.” <verse eid="LUK 2:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 2:49"/>And He said to them, “Why [is it] that you were seeking Me? Did you not know that it is necessary for Me to be in the things of My Father?” <verse eid="LUK 2:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 2:50"/>And they did not understand the saying that He spoke to them, <verse eid="LUK 2:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 2:51"/>and He went down with them, and came to Nazareth, and He was subject to them, and His mother was keeping all these sayings in her heart, <verse eid="LUK 2:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 2:52"/>and Jesus was advancing in wisdom, and in stature, and in favor with God and men.<verse eid="LUK 2:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="LUK 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 3:1"/>And in the fifteenth year of the government of Tiberius Caesar—Pontius Pilate being governor of Judea, and Herod tetrarch of Galilee, and his brother Philip, tetrarch of Ituraea and of the region of Trachonitis, and Lysanias tetrarch of Abilene, <verse eid="LUK 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 3:2"/>[and] Annas and Caiaphas being chief priests—there came a word of God to John the son of Zacharias, in the wilderness, <verse eid="LUK 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 3:3"/>and he came to all the region around the Jordan, proclaiming an immersion of conversion for forgiveness of sins, <verse eid="LUK 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 3:4"/>as it has been written in the scroll of the words of Isaiah the prophet: “A voice of one crying in the wilderness: Prepare the way of the LORD, || Make His paths straight; <verse eid="LUK 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 3:5"/>Every valley will be filled, || And every mountain and hill will be made low, || And the crooked will become straightness, || And the rough become smooth ways; <verse eid="LUK 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 3:6"/>And all flesh will see the salvation of God.” <verse eid="LUK 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 3:7"/>Then he said to the multitudes coming forth to be immersed by him, “Brood of vipers! Who prompted you to flee from the coming wrath? <verse eid="LUK 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 3:8"/>Make, therefore, fruits worthy of conversion, and do not begin to say within yourselves, We have a father—Abraham; for I say to you that God is able to raise children to Abraham out of these stones; <verse eid="LUK 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 3:9"/>and also the axe is already laid to the root of the trees, every tree, therefore, not making good fruit is cut down, and it is cast into fire.” <verse eid="LUK 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 3:10"/>And the multitudes were questioning him, saying, “What, then, will we do?” <verse eid="LUK 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 3:11"/>And he answering says to them, “He having two coats, let him impart to him having none; and he having food, let him do in like manner.” <verse eid="LUK 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 3:12"/>And there also came tax collectors to be immersed, and they said to him, “Teacher, what will we do?” <verse eid="LUK 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 3:13"/>And he said to them, “Exact no more than that directed you.” <verse eid="LUK 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 3:14"/>And also questioning him were those warring, saying, “And we, what will we do?” And he said to them, “Do violence to no one, nor accuse falsely, and be content with your wages.” <verse eid="LUK 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 3:15"/>And the people are looking forward, and all are reasoning in their hearts concerning John, whether or not he may be the Christ; <verse eid="LUK 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 3:16"/>John answered, saying to all, “I indeed immerse you in water, but He comes who is mightier than I, of whom I am not worthy to loose the strap of His sandals—He will immerse you in the Holy Spirit and fire; <verse eid="LUK 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 3:17"/>whose winnowing shovel [is] in His hand, and He will thoroughly cleanse His floor, and will gather the wheat into His storehouse, and He will burn the chaff with unquenchable fire.” <verse eid="LUK 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 3:18"/>And therefore, indeed, with many other things, exhorting, he was proclaiming good news to the people, <verse eid="LUK 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 3:19"/>and Herod the tetrarch, being reproved by him concerning Herodias, the wife of his brother Philip, and concerning all the evils that Herod did, <verse eid="LUK 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 3:20"/>added also this to all, that he shut up John in the prison. <verse eid="LUK 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 3:21"/>And it came to pass, in all the people being immersed, Jesus also being immersed, and praying, Heaven was opened, <verse eid="LUK 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 3:22"/>and the Holy Spirit came down in a bodily appearance, as if a dove, on Him, and a voice came out of Heaven, saying, “You are My Son, the Beloved, in You I delighted.” <verse eid="LUK 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 3:23"/>And Jesus Himself was beginning to be about thirty years of age, being, as was supposed, Son of Joseph, <verse eid="LUK 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 3:24"/>the [son] of Eli, the [son] of Matthat, the [son] of Levi, the [son] of Melchi, the [son] of Janna, the [son] of Joseph, <verse eid="LUK 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 3:25"/>the [son] of Mattathias, the [son] of Amos, the [son] of Nahum, the [son] of Esli, <verse eid="LUK 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 3:26"/>the [son] of Naggai, the [son] of Maath, the [son] of Mattathias, the [son] of Semei, the [son] of Joseph, the [son] of Judah, <verse eid="LUK 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 3:27"/>the [son] of Joanna, the [son] of Rhesa, the [son] of Zerubbabel, the [son] of Shealtiel, <verse eid="LUK 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 3:28"/>the [son] of Neri, the [son] of Melchi, the [son] of Addi, the [son] of Cosam, the [son] of Elmodam, the [son] of Er, <verse eid="LUK 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 3:29"/>the [son] of Jose, the [son] of Eliezer, the [son] of Jorim, the [son] of Matthat, <verse eid="LUK 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 3:30"/>the [son] of Levi, the [son] of Simeon, the [son] of Judah, the [son] of Joseph, the [son] of Jonan, the [son] of Eliakim, <verse eid="LUK 3:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 3:31"/>the [son] of Melea, the [son] of Mainan, the [son] of Mattatha, the [son] of Nathan, <verse eid="LUK 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 3:32"/>the [son] of David, the [son] of Jesse, the [son] of Obed, the [son] of Boaz, the [son] of Salmon, the [son] of Nahshon, <verse eid="LUK 3:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 3:33"/>the [son] of Amminadab, the [son] of Aram, the [son] of Esrom, the [son] of Perez, <verse eid="LUK 3:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 3:34"/>the [son] of Judah, the [son] of Jacob, the [son] of Isaac, the [son] of Abraham, the [son] of Terah, the [son] of Nahor, <verse eid="LUK 3:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 3:35"/>the [son] of Serug, the [son] of Reu, the [son] of Peleg, the [son] of Eber, <verse eid="LUK 3:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 3:36"/>the [son] of Salah, the [son] of Cainan, the [son] of Arphaxad, the [son] of Shem, the [son] of Noah, the [son] of Lamech, <verse eid="LUK 3:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 3:37"/>the [son] of Methuselah, the [son] of Enoch, the [son] of Jared, the [son] of Mahalaleel, <verse eid="LUK 3:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 3:38"/>the [son] of Cainan, the [son] of Enos, the [son] of Seth, the [son] of Adam, the [son] of God.<verse eid="LUK 3:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="LUK 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 4:1"/>And Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, turned back from the Jordan, and was brought in the Spirit into the wilderness, <verse eid="LUK 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 4:2"/>being tempted by the Devil forty days, and He did not eat anything in those days, and they having been ended, He afterward hungered, <verse eid="LUK 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 4:3"/>and the Devil said to Him, “If You are [the] Son of God, speak to this stone that it may become bread.” <verse eid="LUK 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 4:4"/>And Jesus answered him, saying, “It has been written, that, Not on bread only will man live, but on every saying of God.” <verse eid="LUK 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 4:5"/>And the Devil having brought Him up to a high mountain, showed to Him all the kingdoms of the world in a moment of time, <verse eid="LUK 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 4:6"/>and the Devil said to Him, “To You I will give all this authority, and their glory, because to me it has been delivered, and to whomsoever I will, I give it; <verse eid="LUK 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 4:7"/>You, then, if You may worship me—all will be Yours.” <verse eid="LUK 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 4:8"/>And Jesus answering him said, “<char style="bd">[[</char>Get behind Me, Satan, for<char style="bd">]]</char> it has been written: You will worship the LORD your God, and Him only you will serve.” <verse eid="LUK 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 4:9"/>And he brought Him to Jerusalem, and set Him on the pinnacle of the temple, and said to Him, “If You are the Son of God, cast Yourself down from here, <verse eid="LUK 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 4:10"/>for it has been written: To His messengers He will give charge concerning you, to guard over you; <verse eid="LUK 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 4:11"/>and: On hands they will bear you up, lest at any time you may dash your foot against a stone.” <verse eid="LUK 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 4:12"/>And Jesus answering said to him, “It has been said, You will not tempt the LORD your God.” <verse eid="LUK 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 4:13"/>And having ended all temptation, the Devil departed from Him until a convenient season. <verse eid="LUK 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 4:14"/>And Jesus turned back in the power of the Spirit to Galilee, and a fame went forth through all the surrounding region concerning Him, <verse eid="LUK 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 4:15"/>and He was teaching in their synagogues, being glorified by all. <verse eid="LUK 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 4:16"/>And He came to Nazareth, where He has been brought up, and He went in, according to His custom, on the day of the Sabbaths, into the synagogue, and stood up to read; <verse eid="LUK 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 4:17"/>and there was given over to Him a scroll of Isaiah the prophet, and having unfolded the scroll, He found the place where it has been written: <verse eid="LUK 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 4:18"/>“The Spirit of the LORD [is] on Me, || Because He anointed Me || To proclaim good news to the poor, || Sent Me to heal the broken of heart, || To proclaim to captives deliverance, || And to blind receiving of sight, || To send the bruised away with deliverance, <verse eid="LUK 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 4:19"/>To proclaim the acceptable year of the LORD.” <verse eid="LUK 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 4:20"/>And having folded the scroll, having given [it] back to the officer, He sat down, and the eyes of all in the synagogue were gazing on Him. <verse eid="LUK 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 4:21"/>And He began to say to them, “Today this writing has been fulfilled in your ears”; <verse eid="LUK 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 4:22"/>and all were bearing testimony to Him, and were wondering at the gracious words that are coming forth out of His mouth, and they said, “Is this not the Son of Joseph?” <verse eid="LUK 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 4:23"/>And He said to them, “Certainly you will say to Me this allegory, Physician, heal yourself; as great things as we heard done in Capernaum, do also here in Your country”; <verse eid="LUK 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 4:24"/>and He said, “Truly I say to you, no prophet is accepted in his own country; <verse eid="LUK 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 4:25"/>and of a truth I say to you, many widows were in the days of Elijah, in Israel, when the sky was shut for three years and six months, when great famine came on all the land, <verse eid="LUK 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 4:26"/>and to none of them was Elijah sent, but—to Sarepta of Sidon, to a woman, a widow; <verse eid="LUK 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 4:27"/>and many lepers were in the time of Elisha the prophet, in Israel, and none of them was cleansed, but—Naaman the Syrian.” <verse eid="LUK 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 4:28"/>And all in the synagogue were filled with wrath, hearing these things, <verse eid="LUK 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 4:29"/>and having risen, they put Him forth outside the city, and brought Him to the brow of the hill on which their city had been built—to cast Him down headlong, <verse eid="LUK 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 4:30"/>and He, having gone through the midst of them, went away. <verse eid="LUK 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 4:31"/>And He came down to Capernaum, a city of Galilee, and was teaching them on the Sabbaths, <verse eid="LUK 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 4:32"/>and they were astonished at His teaching, because His word was with authority. <verse eid="LUK 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 4:33"/>And in the synagogue was a man having a spirit of an unclean demon, and he cried out with a great voice, <verse eid="LUK 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 4:34"/>“Aah! What [regards] us and You, Jesus, O Nazarene? You came to destroy us; I have known who You are—the Holy One of God!” <verse eid="LUK 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 4:35"/>And Jesus rebuked him, saying, “Be silenced, and come forth out of him”; and the demon having cast him into the midst, came forth from him, having hurt him nothing; <verse eid="LUK 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 4:36"/>and amazement came on all, and they were speaking together with one another, saying, “What [is] this word, that with authority and power He commands the unclean spirits, and they come forth?” <verse eid="LUK 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 4:37"/>And there was going forth a fame concerning Him to every place of the surrounding region. <verse eid="LUK 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 4:38"/>And having risen out of the synagogue, He entered into the house of Simon, and the mother-in-law of Simon was pressed with a great fever, and they asked Him about her, <verse eid="LUK 4:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 4:39"/>and having stood over her, He rebuked the fever, and it left her, and immediately, having risen, she was ministering to them. <verse eid="LUK 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 4:40"/>And at the setting of the sun, all, as many as had any ailing with manifold diseases, brought them to Him, and He, having put hands on each one of them, healed them. <verse eid="LUK 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 4:41"/>And demons were also coming forth from many, crying out and saying, “You are the Christ, the Son of God”; and rebuking, He did not permit them to speak, because they knew Him to be the Christ. <verse eid="LUK 4:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 4:42"/>And day having come, having gone forth, He went on to a desolate place, and the multitudes were seeking Him, and they came to Him, and were restraining Him—not to go on from them, <verse eid="LUK 4:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 4:43"/>and He said to them, “Also to the other cities it is necessary for Me to proclaim good news of the Kingdom of God, because for this I have been sent”; <verse eid="LUK 4:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 4:44"/>and He was preaching in the synagogues of Galilee.<verse eid="LUK 4:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="LUK 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 5:1"/>And it came to pass, in the multitude pressing on Him to hear the word of God, that He was standing beside the Lake of Gennesaret, <verse eid="LUK 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 5:2"/>and He saw two boats standing beside the lake, and the fishers, having gone away from them, were washing the nets, <verse eid="LUK 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 5:3"/>and having entered into one of the boats, that was Simon’s, He asked him to put back a little from the land, and having sat down, was teaching the multitudes out of the boat. <verse eid="LUK 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 5:4"/>And when He left off speaking, He said to Simon, “Put back into the deep, and let down your nets for a catch”; <verse eid="LUK 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 5:5"/>and Simon answering said to Him, “Master, through the whole night, having labored, we have taken nothing, but at Your saying I will let down the net.” <verse eid="LUK 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 5:6"/>And having done this, they enclosed a great multitude of fishes, and their net was breaking, <verse eid="LUK 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 5:7"/>and they beckoned to the partners who [are] in the other boat, having come, to help them; and they came, and filled both the boats, so that they were sinking. <verse eid="LUK 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 5:8"/>And Simon Peter having seen, fell down at the knees of Jesus, saying, “Depart from me, because I am a sinful man, O Lord”; <verse eid="LUK 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 5:9"/>for astonishment seized him, and all those with him, at the catch of the fishes that they took, <verse eid="LUK 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 5:10"/>and in like manner also James and John, sons of Zebedee, who were partners with Simon; and Jesus said to Simon, “Do not fear, from now on you will be catching men”; <verse eid="LUK 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 5:11"/>and they, having brought the boats on the land, having left all, followed Him. <verse eid="LUK 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 5:12"/>And it came to pass, in His being in one of the cities, that behold, a man full of leprosy, and having seen Jesus, having fallen on [his] face, he implored Him, saying, “Lord, if You may will, You are able to cleanse me”; <verse eid="LUK 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 5:13"/>and having stretched forth [His] hand, He touched him, having said, “I will, be cleansed”; and immediately the leprosy went away from him. <verse eid="LUK 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 5:14"/>And He charged him to tell no one, “But having gone away, show yourself to the priest, and bring near for your cleansing according as Moses directed, for a testimony to them”; <verse eid="LUK 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 5:15"/>but the more was the report going abroad concerning Him, and great multitudes were coming together to hear, and to be healed by Him of their sicknesses, <verse eid="LUK 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 5:16"/>and He was withdrawing Himself in the desolate places and was praying. <verse eid="LUK 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 5:17"/>And it came to pass, on one of the days, that He was teaching, and there were sitting by Pharisees and teachers of the Law, who were come out of every village of Galilee, and Judea, and Jerusalem, and the power of the LORD was—to heal them. <verse eid="LUK 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 5:18"/>And behold, men carrying a man on a bed, who has been struck with palsy, and they were seeking to bring him in, and to place before Him, <verse eid="LUK 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 5:19"/>and having not found by what way they may bring him in because of the multitude, having gone up on the housetop, through the tiles they let him down with the little bed, into the midst before Jesus, <verse eid="LUK 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 5:20"/>and He having seen their faith, said to him, “Man, your sins have been forgiven you.” <verse eid="LUK 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 5:21"/>And the scribes and the Pharisees began to reason, saying, “Who is this that speaks evil words? Who is able to forgive sins, except God only?” <verse eid="LUK 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 5:22"/>And Jesus having known their reasonings, answering, said to them, “What reason you in your hearts? <verse eid="LUK 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 5:23"/>Which is easier—to say, Your sins have been forgiven you? Or to say, Arise, and walk? <verse eid="LUK 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 5:24"/>And that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on the earth to forgive sins—(He said to the one struck with palsy)—I say to you, arise, and having taken up your little bed, be going on to your house.” <verse eid="LUK 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 5:25"/>And immediately having risen before them, having taken up [that] on which he was lying, he went away to his house, glorifying God, <verse eid="LUK 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 5:26"/>and astonishment took all, and they were glorifying God, and were filled with fear, saying, “We saw strange things today.” <verse eid="LUK 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 5:27"/>And after these things He went forth, and beheld a tax collector, by name Levi, sitting at the tax office, and said to him, “Follow Me”; <verse eid="LUK 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 5:28"/>and he, having left all, having arisen, followed Him. <verse eid="LUK 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 5:29"/>And Levi made a great entertainment to Him in his house, and there was a great multitude of tax collectors and others who were with them reclining, <verse eid="LUK 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 5:30"/>and the scribes and the Pharisees among them were murmuring at His disciples, saying, “Why do You eat and drink with tax collectors and sinners?” <verse eid="LUK 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 5:31"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “They who are well have no need of a physician, but they that are ill: <verse eid="LUK 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 5:32"/>I did not come to call righteous men, but sinners, to conversion.” <verse eid="LUK 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 5:33"/>And they said to Him, “Why do the disciples of John fast often, and make supplications—in like manner also those of the Pharisees—but Yours eat and drink?” <verse eid="LUK 5:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 5:34"/>And He said to them, “Are you able to make the sons of the bride-chamber—in the Bridegroom being with them—to fast? <verse eid="LUK 5:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 5:35"/>But days will come, and when the Bridegroom may be taken away from them, then they will fast in those days.” <verse eid="LUK 5:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 5:36"/>And He spoke also an allegory to them: “No one puts a patch of new clothing on old clothing, and if otherwise, the new also makes a split, and with the old the patch does not agree, that [is] from the new. <verse eid="LUK 5:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 5:37"/>And no one puts new wine into old skins, and if otherwise, the new wine will burst the skins, and itself will be poured out, and the skins will be destroyed; <verse eid="LUK 5:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 5:38"/>but new wine is to be put into new skins, and both are preserved together; <verse eid="LUK 5:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 5:39"/>and no one having drunk old, immediately wishes new, for he says, The old is better.”<verse eid="LUK 5:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="LUK 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 6:1"/>And it came to pass, on a Sabbath, as He is going through the grainfields, that His disciples were plucking the ears, and were eating, rubbing with the hands, <verse eid="LUK 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 6:2"/>and certain of the Pharisees said to them, “Why do you do that which is not lawful to do on the Sabbaths?” <verse eid="LUK 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 6:3"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “Did you not read even this that David did when he hungered, himself and those who are with him, <verse eid="LUK 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 6:4"/>how he went into the house of God, and took the Bread of the Presentation, and ate, and gave also to those with him, which it is not lawful to eat, except only to the priests?” <verse eid="LUK 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 6:5"/>And He said to them, “The Son of Man is Lord also of the Sabbath.” <verse eid="LUK 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 6:6"/>And it came to pass also, on another Sabbath, that He goes into the synagogue, and teaches, and there was there a man, and his right hand was withered, <verse eid="LUK 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 6:7"/>and the scribes and the Pharisees were watching Him, if on the Sabbath He will heal, that they might find an accusation against Him. <verse eid="LUK 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 6:8"/>And He Himself had known their reasonings and said to the man having the withered hand, “Rise, and stand in the midst”; and he having risen, stood. <verse eid="LUK 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 6:9"/>Then Jesus said to them, “I will question you something: is it lawful on the Sabbaths to do good, or to do evil? To save life or to kill?” <verse eid="LUK 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 6:10"/>And having looked around on them all, He said to the man, “Stretch forth your hand”; and he did so, and his hand was restored whole as the other; <verse eid="LUK 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 6:11"/>and they were filled with madness, and were speaking with one another what they might do to Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 6:12"/>And it came to pass in those days, He went forth to the mountain to pray, and was passing the night in the prayer of God, <verse eid="LUK 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 6:13"/>and when it became day, He called near His disciples, also having chosen twelve from them, whom He also named apostles: <verse eid="LUK 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 6:14"/>Simon, whom He also named Peter, and his brother Andrew, James and John, Philip and Bartholomew, <verse eid="LUK 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 6:15"/>Matthew and Thomas, James of Alphaeus, and Simon called Zealot, <verse eid="LUK 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 6:16"/>Judas of James, and Judas Iscariot, who also became betrayer. <verse eid="LUK 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 6:17"/>And having come down with them, He stood on a level spot; and a crowd of His disciples, and a great multitude of the people from all Judea, and Jerusalem, and the seacoast of Tyre and Sidon, <verse eid="LUK 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 6:18"/>who came to hear Him and to be healed of their diseases, [gathered]. And those harassed by unclean spirits [also gathered] and were healed. <verse eid="LUK 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 6:19"/>And all the multitude were seeking to touch Him, because power was going forth from Him, and He was healing all. <verse eid="LUK 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 6:20"/>And He, having lifted up His eyes to His disciples, said: “Blessed the poor—because yours is the Kingdom of God. <verse eid="LUK 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 6:21"/>Blessed those hungering now—because you will be filled. Blessed those weeping now—because you will laugh. <verse eid="LUK 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 6:22"/>Blessed are you when men will hate you, and when they will separate you, and will reproach, and will cast forth your name as evil, for the Son of Man’s sake— <verse eid="LUK 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 6:23"/>rejoice in that day, and leap, for behold, your reward [is] great in Heaven, for according to these things were their fathers doing to the prophets. <verse eid="LUK 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 6:24"/>But woe to you—the rich, because you have gotten your comfort. <verse eid="LUK 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 6:25"/>Woe to you who have been filled—because you will hunger. Woe to you who are laughing now—because you will mourn and weep. <verse eid="LUK 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 6:26"/>Woe to you when all men will speak well of you—for according to these things were their fathers doing to false prophets. <verse eid="LUK 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 6:27"/>But I say to you who are hearing, love your enemies, do good to those hating you, <verse eid="LUK 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 6:28"/>bless those cursing you, pray for those maligning you; <verse eid="LUK 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 6:29"/>and to him striking you on the cheek, give also the other, and from him taking away from you the mantle, also the coat you may not keep back. <verse eid="LUK 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 6:30"/>And to everyone who is asking of you, be giving; and from him who is taking away your goods, do not be asking again; <verse eid="LUK 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 6:31"/>and as you wish that men may do to you, do also to them in like manner; <verse eid="LUK 6:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 6:32"/>and—if you love those loving you, what grace is it to you? For also the sinful love those loving them; <verse eid="LUK 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 6:33"/>and if you do good to those doing good to you, what grace is it to you? For also the sinful do the same; <verse eid="LUK 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 6:34"/>and if you lend [to those] of whom you hope to receive back, what grace is it to you? For also the sinful lend to sinners—that they may receive again as much. <verse eid="LUK 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 6:35"/>But love your enemies, and do good, and lend, hoping for nothing again, and your reward will be great, and you will be sons of the Highest, because He is kind to the ungracious and evil; <verse eid="LUK 6:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 6:36"/>be therefore merciful, as also your Father is merciful. <verse eid="LUK 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 6:37"/>And do not judge, and you may not be judged; do not condemn, and you may not be condemned; release, and you will be released. <verse eid="LUK 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 6:38"/>Give, and it will be given to you; good measure, pressed, and shaken, and running over, they will give into your bosom; for with that measure with which you measure, it will be measured to you again.” <verse eid="LUK 6:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 6:39"/>And He spoke an allegory to them, “Is blind able to lead blind? Will they not both fall into a pit? <verse eid="LUK 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 6:40"/>A disciple is not above his teacher, but everyone perfected will be as his teacher. <verse eid="LUK 6:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 6:41"/>And why do you behold the speck that is in your brother’s eye, and do not consider the beam that [is] in your own eye? <verse eid="LUK 6:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 6:42"/>Or how are you able to say to your brother, Brother, permit, I may take out the speck that [is] in your eye—yourself not beholding the beam in your own eye? Hypocrite, first take the beam out of your own eye, and then you will see clearly to take out the speck that [is] in your brother’s eye. <verse eid="LUK 6:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 6:43"/>For there is not a good tree making bad fruit, nor a bad tree making good fruit; <verse eid="LUK 6:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 6:44"/>for each tree is known from its own fruit, for they do not gather figs from thorns, nor do they crop a grape from a bramble. <verse eid="LUK 6:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 6:45"/>The good man out of the good treasure of his heart brings forth that which [is] good; and the evil man out of the evil treasure of his heart brings forth that which [is] evil; for out of the abounding of the heart his mouth speaks. <verse eid="LUK 6:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 6:46"/>And why do you call Me, Lord, Lord, and do not do what I say? <verse eid="LUK 6:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 6:47"/>Everyone who is coming to Me, and is hearing My words, and is doing them, I will show you to whom he is like: <verse eid="LUK 6:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 6:48"/>he is like to a man building a house, who dug and deepened, and laid a foundation on the rock, and a flood having come, the stream broke forth on that house, and was not able to shake it, for it had been founded on the rock. <verse eid="LUK 6:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 6:49"/>And he who heard and did not, is like to a man having built a house on the earth, without a foundation, against which the stream broke forth, and immediately it fell, and the ruin of that house became great.”<verse eid="LUK 6:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="LUK 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 7:1"/>And when He completed all His sayings in the ears of the people, He went into Capernaum; <verse eid="LUK 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 7:2"/>and a certain centurion’s servant being ill, was about to die, who was much valued by him, <verse eid="LUK 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 7:3"/>and having heard about Jesus, he sent to Him elders of the Jews, imploring Him, that having come He might thoroughly save his servant. <verse eid="LUK 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 7:4"/>And they, having come near to Jesus, were calling on Him earnestly, saying, “He is worthy to whom You will do this, <verse eid="LUK 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 7:5"/>for he loves our nation, and he built to us the synagogue.” <verse eid="LUK 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 7:6"/>And Jesus was going on with them, and now when He is not far distant from the house the centurion sent to Him friends, saying to Him, “Lord, do not be troubled, for I am not worthy that You may enter under my roof; <verse eid="LUK 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 7:7"/>for this reason I did not consider myself worthy to come to You, but say in a word, and my boy will be healed; <verse eid="LUK 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 7:8"/>for I also am a man placed under authority, having under myself soldiers, and I say to this [one], Go, and he goes; and to another, Be coming, and he comes; and to my servant, Do this, and he does [it].” <verse eid="LUK 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 7:9"/>And having heard these things Jesus wondered at him, and having turned to the multitude following Him, He said, “I say to you, not even in Israel did I find so much faith”; <verse eid="LUK 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 7:10"/>and those sent, having turned back to the house, found the ailing servant in health. <verse eid="LUK 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 7:11"/>And it came to pass, on the next day, He was going on to a city called Nain, and there were going with Him many of His disciples, and a great multitude, <verse eid="LUK 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 7:12"/>and as He came near to the gate of the city, then, behold, one dead was being carried forth, an only son of his mother, and she a widow, and a great multitude of the city was with her. <verse eid="LUK 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 7:13"/>And the LORD having seen her, was moved with compassion toward her and said to her, “Do not be weeping”; <verse eid="LUK 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 7:14"/>and having come near, He touched the bier, and those carrying [it] stood still, and He said, “Young man, to you I say, Arise”; <verse eid="LUK 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 7:15"/>and the dead sat up, and began to speak, and He gave him to his mother; <verse eid="LUK 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 7:16"/>and fear took hold of all, and they were glorifying God, saying, “A great prophet has risen among us,” and, “God looked on His people.” <verse eid="LUK 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 7:17"/>And the account of this went forth in all Judea about Him, and in all the region around. <verse eid="LUK 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 7:18"/>And the disciples of John told him about all these things, <verse eid="LUK 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 7:19"/>and John having called near a certain two of his disciples, sent to Jesus, saying, “Are You He who is coming, or do we look for another?” <verse eid="LUK 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 7:20"/>And having come near to Him, the men said, “John the Immerser sent us to You, saying, Are You He who is coming, or do we look for another?” <verse eid="LUK 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 7:21"/>And in that hour He cured many from diseases, and plagues, and evil spirits, and He granted sight to many blind. <verse eid="LUK 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 7:22"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “Having gone on, report to John what you saw and heard, that blind men see again, lame walk, lepers are cleansed, deaf hear, dead are raised, poor have good news proclaimed; <verse eid="LUK 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 7:23"/>and blessed is he whoever may not be stumbled in Me.” <verse eid="LUK 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 7:24"/>And the messengers of John having gone away, He began to say to the multitudes concerning John: “What have you gone forth into the wilderness to look on? A reed shaken by the wind? <verse eid="LUK 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 7:25"/>But what have you gone forth to see? A man clothed in soft garments? Behold, they in splendid clothing, and living in luxury, are in the houses of kings! <verse eid="LUK 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 7:26"/>But what have you gone forth to see? A prophet? Yes, I say to you, and much more than a prophet: <verse eid="LUK 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 7:27"/>this is he concerning whom it has been written: Behold, I send My messenger before Your face, who will prepare Your way before You; <verse eid="LUK 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 7:28"/>for I say to you, there is not a greater prophet, among those born of women, than John the Immerser; but the least in the Kingdom of God is greater than he.” <verse eid="LUK 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 7:29"/>And all the people having heard, and the tax collectors, declared God righteous, having been immersed with the immersion of John, <verse eid="LUK 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 7:30"/>but the Pharisees and the lawyers put away the counsel of God for themselves, having not been immersed by him. <verse eid="LUK 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 7:31"/>And the LORD said, “To what, then, will I liken the men of this generation? And to what are they like? <verse eid="LUK 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 7:32"/>They are like to children, to those sitting in a marketplace, and calling to one another, and saying, We piped to you, and you did not dance, we mourned to you, and you did not weep! <verse eid="LUK 7:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 7:33"/>For John the Immerser came neither eating bread nor drinking wine, and you say, He has a demon; <verse eid="LUK 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 7:34"/>the Son of Man came eating and drinking, and you say, Behold, a man, a glutton, and a wine drinker, a friend of tax collectors and sinners; <verse eid="LUK 7:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 7:35"/>and the wisdom was justified from all her children.” <verse eid="LUK 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 7:36"/>And a certain one of the Pharisees was asking Him that He might eat with him, and having gone into the house of the Pharisee He reclined, <verse eid="LUK 7:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 7:37"/>and behold, a woman in the city, who was a sinner, having known that He reclines in the house of the Pharisee, having provided an alabaster box of ointment, <verse eid="LUK 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 7:38"/>and having stood behind, beside His feet, weeping, she began to wet His feet with the tears, and with the hairs of her head she was wiping, and was kissing His feet, and was anointing with the ointment. <verse eid="LUK 7:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 7:39"/>And the Pharisee who called Him, having seen, spoke within himself, saying, “This One, if He were a prophet, would have known who and of what kind [is] the woman who touches Him, that she is a sinner.” <verse eid="LUK 7:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 7:40"/>And Jesus answering said to him, “Simon, I have something to say to you”; and he says, “Teacher, say on.” <verse eid="LUK 7:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 7:41"/>“Two debtors were to a certain creditor; one was owing five hundred denarii, and the other fifty; <verse eid="LUK 7:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 7:42"/>and they not having [with which] to give back, he forgave both; which of them then, do you say, will love him more?” <verse eid="LUK 7:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 7:43"/>And Simon answering said, “I suppose that to whom he forgave the more”; and He said to him, “You judged correctly.” <verse eid="LUK 7:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 7:44"/>And having turned to the woman, He said to Simon, “See this woman? I entered into your house; you did not give water for My feet, but this woman wet My feet with tears, and wiped with the hairs of her head; <verse eid="LUK 7:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 7:45"/>you did not give a kiss to Me, but this woman, from what [time] I came in, did not cease kissing My feet; <verse eid="LUK 7:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 7:46"/>you did not anoint My head with oil, but this woman anointed My feet with oil; <verse eid="LUK 7:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 7:47"/>therefore I say to you, her many sins have been forgiven, because she loved much; but to whom is forgiven little, loves little.” <verse eid="LUK 7:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 7:48"/>And He said to her, “Your sins have been forgiven”; <verse eid="LUK 7:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 7:49"/>and those dining with Him began to say within themselves, “Who is this, who also forgives sins?” <verse eid="LUK 7:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 7:50"/>And He said to the woman, “Your faith has saved you, be going on to peace.”<verse eid="LUK 7:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="LUK 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 8:1"/>And it came to pass thereafter, that He was going through every city and village, preaching and proclaiming good news of the Kingdom of God, and the Twelve [are] with Him, <verse eid="LUK 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 8:2"/>and certain women who were healed of evil spirits and sicknesses, Mary who is called Magdalene, from whom seven demons had gone forth, <verse eid="LUK 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 8:3"/>and Joanna wife of Chuza, steward of Herod, and Susanna, and many others, who were ministering to Him from their substance. <verse eid="LUK 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 8:4"/>And a great multitude having gathered, and those who from city and city were coming to Him, He spoke by an allegory: <verse eid="LUK 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 8:5"/>“The sower went forth to sow his seed, and in his sowing some indeed fell beside the way, and it was trodden down, and the birds of the sky devoured it. <verse eid="LUK 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 8:6"/>And other fell on the rock, and having sprung up, it withered, through having no moisture. <verse eid="LUK 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 8:7"/>And other fell amidst the thorns, and the thorns having sprung up with it, choked it. <verse eid="LUK 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 8:8"/>And other fell on the good ground, and having sprung up, it made fruit a hundredfold.” Saying these things, He was calling, “He having ears to hear—let him hear.” <verse eid="LUK 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 8:9"/>And His disciples were questioning Him, saying, “What may this allegory be?” <verse eid="LUK 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 8:10"/>And He said, “To you it has been given to know the secrets of the Kingdom of God, but to the rest in allegories, that seeing they may not see, and hearing they may not understand. <verse eid="LUK 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 8:11"/>And this is the allegory: the seed is the word of God, <verse eid="LUK 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 8:12"/>and those beside the way are those hearing, then comes the Devil, and takes up the word from their heart, lest having believed, they may be saved. <verse eid="LUK 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 8:13"/>And those on the rock: they who, when they may hear, receive the word with joy, and these have no root, who for a time believe, and in time of temptation fall away. <verse eid="LUK 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 8:14"/>And that which fell to the thorns: these are they who have heard, and going forth, through anxieties, and riches, and pleasures of life, are choked, and do not bear to completion. <verse eid="LUK 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 8:15"/>And that in the good ground: these are they who in an upright and good heart, having heard the word, retain [it], and bear fruit in continuance. <verse eid="LUK 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 8:16"/>And no one having lighted a lamp covers it with a vessel, or puts [it] under a bed; but he puts [it] on a lampstand, that those coming in may see the light, <verse eid="LUK 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 8:17"/>for nothing is secret, that will not become visible, nor hid, that will not be known and become visible. <verse eid="LUK 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 8:18"/>See, therefore, how you hear, for whoever may have, there will be given to him, and whoever may not have, also what he seems to have will be taken from him.” <verse eid="LUK 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 8:19"/>And there came to Him His mother and brothers, and they were not able to get to Him because of the multitude, <verse eid="LUK 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 8:20"/>and it was told Him, saying, “Your mother and Your brothers stand outside, wishing to see You”; <verse eid="LUK 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 8:21"/>and He answering said to them, “My mother and My brothers! They are those who are hearing the word of God, and doing.” <verse eid="LUK 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 8:22"/>And it came to pass, on one of the days, that He Himself went into a boat with His disciples, and He said to them, “We may go over to the other side of the lake”; and they set forth, <verse eid="LUK 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 8:23"/>and as they are sailing He fell deeply asleep, and there came down a storm of wind to the lake, and they were filling, and were in peril. <verse eid="LUK 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 8:24"/>And having come near, they awoke Him, saying, “Master, Master, we perish!” And He, having arisen, rebuked the wind and the raging of the water, and they ceased, and there came a calm, <verse eid="LUK 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 8:25"/>and He said to them, “Where is your faith?” And they being afraid wondered, saying to one another, “Who, then, is this, that He even commands the winds and the water, and they obey Him?” <verse eid="LUK 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 8:26"/>And they sailed down to the region of the Gadarenes that is opposite Galilee, <verse eid="LUK 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 8:27"/>and He having gone forth on the land, there met Him a certain man, out of the city, who had demons for a long time, and was not clothed with a garment, and was not abiding in a house, but in the tombs, <verse eid="LUK 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 8:28"/>and having seen Jesus, and having cried out, he fell before Him, and with a loud voice, said, “What [regards] me and You, Jesus, Son of God Most High? I implore You, may You not afflict me!” <verse eid="LUK 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 8:29"/>For He commanded the unclean spirit to come forth from the man, for many times it had caught him, and he was being bound with chains and shackles—guarded, and breaking apart the bonds he was driven by the demons into the deserts. <verse eid="LUK 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 8:30"/>And Jesus questioned him, saying, “What is your name?” And he said, “Legion,” because many demons were entered into him, <verse eid="LUK 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 8:31"/>and he was calling on Him that He may not command them to go away into the abyss, <verse eid="LUK 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 8:32"/>and there was there a herd of many pigs feeding on the mountain, and they were calling on Him that He might permit them to enter into these, and He permitted them, <verse eid="LUK 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 8:33"/>and the demons having gone forth from the man, entered into the pigs, and the herd rushed down the steep into the lake, and were drowned. <verse eid="LUK 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 8:34"/>And those feeding [them], having seen what was come to pass, fled, and having gone, told [it] to the city, and to the fields; <verse eid="LUK 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 8:35"/>and they came forth to see what was come to pass, and they came to Jesus, and found the man sitting, out of whom the demons had gone forth, clothed, and right-minded, at the feet of Jesus, and they were afraid; <verse eid="LUK 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 8:36"/>and those also having seen [it], told them how the demoniac was saved. <verse eid="LUK 8:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 8:37"/>And the whole multitude of the region of the Gadarenes asked Him to go away from them, because they were pressed with great fear, and He having entered into the boat, turned back. <verse eid="LUK 8:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 8:38"/>And the man from whom the demons had gone forth was imploring of Him to be with Him, and Jesus sent him away, saying, <verse eid="LUK 8:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 8:39"/>“Return to your house, and tell how God did great things to you”; and he went away through all the city proclaiming how Jesus did great things to him. <verse eid="LUK 8:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 8:40"/>And it came to pass, in the turning back of Jesus, the multitude received Him, for they were all looking for Him, <verse eid="LUK 8:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 8:41"/>and behold, there came a man whose name [is] Jairus, and he was a chief of the synagogue, and having fallen at the feet of Jesus, was calling on Him to come to his house, <verse eid="LUK 8:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 8:42"/>because he had an only daughter about twelve years [old], and she was dying. And in His going away, the multitudes were thronging Him, <verse eid="LUK 8:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 8:43"/>and a woman, being with a flow of blood for twelve years, who, having spent all her living on physicians, was not able to be healed by any, <verse eid="LUK 8:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 8:44"/>having come near behind, touched the fringe of His garment, and immediately the flow of her blood stood still. <verse eid="LUK 8:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 8:45"/>And Jesus said, “Who [is] it that touched Me?” And all denying, Peter and those with him said, “Master, the multitudes press You, and throng [You], and You say, Who [is] it that touched Me?” <verse eid="LUK 8:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 8:46"/>And Jesus said, “Someone touched Me, for I knew power having gone forth from Me.” <verse eid="LUK 8:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 8:47"/>And the woman, having seen that she was not hid, trembling, came, and having fallen before Him, for what cause she touched Him declared to Him before all the people, and how she was healed instantly; <verse eid="LUK 8:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 8:48"/>and He said to her, “Take courage, daughter, your faith has saved you, be going on to peace.” <verse eid="LUK 8:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 8:49"/>While He is yet speaking, there comes a certain one from the chief of the synagogue’s [house], saying to him, “Your daughter has died, do not harass the Teacher”; <verse eid="LUK 8:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 8:50"/>and Jesus having heard, answered him, saying, “Do not be afraid, only believe, and she will be saved.” <verse eid="LUK 8:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 8:51"/>And having come into the house, He permitted no one to go in, except Peter, and James, and John, and the father of the child, and the mother; <verse eid="LUK 8:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 8:52"/>and they were all weeping, and beating themselves for her, and He said, “Do not weep, she did not die, but sleeps”; <verse eid="LUK 8:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 8:53"/>and they were deriding Him, knowing that she died; <verse eid="LUK 8:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 8:54"/>and He having put all forth outside, and having taken hold of her hand, called, saying, “Child, arise”; <verse eid="LUK 8:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 8:55"/>and her spirit came back, and she arose immediately, and He directed that there be given to her to eat; <verse eid="LUK 8:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 8:56"/>and her parents were amazed, but He charged them to say to no one what had come to pass.<verse eid="LUK 8:56"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="LUK 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 9:1"/>And having called together His twelve disciples, He gave them power and authority over all the demons, and to cure diseases, <verse eid="LUK 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 9:2"/>and He sent them to proclaim the Kingdom of God, and to heal the ailing. <verse eid="LUK 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 9:3"/>And He said to them, “Take nothing for the way, neither staff, nor leather pouch, nor bread, nor money; neither have two coats each; <verse eid="LUK 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 9:4"/>and into whatever house you may enter, remain there, and depart from there; <verse eid="LUK 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 9:5"/>and as many as may not receive you, going forth from that city, even the dust from your feet shake off, for a testimony against them.” <verse eid="LUK 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 9:6"/>And going forth they were going through the several villages, proclaiming good news, and healing everywhere. <verse eid="LUK 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 9:7"/>And Herod the tetrarch heard of all the things being done by Him, and was perplexed, because it was said by some that John has been raised out of the dead, <verse eid="LUK 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 9:8"/>and by some that Elijah appeared, and by others, that a prophet, one of the ancients, was risen; <verse eid="LUK 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 9:9"/>and Herod said, “I beheaded John, but who is this concerning whom I hear such things?” And he was seeking to see Him. <verse eid="LUK 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 9:10"/>And the apostles having turned back, declared to Him how they did great things, and having taken them, He withdrew by Himself into a city called Bethsaida, <verse eid="LUK 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 9:11"/>and the multitudes having known followed Him, and having received them, He was speaking to them concerning the Kingdom of God, and He cured those having need of service. <verse eid="LUK 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 9:12"/>And the day began to decline, and the Twelve having come near, said to Him, “Let away the multitude, that having gone into the surrounding villages and the fields, they may lodge and may find provision, because here we are in a desolate place.” <verse eid="LUK 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 9:13"/>And He said to them, “You give them to eat”; and they said, “We have no more than five loaves and two fishes: except, having gone, we may buy food for all this people”; <verse eid="LUK 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 9:14"/>for they were about five thousand men. And He said to His disciples, “Cause them to recline in companies, in each fifty”; <verse eid="LUK 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 9:15"/>and they did so, and made all to recline; <verse eid="LUK 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 9:16"/>and having taken the five loaves and the two fishes, having looked up to the sky, He blessed them, and broke, and was giving to the disciples to set before the multitude; <verse eid="LUK 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 9:17"/>and they ate, and were all filled, and there was taken up what was over to them of broken pieces, twelve baskets. <verse eid="LUK 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 9:18"/>And it came to pass, as He is praying alone, the disciples were with Him, and He questioned them, saying, “Who do the multitudes say I am?” <verse eid="LUK 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 9:19"/>And they answering said, “John the Immerser; and others, Elijah; and others, that a prophet, one of the ancients, was risen”; <verse eid="LUK 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 9:20"/>and He said to them, “And you—who do you say I am?” And Peter answering said, “The Christ of God.” <verse eid="LUK 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 9:21"/>And having charged them, He commanded [them] to say this to no one, <verse eid="LUK 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 9:22"/>saying, “It is necessary for the Son of Man to suffer many things, and to be rejected by the elders, and chief priests, and scribes, and to be killed, and to be raised the third day.” <verse eid="LUK 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 9:23"/>And He said to all, “If anyone wills to come after Me, let him disown himself, and take up his cross daily, and follow Me; <verse eid="LUK 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 9:24"/>for whoever may will to save his life will lose it, and whoever may lose his life for My sake, he will save it; <verse eid="LUK 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 9:25"/>for what is a man profited, having gained the whole world, and having lost or having forfeited himself? <verse eid="LUK 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 9:26"/>For whoever may be ashamed of Me and of My words, of this one will the Son of Man be ashamed when He may come in His glory, and the Father’s, and the holy messengers’; <verse eid="LUK 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 9:27"/>and I say to you, truly, there are certain of those standing here who will not taste of death until they may see the Kingdom of God.” <verse eid="LUK 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 9:28"/>And it came to pass, after these words, as it were eight days, that having taken Peter, and John, and James, He went up to the mountain to pray, <verse eid="LUK 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 9:29"/>and it came to pass, in His praying, the appearance of His face became altered, and His clothing became flashing white. <verse eid="LUK 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 9:30"/>And behold, two men were speaking together with Him, who were Moses and Elijah, <verse eid="LUK 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 9:31"/>who having appeared in glory, spoke of His outgoing that He was about to fulfill in Jerusalem, <verse eid="LUK 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 9:32"/>but Peter and those with him were heavy with sleep, and having awoken, they saw His glory, and the two men standing with Him. <verse eid="LUK 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 9:33"/>And it came to pass, in their parting from Him, Peter said to Jesus, “Master, it is good to us to be here; and we may make three shelters: one for You, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah,” not knowing what he says: <verse eid="LUK 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 9:34"/>and as he was speaking these things, there came a cloud, and overshadowed them, and they feared in their entering into the cloud, <verse eid="LUK 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 9:35"/>and a voice came out of the cloud, saying, “This is My Son, the Beloved; hear Him”; <verse eid="LUK 9:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 9:36"/>and when the voice was past, Jesus was found alone; and they were silent, and declared to no one in those days anything of what they have seen. <verse eid="LUK 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 9:37"/>And it came to pass on the next day, they having come down from the mountain, a great multitude met Him there, <verse eid="LUK 9:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 9:38"/>and behold, a man from the multitude cried out, saying, “Teacher, I implore You, look on my son, because he is my only begotten; <verse eid="LUK 9:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 9:39"/>and behold, a spirit takes him, and suddenly he cries out, and it convulses him, with foaming, and it hardly departs from him, bruising him, <verse eid="LUK 9:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 9:40"/>and I implored Your disciples that they might cast it out, and they were not able.” <verse eid="LUK 9:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 9:41"/>And Jesus answering said, “O generation, unsteadfast and perverse, until when will I be with you, and endure you? Bring your son near here”; <verse eid="LUK 9:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 9:42"/>and as he is yet coming near, the demon threw him down, and convulsed [him], and Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit, and healed the youth, and gave him back to his father. <verse eid="LUK 9:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 9:43"/>And they were all amazed at the greatness of God, and while all are wondering at all things that Jesus did, He said to His disciples, <verse eid="LUK 9:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 9:44"/>“Lay to your ears these words, for the Son of Man is about to be delivered up into the hands of men.” <verse eid="LUK 9:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 9:45"/>And they were not knowing this saying, and it was veiled from them, that they might not perceive it, and they were afraid to ask Him about this saying. <verse eid="LUK 9:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 9:46"/>And there entered a reasoning among them, this—who may be greater of them. <verse eid="LUK 9:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 9:47"/>And Jesus having seen the reasoning of their heart, having taken hold of a child, set him beside Him, <verse eid="LUK 9:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 9:48"/>and said to them, “Whoever may receive this child in My Name, receives Me, and whoever may receive Me, receives Him who sent Me, for he who is least among you all—he will be great.” <verse eid="LUK 9:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 9:49"/>And John answering said, “Master, we saw a certain one casting forth the demons in Your Name, and we forbade him, because he does not follow with us”; <verse eid="LUK 9:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 9:50"/>and Jesus said to him, “Do not forbid, for he who is not against us, is for us.” <verse eid="LUK 9:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 9:51"/>And it came to pass, in the completing of the days of His being taken up, that He fixed His face to go on to Jerusalem, <verse eid="LUK 9:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 9:52"/>and He sent messengers before His face, and having gone on, they went into a village of Samaritans, to make ready for Him, <verse eid="LUK 9:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 9:53"/>and they did not receive Him, because His face was going on to Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 9:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 9:54"/>And His disciples James and John having seen, said, “Lord, will You [that] we may command fire to come down from Heaven, and to consume them, as Elijah also did?” <verse eid="LUK 9:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 9:55"/>And having turned, He rebuked them and said, “You have not known of what spirit you are, <verse eid="LUK 9:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 9:56"/>for the Son of Man did not come to destroy men’s lives, but to save”; and they went on to another village. <verse eid="LUK 9:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LUK 9:57"/>And it came to pass, as they are going on in the way, a certain one said to Him, “I will follow You wherever You may go, Lord”; <verse eid="LUK 9:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LUK 9:58"/>and Jesus said to him, “The foxes have holes, and the birds of the sky places of rest, but the Son of Man has nowhere He may recline the head.” <verse eid="LUK 9:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="LUK 9:59"/>And He said to another, “Follow Me”; and he said, “Lord, permit me, having gone away, to first bury my father”; <verse eid="LUK 9:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="LUK 9:60"/>and Jesus said to him, “Permit the dead to bury their own dead, and you, having gone away, publish the Kingdom of God.” <verse eid="LUK 9:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="LUK 9:61"/>And another also said, “I will follow You, Lord, but first permit me to take leave of those in my house”; <verse eid="LUK 9:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="LUK 9:62"/>and Jesus said to him, “No one having put his hand on a plow, and looking back, is fit for the Kingdom of God.”<verse eid="LUK 9:62"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="LUK 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 10:1"/>And after these things, the LORD also appointed seventy others, and sent them by twos before His face, to every city and place to where He Himself was about to come, <verse eid="LUK 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 10:2"/>then He said to them, “The harvest [is] indeed abundant, but the workmen few; implore then the Lord of the harvest, that He may put forth workmen to His harvest. <verse eid="LUK 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 10:3"/>Go away; behold, I send you forth as lambs in the midst of wolves; <verse eid="LUK 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 10:4"/>carry no bag, no leather pouch, nor sandals; and greet no one on the way; <verse eid="LUK 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 10:5"/>and into whatever house you enter, first say, Peace to this house; <verse eid="LUK 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 10:6"/>and if indeed there may be there the son of peace, your peace will rest on it; and if not so, it will turn back on you. <verse eid="LUK 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 10:7"/>And remain in that house, eating and drinking the things they have, for worthy [is] the workman of his hire; do not go from house to house, <verse eid="LUK 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 10:8"/>and into whatever city you enter, and they may receive you, eat the things set before you, <verse eid="LUK 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 10:9"/>and heal the ailing in it, and say to them, The Kingdom of God has come near to you. <verse eid="LUK 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 10:10"/>And into whatever city you enter, and they may not receive you, having gone forth to its broad places, say, <verse eid="LUK 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 10:11"/>And the dust that has cleaved to us from your city, we wipe off against you, but know this, that the Kingdom of God has come near to you; <verse eid="LUK 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 10:12"/>and I say to you that it will be more tolerable for Sodom in that day than for that city. <verse eid="LUK 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 10:13"/>Woe to you, Chorazin; woe to you, Bethsaida; for if the mighty works that were done in you had been done in Tyre and Sidon, they had converted long ago, sitting in sackcloth and ashes; <verse eid="LUK 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 10:14"/>but it will be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon in the judgment than for you. <verse eid="LUK 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 10:15"/>And you, Capernaum, which were exalted to Heaven, you will be brought down to Hades. <verse eid="LUK 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 10:16"/>He who is hearing you, hears Me; and he who is putting you away, puts Me away; and he who is putting Me away, puts away Him who sent Me.” <verse eid="LUK 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 10:17"/>And the seventy turned back with joy, saying, “Lord, and the demons are being subjected to us in Your Name”; <verse eid="LUK 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 10:18"/>and He said to them, “I was beholding Satan having fallen as lightning from Heaven; <verse eid="LUK 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 10:19"/>behold, I give to you the authority to tread on serpents and scorpions, and on all the power of the enemy, and nothing by any means will hurt you; <verse eid="LUK 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 10:20"/>but do not rejoice in this, that the spirits are subjected to you, but rejoice rather that your names were written in the heavens.” <verse eid="LUK 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 10:21"/>In that hour Jesus was glad in the Spirit and said, “I confess to You, Father, Lord of Heaven and of earth, that You hid these things from wise men and understanding, and revealed them to babies; yes, Father, because so it became good pleasure before You. <verse eid="LUK 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 10:22"/>All things were delivered up to Me by My Father, and no one knows who the Son is, except the Father, and who the Father is, except the Son, and he to whom the Son may resolve to reveal [Him].” <verse eid="LUK 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 10:23"/>And having turned to the disciples, He said, by themselves, “Blessed the eyes that are perceiving what you perceive; <verse eid="LUK 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 10:24"/>for I say to you that many prophets and kings wished to see what you perceive, and did not see, and to hear what you hear, and did not hear.” <verse eid="LUK 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 10:25"/>And behold, a certain lawyer stood up, trying Him, and saying, “Teacher, what having done, will I inherit continuous life?” <verse eid="LUK 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 10:26"/>And He said to him, “In the Law what has been written? How do you read [it]?” <verse eid="LUK 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 10:27"/>And he answering said, “You will love the LORD your God out of all your heart, and out of all your soul, and out of all your strength, and out of all your understanding, and your neighbor as yourself.” <verse eid="LUK 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 10:28"/>And He said to him, “You answered correctly; do this, and you will live.” <verse eid="LUK 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 10:29"/>And he, willing to declare himself righteous, said to Jesus, “And who is my neighbor?” <verse eid="LUK 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 10:30"/>And Jesus having taken up [the word], said, “A certain man was going down from Jerusalem to Jericho, and fell among robbers, and having stripped him and inflicted blows, they went away, leaving [him] half dead. <verse eid="LUK 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 10:31"/>And by a coincidence a certain priest was going down in that way, and having seen him, he passed over on the opposite side; <verse eid="LUK 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 10:32"/>and in like manner also, a Levite, having been around the place, having come and seen, passed over on the opposite side. <verse eid="LUK 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 10:33"/>But a certain Samaritan, journeying, came along him, and having seen him, he was moved with compassion, <verse eid="LUK 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 10:34"/>and having come near, he bound up his wounds, pouring on oil and wine, and having lifted him up on his own beast, he brought him to an inn, and was careful of him; <verse eid="LUK 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 10:35"/>and on the next day, going forth, taking out two denarii, he gave to the innkeeper and said to him, Be careful of him, and whatever you may spend more, I, in my coming again, will give back to you. <verse eid="LUK 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 10:36"/>Who, then, of these three, seems to you to have become neighbor of him who fell among the robbers?” <verse eid="LUK 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 10:37"/>And he said, “He who did the kindness with him,” then Jesus said to him, “Be going on, and you be doing in like manner.” <verse eid="LUK 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 10:38"/>And it came to pass, in their going on, that He entered into a certain village, and a certain woman, by name Martha, received Him into her house, <verse eid="LUK 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 10:39"/>and she also had a sister, called Mary, who also, having seated herself beside the feet of Jesus, was hearing the word, <verse eid="LUK 10:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 10:40"/>and Martha was distracted about much serving, and having stood by Him, she said, “Lord, do You not care that my sister left me alone to serve? Say then to her that she may partake along with me.” <verse eid="LUK 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 10:41"/>And Jesus answering said to her, “Martha, Martha, you are anxious and disquieted about many things, <verse eid="LUK 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 10:42"/>but of one thing there is need, and Mary chose the good part; that will not be taken away from her.”<verse eid="LUK 10:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="LUK 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 11:1"/>And it came to pass, in His being in a certain place praying, as He ceased, a certain one of His disciples said to Him, “Lord, teach us to pray, as also John taught his disciples.” <verse eid="LUK 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 11:2"/>And He said to them, “When you may pray, say: Our Father who is in the heavens, hallowed be Your Name; Your kingdom come, Your will come to pass, as in Heaven also on earth; <verse eid="LUK 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 11:3"/>be giving us daily our appointed bread; <verse eid="LUK 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 11:4"/>and forgive us our sins, for we also ourselves forgive everyone indebted to us; and may You not bring us into temptation, but deliver us from the evil [one].” <verse eid="LUK 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 11:5"/>And He said to them, “Who of you will have a friend, and will go on to him at midnight, and may say to him, Friend, lend me three loaves, <verse eid="LUK 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 11:6"/>seeing a friend of mine came out of the way to me, and I have not what I will set before him, <verse eid="LUK 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 11:7"/>and he from within answering may say, Do not give me trouble, the door has already been shut, and my children are with me in the bed, I am not able, having risen, to give to you. <verse eid="LUK 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 11:8"/>I say to you, even if he will not give to him, having risen, because of his being his friend, yet because of his persistence, having risen, he will give him as many as he needs; <verse eid="LUK 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 11:9"/>and I say to you, ask, and it will be given to you; seek, and you will find; knock, and it will be opened to you; <verse eid="LUK 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 11:10"/>for everyone who is asking receives; and he who is seeking finds; and to him who is knocking it will be opened. <verse eid="LUK 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 11:11"/>And of which of you—the father—[if] the son will ask [for] a loaf, will present to him a stone? And [if] a fish, instead of a fish, will present to him a serpent? <verse eid="LUK 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 11:12"/>And [if] he may ask [for] an egg, will present to him a scorpion? <verse eid="LUK 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 11:13"/>If, then, you, being evil, have known to be giving good gifts to your children, how much more will the Father who is from Heaven give the Holy Spirit to those asking Him!” <verse eid="LUK 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 11:14"/>And He was casting forth a demon, and it was mute, and it came to pass, the demon having gone forth, the mute man spoke, and the multitudes wondered, <verse eid="LUK 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 11:15"/>and certain of them said, “By Beelzebul, ruler of the demons, He casts forth the demons”; <verse eid="LUK 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 11:16"/>and others, tempting, were asking [for] a sign out of Heaven from Him. <verse eid="LUK 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 11:17"/>And He, knowing their thoughts, said to them, “Every kingdom having been divided against itself is desolated; and house against house falls; <verse eid="LUK 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 11:18"/>and if Satan was also divided against himself, how will his kingdom be made to stand? For you say by Beelzebul is My casting forth the demons, <verse eid="LUK 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 11:19"/>but if I, by Beelzebul, cast forth the demons—your sons, by whom do they cast forth? Because of this they will be your judges; <verse eid="LUK 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 11:20"/>but if by the finger of God I cast forth the demons, then the Kingdom of God came unaware on you. <verse eid="LUK 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 11:21"/>When the strong man may keep his hall armed, his goods are in peace; <verse eid="LUK 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 11:22"/>but when the stronger than he, having come on [him], may overcome him, he takes away his whole armor in which he had trusted, and he distributes his spoils; <verse eid="LUK 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 11:23"/>he who is not with Me is against Me, and he who is not gathering with Me scatters. <verse eid="LUK 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 11:24"/>When the unclean spirit may go forth from the man, it walks through waterless places seeking rest, and not finding, it says, I will return to my house from where I came forth; <verse eid="LUK 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 11:25"/>and having come, it finds [it] swept and adorned; <verse eid="LUK 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 11:26"/>then it goes, and takes to it seven other spirits more evil than itself, and having entered, they dwell there, and the last of that man becomes worse than the first.” <verse eid="LUK 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 11:27"/>And it came to pass, in His saying these things, a certain woman having lifted up the voice out of the multitude, said to Him, “Blessed the womb that carried You, and the breasts that You sucked!” <verse eid="LUK 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 11:28"/>And He said, “Indeed, rather, blessed those hearing the word of God, and keeping [it]!” <verse eid="LUK 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 11:29"/>And the multitudes crowding together on Him, He began to say, “This generation is evil, it seeks after a sign, and a sign will not be given to it, except the sign of Jonah the prophet, <verse eid="LUK 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 11:30"/>for as Jonah became a sign to the Ninevites, so also will the Son of Man be to this generation. <verse eid="LUK 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 11:31"/>A queen of the south will rise up in the judgment with the men of this generation, and will condemn them, because she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and behold, [One] greater than Solomon [is] here! <verse eid="LUK 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 11:32"/>Men of Nineveh will stand up in the judgment with this generation, and will condemn it, because they converted at the proclamation of Jonah; and behold, [One] greater than Jonah [is] here! <verse eid="LUK 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 11:33"/>And no one having lighted a lamp, puts [it] in a secret place, nor under the measure, but on the lampstand, that those coming in may behold the light. <verse eid="LUK 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 11:34"/>The lamp of the body is the eye, when then your eye may be simple, your whole body is also lightened; and when it may be evil, your body is also darkened; <verse eid="LUK 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 11:35"/>take heed, then, lest the light that [is] in you is darkness; <verse eid="LUK 11:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 11:36"/>if then your whole body is lightened, not having any part darkened, the whole will be lightened, as when the lamp by the brightness may give you light.” <verse eid="LUK 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 11:37"/>And in [His] speaking, a certain Pharisee was asking Him that He might dine with him, and having gone in, He reclined, <verse eid="LUK 11:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 11:38"/>and the Pharisee having seen, wondered that He did not first immerse Himself before the early meal. <verse eid="LUK 11:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 11:39"/>And the LORD said to him, “Now you, the Pharisees, make the outside of the cup and of the plate clean, but your inward part is full of robbery and wickedness. <verse eid="LUK 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 11:40"/>Unthinking [ones]! Did He who made the outside not also make the inside? <verse eid="LUK 11:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 11:41"/>But what you have given [as] alms, and behold, all things are clean to you. <verse eid="LUK 11:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 11:42"/>But woe to you, the Pharisees, because you tithe the mint, and the rue, and every herb, and you pass by the judgment and the love of God; these things [you] should do, and those not to be neglecting. <verse eid="LUK 11:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 11:43"/>Woe to you, the Pharisees, because you love the first seats in the synagogues and the salutations in the marketplaces. <verse eid="LUK 11:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 11:44"/>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, because you are as the unseen tombs, and the men walking above have not known.” <verse eid="LUK 11:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 11:45"/>And one of the lawyers answering, says to Him, “Teacher, saying these things, You also insult us”; <verse eid="LUK 11:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 11:46"/>and He said, “And to you, the lawyers, woe! Because you burden men with burdens [too] grievous to bear, and you yourselves do not touch the burdens with one of your fingers. <verse eid="LUK 11:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 11:47"/>Woe to you, because you build the tombs of the prophets, and your fathers killed them. <verse eid="LUK 11:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 11:48"/>Then you testify, and are well pleased with the works of your fathers, because they indeed killed them, and you build their tombs; <verse eid="LUK 11:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 11:49"/>because of this also the wisdom of God said: I will send to them prophets, and apostles, and some of them they will kill and persecute, <verse eid="LUK 11:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 11:50"/>that the blood of all the prophets, that is being poured forth from the foundation of the world, may be required from this generation— <verse eid="LUK 11:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 11:51"/>from the blood of Abel to the blood of Zacharias, who perished between the altar and the house; yes, I say to you, it will be required from this generation. <verse eid="LUK 11:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 11:52"/>Woe to you, the lawyers, because you took away the key of the knowledge; you yourselves did not enter; and you hindered those coming in.” <verse eid="LUK 11:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 11:53"/>And in His speaking these things to them, the scribes and the Pharisees began fearfully to urge and to press Him to speak about many things, <verse eid="LUK 11:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 11:54"/>laying wait for Him, and seeking to catch something out of His mouth, that they might accuse Him.<verse eid="LUK 11:54"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="LUK 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 12:1"/>At which time the myriads of the multitude having been gathered together, so as to tread on one another, He began to say to His disciples, first, “Take heed to yourselves of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy; <verse eid="LUK 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 12:2"/>and there is nothing covered that will not be revealed, and hid that will not be known; <verse eid="LUK 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 12:3"/>because whatever you said in the darkness will be heard in the light, and what you spoke to the ear in the inner-chambers will be proclaimed on the housetops. <verse eid="LUK 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 12:4"/>And I say to you, my friends, do not be afraid of those killing the body, and after these things are not having anything more to do; <verse eid="LUK 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 12:5"/>but I will show to you whom you may fear: fear Him who, after the killing, is having authority to cast into Gehenna; yes, I say to you, fear Him. <verse eid="LUK 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 12:6"/>Are not five sparrows sold for two assaria? And one of them is not forgotten before God, <verse eid="LUK 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 12:7"/>but even the hairs of your head have all been numbered; therefore do not fear, you are of more value than many sparrows. <verse eid="LUK 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 12:8"/>And I say to you, everyone who may confess in Me before men, the Son of Man will also confess in him before the messengers of God, <verse eid="LUK 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 12:9"/>and he who has denied Me before men, will be denied before the messengers of God, <verse eid="LUK 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 12:10"/>and everyone who will say a word to the Son of Man, it will be forgiven to him, but the [one] having slandered to the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven. <verse eid="LUK 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 12:11"/>And when they bring you before the synagogues, and the rulers, and the authorities, do not be anxious how or what you may reply, or what you may say, <verse eid="LUK 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 12:12"/>for the Holy Spirit will teach you in that hour what [you] should say.” <verse eid="LUK 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 12:13"/>And a certain one out of the multitude said to Him, “Teacher, say to my brother to divide with me the inheritance.” <verse eid="LUK 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 12:14"/>And He said to him, “Man, who set Me a judge or a divider over you?” <verse eid="LUK 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 12:15"/>And He said to them, “Observe, and beware of the covetousness, because his life is not in the abundance of one’s goods.” <verse eid="LUK 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 12:16"/>And He spoke an allegory to them, saying, “Of a certain rich man the field brought forth well; <verse eid="LUK 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 12:17"/>and he was reasoning within himself, saying, What will I do, because I have nowhere I will gather together my fruits? <verse eid="LUK 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 12:18"/>And he said, This I will do, I will take down my storehouses, and I will build greater ones, and I will gather together there all my products and my good things, <verse eid="LUK 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 12:19"/>and I will say to my soul, Soul, you have many good things laid up for many years, be resting, eat, drink, be merry. <verse eid="LUK 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 12:20"/>And God said to him, Unthinking [one]! This night your life is required of you, and what things you prepared—to whom will they be [given]? <verse eid="LUK 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 12:21"/>So [is] he who is treasuring up to himself, and is not rich toward God.” <verse eid="LUK 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 12:22"/>And He said to His disciples, “Because of this, to you I say, do not be anxious for your life, what you may eat; nor for the body, what you may put on; <verse eid="LUK 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 12:23"/>life is more than nourishment, and the body than clothing. <verse eid="LUK 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 12:24"/>Consider the ravens, that they do not sow, nor reap, to which there is no barn nor storehouse, and God nourishes them; how much better are you than the birds? <verse eid="LUK 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 12:25"/>And who of you, being anxious, is able to add to his age one cubit? <verse eid="LUK 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 12:26"/>If, then, you are not able for the least—why are you anxious for the rest? <verse eid="LUK 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 12:27"/>Consider the lilies, how do they grow? They do not labor, nor do they spin, and I say to you, not even Solomon in all his glory was clothed as one of these; <verse eid="LUK 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 12:28"/>and if the herbage in the field, that today is, and tomorrow is cast into an oven, God so clothes, how much more you of little faith? <verse eid="LUK 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 12:29"/>And you—do not seek what you may eat, or what you may drink, and do not be in suspense, <verse eid="LUK 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 12:30"/>for the nations of the world seek after all these things, and your Father has known that you have need of these things; <verse eid="LUK 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 12:31"/>but seek the Kingdom of God, and all these things will be added to you. <verse eid="LUK 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 12:32"/>Do not fear, little flock, because your Father delighted to give you the kingdom; <verse eid="LUK 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 12:33"/>sell your goods, and give alms, make to yourselves bags that do not become old, a treasure unfailing in the heavens, where thief does not come near, nor moth destroy; <verse eid="LUK 12:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 12:34"/>for where your treasure is, there your heart will be also. <verse eid="LUK 12:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 12:35"/>Let your loins be girded, and the lamps burning, <verse eid="LUK 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 12:36"/>and you [be] like to men waiting for their lord when he will return out of the wedding feasts, that he having come and knocked, immediately they may open to him. <verse eid="LUK 12:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 12:37"/>Blessed those servants, whom the lord, having come, will find watching; truly I say to you that he will gird himself, and will cause them to recline, and having come near, will minister to them; <verse eid="LUK 12:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 12:38"/>and if he may come in the second watch, and in the third watch he may come, and may find [it] so, blessed are those servants. <verse eid="LUK 12:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 12:39"/>And know this, that if the master of the house had known what hour the thief comes, he would have watched, and would not have permitted his house to be broken through; <verse eid="LUK 12:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 12:40"/>and you, then, become ready, because at the hour you do not think, the Son of Man comes.” <verse eid="LUK 12:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 12:41"/>And Peter said to Him, “Lord, do You speak this allegory to us, or also to all?” <verse eid="LUK 12:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 12:42"/>And the LORD said, “Who, then, is the faithful and prudent steward whom the lord will set over his household, to give in season the wheat measure? <verse eid="LUK 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 12:43"/>Blessed that servant, whom his lord, having come, will find doing so; <verse eid="LUK 12:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 12:44"/>truly I say to you that he will set him over all his goods. <verse eid="LUK 12:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 12:45"/>And if that servant may say in his heart, My lord delays to come, and may begin to beat the menservants and the maidservants, to eat also, and to drink, and to be drunken, <verse eid="LUK 12:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 12:46"/>the lord of that servant will come in a day in which he does not look for [him], and in an hour that he does not know, and will cut him off, and he will appoint his portion with the unfaithful. <verse eid="LUK 12:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 12:47"/>And that servant, who having known his lord’s will, and having not prepared, nor having gone according to his will, will be beaten with many stripes, <verse eid="LUK 12:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 12:48"/>and he who, not having known, and having done things worthy of stripes, will be beaten with few; and to everyone to whom much was given, much will be required from him; and to whom they committed much, more abundantly they will ask of him. <verse eid="LUK 12:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 12:49"/>I came to cast fire to the earth, and what I wish [is] if it were already kindled! <verse eid="LUK 12:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 12:50"/>But I have an immersion to be immersed with, and how I am pressed until it may be accomplished! <verse eid="LUK 12:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 12:51"/>Do you think that I came to give peace in the earth? No, I say to you, but rather division; <verse eid="LUK 12:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 12:52"/>for there will be from now on five in one house divided—three against two, and two against three; <verse eid="LUK 12:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 12:53"/>a father will be divided against a son, and a son against a father, a mother against a daughter, and a daughter against a mother, a mother-in-law against her daughter-in-law, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law.” <verse eid="LUK 12:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 12:54"/>And He also said to the multitudes, “When you may see the cloud rising from the west, immediately you say, A shower comes, and it is so; <verse eid="LUK 12:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 12:55"/>and when a south wind is blowing, you say that there will be heat, and it is; <verse eid="LUK 12:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 12:56"/>hypocrites! You have known to discern the face of the earth and of the sky, but how do you not discern this time? <verse eid="LUK 12:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LUK 12:57"/>And why, also, of yourselves, do you not judge what is righteous? <verse eid="LUK 12:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LUK 12:58"/>For as you are going away with your opponent to the ruler, in the way give diligence to be released from him, lest he may drag you to the judge, and the judge may deliver you to the officer, and the officer may cast you into prison; <verse eid="LUK 12:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="LUK 12:59"/>I say to you, you may not come forth from there until even the last mite you may give back.”<verse eid="LUK 12:59"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="LUK 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 13:1"/>And there were some present at that time, telling Him about the Galileans, whose blood Pilate mingled with their sacrifices; <verse eid="LUK 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 13:2"/>and Jesus answering said to them, “Do you think that these Galileans became sinners beyond all the Galileans, because they have suffered such things? <verse eid="LUK 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 13:3"/>No—I say to you, but if you may not convert, even so will all you perish. <verse eid="LUK 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 13:4"/>Or those eighteen on whom the tower in Siloam fell, and killed them, do you think that these became debtors beyond all men who are dwelling in Jerusalem? <verse eid="LUK 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 13:5"/>No—I say to you, but if you may not convert, all you will perish in like manner.” <verse eid="LUK 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 13:6"/>And He spoke this allegory: “A certain one had a fig tree planted in his vineyard, and he came seeking fruit in it, and he did not find; <verse eid="LUK 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 13:7"/>and he said to the vinedresser, Behold, three years I come seeking fruit in this fig tree, and do not find [it], cut it off, why does it also render the ground useless? <verse eid="LUK 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 13:8"/>And he answering says to him, Lord, permit it also this year, until I may dig around it, and cast in dung; <verse eid="LUK 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 13:9"/>and if indeed it may bear fruit—and if not so, thereafter you will cut it off.” <verse eid="LUK 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 13:10"/>And He was teaching in one of the synagogues on the Sabbath, <verse eid="LUK 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 13:11"/>and behold, there was a woman having a spirit of disability [for] eighteen years, and she was bent together, and not able to bend back at all, <verse eid="LUK 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 13:12"/>and Jesus having seen her, called [her] near and said to her, “Woman, you have been loosed from your disability”; <verse eid="LUK 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 13:13"/>and He laid on her [His] hands, and immediately she was set upright, and was glorifying God. <verse eid="LUK 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 13:14"/>And the chief of the synagogue answering—much displeased that on the Sabbath Jesus healed—said to the multitude, “Six days there are in which it is necessary to be working; in these, then, coming, be healed, and not on the day of the Sabbath.” <verse eid="LUK 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 13:15"/>Then the LORD answered him and said, “Hypocrite, do not each of you loose his ox or donkey from the stall on the Sabbath, and having led [it] away, water [it]? <verse eid="LUK 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 13:16"/>And this one, being a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan bound eighteen years, behold, did [she] not ought to be loosed from this bond on the day of the Sabbath?” <verse eid="LUK 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 13:17"/>And He saying these things, all who were opposed to Him were being ashamed, and all the multitude were rejoicing over all the glorious things that are being done by Him. <verse eid="LUK 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 13:18"/>And He said, “To what is the Kingdom of God like? And to what will I liken it? <verse eid="LUK 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 13:19"/>It is like to a grain of mustard, which a man having taken, cast into his garden, and it increased, and came to a great tree, and the birds of the heavens rested in its branches.” <verse eid="LUK 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 13:20"/>And again He said, “To what will I liken the Kingdom of God? <verse eid="LUK 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 13:21"/>It is like leaven, which a woman, having taken, hid in three measures of meal, until all was leavened.” <verse eid="LUK 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 13:22"/>And He was going through cities and villages, teaching, and making progress toward Jerusalem; <verse eid="LUK 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 13:23"/>and a certain one said to Him, “Lord, are those saved few?” And He said to them, <verse eid="LUK 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 13:24"/>“Be striving to go in through the straight gate, because many, I say to you, will seek to go in, and will not be able; <verse eid="LUK 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 13:25"/>from the time the Master of the house may have risen up, and may have shut the door, and you may begin to stand outside, and to knock at the door, saying, Lord, Lord, open to us, and He answering will say to you, I have not known you from where you are, <verse eid="LUK 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 13:26"/>then you may begin to say, We ate before You, and drank, and You taught in our broad places; <verse eid="LUK 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 13:27"/>and He will say, I say to you, I have not known you from where you are; depart from Me, all you workers of the unrighteousness. <verse eid="LUK 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 13:28"/>There will be there the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth when you may see Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, and all the prophets, in the Kingdom of God, and yourselves being cast outside; <verse eid="LUK 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 13:29"/>and they will come from east and west, and from north and south, and will recline in the Kingdom of God, <verse eid="LUK 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 13:30"/>and behold, there are last who will be first, and there are first who will be last.” <verse eid="LUK 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 13:31"/>On that day there came near certain Pharisees, saying to Him, “Go forth, and be going on from here, for Herod wishes to kill You”; <verse eid="LUK 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 13:32"/>and He said to them, “Having gone, say to that fox, Behold, I cast forth demons, and perfect cures today and tomorrow, and the third [day] I am being perfected; <verse eid="LUK 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 13:33"/>but it is necessary for Me today, and tomorrow, and the [day] following, to go on, because it is not possible for a prophet to perish out of Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 13:34"/>Jerusalem, Jerusalem, that is killing the prophets, and stoning those sent to her, how often I willed to gather together your children, as a hen [gathers] her brood under the wings, and you did not will. <verse eid="LUK 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 13:35"/>Behold, your house is being left to you desolate, and truly I say to you, you may not see Me, until it may come when you may say, Blessed [is] He who is coming in the Name of the LORD.”<verse eid="LUK 13:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="LUK 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 14:1"/>And it came to pass, on His going into the house of a certain one of the chiefs of the Pharisees, on a Sabbath, to eat bread, that they were watching Him, <verse eid="LUK 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 14:2"/>and behold, there was a certain dropsical man before Him; <verse eid="LUK 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 14:3"/>and Jesus answering spoke to the lawyers and Pharisees, saying, “Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath?” <verse eid="LUK 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 14:4"/>And they were silent, and having taken hold of [him], He healed him, and let [him] go; <verse eid="LUK 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 14:5"/>and answering them He said, “Of which of you will a donkey or ox fall into a pit, and he will not immediately draw it up on the Sabbath day?” <verse eid="LUK 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 14:6"/>And they were not able to answer Him again to these things. <verse eid="LUK 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 14:7"/>And He spoke an allegory to those called, marking how they were choosing out the first couches, saying to them, <verse eid="LUK 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 14:8"/>“When you may be called by anyone to wedding feasts, you may not recline on the first couch, lest [one] more honorable than you may have been called by him, <verse eid="LUK 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 14:9"/>and he who called you and him having come will say to you, Give to this one [your] place, and then you may begin to occupy the last place with shame. <verse eid="LUK 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 14:10"/>But when you may be called, having gone on, recline in the last place, that when he who called you may come, he may say to you, Friend, come up higher; then you will have glory before those dining with you; <verse eid="LUK 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 14:11"/>because everyone who is exalting himself will be humbled, and he who is humbling himself will be exalted.” <verse eid="LUK 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 14:12"/>And He also said to him who called Him, “When you may make an early meal or a dinner, do not be calling your friends, nor your brothers, nor your relatives, nor rich neighbors, lest they may also call you again, and a repayment may come to you; <verse eid="LUK 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 14:13"/>but when you may make a feast, be calling poor, maimed, lame, blind, <verse eid="LUK 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 14:14"/>and you will be blessed, because they have nothing to repay you, for it will be repaid to you in the resurrection of the righteous.” <verse eid="LUK 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 14:15"/>And one of those dining with Him, having heard these things, said to Him, “Blessed [is] he who will eat bread in the Kingdom of God”; <verse eid="LUK 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 14:16"/>and He said to him, “A certain man made a great dinner, and called many, <verse eid="LUK 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 14:17"/>and he sent his servant at the hour of the dinner to say to those having been called, Be coming, because now all things are ready. <verse eid="LUK 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 14:18"/>And all began with one [voice] to excuse themselves. The first said to him, I bought a field, and I have need to go forth and see it; I beg of you, have me excused. <verse eid="LUK 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 14:19"/>And another said, I bought five yoke of oxen, and I go on to prove them; I beg of you, have me excused. <verse eid="LUK 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 14:20"/>And another said, I married a wife, and because of this I am not able to come. <verse eid="LUK 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 14:21"/>And that servant having come, told these things to his lord, then the master of the house, having been angry, said to his servant, Go forth quickly into the broad places and lanes of the city, and the poor, and maimed, and lame, and blind, bring in here. <verse eid="LUK 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 14:22"/>And the servant said, Lord, it has been done as you commanded, and still there is room. <verse eid="LUK 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 14:23"/>And the lord said to the servant, Go forth into the ways and hedges, and constrain to come in, that my house may be filled; <verse eid="LUK 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 14:24"/>for I say to you that none of those men who have been called will taste of my dinner.” <verse eid="LUK 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 14:25"/>And there were going on with Him great multitudes, and having turned, He said to them, <verse eid="LUK 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 14:26"/>“If anyone comes to Me, and does not hate his own father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brothers, and sisters, and yet even his own life, he is not able to be My disciple; <verse eid="LUK 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 14:27"/>and whoever does not carry his cross, and come after Me, is not able to be My disciple. <verse eid="LUK 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 14:28"/>For who of you, willing to build a tower, does not first, having sat down, count the expense, whether he has the things for completing? <verse eid="LUK 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 14:29"/>Lest that he having laid a foundation, and not being able to finish, all who are beholding may begin to mock him, <verse eid="LUK 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 14:30"/>saying, This man began to build, and was not able to finish. <verse eid="LUK 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 14:31"/>Or what king going on to engage with another king in war, does not, having sat down, first consult if he with ten thousand is able to meet him who is coming against him with twenty thousand? <verse eid="LUK 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 14:32"/>And if not so—he being yet a long way off—having sent a delegation, he asks the things for peace. <verse eid="LUK 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 14:33"/>So, then, everyone of you who does not take leave of all that he himself has, is not able to be My disciple. <verse eid="LUK 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 14:34"/>The salt [is] good, but if the salt becomes tasteless, with what will it be seasoned? <verse eid="LUK 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 14:35"/>It is neither fit for land nor for manure—they cast it outside. He who is having ears to hear—let him hear.”<verse eid="LUK 14:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="LUK 15"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 15:1"/>And all the tax collectors and sinners were coming near to Him, to hear Him, <verse eid="LUK 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 15:2"/>and the Pharisees and the scribes were murmuring, saying, “This One receives sinners, and eats with them.” <verse eid="LUK 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 15:3"/>And He spoke to them this allegory, saying, <verse eid="LUK 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 15:4"/>“What man of you having one hundred sheep, and having lost one out of them, does not leave behind the ninety-nine in the wilderness, and go on after the lost one, until he may find it? <verse eid="LUK 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 15:5"/>And having found, he lays [it] on his shoulders rejoicing, <verse eid="LUK 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 15:6"/>and having come into the house, he calls together the friends and the neighbors, saying to them, Rejoice with me, because I found my sheep—the lost one. <verse eid="LUK 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 15:7"/>I say to you that [more] joy will be in Heaven over one sinner converting, rather than over ninety-nine righteous men who have no need of conversion. <verse eid="LUK 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 15:8"/>Or what woman having ten drachmas, if she may lose one drachma, does not light a lamp, and sweep the house, and seek carefully until she may find? <verse eid="LUK 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 15:9"/>And having found, she calls together the female friends and the neighbors, saying, Rejoice with me, for I found the drachma that I lost. <verse eid="LUK 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 15:10"/>So I say to you, joy comes before the messengers of God over one sinner converting.” <verse eid="LUK 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 15:11"/>And He said, “A certain man had two sons, <verse eid="LUK 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 15:12"/>and the younger of them said to the father, Father, give me the portion of the substance falling to [me], and he divided to them the living. <verse eid="LUK 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 15:13"/>And not many days after, having gathered all together, the younger son went abroad to a far country, and there he scattered his substance, living riotously; <verse eid="LUK 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 15:14"/>and he having spent all, there came a mighty famine on that country, and himself began to be in want; <verse eid="LUK 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 15:15"/>and having gone on, he joined himself to one of the citizens of that country, and he sent him into the fields to feed pigs, <verse eid="LUK 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 15:16"/>and he was desirous to fill his belly from the husks that the pigs were eating, and no one was giving to him. <verse eid="LUK 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 15:17"/>And having come to himself, he said, How many hired workers of my father have a superabundance of bread, and I am perishing here with hunger! <verse eid="LUK 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 15:18"/>Having risen, I will go on to my father, and will say to him, Father, I sinned—to Heaven, and before you, <verse eid="LUK 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 15:19"/>and I am no longer worthy to be called your son; make me as one of your hired workers. <verse eid="LUK 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 15:20"/>And having risen, he went to his own father, and he being yet far distant, his father saw him, and was moved with compassion, and having ran he fell on his neck and kissed him; <verse eid="LUK 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 15:21"/>and the son said to him, Father, I sinned—to Heaven, and before you, and I am no longer worthy to be called your son. <verse eid="LUK 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 15:22"/>And the father said to his servants, Bring forth the foremost robe, and clothe him, and give a ring for his hand, and sandals for the feet; <verse eid="LUK 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 15:23"/>and having brought the fatted calf, kill [it], and having eaten, we may be merry, <verse eid="LUK 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 15:24"/>because this son of mine was dead, and lived again, and he was lost, and was found; and they began to be merry. <verse eid="LUK 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 15:25"/>And his elder son was in a field, and as, coming, he drew near to the house, he heard music and dancing, <verse eid="LUK 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 15:26"/>and having called near one of the young men, he was inquiring what these things might be, <verse eid="LUK 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 15:27"/>and he said to him, Your brother has arrived, and your father killed the fatted calf, because he received him back in health. <verse eid="LUK 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 15:28"/>And he was angry, and would not go in, therefore his father, having come forth, was pleading him; <verse eid="LUK 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 15:29"/>and he answering said to the father, Behold, so many years I serve you, and never did I transgress your command, and you never gave to me a kid that I might make merry with my friends; <verse eid="LUK 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 15:30"/>but when your son—this one who devoured your living with prostitutes—came, you killed to him the fatted calf. <verse eid="LUK 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 15:31"/>And he said to him, Child, you are always with me, and all my things are yours; <verse eid="LUK 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 15:32"/>but to be merry, and to be glad, it was necessary, because this your brother was dead, and lived again, he was lost, and was found.”<verse eid="LUK 15:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="LUK 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 16:1"/>And He also said to His disciples, “A certain man was rich, who had a steward, and he was accused to him as scattering his goods; <verse eid="LUK 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 16:2"/>and having called him, he said to him, What [is] this I hear about you? Render the account of your stewardship, for you may not be steward any longer. <verse eid="LUK 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 16:3"/>And the steward said in himself, What will I do, because my lord takes away the stewardship from me? I am not able to dig, I am ashamed to beg— <verse eid="LUK 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 16:4"/>I have known what I will do, that, when I may be removed from the stewardship, they may receive me to their houses. <verse eid="LUK 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 16:5"/>And having called near each one of his lord’s debtors, he said to the first, How much do you owe to my lord? <verse eid="LUK 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 16:6"/>And he said, One hundred baths of oil; and he said to him, Take your bill, and having sat down write fifty. <verse eid="LUK 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 16:7"/>Afterward to another he said, And you, how much do you owe? And he said, One hundred cors of wheat; and he says to him, Take your bill, and write eighty. <verse eid="LUK 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 16:8"/>And the lord commended the unrighteous steward that he did prudently, because the sons of this age are more prudent than the sons of the light in respect to their generation. <verse eid="LUK 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 16:9"/>And I say to you, make to yourselves friends out of the wealth of unrighteousness, that when you may fail, they may receive you into the continuous dwelling places. <verse eid="LUK 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 16:10"/>He who is faithful in the least, [is] also faithful in much; and he who in the least [is] unrighteous, is also unrighteous in much; <verse eid="LUK 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 16:11"/>if, then, in the unrighteous wealth you did not become faithful—who will entrust to you the true? <verse eid="LUK 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 16:12"/>And if in the other’s you did not become faithful—who will give to you your own? <verse eid="LUK 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 16:13"/>No servant is able to serve two lords, for either he will hate the one, and he will love the other; or one he will hold to, and of the other he will be heedless; you are not able to serve God and wealth.” <verse eid="LUK 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 16:14"/>And also the Pharisees, being lovers of money, were hearing all these things, and were deriding Him, <verse eid="LUK 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 16:15"/>and He said to them, “You are those declaring yourselves righteous before men, but God knows your hearts; because that which is high among men [is] abomination before God; <verse eid="LUK 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 16:16"/>the Law and the Prophets [are] until John; since then the good news of the Kingdom of God is proclaimed, and everyone presses into it; <verse eid="LUK 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 16:17"/>and it is easier for the heaven and the earth to pass away, than one tittle to fall of the Law. <verse eid="LUK 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 16:18"/>Everyone who is sending his wife away, and marrying another, commits adultery; and everyone who is marrying her sent away from a husband commits adultery. <verse eid="LUK 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 16:19"/>And—a certain man was rich, and was clothed in purple and fine linen, making merry sumptuously every day, <verse eid="LUK 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 16:20"/>and there was a certain poor man, by name Lazarus, who was laid at his porch, full of sores, <verse eid="LUK 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 16:21"/>and desiring to be filled from the crumbs that are falling from the table of the rich man; indeed, also the dogs, coming, were licking his sores. <verse eid="LUK 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 16:22"/>And it came to pass, that the poor man died, and that he was carried away by the messengers into the bosom of Abraham—and the rich man also died, and was buried; <verse eid="LUK 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 16:23"/>and having lifted up his eyes in Hades, being in torments, he sees Abraham far off, and Lazarus in his bosom, <verse eid="LUK 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 16:24"/>and having cried, he said, Father Abraham, deal kindly with me, and send Lazarus, that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and may cool my tongue, because I am distressed in this flame. <verse eid="LUK 16:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 16:25"/>And Abraham said, Child, remember that you received your good things in your life, and Lazarus in like manner the evil things, and now he is comforted, and you are distressed; <verse eid="LUK 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 16:26"/>and besides all these things, between us and you a great chasm is fixed, so that they who are willing to go over from here to you are not able, nor do they pass through from there to us. <verse eid="LUK 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 16:27"/>And he said, I ask, then, father, that you may send him to the house of my father, <verse eid="LUK 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 16:28"/>for I have five brothers, so that he may thoroughly testify to them, that they also may not come to this place of torment. <verse eid="LUK 16:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 16:29"/>Abraham says to him, They have Moses and the prophets, let them hear them; <verse eid="LUK 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 16:30"/>and he said, No, father Abraham, but if anyone from the dead may go to them, they will convert. <verse eid="LUK 16:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 16:31"/>And he said to him, If they do not hear Moses and the prophets, neither will they be persuaded if one may rise out of the dead.”<verse eid="LUK 16:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="LUK 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 17:1"/>And He said to the disciples, “It is impossible for the stumbling blocks not to come, but woe [to him] through whom they come; <verse eid="LUK 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 17:2"/>it is more profitable to him if a weighty millstone is put around his neck, and he has been cast into the sea, than that he may cause one of these little ones to stumble. <verse eid="LUK 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 17:3"/>Take heed to yourselves, and if your brother may sin in regard to you, rebuke him, and if he may change his mind, forgive him, <verse eid="LUK 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 17:4"/>and if seven times in the day he may sin against you, and seven times in the day may return to you, saying, I change my mind, you will forgive him.” <verse eid="LUK 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 17:5"/>And the apostles said to the LORD, “Add to us faith”; <verse eid="LUK 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 17:6"/>and the LORD said, “If you had faith as a grain of mustard, you would have said to this sycamine, Be uprooted, and be planted in the sea, and it would have obeyed you. <verse eid="LUK 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 17:7"/>But who is he of you—having a servant plowing or feeding—who, to him having come in out of the field, will say, Having come, recline at once? <verse eid="LUK 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 17:8"/>But will not [rather] say to him, Prepare what I may dine, and having girded yourself around, minister to me, until I eat and drink, and after these things you will eat and drink? <verse eid="LUK 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 17:9"/>Does he have favor to that servant because he did the things directed? I think not. <verse eid="LUK 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 17:10"/>So also you, when you may have done all the things directed you, say, We are unprofitable servants, because that which we owed to do we have done.” <verse eid="LUK 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 17:11"/>And it came to pass, in His going on to Jerusalem, that He passed through the midst of Samaria and Galilee, <verse eid="LUK 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 17:12"/>and He entering into a certain village, there ten leprous men met Him, who stood far off, <verse eid="LUK 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 17:13"/>and they lifted up the voice, saying, “Jesus, Master, deal kindly with us”; <verse eid="LUK 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 17:14"/>and having seen [them], He said to them, “Having gone on, show yourselves to the priests”; and it came to pass, in their going, they were cleansed, <verse eid="LUK 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 17:15"/>and one of them having seen that he was healed turned back, glorifying God with a loud voice, <verse eid="LUK 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 17:16"/>and he fell on [his] face at His feet, giving thanks to Him, and he was a Samaritan. <verse eid="LUK 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 17:17"/>And Jesus answering said, “Were not the ten cleansed, and the nine—where? <verse eid="LUK 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 17:18"/>There were none found who turned back to give glory to God, except this foreigner”; <verse eid="LUK 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 17:19"/>and He said to him, “Having risen, be going on, your faith has saved you.” <verse eid="LUK 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 17:20"/>And having been questioned by the Pharisees when the Kingdom of God comes, He answered them and said, “The Kingdom of God does not come with observation; <verse eid="LUK 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 17:21"/>nor will they say, Behold, here; or, Behold, there; for behold, the Kingdom of God is within you.” <verse eid="LUK 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 17:22"/>And He said to His disciples, “Days will come when you will desire to see one of the days of the Son of Man and you will not behold [it]; <verse eid="LUK 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 17:23"/>and they will say to you, Behold, here; or, Behold, there; you may not go away, nor follow; <verse eid="LUK 17:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 17:24"/>for as the lightning is flashing out of one [part] under the sky [and] shines to the other [part] under the sky, so will the Son of Man also be in His day; <verse eid="LUK 17:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 17:25"/>and first it is necessary for Him to suffer many things, and to be rejected by this generation. <verse eid="LUK 17:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 17:26"/>And as it came to pass in the days of Noah, so will it also be in the days of the Son of Man; <verse eid="LUK 17:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 17:27"/>they were eating, they were drinking, they were marrying, they were given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the Ark, and the flood came, and destroyed all; <verse eid="LUK 17:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 17:28"/>in like manner also, as it came to pass in the days of Lot; they were eating, they were drinking, they were buying, they were selling, they were planting, they were building; <verse eid="LUK 17:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 17:29"/>and on the day Lot went forth from Sodom, He rained fire and brimstone from the sky, and destroyed all. <verse eid="LUK 17:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 17:30"/>According to these things it will be, in the day the Son of Man is revealed; <verse eid="LUK 17:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 17:31"/>in that day, he who will be on the housetop, and his vessels in the house, do not let him come down to take them away; and he in the field, in like manner, do not let him turn backward; <verse eid="LUK 17:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 17:32"/>remember the wife of Lot. <verse eid="LUK 17:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 17:33"/>Whoever may seek to save his life, will lose it; and whoever may lose it, will preserve it. <verse eid="LUK 17:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 17:34"/>I say to you, in that night there will be two [men] on one bed: one will be taken, and the other will be left; <verse eid="LUK 17:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 17:35"/>two [women] will be grinding at the same place together: one will be taken, and the other will be left; <verse eid="LUK 17:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 17:36"/><char style="bd">[[</char>two [men] will be in the field: one will be taken, and the other left.”<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 17:37"/>And they answering say to Him, “Where, Lord?” And He said to them, “Where the body [is], there the eagles will be gathered together.”<verse eid="LUK 17:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="LUK 18"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 18:1"/>And He also spoke an allegory to them, that it is always necessary to pray and not to faint, <verse eid="LUK 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 18:2"/>saying, “A certain judge was in a certain city—he is not fearing God, and he is not regarding man— <verse eid="LUK 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 18:3"/>and a widow was in that city, and she was coming to him, saying, Do me justice on my opponent, <verse eid="LUK 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 18:4"/>and he would not for a time, but after these things he said in himself, Even if I do not fear God, and do not regard man, <verse eid="LUK 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 18:5"/>yet because this widow gives me trouble, I will do her justice, lest, continuously coming, she may bruise me.” <verse eid="LUK 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 18:6"/>And the LORD said, “Hear what the unrighteous judge says: <verse eid="LUK 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 18:7"/>and will God not execute justice to His chosen ones, who are crying to Him day and night—bearing long in regard to them? <verse eid="LUK 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 18:8"/>I say to you that He will execute justice to them quickly; but the Son of Man having come, will He find faith on the earth?” <verse eid="LUK 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 18:9"/>And He also spoke to some who have been trusting in themselves that they were righteous, and have been despising the rest, this allegory: <verse eid="LUK 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 18:10"/>“Two men went up to the temple to pray, one a Pharisee, and the other a tax collector; <verse eid="LUK 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 18:11"/>the Pharisee having stood by himself, thus prayed: God, I thank You that I am not as the rest of men, rapacious, unrighteous, adulterers, or even as this tax collector; <verse eid="LUK 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 18:12"/>I fast twice in the week, I give tithes of all things—as many as I possess. <verse eid="LUK 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 18:13"/>And the tax collector, having stood far off, would not even lift up the eyes to the sky, but was striking on his breast, saying, God be propitious to me—the sinner! <verse eid="LUK 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 18:14"/>I say to you, this one went down declared righteous, to his house, rather than that one: for everyone who is exalting himself will be humbled, and he who is humbling himself will be exalted.” <verse eid="LUK 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 18:15"/>And they were also bringing the babies near, that He may touch them, and the disciples having seen, rebuked them, <verse eid="LUK 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 18:16"/>and Jesus having called them near, said, “Permit the little children to come to Me, and do not forbid them, for of such is the Kingdom of God; <verse eid="LUK 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 18:17"/>truly I say to you, whoever may not receive the Kingdom of God as a little child, may not enter into it.” <verse eid="LUK 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 18:18"/>And a certain ruler questioned Him, saying, “Good Teacher, what having done—will I inherit continuous life?” <verse eid="LUK 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 18:19"/>And Jesus said to him, “Why do you call Me good? No one [is] good, except one—God; <verse eid="LUK 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 18:20"/>you have known the commands: You may not commit adultery, You may not murder, You may not steal, You may not bear false witness, Honor your father and your mother.” <verse eid="LUK 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 18:21"/>And he said, “All these I kept from my youth”; <verse eid="LUK 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 18:22"/>and having heard these things, Jesus said to him, “Yet one thing to you is lacking: all things—as many as you have—sell, and distribute to the poor, and you will have treasure in Heaven, and come, follow Me”; <verse eid="LUK 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 18:23"/>and he, having heard these things, became very sorrowful, for he was exceedingly rich. <verse eid="LUK 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 18:24"/>And Jesus having seen him become very sorrowful, said, “How hardly will those having riches enter into the Kingdom of God! <verse eid="LUK 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 18:25"/>For it is easier for a camel to enter through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God.” <verse eid="LUK 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 18:26"/>And those who heard, said, “And who is able to be saved?” <verse eid="LUK 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 18:27"/>And He said, “The things impossible with men are possible with God.” <verse eid="LUK 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 18:28"/>And Peter said, “Behold, we left all, and followed You”; <verse eid="LUK 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 18:29"/>and He said to them, “Truly I say to you that there is not one who left house, or parents, or brothers, or wife, or children, for the sake of the Kingdom of God, <verse eid="LUK 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 18:30"/>who may not receive back manifold more in this time, and in the coming age, continuous life.” <verse eid="LUK 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 18:31"/>And having taken the Twelve aside, He said to them, “Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and all things will be accomplished that have been written through the prophets to the Son of Man, <verse eid="LUK 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 18:32"/>for He will be delivered up to the nations, and will be mocked, and insulted, and spit on, <verse eid="LUK 18:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 18:33"/>and having scourged they will put Him to death, and on the third day He will rise again.” <verse eid="LUK 18:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 18:34"/>And they understood none of these things, and this saying was hid from them, and they were not knowing the things said. <verse eid="LUK 18:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 18:35"/>And it came to pass, in His coming near to Jericho, a certain blind man was sitting beside the way begging, <verse eid="LUK 18:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 18:36"/>and having heard a multitude going by, he was inquiring what this may be, <verse eid="LUK 18:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 18:37"/>and they brought him word that Jesus the Nazarene passes by, <verse eid="LUK 18:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 18:38"/>and he cried out, saying, “Jesus, Son of David, deal kindly with me”; <verse eid="LUK 18:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 18:39"/>and those going before were rebuking him, that he might be silent, but he was crying out much more, “Son of David, deal kindly with me!” <verse eid="LUK 18:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 18:40"/>And Jesus having stood, commanded him to be brought to Him, and he having come near, He questioned him, <verse eid="LUK 18:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 18:41"/>saying, “What do you will I will do to you?” And he said, “Lord, that I may receive sight.” <verse eid="LUK 18:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 18:42"/>And Jesus said to him, “Receive your sight; your faith has saved you”; <verse eid="LUK 18:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 18:43"/>and instantly he received sight, and was following Him, glorifying God; and all the people, having seen, gave praise to God.<verse eid="LUK 18:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="LUK 19"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 19:1"/>And having entered, He was passing through Jericho, <verse eid="LUK 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 19:2"/>and behold, a man, by name called Zaccheus, and he was a chief tax collector, and he was rich, <verse eid="LUK 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 19:3"/>and he was seeking to see Jesus, who He is, and was not able for the multitude, because he was small in stature, <verse eid="LUK 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 19:4"/>and having run forward before, he went up on a sycamore, that he may see Him, because through that [way] He was about to pass by. <verse eid="LUK 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 19:5"/>And as Jesus came up to the place, having looked up, He saw him and said to him, “Zaccheus, having hurried, come down, for it is necessary for Me to remain in your house today”; <verse eid="LUK 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 19:6"/>and he having hurried came down, and received Him rejoicing; <verse eid="LUK 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 19:7"/>and having seen [it], they were all murmuring, saying, “He went in to lodge with a sinful man!” <verse eid="LUK 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 19:8"/>And Zaccheus having stood, said to the LORD, “Behold, half of my goods, Lord, I give to the poor, and if I took by false accusation anything of anyone, I give back fourfold.” <verse eid="LUK 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 19:9"/>And Jesus said to him, “Today salvation came to this house, inasmuch as he also is a son of Abraham; <verse eid="LUK 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 19:10"/>for the Son of Man came to seek and to save the lost.” <verse eid="LUK 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 19:11"/>And while they are hearing these things, having added He spoke an allegory, because of His being near to Jerusalem, and of their thinking that the Kingdom of God is immediately about to appear. <verse eid="LUK 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 19:12"/>He therefore said, “A certain man of birth went on to a far country, to take to himself a kingdom, and to return, <verse eid="LUK 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 19:13"/>and having called ten servants of his own, he gave ten minas to them and said to them, Do business—until I come; <verse eid="LUK 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 19:14"/>and his citizens were hating him, and sent a delegation after him, saying, We do not wish this one to reign over us. <verse eid="LUK 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 19:15"/>And it came to pass, on his coming back, having taken the kingdom, that he commanded these servants to be called to him, to whom he gave the money, that he might know what anyone had done in business. <verse eid="LUK 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 19:16"/>And the first came near, saying, Lord, your mina gained ten minas; <verse eid="LUK 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 19:17"/>and he said to him, Well done, good servant, because you became faithful in a very little, be having authority over ten cities. <verse eid="LUK 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 19:18"/>And the second came, saying, Lord, your mina made five minas; <verse eid="LUK 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 19:19"/>and he also said to this one, And you, become [ruler] over five cities. <verse eid="LUK 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 19:20"/>And another came, saying, Lord, behold, your mina, that I had lying away in a napkin; <verse eid="LUK 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 19:21"/>for I was afraid of you, because you are an austere man; you take up what you did not lay down, and reap what you did not sow. <verse eid="LUK 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 19:22"/>And he says to him, Out of your mouth I will judge you, evil servant: you knew that I am an austere man, taking up what I did not lay down, and reaping what I did not sow! <verse eid="LUK 19:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 19:23"/>And why did you not give my money to the bank, and I, having come, might have received it with interest? <verse eid="LUK 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 19:24"/>And to those standing by he said, Take the mina from him, and give to him having the ten minas— <verse eid="LUK 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 19:25"/>(and they said to him, Lord, he has ten minas)— <verse eid="LUK 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 19:26"/>for I say to you that to everyone having will be given, and from him not having, also what he has will be taken from him, <verse eid="LUK 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 19:27"/>but those my enemies, who did not wish me to reign over them, bring here and slay before me.” <verse eid="LUK 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 19:28"/>And having said these things, He went on before, going up to Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 19:29"/>And it came to pass, as He came near to Bethphage and Bethany, to that called the Mount of Olives, He sent two of His disciples, <verse eid="LUK 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 19:30"/>having said, “Go away into the village in front of [you], in which, entering in, you will find a colt bound, on which no one of men ever sat, having loosed it, bring [it]; <verse eid="LUK 19:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 19:31"/>and if anyone questions you, Why do you loose [it]? Thus you will say to him: The LORD has need of it.” <verse eid="LUK 19:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 19:32"/>And those sent, having gone away, found according as He said to them, <verse eid="LUK 19:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 19:33"/>and while they are loosing the colt, its owners said to them, “Why do you loose the colt?” <verse eid="LUK 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 19:34"/>And they said, “The LORD has need of it”; <verse eid="LUK 19:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 19:35"/>and they brought it to Jesus, and having cast their garments on the colt, they sat Jesus on it. <verse eid="LUK 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 19:36"/>And as He is going, they were spreading their garments in the way, <verse eid="LUK 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 19:37"/>and as He is coming near now, at the descent of the Mount of Olives, the whole multitude of the disciples began rejoicing to praise God with a great voice for all the mighty works they had seen, <verse eid="LUK 19:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 19:38"/>saying, “Blessed [is] the King coming in the Name of the LORD; peace in Heaven, and glory in the highest!” <verse eid="LUK 19:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 19:39"/>And certain of the Pharisees from the multitude said to Him, “Teacher, rebuke Your disciples”; <verse eid="LUK 19:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 19:40"/>and He answering said to them, “I say to you that if these will be silent, the stones will cry out!” <verse eid="LUK 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 19:41"/>And when He came near, having seen the city, He wept over it, <verse eid="LUK 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 19:42"/>saying, “If you knew, even you, at least in this your day, the things for your peace; but now they were hid from your eyes. <verse eid="LUK 19:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 19:43"/>Because days will come on you, and your enemies will cast a rampart around you, and surround you around, and press you on every side, <verse eid="LUK 19:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 19:44"/>and lay you low, and your children within you, and they will not leave in you a stone on a stone, because you did not know the time of your inspection.” <verse eid="LUK 19:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 19:45"/>And having entered into the temple, He began to cast forth those selling in it, and those buying, <verse eid="LUK 19:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 19:46"/>saying to them, “It has been written, My house is a house of prayer—but you made it a den of robbers.” <verse eid="LUK 19:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 19:47"/>And He was teaching daily in the temple, but the chief priests and the scribes were seeking to destroy Him—also the chiefs of the people— <verse eid="LUK 19:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 19:48"/>and they were not finding what they will do, for all the people were hanging on Him, hearing Him.<verse eid="LUK 19:48"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="LUK 20"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 20:1"/>And it came to pass, on one of those days, as He is teaching the people in the temple, and proclaiming good news, the chief priests and the scribes, with the elders, came on [Him], <verse eid="LUK 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 20:2"/>and spoke to Him, saying, “Tell us by what authority You do these things? Or who is he that gave to You this authority?” <verse eid="LUK 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 20:3"/>And He answering said to them, “I will question you—I also—one thing, and tell Me: <verse eid="LUK 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 20:4"/>the immersion of John, was it from Heaven, or from men?” <verse eid="LUK 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 20:5"/>And they reasoned with themselves, saying, “If we may say, From Heaven, He will say, Why, then, did you not believe him? <verse eid="LUK 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 20:6"/>And if we may say, From men, all the people will stone us, for they are having been persuaded John to be a prophet.” <verse eid="LUK 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 20:7"/>And they answered that they did not know from where [it was], <verse eid="LUK 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 20:8"/>and Jesus said to them, “Neither do I say to you by what authority I do these things.” <verse eid="LUK 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 20:9"/>And He began to speak to the people this allegory: “A certain man planted a vineyard, and gave it out to farmers, and went abroad for a long time, <verse eid="LUK 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 20:10"/>and at the season he sent a servant to the farmers, that they may give to him from the fruit of the vineyard, but the farmers having beat him, sent [him] away empty. <verse eid="LUK 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 20:11"/>And he added to send another servant, and they also having beaten and dishonored that one, sent [him] away empty; <verse eid="LUK 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 20:12"/>and he added to send a third, and this one also, having wounded, they cast out. <verse eid="LUK 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 20:13"/>And the owner of the vineyard said, What will I do? I will send my son, the beloved, perhaps having seen this one, they will respect [him]; <verse eid="LUK 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 20:14"/>and having seen him, the farmers reasoned among themselves, saying, This is the heir; come, we may kill him, that the inheritance may become ours; <verse eid="LUK 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 20:15"/>and having cast him outside of the vineyard, they killed [him]; what, then, will the owner of the vineyard do to them? <verse eid="LUK 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 20:16"/>He will come, and destroy these farmers, and will give the vineyard to others.” And having heard, they said, “Let it not be!” <verse eid="LUK 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 20:17"/>And He, having looked on them, said, “What, then, is this that has been written: A stone that the builders rejected—this became head of a corner? <verse eid="LUK 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 20:18"/>Everyone who has fallen on that stone will be broken, and on whom it may fall, it will crush him to pieces.” <verse eid="LUK 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 20:19"/>And the chief priests and the scribes sought to lay hands on Him in that hour, and they feared the people, for they knew that He spoke this allegory against them. <verse eid="LUK 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 20:20"/>And having watched [Him], they sent forth ones lying in wait, feigning themselves to be righteous, that they might take hold of His word, to deliver Him up to the rule and to the authority of the governor, <verse eid="LUK 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 20:21"/>and they questioned Him, saying, “Teacher, we have known that You say and teach correctly, and do not receive a person, but in truth teach the way of God. <verse eid="LUK 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 20:22"/>Is it lawful to us to give tribute to Caesar or not?” <verse eid="LUK 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 20:23"/>And He, having perceived their craftiness, said to them, “Why do you tempt Me? <verse eid="LUK 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 20:24"/>Show Me a denarius; of whom does it have an image and inscription?” And they answering said, “Of Caesar”: <verse eid="LUK 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 20:25"/>and He said to them, “Give back, therefore, the things of Caesar to Caesar, and the things of God to God”; <verse eid="LUK 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 20:26"/>and they were not able to take hold on His saying before the people, and having wondered at His answer, they were silent. <verse eid="LUK 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 20:27"/>And certain of the Sadducees, who are denying that there is a resurrection, having come near, questioned Him, <verse eid="LUK 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 20:28"/>saying, “Teacher, Moses wrote to us if anyone’s brother may die, having a wife, and he may die childless—that his brother may take the wife, and may raise up seed to his brother. <verse eid="LUK 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 20:29"/>There were, then, seven brothers, and the first having taken a wife, died childless, <verse eid="LUK 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 20:30"/>and the second took the wife, and he died childless, <verse eid="LUK 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 20:31"/>and the third took her, and in like manner also the seven—they left no children, and they died; <verse eid="LUK 20:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 20:32"/>and last of all the woman also died: <verse eid="LUK 20:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 20:33"/>in the resurrection, then, of which of them does she become wife? For the seven had her as wife.” <verse eid="LUK 20:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 20:34"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “The sons of this age marry and are given in marriage, <verse eid="LUK 20:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 20:35"/>but those accounted worthy to obtain that age, and the resurrection that is out of the dead, neither marry, nor are they given in marriage; <verse eid="LUK 20:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 20:36"/>for neither are they able to die anymore—for they are like messengers—and they are sons of God, being sons of the resurrection. <verse eid="LUK 20:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 20:37"/>And that the dead are raised, even Moses showed at the Bush, since he calls the LORD the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob; <verse eid="LUK 20:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 20:38"/>and He is not a God of dead men, but of living, for all live to Him.” <verse eid="LUK 20:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 20:39"/>And certain of the scribes answering said, “Teacher, You said well”; <verse eid="LUK 20:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 20:40"/>and they no longer dared question Him anything. <verse eid="LUK 20:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 20:41"/>And He said to them, “How do they say the Christ is [the] son of David, <verse eid="LUK 20:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 20:42"/>and David himself says in [the] Scroll of Psalms, The LORD said to my Lord, || Sit on My right hand, <verse eid="LUK 20:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 20:43"/>Until I will make Your enemies Your footstool; <verse eid="LUK 20:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 20:44"/>David, then, calls Him Lord, and how is He his son?” <verse eid="LUK 20:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 20:45"/>And all the people hearing, He said to His disciples, <verse eid="LUK 20:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 20:46"/>“Take heed of the scribes, who are wishing to walk in long robes, and are cherishing salutations in the markets, and first seats in the synagogues, and first couches at the banquets, <verse eid="LUK 20:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 20:47"/>who devour the houses of the widows, and make long prayers for a pretense, these will receive more abundant judgment.”<verse eid="LUK 20:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="LUK 21"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 21:1"/>And having looked up, He saw those who cast their gifts into the treasury—rich men, <verse eid="LUK 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 21:2"/>and He also saw a certain poor widow casting two mites there, <verse eid="LUK 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 21:3"/>and He said, “Truly I say to you that this poor widow cast in more than all; <verse eid="LUK 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 21:4"/>for all these out of their superabundance cast into the gifts to God, but this one out of her want, all the living that she had, cast in.” <verse eid="LUK 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 21:5"/>And [as] some were speaking about the temple, that it has been adorned with good stones and devoted things, He said, <verse eid="LUK 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 21:6"/>“These things that you behold—days will come in which there will not be left a stone on a stone that will not be thrown down.” <verse eid="LUK 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 21:7"/>And they questioned Him, saying, “Teacher, when, then, will these things be? And what [is] the sign when these things may be about to happen?” <verse eid="LUK 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 21:8"/>And He said, “See—you may not be led astray, for many will come in My Name, saying, I am [He], and the time has come near; do not then go on after them; <verse eid="LUK 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 21:9"/>and when you may hear of wars and uprisings, do not be terrified, for it is necessary for these things to happen first, but the end [is] not immediately.” <verse eid="LUK 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 21:10"/>Then He said to them, “Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom, <verse eid="LUK 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 21:11"/>also great shakings, and there will be famines and pestilences in every place; also there will be fearful things and great signs from the sky; <verse eid="LUK 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 21:12"/>and before all these, they will lay on you their hands, and persecute, delivering up to synagogues and prisons, being brought before kings and governors for My Name’s sake; <verse eid="LUK 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 21:13"/>and it will become to you for a testimony. <verse eid="LUK 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 21:14"/>Settle, then, to your hearts, not to meditate beforehand to reply, <verse eid="LUK 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 21:15"/>for I will give to you a mouth and wisdom that all your opposers will not be able to refute or resist. <verse eid="LUK 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 21:16"/>And you will be delivered up also by parents, and brothers, and relatives, and friends, and they will put [some] of you to death; <verse eid="LUK 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 21:17"/>and you will be hated by all because of My Name— <verse eid="LUK 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 21:18"/>and a hair out of your head will not perish; <verse eid="LUK 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 21:19"/>in your patience possess your souls. <verse eid="LUK 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 21:20"/>And when you may see Jerusalem surrounded by encampments, then know that her desolation has come near; <verse eid="LUK 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 21:21"/>then those in Judea, let them flee to the mountains; and those in her midst, let them depart out; and those in the countries, do not let them come in to her; <verse eid="LUK 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 21:22"/>because these are days of vengeance, to fulfill all things that have been written. <verse eid="LUK 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 21:23"/>And woe to those with child, and to those giving suck, in those days; for there will be great distress on the land, and wrath on this people; <verse eid="LUK 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 21:24"/>and they will fall by the mouth of the sword, and will be led captive to all the nations, and Jerusalem will be trodden down by nations, until the times of nations be fulfilled. <verse eid="LUK 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 21:25"/>And there will be signs in sun, and moon, and stars, and on the earth distress of nations with perplexity, sea and wave roaring; <verse eid="LUK 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 21:26"/>men fainting at heart from fear, and expectation of the things coming on the world, for the powers of the heavens will be shaken. <verse eid="LUK 21:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 21:27"/>And then they will see the Son of Man coming in a cloud, with power and much glory; <verse eid="LUK 21:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 21:28"/>and these things beginning to happen, bend yourselves back, and lift up your heads, because your redemption draws near.” <verse eid="LUK 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 21:29"/>And He spoke an allegory to them: “See the fig tree, and all the trees, <verse eid="LUK 21:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 21:30"/>when they may now cast forth, having seen, of yourselves you know that now the summer is near; <verse eid="LUK 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 21:31"/>so also you, when you may see these things happening, you know that the Kingdom of God is near; <verse eid="LUK 21:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 21:32"/>truly I say to you, this generation may not pass away until all may have come to pass; <verse eid="LUK 21:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 21:33"/>the sky and the earth will pass away, but My words may not pass away. <verse eid="LUK 21:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 21:34"/>And take heed to yourselves lest your hearts may be weighed down with carousing, and drunkenness, and anxieties of life, and suddenly that day may come on you, <verse eid="LUK 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 21:35"/>for it will come as a snare on all those dwelling on the face of all the earth, <verse eid="LUK 21:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 21:36"/>watch, then, in every season, praying that you may be accounted worthy to escape all these things that are about to come to pass, and to stand before the Son of Man.” <verse eid="LUK 21:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 21:37"/>And He was teaching in the temple during the days, and during the nights, going forth, He was lodging at [that] called the Mount of Olives; <verse eid="LUK 21:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 21:38"/>and all the people were coming early to Him in the temple to hear Him.<verse eid="LUK 21:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="LUK 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 22:1"/>And the Celebration of the Unleavened [Bread] was coming near, that is called Passover, <verse eid="LUK 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 22:2"/>and the chief priests and the scribes were seeking how they may take Him up, for they were afraid of the people. <verse eid="LUK 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 22:3"/>And Satan entered into Judas, who is surnamed Iscariot, being of the number of the Twelve, <verse eid="LUK 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 22:4"/>and he, having gone away, spoke with the chief priests and the magistrates, how he might deliver Him up to them, <verse eid="LUK 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 22:5"/>and they rejoiced, and covenanted to give him money, <verse eid="LUK 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 22:6"/>and he agreed, and was seeking a favorable season to deliver Him up to them without tumult. <verse eid="LUK 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 22:7"/>And the day of the Unleavened [Bread] came, in which it was necessary [for] the Passover to be sacrificed, <verse eid="LUK 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 22:8"/>and He sent Peter and John, saying, “Having gone on, prepare to us the Passover, that we may eat”; <verse eid="LUK 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 22:9"/>and they said to Him, “Where do You will that we might prepare?” <verse eid="LUK 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 22:10"/>And He said to them, “Behold, in your entering into the city, a man will meet you there, carrying a pitcher of water, follow him into the house where he goes in, <verse eid="LUK 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 22:11"/>and you will say to the master of the house, The Teacher says to you, Where is the guest-chamber where I may eat the Passover with My disciples? <verse eid="LUK 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 22:12"/>And he will show you a large upper room furnished, make ready there”; <verse eid="LUK 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 22:13"/>and they, having gone away, found as He has said to them, and they made the Passover ready. <verse eid="LUK 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 22:14"/>And when the hour was come, He reclined, and the twelve apostles with Him, <verse eid="LUK 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 22:15"/>and He said to them, “With desire I desired to eat this Passover with you before My suffering, <verse eid="LUK 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 22:16"/>for I say to you that I may eat of it no longer until it may be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God.” <verse eid="LUK 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 22:17"/>And having taken a cup, having given thanks, He said, “Take this and divide to yourselves, <verse eid="LUK 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 22:18"/>for I say to you that I may not drink of the produce of the vine until the Kingdom of God may come.” <verse eid="LUK 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 22:19"/>And having taken bread, having given thanks, He broke and gave to them, saying, “This is My body, that is being given for you, do this in remembrance of Me.” <verse eid="LUK 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 22:20"/>In like manner, also, the cup after the dining, saying, “This cup [is] the New Covenant in My blood, that is being poured forth for you. <verse eid="LUK 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 22:21"/>But behold, the hand of him delivering Me up [is] with Me on the table, <verse eid="LUK 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 22:22"/>and, indeed, the Son of Man goes according to what has been determined; but woe to that man through whom He is being delivered up.” <verse eid="LUK 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 22:23"/>And they began to reason among themselves who then of them it may be who is about to do this thing. <verse eid="LUK 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 22:24"/>And there happened also a strife among them—who of them is accounted to be greater. <verse eid="LUK 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 22:25"/>And He said to them, “The kings of the nations exercise lordship over them, and those exercising authority on them are called benefactors; <verse eid="LUK 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 22:26"/>but you [are] not so, but he who is greater among you—let him be as the younger; and he who is leading, as he who is ministering; <verse eid="LUK 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 22:27"/>for who is greater? He who is reclining, or he who is ministering? Is it not he who is reclining? And I am in your midst as He who is ministering. <verse eid="LUK 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 22:28"/>And you are those who have remained with Me in My temptations, <verse eid="LUK 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 22:29"/>and I appoint to you a kingdom, as My Father appointed to Me, <verse eid="LUK 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 22:30"/>that you may eat and may drink at My table, in My kingdom, and may sit on thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel.” <verse eid="LUK 22:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 22:31"/>And the LORD said, “Simon, Simon, behold, Satan asked for himself to sift you as the wheat, <verse eid="LUK 22:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 22:32"/>and I implored for you that your faith may not fail; and you, when you turned, strengthen your brothers.” <verse eid="LUK 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 22:33"/>And he said to Him, “Lord, I am ready to go with You both to prison and to death”; <verse eid="LUK 22:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 22:34"/>and He said, “I say to you, Peter, a rooster will not crow today, before you may disown knowing Me three times.” <verse eid="LUK 22:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 22:35"/>And He said to them, “When I sent you without bag, and leather pouch, and sandals, did you lack anything?” And they said, “Nothing.” <verse eid="LUK 22:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 22:36"/>Then He said to them, “But now, he who is having a bag, let him take [it] up, and in like manner also a leather pouch; and he who is not having, let him sell his garment, and buy a sword, <verse eid="LUK 22:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 22:37"/>for I say to you that this which has been written is necessary to be accomplished in Me: And He was reckoned with lawless ones; for also the things concerning Me have an end.” <verse eid="LUK 22:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 22:38"/>And they said, “Lord, behold, here [are] two swords”; and He said to them, “It is sufficient.” <verse eid="LUK 22:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 22:39"/>And having gone forth, He went on, according to custom, to the Mount of Olives, and His disciples also followed Him, <verse eid="LUK 22:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 22:40"/>and having come to the place, He said to them, “Pray to not enter into temptation.” <verse eid="LUK 22:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 22:41"/>And He was withdrawn from them, as it were a stone’s cast, and having fallen on the knees He was praying, <verse eid="LUK 22:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 22:42"/>saying, “Father, if You are willing, remove this cup from Me, but not My will, but Yours be done.” <verse eid="LUK 22:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 22:43"/>And there appeared to Him a messenger from Heaven strengthening Him; <verse eid="LUK 22:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 22:44"/>and having been in agony, He was more earnestly praying, and His sweat became, as it were, great drops of blood falling on the ground. <verse eid="LUK 22:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 22:45"/>And having risen up from the prayer, having come to the disciples, He found them sleeping from the sorrow, <verse eid="LUK 22:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 22:46"/>and He said to them, “Why do you sleep? Having risen, pray that you may not enter into temptation.” <verse eid="LUK 22:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 22:47"/>And while He is speaking, behold, a multitude, and he who is called Judas, one of the Twelve, was coming before them, and he came near to Jesus to kiss Him, <verse eid="LUK 22:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 22:48"/>and Jesus said to him, “Judas, do you deliver up the Son of Man with a kiss?” <verse eid="LUK 22:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 22:49"/>And those around Him, having seen what was about to be, said to Him, “Lord, will we strike with a sword?” <verse eid="LUK 22:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 22:50"/>And a certain one of them struck the servant of the chief priest, and took off his right ear, <verse eid="LUK 22:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 22:51"/>and Jesus answering said, “Permit thus far,” and having touched his ear, He healed him. <verse eid="LUK 22:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 22:52"/>And Jesus said to those having come on Him—chief priests, and magistrates of the temple, and elders, “Have you come forth with swords and sticks as on a robber? <verse eid="LUK 22:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 22:53"/>While daily I was with you in the temple, you stretched forth no hands against Me; but this is your hour and the power of the darkness.” <verse eid="LUK 22:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 22:54"/>And having taken Him, they led and brought Him into the house of the chief priest. And Peter was following far off, <verse eid="LUK 22:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 22:55"/>and they having kindled a fire in the midst of the court, and having sat down together, Peter was sitting in the midst of them, <verse eid="LUK 22:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 22:56"/>and a certain maid having seen him sitting at the light, and having earnestly looked at him, she said, “And this one was with Him!” <verse eid="LUK 22:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LUK 22:57"/>And he disowned Him, saying, “Woman, I have not known Him.” <verse eid="LUK 22:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LUK 22:58"/>And after a while, another having seen him, said, “And you are of them!” And Peter said, “Man, I am not.” <verse eid="LUK 22:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="LUK 22:59"/>And one hour, as it were, having intervened, a certain other was confidently affirming, saying, “Of a truth this one also was with Him, for he is also a Galilean”; <verse eid="LUK 22:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="LUK 22:60"/>and Peter said, “Man, I have not known what you say”; and immediately, while he is speaking, a rooster crowed. <verse eid="LUK 22:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="LUK 22:61"/>And the LORD, having turned, looked on Peter, and Peter remembered the word of the LORD, how He said to him, “Before a rooster will crow, you may disown Me three times”; <verse eid="LUK 22:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="LUK 22:62"/>and Peter having gone outside, wept bitterly. <verse eid="LUK 22:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="LUK 22:63"/>And the men who were holding Jesus were mocking Him, beating [Him]; <verse eid="LUK 22:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="LUK 22:64"/>and having blindfolded Him, they were striking Him on the face, and were questioning Him, saying, “Prophesy who he is who struck You?” <verse eid="LUK 22:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="LUK 22:65"/>And many other things, slandering, they spoke in regard to Him. <verse eid="LUK 22:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="LUK 22:66"/>And when it became day there was gathered together the eldership of the people, chief priests also, and scribes, and they led Him up to their own Sanhedrin, <verse eid="LUK 22:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="LUK 22:67"/>saying, “If You are the Christ, tell us.” And He said to them, “If I may tell you, you will not believe; <verse eid="LUK 22:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="LUK 22:68"/>and if I also question [you], you will not answer Me or send Me away; <verse eid="LUK 22:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="LUK 22:69"/>from now on, there will be the Son of Man sitting on the right hand of the power of God.” <verse eid="LUK 22:69"/><verse number="70" style="v" sid="LUK 22:70"/>And they all said, “You, then, are the Son of God?” And He said to them, “You say [it], because I AM”; <verse eid="LUK 22:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="LUK 22:71"/>and they said, “What need do we have yet of testimony? For we ourselves heard [it] from His mouth.”<verse eid="LUK 22:71"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="LUK 23"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 23:1"/>And having risen, the whole multitude of them led Him to Pilate, <verse eid="LUK 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 23:2"/>and began to accuse Him, saying, “We found this One perverting the nation, and forbidding to give tribute to Caesar, saying Himself to be Christ, a king.” <verse eid="LUK 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 23:3"/>And Pilate questioned Him, saying, “You are the King of the Jews?” And He answering him, said, “You say [it].” <verse eid="LUK 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 23:4"/>And Pilate said to the chief priests and the multitude, “I find no fault in this Man”; <verse eid="LUK 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 23:5"/>and they were the more urgent, saying, “He stirs up the people, teaching throughout the whole of Judea—having begun from Galilee—to this place.” <verse eid="LUK 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 23:6"/>And Pilate having heard of Galilee, questioned if the Man is a Galilean, <verse eid="LUK 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 23:7"/>and having known that He is from the jurisdiction of Herod, he sent Him back to Herod, he also being in Jerusalem in those days. <verse eid="LUK 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 23:8"/>And Herod rejoiced exceedingly having seen Jesus, for he was wishing to see Him for a long [time], because of hearing many things about Him, and he was hoping to see some sign done by Him, <verse eid="LUK 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 23:9"/>and was questioning Him in many words, and He answered him nothing. <verse eid="LUK 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 23:10"/>And the chief priests and the scribes stood vehemently accusing Him, <verse eid="LUK 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 23:11"/>and Herod with his soldiers having set Him at nothing, and having mocked, having cast radiant apparel around Him, sent Him back to Pilate, <verse eid="LUK 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 23:12"/>and both Pilate and Herod became friends with one another on that day, for they were previously at enmity between themselves. <verse eid="LUK 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 23:13"/>And Pilate having called together the chief priests, and the rulers, and the people, <verse eid="LUK 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 23:14"/>said to them, “You brought this Man to me as perverting the people, and behold, I having examined [Him] before you, found no fault in this Man in those things you bring forward against Him; <verse eid="LUK 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 23:15"/>no, neither Herod, for he sent Him back to us, and behold, nothing worthy of death is having been done by Him; <verse eid="LUK 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 23:16"/>having corrected, therefore, I will release Him,” <verse eid="LUK 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 23:17"/><char style="bd">[[</char>for it was necessary for him to release to them one at every celebration,<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="LUK 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 23:18"/>and they cried out—the whole multitude—saying, “Away with this One, and release Barabbas to us,” <verse eid="LUK 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 23:19"/>who had been cast into prison, because of a certain sedition made in the city, and murder. <verse eid="LUK 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 23:20"/>Pilate again then—wishing to release Jesus—called to them, <verse eid="LUK 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 23:21"/>but they were calling out, saying, “Crucify! Crucify Him!” <verse eid="LUK 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 23:22"/>And he said to them a third time, “Why, what evil did He do? I found no cause of death in Him; having corrected Him, then, I will release [Him].” <verse eid="LUK 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 23:23"/>And they were pressing with loud voices asking Him to be crucified, and their voices, and those of the chief priests, were prevailing, <verse eid="LUK 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 23:24"/>and Pilate gave judgment for their request being done, <verse eid="LUK 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 23:25"/>and he released him who because of sedition and murder has been cast into the prison, whom they were asking for, and he gave up Jesus to their will. <verse eid="LUK 23:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 23:26"/>And as they led Him away, having taken hold on Simon, a certain Cyrenian, coming from the field, they put the cross on him to carry [it] behind Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 23:27"/>And a great multitude of the people were following Him, and of women, who also were beating themselves and lamenting Him, <verse eid="LUK 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 23:28"/>and Jesus having turned to them, said, “Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep for Me, but weep for yourselves and for your children; <verse eid="LUK 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 23:29"/>for behold, days come in which they will say, Blessed the barren, and wombs that did not bear, and breasts that did not give suck; <verse eid="LUK 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 23:30"/>then they will begin to say to the mountains, Fall on us, and to the hills, Cover us; <verse eid="LUK 23:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 23:31"/>for if they do these things in the green tree, what may happen in the dry?” <verse eid="LUK 23:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 23:32"/>And there were also others—two evildoers—with Him, to be put to death; <verse eid="LUK 23:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 23:33"/>and when they came to the place that is called “[Place] of [the] Skull,” there they crucified Him and the evildoers, one on the right hand and one on the left. <verse eid="LUK 23:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 23:34"/>And Jesus said, “Father, forgive them, for they have not known what they do”; and parting His garments they cast a lot. <verse eid="LUK 23:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 23:35"/>And the people were standing, looking on, and the rulers were also sneering with them, saying, “He saved others, let Him save Himself, if this be the Christ, the Chosen One of God.” <verse eid="LUK 23:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 23:36"/>And the soldiers were also mocking Him, coming near and offering vinegar to Him, <verse eid="LUK 23:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 23:37"/>and saying, “If You are the King of the Jews, save Yourself.” <verse eid="LUK 23:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 23:38"/>And there was also an inscription written over Him <char style="bd">[[</char>in letters of Greek, and Latin, and Hebrew<char style="bd">]]</char>: “THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS.” <verse eid="LUK 23:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 23:39"/>And one of the evildoers who were hanged was slandering Him, saying, “If You are the Christ, save Yourself and us.” <verse eid="LUK 23:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 23:40"/>And the other answering, was rebuking him, saying, “Do you not even fear God, that you are in the same judgment? <verse eid="LUK 23:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 23:41"/>And we indeed justly, for we are receiving back [things] worthy of what we did, but this One did nothing out of place”; <verse eid="LUK 23:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 23:42"/>and he said to Jesus, “Remember me, Lord, when You may come in Your kingdom”; <verse eid="LUK 23:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 23:43"/>and Jesus said to him, “Truly I say to you, today you will be with Me in Paradise.” <verse eid="LUK 23:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 23:44"/>And it was, as it were, the sixth hour, and darkness came over all the land until the ninth hour, <verse eid="LUK 23:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 23:45"/>and the sun was darkened, and the veil of the temple was torn in the middle, <verse eid="LUK 23:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 23:46"/>and having cried with a loud voice, Jesus said, “Father, into Your hands I commit My spirit”; now having said this, He breathed His last. <verse eid="LUK 23:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 23:47"/>And the centurion having seen what was done, glorified God, saying, “Truly this Man was righteous”; <verse eid="LUK 23:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 23:48"/>and all the multitudes having come together to this sight, beholding the things that came to pass, turned back striking their breasts; <verse eid="LUK 23:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 23:49"/>and all His acquaintances stood far off, and women who followed Him from Galilee, beholding these things. <verse eid="LUK 23:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 23:50"/>And behold, a man, by name Joseph, being a counselor, a man good and righteous, <verse eid="LUK 23:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 23:51"/>from Arimathea, a city of the Jews, who also himself was expecting the Kingdom of God, he was not consenting to their counsel and deed, <verse eid="LUK 23:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 23:52"/>he having gone near to Pilate, asked for the body of Jesus, <verse eid="LUK 23:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 23:53"/>and having taken it down, he wrapped it in fine linen, and placed it in a hewn out tomb, where no one was yet laid. <verse eid="LUK 23:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 23:54"/>And it was [the] Day of Preparation, and Sabbath was approaching, <verse eid="LUK 23:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 23:55"/>and the women who also have come with Him out of Galilee having followed after, beheld the tomb, and how His body was placed, <verse eid="LUK 23:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 23:56"/>and having turned back, they made ready spices and ointments, and on the Sabbath, indeed, they rested, according to the command.<verse eid="LUK 23:56"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="LUK 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 24:1"/>And on the first [day] of the weeks, at early dawn, they came to the tomb, carrying the spices they made ready, and certain [others] with them, <verse eid="LUK 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 24:2"/>and they found the stone having been rolled away from the tomb, <verse eid="LUK 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 24:3"/>and having gone in, they did not find the body of the Lord Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 24:4"/>And it came to pass, while they are perplexed about this, that behold, two men stood by them in clothing—flashing [with light]; <verse eid="LUK 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 24:5"/>and on their having become afraid, and having inclined the face to the earth, they said to them, “Why do you seek the living with the dead? <verse eid="LUK 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 24:6"/>He is not here, but was raised; remember how He spoke to you, being yet in Galilee, <verse eid="LUK 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 24:7"/>saying, It is necessary for the Son of Man to be delivered up into the hands of sinful men, and to be crucified, and to rise again [on] the third day.” <verse eid="LUK 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 24:8"/>And they remembered His sayings, <verse eid="LUK 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 24:9"/>and having turned back from the tomb, told all these things to the Eleven, and to all the rest. <verse eid="LUK 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 24:10"/>And it was Mary the Magdalene, and Joanna, and Mary of James, and the other women with them, who told these things to the apostles, <verse eid="LUK 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 24:11"/>and their sayings appeared before them as idle talk, and they were not believing them. <verse eid="LUK 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 24:12"/>And Peter having risen, ran to the tomb, and having stooped down he sees the linen clothes lying alone, and he went away to his own home, wondering at that having come to pass. <verse eid="LUK 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 24:13"/>And behold, two of them were going on during that day to a village, being sixty stadia distant from Jerusalem, the name of which [is] Emmaus, <verse eid="LUK 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 24:14"/>and they were conversing with one another about all these things that have happened. <verse eid="LUK 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 24:15"/>And it came to pass in their conversing and reasoning together, that Jesus Himself, having come near, was going on with them, <verse eid="LUK 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 24:16"/>and their eyes were restrained so as not to know Him, <verse eid="LUK 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 24:17"/>and He said to them, “What [are] these words that you exchange with one another, walking, and you are sad?” <verse eid="LUK 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 24:18"/>And one, whose name was Cleopas, answering, said to Him, “Are You alone visiting Jerusalem and have not known the things having come to pass in it in these days?” <verse eid="LUK 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 24:19"/>And He said to them, “What things?” And they said to Him, “The things about Jesus of Nazareth, who became a man—a prophet—powerful in deed and word, before God and all the people, <verse eid="LUK 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 24:20"/>how also the chief priests and our rulers delivered Him up to a judgment of death, and crucified Him; <verse eid="LUK 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 24:21"/>and we were hoping that it is He who is about to redeem Israel, and also with all these things, this third day is passing today since these things happened. <verse eid="LUK 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 24:22"/>And certain of our women also astonished us, coming early to the tomb, <verse eid="LUK 24:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 24:23"/>and having not found His body, they came, saying to have also seen an apparition of messengers who say He is alive, <verse eid="LUK 24:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 24:24"/>and certain of those with us went away to the tomb, and found [it] so, even as the women said, and they did not see Him.” <verse eid="LUK 24:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 24:25"/>And He said to them, “O inconsiderate and slow in heart to believe on all that the prophets spoke! <verse eid="LUK 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 24:26"/>Was it not necessary [for] the Christ to suffer these things, and to enter into His glory?” <verse eid="LUK 24:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 24:27"/>And having begun from Moses, and from all the Prophets, He was expounding to them in all the Writings the things about Himself. <verse eid="LUK 24:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 24:28"/>And they came near to the village to where they were going, and He made an appearance of going on further, <verse eid="LUK 24:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 24:29"/>and they constrained Him, saying, “Remain with us, for it is toward evening,” and the day declined, and He went in to remain with them. <verse eid="LUK 24:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 24:30"/>And it came to pass, in His reclining with them, having taken the bread, He blessed, and having broken, He was giving to them, <verse eid="LUK 24:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 24:31"/>and their eyes were opened, and they recognized Him, and He became unseen by them. <verse eid="LUK 24:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 24:32"/>And they said to one another, “Was our heart not burning within us as He was speaking to us in the way, and as He was opening the Writings up to us?” <verse eid="LUK 24:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 24:33"/>And they, having risen up the same hour, turned back to Jerusalem, and found the Eleven gathered together, and those with them, <verse eid="LUK 24:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 24:34"/>saying, “The Lord was indeed raised, and was seen by Simon”; <verse eid="LUK 24:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 24:35"/>and they were expounding the things in the way, and how He was made known to them in the breaking of the bread, <verse eid="LUK 24:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 24:36"/>and as they are speaking these things, Jesus Himself stood in the midst of them, and says to them, “Peace to you”; <verse eid="LUK 24:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 24:37"/>and being amazed, and becoming frightened, they were thinking themselves to see a spirit. <verse eid="LUK 24:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 24:38"/>And He said to them, “Why are you troubled? And why do reasonings come up in your hearts? <verse eid="LUK 24:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 24:39"/>See My hands and My feet, that I am He; handle Me and see, because a spirit does not have flesh and bones as you see Me having.” <verse eid="LUK 24:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 24:40"/>And having said this, He showed the hands and the feet to them, <verse eid="LUK 24:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 24:41"/>and while they are not believing from the joy, and wondering, He said to them, “Do you have anything here to eat?” <verse eid="LUK 24:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 24:42"/>And they gave to Him part of a broiled fish, and of a honeycomb, <verse eid="LUK 24:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 24:43"/>and having taken, He ate before them, <verse eid="LUK 24:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 24:44"/>and He said to them, “These [are] the words that I spoke to you, being yet with you, that it is necessary to be fulfilled all the things that are written in the Law of Moses, and the Prophets, and the Psalms, about Me.” <verse eid="LUK 24:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 24:45"/>Then He opened up their understanding to understand the Writings, <verse eid="LUK 24:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 24:46"/>and He said to them, “Thus it has been written, and thus it was necessary [for] the Christ to suffer, and to rise out of the dead [on] the third day, <verse eid="LUK 24:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 24:47"/>and conversion and forgiveness of sins is to be proclaimed in His Name to all the nations, beginning from Jerusalem: <verse eid="LUK 24:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 24:48"/>and you are witnesses of these things. <verse eid="LUK 24:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 24:49"/>And behold, I send the promise of My Father on you, but you—abide in the city of Jerusalem until you are clothed with power from on high.” <verse eid="LUK 24:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 24:50"/>And He led them forth outside—to Bethany, and having lifted up His hands He blessed them, <verse eid="LUK 24:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 24:51"/>and it came to pass, in His blessing them, He was parted from them, and was carried up into Heaven; <verse eid="LUK 24:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 24:52"/>and they, having worshiped Him, turned back to Jerusalem with great joy, <verse eid="LUK 24:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 24:53"/>and were continually in the temple, praising and blessing God. Amen.<verse eid="LUK 24:53"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 24"/>
</usx>
