<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="MAT" style="id">- Literal Standard Version</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Matthew</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Gospel of Matthew</para>
  <para style="toc2">Matthew</para>
  <para style="toc3">Mat</para>
  <para style="mt">Matthew</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="MAT 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 1:1"/>[The] scroll of the birth of Jesus Christ, Son of David, Son of Abraham. <verse eid="MAT 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 1:2"/>Abraham begot Isaac, and Isaac begot Jacob, and Jacob begot Judah and his brothers, <verse eid="MAT 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 1:3"/>and Judah begot Perez and Zerah of Tamar, and Perez begot Hezron, and Hezron begot Ram, <verse eid="MAT 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 1:4"/>and Ram begot Amminadab, and Amminadab begot Nahshon, and Nahshon begot Salmon, <verse eid="MAT 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 1:5"/>and Salmon begot Boaz of Rahab, and Boaz begot Obed of Ruth, and Obed begot Jesse, <verse eid="MAT 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 1:6"/>and Jesse begot David the king. And David the king begot Solomon, of her [who had been] Uriah’s, <verse eid="MAT 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 1:7"/>and Solomon begot Rehoboam, and Rehoboam begot Abijah, and Abijah begot Asa, <verse eid="MAT 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 1:8"/>and Asa begot Jehoshaphat, and Jehoshaphat begot Joram, and Joram begot Uzziah, <verse eid="MAT 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 1:9"/>and Uzziah begot Jotham, and Jotham begot Ahaz, and Ahaz begot Hezekiah, <verse eid="MAT 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 1:10"/>and Hezekiah begot Manasseh, and Manasseh begot Amon, and Amon begot Josiah, <verse eid="MAT 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 1:11"/>and Josiah begot Jeconiah and his brothers, at the Babylonian removal. <verse eid="MAT 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 1:12"/>And after the Babylonian removal, Jeconiah begot Shealtiel, and Shealtiel begot Zerubbabel, <verse eid="MAT 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 1:13"/>and Zerubbabel begot Abiud, and Abiud begot Eliakim, and Eliakim begot Azor, <verse eid="MAT 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 1:14"/>and Azor begot Sadok, and Sadok begot Achim, and Achim begot Eliud, <verse eid="MAT 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 1:15"/>and Eliud begot Eleazar, and Eleazar begot Matthan, and Matthan begot Jacob, <verse eid="MAT 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 1:16"/>and Jacob begot Joseph, the husband of Mary, of whom was begotten Jesus, who is named Christ. <verse eid="MAT 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 1:17"/>All the generations, therefore, from Abraham to David [are] fourteen generations, and from David to the Babylonian removal fourteen generations, and from the Babylonian removal to the Christ, fourteen generations. <verse eid="MAT 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 1:18"/>And of Jesus Christ, the birth was thus: for His mother Mary having been betrothed to Joseph, before their coming together she was found to have conceived from the Holy Spirit, <verse eid="MAT 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 1:19"/>and her husband Joseph being righteous, and not willing to make her an example, resolved to send her away privately. <verse eid="MAT 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 1:20"/>And on his thinking of these things, behold, a messenger of the LORD appeared to him in a dream, saying, “Joseph, son of David, you may not fear to receive your wife Mary, for that which was begotten in her is of [the] Holy Spirit, <verse eid="MAT 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 1:21"/>and she will bring forth a Son, and you will call His Name Jesus, for He will save His people from their sins.” <verse eid="MAT 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 1:22"/>And all this has come to pass, that it may be fulfilled that was spoken by the LORD through the prophet, saying, <verse eid="MAT 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 1:23"/>“Behold, the virgin will conceive, and she will bring forth a Son, and they will call His Name Emmanuel,” which is, being interpreted, “God with us.” <verse eid="MAT 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 1:24"/>And Joseph, having risen from sleep, did as the messenger of the LORD directed him, and received his wife, <verse eid="MAT 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 1:25"/>and did not know her until she brought forth her Son—the firstborn, and he called His Name Jesus.<verse eid="MAT 1:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="MAT 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 2:1"/>And Jesus having been born in Beth-Lehem of Judea, in the days of Herod the king, behold, magi from the east came to Jerusalem, <verse eid="MAT 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 2:2"/>saying, “Where is He who was born King of the Jews? For we saw His star in the east, and we came to worship Him.” <verse eid="MAT 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 2:3"/>And Herod the king having heard, was stirred, and all Jerusalem with him, <verse eid="MAT 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 2:4"/>and having gathered all the chief priests and scribes of the people, he was inquiring from them where the Christ is born. <verse eid="MAT 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 2:5"/>And they said to him, “In Beth-Lehem of Judea, for thus it has been written through the prophet: <verse eid="MAT 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 2:6"/>And you, Beth-Lehem, the land of Judah, you are by no means the least among the leaders of Judah, for out of you will come One leading, who will feed My people Israel.” <verse eid="MAT 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 2:7"/>Then Herod, having called the magi privately, inquired exactly from them the time of the appearing star, <verse eid="MAT 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 2:8"/>and having sent them to Beth-Lehem, he said, “Having gone—inquire exactly for the Child, and whenever you may have found, bring me back word, that I also having come may worship Him.” <verse eid="MAT 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 2:9"/>And they, having heard the king, departed, and behold, the star, that they saw in the east, went before them, until, having come, it stood over where the Child was. <verse eid="MAT 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 2:10"/>And having seen the star, they rejoiced with exceedingly great joy, <verse eid="MAT 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 2:11"/>and having come into the house, they found the Child with His mother Mary, and having fallen down they worshiped Him, and having opened their treasures, they presented to Him gifts, gold, and frankincense, and myrrh, <verse eid="MAT 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 2:12"/>and having been divinely warned in a dream not to return to Herod, through another way they withdrew to their own region. <verse eid="MAT 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 2:13"/>And on their having withdrawn, behold, a messenger of the LORD appears in a dream to Joseph, saying, “Having risen, take the Child and His mother, and flee to Egypt, and be there until I may speak to you, for Herod is about to seek the Child to destroy Him.” <verse eid="MAT 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 2:14"/>And he, having risen, took the Child and His mother by night, and withdrew to Egypt, <verse eid="MAT 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 2:15"/>and he was there until the death of Herod, that it might be fulfilled that was spoken by the LORD through the prophet, saying, “Out of Egypt I called My Son.” <verse eid="MAT 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 2:16"/>Then Herod, having seen that he was deceived by the magi, was very angry, and having sent forth, he slew all the male children in Beth-Lehem, and in all its borders, from two years and under, according to the time that he inquired exactly from the magi. <verse eid="MAT 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 2:17"/>Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by Jeremiah the prophet, saying, <verse eid="MAT 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 2:18"/>“A voice in Ramah was heard—weeping and much mourning—Rachel weeping [for] her children, and she would not be comforted because they are not.” <verse eid="MAT 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 2:19"/>And Herod having died, behold, a messenger of the LORD appears in a dream to Joseph in Egypt, <verse eid="MAT 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 2:20"/>saying, “Having risen, take the Child and His mother, and be going to the land of Israel, for they have died—those seeking the life of the Child.” <verse eid="MAT 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 2:21"/>And he, having risen, took the Child and His mother, and came to the land of Israel, <verse eid="MAT 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 2:22"/>and having heard that Archelaus reigns over Judea instead of his father Herod, he was afraid to go there, and having been divinely warned in a dream, he withdrew to the parts of Galilee, <verse eid="MAT 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 2:23"/>and coming, he dwelt in a city named Nazareth, that it might be fulfilled that was spoken through the Prophets, that “He will be called a Nazarene.”<verse eid="MAT 2:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="MAT 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 3:1"/>And in those days John the Immerser comes, proclaiming in the wilderness of Judea, <verse eid="MAT 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 3:2"/>and saying, “Convert, for the kingdom of the heavens has come near,” <verse eid="MAT 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 3:3"/>for this is he having been spoken of by Isaiah the prophet, saying, “A voice of one crying in the wilderness: Prepare the way of the LORD, || Make His paths straight.” <verse eid="MAT 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 3:4"/>And this John had his clothing of camel’s hair, and a girdle of skin around his loins, and his nourishment was locusts and honey of the field. <verse eid="MAT 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 3:5"/>Then were going forth to him Jerusalem, and all Judea, and all the region around the Jordan, <verse eid="MAT 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 3:6"/>and they were immersed in the Jordan by him, confessing their sins. <verse eid="MAT 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 3:7"/>And having seen many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming about his immersion, he said to them, “Brood of vipers! Who showed you to flee from the coming wrath? <verse eid="MAT 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 3:8"/>Bear, therefore, fruits worthy of conversion, <verse eid="MAT 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 3:9"/>and do not think to say in yourselves, We have a father—Abraham, for I say to you that God is able to raise children to Abraham out of these stones, <verse eid="MAT 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 3:10"/>and now also, the axe is laid to the root of the trees, therefore, every tree not bearing good fruit is cut down, and is cast into fire. <verse eid="MAT 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 3:11"/>I indeed immerse you in water for conversion, but He who is coming after me is mightier than I, of whom I am not worthy to carry the sandals, He will immerse you in the Holy Spirit and fire, <verse eid="MAT 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 3:12"/>whose fan [is] in His hand, and He will thoroughly cleanse His floor, and will gather His wheat into the storehouse, but He will burn the chaff with unquenchable fire.” <verse eid="MAT 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 3:13"/>Then Jesus comes from Galilee to John at the Jordan, to be immersed by him, <verse eid="MAT 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 3:14"/>but John was forbidding Him, saying, “I have need to be immersed by You—and You come to me?” <verse eid="MAT 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 3:15"/>But Jesus answering said to him, “Permit [it] now, for thus it is fitting to us to fulfill all righteousness,” then he permits Him. <verse eid="MAT 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 3:16"/>And having been immersed, Jesus immediately went up from the water, and behold, the heavens were opened to Him, and He saw the Spirit of God descending as a dove, and coming on Him, <verse eid="MAT 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 3:17"/>and behold, a voice out of the heavens, saying, “This is My Son, the Beloved, in whom I delighted.”<verse eid="MAT 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="MAT 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 4:1"/>Then Jesus was led up to the wilderness by the Spirit, to be tempted by the Devil, <verse eid="MAT 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 4:2"/>and having fasted forty days and forty nights, afterward He hungered. <verse eid="MAT 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 4:3"/>And the tempting [one], having come to Him, said, “If You are the Son of God—speak that these stones may become loaves.” <verse eid="MAT 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 4:4"/>But He answering said, “It has been written: Man does not live on bread alone, but on every word coming forth from the mouth of God.” <verse eid="MAT 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 4:5"/>Then the Devil takes Him to the [holy] city, and sets Him on the pinnacle of the temple, <verse eid="MAT 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 4:6"/>and says to Him, “If You are the Son of God—cast Yourself down, for it has been written that, His messengers He will charge concerning you, and on hands they will bear you up, that you may not dash your foot on a stone.” <verse eid="MAT 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 4:7"/>Jesus said to him again, “It has been written: You will not tempt the LORD your God.” <verse eid="MAT 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 4:8"/>Again the Devil takes Him to a very high mountain, and shows to Him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory, <verse eid="MAT 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 4:9"/>and says to Him, “All these I will give to You, if falling down You may worship me.” <verse eid="MAT 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 4:10"/>Then Jesus says to him, “Go—Satan, for it has been written: You will worship the LORD your God, and Him only will you serve.” <verse eid="MAT 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 4:11"/>Then the Devil leaves Him, and behold, messengers came and were ministering to Him. <verse eid="MAT 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 4:12"/>And Jesus, having heard that John was delivered up, withdrew to Galilee, <verse eid="MAT 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 4:13"/>and having left Nazareth, having come, He dwelt at Capernaum that is by the sea, in the borders of Zebulun and Naphtali, <verse eid="MAT 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 4:14"/>that it might be fulfilled that was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying, <verse eid="MAT 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 4:15"/>“Land of Zebulun and land of Naphtali, way of the sea, beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the nations! <verse eid="MAT 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 4:16"/>The people that is sitting in darkness saw a great light, and to those sitting in a region and shadow of death—light arose to them.” <verse eid="MAT 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 4:17"/>From that time Jesus began to proclaim and to say, “Convert, for the kingdom of the heavens has come near.” <verse eid="MAT 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 4:18"/>And Jesus, walking by the Sea of Galilee, saw two brothers, Simon named Peter and his brother Andrew, casting a drag into the sea—for they were fishers— <verse eid="MAT 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 4:19"/>and He says to them, “Come after Me, and I will make you fishers of men,” <verse eid="MAT 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 4:20"/>and they, immediately, having left the nets, followed Him. <verse eid="MAT 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 4:21"/>And having advanced from there, He saw two other brothers, James of Zebedee, and his brother John, in the boat with their father Zebedee, refitting their nets, and He called them, <verse eid="MAT 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 4:22"/>and they, immediately, having left the boat and their father, followed Him. <verse eid="MAT 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 4:23"/>And Jesus was going in all of Galilee teaching in their synagogues, and proclaiming the good news of the kingdom, and healing every disease and every sickness among the people, <verse eid="MAT 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 4:24"/>and His fame went forth to all Syria, and they brought to Him all the ill having manifold oppressing diseases and torments—and demoniacs, and lunatics, and paralytics—and He healed them. <verse eid="MAT 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 4:25"/>And there followed Him many multitudes from Galilee, and Decapolis, and Jerusalem, and Judea, and beyond the Jordan.<verse eid="MAT 4:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="MAT 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 5:1"/>And having seen the multitudes, He went up to the mountain, and He having sat down, His disciples came to Him, <verse eid="MAT 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 5:2"/>and having opened His mouth, He was teaching them, saying, <verse eid="MAT 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 5:3"/>“Blessed the poor in spirit—because theirs is the kingdom of the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 5:4"/>Blessed the mourning—because they will be comforted. <verse eid="MAT 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 5:5"/>Blessed the meek—because they will inherit the land. <verse eid="MAT 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 5:6"/>Blessed those hungering and thirsting for righteousness—because they will be filled. <verse eid="MAT 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 5:7"/>Blessed the kind—because they will find kindness. <verse eid="MAT 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 5:8"/>Blessed the clean in heart—because they will see God. <verse eid="MAT 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 5:9"/>Blessed the peacemakers—because they will be called sons of God. <verse eid="MAT 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 5:10"/>Blessed those persecuted for righteousness’ sake—because theirs is the kingdom of the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 5:11"/>Blessed are you whenever they may reproach you, and may persecute, and may say any evil thing against you falsely for My sake— <verse eid="MAT 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 5:12"/>rejoice and be glad, because your reward [is] great in the heavens, for thus they persecuted the prophets who were before you. <verse eid="MAT 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 5:13"/>You are the salt of the earth, but if the salt may lose savor, in what will it be salted? It is good for nothing from now on, except to be cast outside, and to be trodden down by men. <verse eid="MAT 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 5:14"/>You are the light of the world, a city set on a mountain is not able to be hid; <verse eid="MAT 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 5:15"/>nor do they light a lamp and put it under the measure, but on the lampstand, and it shines to all those in the house; <verse eid="MAT 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 5:16"/>so let your light shine before men, that they may see your good works, and may glorify your Father who [is] in the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 5:17"/>Do not suppose that I came to throw down the Law or the Prophets—I did not come to throw down, but to fulfill; <verse eid="MAT 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 5:18"/>for truly I say to you, until the heaven and the earth may pass away, one iota or one tittle may not pass away from the Law, until all may come to pass. <verse eid="MAT 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 5:19"/>Therefore whoever may loose one of these commands—the least—and may teach men so, he will be called least in the kingdom of the heavens, but whoever may do and may teach [them], he will be called great in the kingdom of the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 5:20"/>For I say to you that if your righteousness may not abound above that of the scribes and Pharisees, you may not enter into the kingdom of the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 5:21"/>You heard that it was said to the ancients: You will not murder, and whoever may murder will be in danger of the judgment; <verse eid="MAT 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 5:22"/>but I say to you that everyone who is angry at his brother without cause will be in danger of the judgment, and whoever may say to his brother, Stupid, will be in danger of the Sanhedrin, and whoever may say, Moron, will be in danger of the Gehenna of fire. <verse eid="MAT 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 5:23"/>If, therefore, you may bring your gift to the altar, and there may remember that your brother has anything against you, <verse eid="MAT 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 5:24"/>leave there your gift before the altar, and go—first be reconciled to your brother, and then having come, bring your gift. <verse eid="MAT 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 5:25"/>Be agreeing with your opponent quickly, while you are in the way with him, that the opponent may not deliver you to the judge, and the judge may deliver you to the officer, and you may be cast into prison; <verse eid="MAT 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 5:26"/>truly I say to you, you may not come forth from there until you may pay the last penny. <verse eid="MAT 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 5:27"/>You heard that it was said to the ancients: You will not commit adultery; <verse eid="MAT 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 5:28"/>but I say to you that everyone who is looking on a woman to desire her, already committed adultery with her in his heart. <verse eid="MAT 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 5:29"/>But if your right eye causes you to stumble, pluck it out and cast from you, for it is good to you that one of your members may perish, and not your whole body be cast into Gehenna. <verse eid="MAT 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 5:30"/>And if your right hand causes you to stumble, cut it off, and cast from you, for it is good to you that one of your members may perish, and not your whole body be cast into Gehenna. <verse eid="MAT 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 5:31"/>And it was said that, Whoever may put away his wife, let him give to her a writing of divorce; <verse eid="MAT 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 5:32"/>but I say to you that whoever may put away his wife, except for the matter of whoredom, makes her to commit adultery; and whoever may marry her who has been put away commits adultery. <verse eid="MAT 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 5:33"/>Again, you heard that it was said to the ancients: You will not swear falsely, but you will pay to the LORD your oaths; <verse eid="MAT 5:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 5:34"/>but I say to you not to swear at all; neither by Heaven, because it is the throne of God, <verse eid="MAT 5:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 5:35"/>nor by the earth, because it is His footstool, nor by Jerusalem, because it is [the] city of [the] great King, <verse eid="MAT 5:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 5:36"/>nor may you swear by your head, because you are not able to make one hair white or black; <verse eid="MAT 5:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 5:37"/>but let your word be, Yes, Yes, No, No, and that which is more than these is of the evil [one]. <verse eid="MAT 5:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 5:38"/>You heard that it was said: Eye for eye, and tooth for tooth; <verse eid="MAT 5:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 5:39"/>but I say to you not to resist the evil, but whoever will slap you on your right cheek, turn to him also the other; <verse eid="MAT 5:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 5:40"/>and whoever is willing to take you to law, and to take your coat—also permit to him the cloak. <verse eid="MAT 5:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 5:41"/>And whoever will impress you one mile, go with him two; <verse eid="MAT 5:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 5:42"/>to him who is asking of you be giving, and him who is willing to borrow from you, you may not turn away. <verse eid="MAT 5:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 5:43"/>You heard that it was said: You will love your neighbor, and will hate your enemy; <verse eid="MAT 5:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 5:44"/>but I say to you, love your enemies, bless those cursing you, do good to those hating you, and pray for those accusing you falsely, and persecuting you, <verse eid="MAT 5:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 5:45"/>that you may be sons of your Father in the heavens, because He causes His sun to rise on evil and good, and He sends rain on righteous and unrighteous. <verse eid="MAT 5:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 5:46"/>For if you may love those loving you, what reward do you have? Do the tax collectors not also do the same? <verse eid="MAT 5:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MAT 5:47"/>And if you may greet your brothers only, what do you do abundant? Do the nations not also do so? <verse eid="MAT 5:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MAT 5:48"/>You will therefore be perfect, as your Father who [is] in the heavens is perfect.”<verse eid="MAT 5:48"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="MAT 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 6:1"/>“Take heed not to do your kindness before men, to be seen by them, and if not—you have no reward from your Father who [is] in the heavens; <verse eid="MAT 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 6:2"/>whenever, therefore, you may do kindness, you may not sound a trumpet before you as the hypocrites do, in the synagogues, and in the streets, that they may have glory from men; truly I say to you, they have their reward! <verse eid="MAT 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 6:3"/>But you, doing kindness, do not let your left hand know what your right hand does, <verse eid="MAT 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 6:4"/>that your kindness may be in secret, and your Father who is seeing in secret will reward you Himself. <verse eid="MAT 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 6:5"/>And when you may pray, you will not be as the hypocrites, because they cherish to pray standing in the synagogues and in the corners of the broad places, that they may be seen of men; truly I say to you that they have their reward. <verse eid="MAT 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 6:6"/>But you, when you may pray, go into your chamber, and having shut your door, pray to your Father who [is] in secret, and your Father who is seeing in secret will reward you. <verse eid="MAT 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 6:7"/>And—praying—you may not use vain repetitions like the nations, for they think that in their speaking much they will be heard, <verse eid="MAT 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 6:8"/>therefore do not be like them, for your Father knows those things that you have need of before your asking Him; <verse eid="MAT 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 6:9"/>therefore pray thus: Our Father who [is] in the heavens, hallowed be Your Name. <verse eid="MAT 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 6:10"/>Your kingdom come, Your will come to pass, as in Heaven also on the earth. <verse eid="MAT 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 6:11"/>Give us today our appointed bread. <verse eid="MAT 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 6:12"/>And forgive us our debts, as we also forgive our debtors. <verse eid="MAT 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 6:13"/>And may You not lead us into temptation, but deliver us from the evil [one], because Yours is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory—for all ages. Amen. <verse eid="MAT 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 6:14"/>For if you may forgive men their trespasses He also will forgive you—your Father who [is] in the heavens; <verse eid="MAT 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 6:15"/>but if you may not forgive men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses. <verse eid="MAT 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 6:16"/>And when you may fast, do not be as the hypocrites, of sour countenances, for they disfigure their faces, that they may appear to men fasting; truly I say to you that they have their reward. <verse eid="MAT 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 6:17"/>But you, fasting, anoint your head, and wash your face, <verse eid="MAT 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 6:18"/>that you may not appear to men fasting, but to your Father who [is] in secret, and your Father, who is seeing in secret, will reward you. <verse eid="MAT 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 6:19"/>Do not treasure up to yourselves treasures on the earth, where moth and rust disfigure, and where thieves break through and steal, <verse eid="MAT 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 6:20"/>but treasure up to yourselves treasures in Heaven, where neither moth nor rust disfigure, and where thieves do not break through nor steal, <verse eid="MAT 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 6:21"/>for where your treasure is, there will your heart be also. <verse eid="MAT 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 6:22"/>The lamp of the body is the eye, if, therefore, your eye may be perfect, all your body will be enlightened, <verse eid="MAT 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 6:23"/>but if your eye may be evil, all your body will be dark; if, therefore, the light that [is] in you is darkness—the darkness, how great! <verse eid="MAT 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 6:24"/>None is able to serve two lords, for either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will hold to the one, and despise the other; you are not able to serve God and wealth. <verse eid="MAT 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 6:25"/>Because of this I say to you, do not be anxious for your life, what you may eat, and what you may drink, nor for your body, what you may put on. Is not life more than nourishment, and the body than clothing? <verse eid="MAT 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 6:26"/>Look to the birds of the sky, for they do not sow, nor reap, nor gather into storehouses, and your heavenly Father nourishes them; are you not much better than they? <verse eid="MAT 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 6:27"/>And who of you, being anxious, is able to add to his age one cubit? <verse eid="MAT 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 6:28"/>And why are you anxious about clothing? Consider well the lilies of the field; how do they grow? They do not labor, nor do they spin; <verse eid="MAT 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 6:29"/>and I say to you that not even Solomon in all his glory was clothed as one of these. <verse eid="MAT 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 6:30"/>And if the herb of the field, that today is, and tomorrow is cast into the furnace, God so clothes—not much more you, O you of little faith? <verse eid="MAT 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 6:31"/>Therefore you may not be anxious, saying, What may we eat? Or, What may we drink? Or, [With] what may we be clothed? <verse eid="MAT 6:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 6:32"/>For the nations seek for all these, for your heavenly Father knows that you have need of all these; <verse eid="MAT 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 6:33"/>but seek first the Kingdom of God and His righteousness, and all these will be added to you. <verse eid="MAT 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 6:34"/>Therefore do not be anxious for tomorrow, for tomorrow will be anxious for its own things; sufficient for the day [is] the evil of it.”<verse eid="MAT 6:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="MAT 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 7:1"/>“Do not judge, that you may not be judged, <verse eid="MAT 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 7:2"/>for in what judgment you judge, you will be judged, and in what measure you measure, it will be measured to you. <verse eid="MAT 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 7:3"/>And why do you behold the speck that [is] in your brother’s eye, and do not consider the beam that [is] in your own eye? <verse eid="MAT 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 7:4"/>Or, how will you say to your brother, Permit [that] I may cast out the speck from your eye, and behold, the beam [is] in your own eye? <verse eid="MAT 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 7:5"/>Hypocrite, first cast out the beam out of your own eye, and then you will see clearly to cast out the speck out of your brother’s eye. <verse eid="MAT 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 7:6"/>You may not give that which is [holy] to the dogs, nor cast your pearls before the pigs, that they may not trample them among their feet, and having turned—may tear you apart. <verse eid="MAT 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 7:7"/>Ask, and it will be given to you; seek, and you will find; knock, and it will be opened to you; <verse eid="MAT 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 7:8"/>for everyone who is asking receives, and he who is seeking finds, and to him who is knocking it will be opened. <verse eid="MAT 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 7:9"/>Or what man is of you, of whom, if his son may ask [for] a loaf—a stone will he present to him? <verse eid="MAT 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 7:10"/>And if he may ask [for] a fish—a serpent will he present to him? <verse eid="MAT 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 7:11"/>If, therefore, you being evil, have known to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father who [is] in the heavens give good things to those asking Him? <verse eid="MAT 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 7:12"/>All things, therefore, whatever you may will that men may be doing to you, so also do to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets. <verse eid="MAT 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 7:13"/>Go in through the narrow gate, because wide [is] the gate and broad the way that is leading to the destruction, and many are those going in through it; <verse eid="MAT 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 7:14"/>how narrow [is] the gate and compressed the way that is leading to life, and few are those finding it! <verse eid="MAT 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 7:15"/>But take heed of the false prophets who come to you in sheep’s clothing, and inwardly are ravenous wolves. <verse eid="MAT 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 7:16"/>From their fruits you will know them; do [men] gather grapes from thorns? Or figs from thistles? <verse eid="MAT 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 7:17"/>So every good tree yields good fruits, but the bad tree yields evil fruits. <verse eid="MAT 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 7:18"/>A good tree is not able to yield evil fruits, nor a bad tree to yield good fruits. <verse eid="MAT 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 7:19"/>Every tree not yielding good fruit is cut down and is cast into fire: <verse eid="MAT 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 7:20"/>therefore from their fruits you will know them. <verse eid="MAT 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 7:21"/>Not everyone who is saying to Me, Lord, Lord, will come into the kingdom of the heavens, but he who is doing the will of My Father who is in the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 7:22"/>Many will say to Me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in Your Name? And in Your Name cast out demons? And in Your Name done many mighty things? <verse eid="MAT 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 7:23"/>And then I will acknowledge to them, that—I never knew you, depart from Me you who are working lawlessness. <verse eid="MAT 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 7:24"/>Therefore, everyone who hears these words of Mine, and does them, I will liken him to a wise man who built his house on the rock; <verse eid="MAT 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 7:25"/>and the rain descended, and the streams came, and the winds blew, and they beat on that house, and it did not fall, for it had been founded on the rock. <verse eid="MAT 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 7:26"/>And everyone who is hearing these words of Mine, and is not doing them, will be likened to a foolish man who built his house on the sand; <verse eid="MAT 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 7:27"/>and the rain descended, and the streams came, and the winds blew, and they beat on that house, and it fell, and its fall was great.” <verse eid="MAT 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 7:28"/>And it came to pass, when Jesus finished these words, the multitudes were astonished at His teaching, <verse eid="MAT 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 7:29"/>for He was teaching them as having authority, and not as the scribes.<verse eid="MAT 7:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="MAT 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 8:1"/>And when He came down from the mountain, great multitudes followed Him, <verse eid="MAT 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 8:2"/>and behold, a leper having come, was prostrating to Him, saying, “Lord, if You are willing, You are able to cleanse me”; <verse eid="MAT 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 8:3"/>and having stretched forth the hand, Jesus touched him, saying, “I will, be cleansed,” and immediately his leprosy was cleansed. <verse eid="MAT 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 8:4"/>And Jesus says to him, “See, you may tell no one, but go, show yourself to the priest, and bring the gift that Moses commanded for a testimony to them.” <verse eid="MAT 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 8:5"/>And Jesus having entered into Capernaum, there came to Him a centurion calling on Him, <verse eid="MAT 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 8:6"/>and saying, “Lord, my young man has been laid in the house a paralytic, fearfully afflicted,” <verse eid="MAT 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 8:7"/>and Jesus says to him, “I, having come, will heal him.” <verse eid="MAT 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 8:8"/>And the centurion answering said, “Lord, I am not worthy that You may enter under my roof, but only say a word, and my servant will be healed; <verse eid="MAT 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 8:9"/>for I also am a man under authority, having under myself soldiers, and I say to this one, Go, and he goes, and to another, Be coming, and he comes, and to my servant, Do this, and he does [it].” <verse eid="MAT 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 8:10"/>And Jesus having heard, wondered, and said to those following, “Truly I say to you, not even in Israel have I found such great faith; <verse eid="MAT 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 8:11"/>and I say to you that many from east and west will come and recline with Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, in the kingdom of the heavens, <verse eid="MAT 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 8:12"/>but the sons of the kingdom will be cast forth into the outer darkness—there will be the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth.” <verse eid="MAT 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 8:13"/>And Jesus said to the centurion, “Go, and as you believed let it be to you”; and his young man was healed in that hour. <verse eid="MAT 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 8:14"/>And Jesus having come into the house of Peter, saw his mother-in-law laid, and fevered, <verse eid="MAT 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 8:15"/>and He touched her hand, and the fever left her, and she arose, and was ministering to them. <verse eid="MAT 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 8:16"/>And evening having come, they brought to Him many demoniacs, and He cast out the spirits with a word, and healed all who were ill, <verse eid="MAT 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 8:17"/>that it might be fulfilled that was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying, “He took our sicknesses Himself, and bore the diseases.” <verse eid="MAT 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 8:18"/>And Jesus having seen great multitudes around Him, commanded to depart to the other side; <verse eid="MAT 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 8:19"/>and a certain scribe having come, said to Him, “Teacher, I will follow You wherever You may go”; <verse eid="MAT 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 8:20"/>and Jesus says to him, “The foxes have holes, and the birds of the sky places of rest, but the Son of Man has nowhere He may lay the head.” <verse eid="MAT 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 8:21"/>And another of His disciples said to Him, “Lord, permit me first to depart and to bury my father”; <verse eid="MAT 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 8:22"/>and Jesus said to him, “Follow Me, and permit the dead to bury their own dead.” <verse eid="MAT 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 8:23"/>And when He entered into the boat His disciples followed Him, <verse eid="MAT 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 8:24"/>and behold, a great storm arose in the sea, so that the boat was being covered by the waves, but He was sleeping, <verse eid="MAT 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 8:25"/>and His disciples having come to Him, awoke Him, saying, “Lord, save us! We are perishing!” <verse eid="MAT 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 8:26"/>And He says to them, “Why are you fearful, O you of little faith?” Then having risen, He rebuked the winds and the sea, and there was a great calm; <verse eid="MAT 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 8:27"/>and the men wondered, saying, “What kind—is this, that even the wind and the sea obey Him?” <verse eid="MAT 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 8:28"/>And He having come to the other side, to the region of the Gergesenes, there met Him two demoniacs, coming forth out of the tombs, very fierce, so that no one was able to pass over by that way, <verse eid="MAT 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 8:29"/>and behold, they cried out, saying, “What [regards] us and You, <char style="bd">[[</char>Jesus,<char style="bd">]]</char> Son of God? Did You come here to afflict us before the time?” <verse eid="MAT 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 8:30"/>And there was a herd of many pigs feeding far off from them, <verse eid="MAT 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 8:31"/>and the demons were calling on Him, saying, “If You cast us forth, permit us to go away into the herd of the pigs”; <verse eid="MAT 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 8:32"/>and He says to them, “Go.” And having come forth, they went into the herd of the pigs, and behold, the whole herd of the pigs rushed down the steep, into the sea, and died in the waters, <verse eid="MAT 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 8:33"/>and those feeding fled, and having gone into the city, they declared all, and the matter of the demoniacs. <verse eid="MAT 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 8:34"/>And behold, all the city came forth to meet Jesus, and having seen Him, they called on [Him] that He might depart from their borders.<verse eid="MAT 8:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="MAT 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 9:1"/>And having gone into the boat, He passed over, and came to His own city, <verse eid="MAT 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 9:2"/>and behold, they were bringing to Him a paralytic, laid on a bed, and Jesus having seen their faith, said to the paralytic, “Take courage, child, your sins have been forgiven.” <verse eid="MAT 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 9:3"/>And behold, certain of the scribes said within themselves, “This One speaks evil.” <verse eid="MAT 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 9:4"/>And Jesus, having known their thoughts, said, “Why think evil in your hearts? <verse eid="MAT 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 9:5"/>For which is easier? To say, Your sins are forgiven; or to say, Rise and walk? <verse eid="MAT 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 9:6"/>But that you may know that the Son of Man has power on the earth to forgive sins—(then He says to the paralytic)—Having risen, take up your bed, and go to your house.” <verse eid="MAT 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 9:7"/>And he, having risen, went to his house, <verse eid="MAT 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 9:8"/>and the multitudes having seen, wondered, and glorified God, who gave such power to men. <verse eid="MAT 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 9:9"/>And Jesus passing on from there saw a man sitting at the tax office named Matthew, and says to him, “Follow Me,” and he, having risen, followed Him. <verse eid="MAT 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 9:10"/>And it came to pass, He reclining in the house, that behold, many tax collectors and sinners having come, were dining with Jesus and His disciples, <verse eid="MAT 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 9:11"/>and the Pharisees having seen, said to His disciples, “Why does your teacher eat with the tax collectors and sinners?” <verse eid="MAT 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 9:12"/>And Jesus having heard, said to them, “They who are whole have no need of a physician, but they who are ill; <verse eid="MAT 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 9:13"/>but having gone, learn what [this] is: Kindness I will, and not sacrifice; for I did not come to call righteous men, but sinners.” <verse eid="MAT 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 9:14"/>Then the disciples of John come to Him, saying, “Why do we and the Pharisees fast much, and Your disciples do not fast?” <verse eid="MAT 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 9:15"/>And Jesus said to them, “Can the sons of the bride-chamber mourn, so long as the bridegroom is with them? But days will come when the bridegroom may be taken from them, and then they will fast. <verse eid="MAT 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 9:16"/>And no one puts a patch of undressed cloth on an old garment, for its filling up takes from the garment, and a worse split is made. <verse eid="MAT 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 9:17"/>Nor do they put new wine into old skins, and if not—the skins burst, and the wine runs out, and the skins are destroyed, but they put new wine into new skins, and both are preserved together.” <verse eid="MAT 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 9:18"/>While He is speaking these things to them, behold, a ruler having come, was prostrating to Him, saying that “My daughter just now died, but having come, lay Your hand on her, and she will live.” <verse eid="MAT 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 9:19"/>And Jesus having risen, followed him, also His disciples, <verse eid="MAT 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 9:20"/>and behold, a woman having a flow of blood [for] twelve years, having come to Him behind, touched the fringe of His garments, <verse eid="MAT 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 9:21"/>for she said within herself, “If only I may touch His garment, I will be saved.” <verse eid="MAT 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 9:22"/>And Jesus having turned, and having seen her, said, “Take courage, daughter, your faith has saved you,” and the woman was saved from that hour. <verse eid="MAT 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 9:23"/>And Jesus having come into the house of the ruler, and having seen the pipers and the multitude making tumult, <verse eid="MAT 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 9:24"/>He says to them, “Withdraw, for the girl did not die, but sleeps,” and they were deriding Him; <verse eid="MAT 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 9:25"/>but when the multitude was put forth, having gone in, He took hold of her hand, and the girl arose, <verse eid="MAT 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 9:26"/>and the fame of this went forth to all the land. <verse eid="MAT 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 9:27"/>And Jesus passing on from there, two blind men followed Him, calling and saying, “Deal kindly with us, Son of David!” <verse eid="MAT 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 9:28"/>And He having come into the house, the blind men came to Him, and Jesus says to them, “Do you believe that I am able to do this?” They say to Him, “Yes, Lord.” <verse eid="MAT 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 9:29"/>Then He touched their eyes, saying, “According to your faith let it be to you,” <verse eid="MAT 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 9:30"/>and their eyes were opened, and Jesus strictly charged them, saying, “See, let no one know”; <verse eid="MAT 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 9:31"/>but they, having gone forth, spread His fame in all that land. <verse eid="MAT 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 9:32"/>And as they are coming forth, behold, they brought to Him a man mute, a demoniac, <verse eid="MAT 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 9:33"/>and the demon having been cast out, the mute spoke, and the multitude wondered, saying that “It was never so seen in Israel,” <verse eid="MAT 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 9:34"/>but the Pharisees said, “By the ruler of the demons He casts out the demons.” <verse eid="MAT 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 9:35"/>And Jesus was going up and down all the cities and the villages, teaching in their synagogues, and proclaiming the good news of the kingdom, and healing every disease and every sickness among the people. <verse eid="MAT 9:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 9:36"/>And having seen the multitudes, He was moved with compassion for them, that they were faint and cast aside, as sheep not having a shepherd; <verse eid="MAT 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 9:37"/>then He says to His disciples, “The harvest indeed [is] abundant, but the workmen few; <verse eid="MAT 9:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 9:38"/>therefore implore the Lord of the harvest that He may put forth workmen to His harvest.”<verse eid="MAT 9:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="MAT 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 10:1"/>And having called His twelve disciples to Himself, He gave to them power over unclean spirits, so as to be casting them out, and to be healing every disease and every sickness. <verse eid="MAT 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 10:2"/>And of the twelve apostles the names are these: first, Simon, who is called Peter, and his brother Andrew; James of Zebedee, and his brother John; <verse eid="MAT 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 10:3"/>Philip, and Bartholomew; Thomas, and Matthew the tax collector; James of Alpheus, and Lebbeus who was surnamed Thaddeus; <verse eid="MAT 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 10:4"/>Simon the Zealot, and Judas Iscariot, who also delivered Him up. <verse eid="MAT 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 10:5"/>These twelve Jesus sent forth, having given command to them, saying, “Do not go away to the way of the nations, and do not go into a city of the Samaritans, <verse eid="MAT 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 10:6"/>and be going rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. <verse eid="MAT 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 10:7"/>And going on, proclaim, saying that the kingdom of the heavens has come near; <verse eid="MAT 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 10:8"/>be healing [those] ailing, raising the dead, cleansing lepers, casting out demons—freely you received, freely give. <verse eid="MAT 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 10:9"/>Do not provide gold, nor silver, nor brass in your girdles, <verse eid="MAT 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 10:10"/>nor leather pouch for the way, nor two coats, nor sandals, nor staff—for the workman is worthy of his nourishment. <verse eid="MAT 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 10:11"/>And into whatever city or village you may enter, inquire who in it is worthy, and abide there, until you may go forth. <verse eid="MAT 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 10:12"/>And coming into the house greet it, <verse eid="MAT 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 10:13"/>and if indeed the house is worthy, let your peace come on it; and if it is not worthy, let your peace return to you. <verse eid="MAT 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 10:14"/>And whoever may not receive you nor hear your words, coming forth from that house or city, shake off the dust of your feet, <verse eid="MAT 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 10:15"/>truly I say to you, it will be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgment than for that city. <verse eid="MAT 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 10:16"/>Behold, I send you forth as sheep in the midst of wolves, therefore be wise as the serpents, and pure as the doves. <verse eid="MAT 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 10:17"/>And take heed of men, for they will give you up to Sanhedrins, and in their synagogues they will scourge you, <verse eid="MAT 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 10:18"/>and before governors and kings you will be brought for My sake, for a testimony to them and to the nations. <verse eid="MAT 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 10:19"/>And whenever they may deliver you up, do not be anxious how or what you may speak, for it will be given you in that hour what you will speak; <verse eid="MAT 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 10:20"/>for you are not the speakers, but the Spirit of your Father that is speaking in you. <verse eid="MAT 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 10:21"/>And brother will deliver up brother to death, and father child, and children will rise up against parents, and will put them to death, <verse eid="MAT 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 10:22"/>and you will be hated by all because of My Name, but he who has endured to the end, he will be saved. <verse eid="MAT 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 10:23"/>And whenever they may persecute you in this city, flee to the other, for truly I say to you, you may not have finished [going through] the cities of Israel until the Son of Man may come. <verse eid="MAT 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 10:24"/>A disciple is not above the teacher, nor a servant above his lord; <verse eid="MAT 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 10:25"/>sufficient to the disciple that he may be as his teacher, and the servant as his lord; if the master of the house they called Beelzebul, how much more those of his household? <verse eid="MAT 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 10:26"/>You may not, therefore, fear them, for there is nothing covered that will not be revealed, and hid that will not be known; <verse eid="MAT 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 10:27"/>that which I tell you in the darkness, speak in the light, and that which you hear at the ear, proclaim on the housetops. <verse eid="MAT 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 10:28"/>And do not be afraid of those killing the body, and are not able to kill the soul, but rather fear Him who is able to destroy both soul and body in Gehenna. <verse eid="MAT 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 10:29"/>Are not two sparrows sold for an assarion? And one of them will not fall on the ground without your Father; <verse eid="MAT 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 10:30"/>and of you—even the hairs of the head are all numbered; <verse eid="MAT 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 10:31"/>therefore, do not be afraid, you are better than many sparrows. <verse eid="MAT 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 10:32"/>Everyone, therefore, who will confess in Me before men, I also will confess in him before My Father who is in the heavens; <verse eid="MAT 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 10:33"/>and whoever will deny Me before men, I also will deny him before My Father who is in the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 10:34"/>You may not suppose that I came to put peace on the earth; I did not come to put peace, but a sword; <verse eid="MAT 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 10:35"/>for I came to set a man at variance against his father, and a daughter against her mother, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law, <verse eid="MAT 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 10:36"/>and the enemies of a man are those of his household. <verse eid="MAT 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 10:37"/>He who is cherishing father or mother above Me, is not worthy of Me, and he who is cherishing son or daughter above Me, is not worthy of Me, <verse eid="MAT 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 10:38"/>and whoever does not receive his cross and follow after Me, is not worthy of Me. <verse eid="MAT 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 10:39"/>He who found his life will lose it, and he who lost his life for My sake will find it. <verse eid="MAT 10:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 10:40"/>He who is receiving you receives Me, and he who is receiving Me receives Him who sent Me; <verse eid="MAT 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 10:41"/>he who is receiving a prophet in the name of a prophet, will receive a prophet’s reward, and he who is receiving a righteous man in the name of a righteous man, will receive a righteous man’s reward, <verse eid="MAT 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 10:42"/>and whoever may give to drink to one of these little ones a cup of cold water only in the name of a disciple, truly I say to you, he may not lose his reward.”<verse eid="MAT 10:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="MAT 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 11:1"/>And it came to pass, when Jesus finished directing His twelve disciples, He departed from there to teach and to preach in their cities. <verse eid="MAT 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 11:2"/>And John having heard in the prison the works of the Christ, having sent two of his disciples, <verse eid="MAT 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 11:3"/>said to Him, “Are You He who is coming, or do we look for another?” <verse eid="MAT 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 11:4"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “Having gone, declare to John the things that you hear and see, <verse eid="MAT 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 11:5"/>blind receive sight, and lame walk, lepers are cleansed, and deaf hear, dead are raised, and poor have good news proclaimed, <verse eid="MAT 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 11:6"/>and blessed is he who may not be stumbled in Me.” <verse eid="MAT 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 11:7"/>And as they are going, Jesus began to say to the multitudes concerning John, “What did you go out to the wilderness to view? A reed shaken by the wind? <verse eid="MAT 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 11:8"/>But what did you go out to see? A man clothed in soft garments? Behold, those wearing the soft things are in the kings’ houses. <verse eid="MAT 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 11:9"/>But what did you go out to see? A prophet? Yes, I say to you, and more than a prophet, <verse eid="MAT 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 11:10"/>for this is he of whom it has been written: Behold, I send My messenger before Your face, who will prepare Your way before You. <verse eid="MAT 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 11:11"/>Truly I say to you, there has not risen, among those born of women, [one] greater than John the Immerser, but he who is least in the kingdom of the heavens is greater than he. <verse eid="MAT 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 11:12"/>And from the days of John the Immerser until now, the kingdom of the heavens suffers violence, and violent men seize it by force, <verse eid="MAT 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 11:13"/>for all the Prophets and the Law prophesied until John, <verse eid="MAT 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 11:14"/>and if you are willing to receive [it], he is Elijah who was about to come; <verse eid="MAT 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 11:15"/>he who is having ears to hear—let him hear. <verse eid="MAT 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 11:16"/>And to what will I liken this generation? It is like little children in marketplaces, sitting and calling to others, <verse eid="MAT 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 11:17"/>and saying, We piped to you, and you did not dance, we lamented to you, and you did not strike the breast. <verse eid="MAT 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 11:18"/>For John came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, He has a demon; <verse eid="MAT 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 11:19"/>the Son of Man came eating and drinking, and they say, Behold, a man, a glutton, and a wine-drinker, a friend of tax collectors and sinners; and wisdom was justified of her children.” <verse eid="MAT 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 11:20"/>Then He began to reproach the cities in which were done most of His mighty works, because they did not convert. <verse eid="MAT 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 11:21"/>“Woe to you, Chorazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! Because, if in Tyre and Sidon had been done the mighty works that were done in you, long ago in sackcloth and ashes they had converted; <verse eid="MAT 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 11:22"/>but I say to you, to Tyre and Sidon it will be more tolerable in [the] day of judgment than for you. <verse eid="MAT 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 11:23"/>And you, Capernaum, which were exalted to Heaven, will be brought down to Hades, because if the mighty works that were done in you had been done in Sodom, it had remained to this day; <verse eid="MAT 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 11:24"/>but I say to you, to the land of Sodom it will be more tolerable in [the] day of judgment than to you.” <verse eid="MAT 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 11:25"/>At that time Jesus answering said, “I confess to You, Father, Lord of the heavens and of the earth, that You hid these things from wise and understanding ones, and revealed them to babies. <verse eid="MAT 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 11:26"/>Yes, Father, because so it was good pleasure before You. <verse eid="MAT 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 11:27"/>All things were delivered to Me by My Father, and none know the Son, except the Father, nor does any know the Father, except the Son, and he to whom the Son may resolve to reveal [Him]. <verse eid="MAT 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 11:28"/>Come to Me, all you laboring and burdened ones, and I will give you rest; <verse eid="MAT 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 11:29"/>take up My yoke on you, and learn from Me, because I am meek and humble in heart, and you will find rest to your souls, <verse eid="MAT 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 11:30"/>for My yoke [is] easy, and My burden is light.”<verse eid="MAT 11:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="MAT 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 12:1"/>At that time Jesus went on the Sabbaths through the grainfields, and His disciples were hungry, and they began to pluck ears, and to eat, <verse eid="MAT 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 12:2"/>and the Pharisees having seen, said to Him, “Behold, Your disciples do that which it is not lawful to do on a Sabbath.” <verse eid="MAT 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 12:3"/>And He said to them, “Did you not read what David did when he was hungry, himself and those with him— <verse eid="MAT 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 12:4"/>how he went into the house of God, and ate the Bread of the Presentation, which it is not lawful to him to eat, nor to those with him, except to the priests alone? <verse eid="MAT 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 12:5"/>Or did you not read in the Law that on the Sabbaths the priests in the temple profane the Sabbath and are blameless? <verse eid="MAT 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 12:6"/>And I say to you that [One] greater than the temple is here; <verse eid="MAT 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 12:7"/>and if you had known what [this] is: Kindness I will, and not sacrifice—you had not condemned the blameless, <verse eid="MAT 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 12:8"/>for the Son of Man is Lord even of the Sabbath.” <verse eid="MAT 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 12:9"/>And having departed from there, He went to their synagogue, <verse eid="MAT 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 12:10"/>and behold, there was a man having the hand withered, and they questioned Him, saying, “Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbaths?” That they might accuse Him. <verse eid="MAT 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 12:11"/>And He said to them, “What man will be of you who will have one sheep, and if this may fall on the Sabbaths into a ditch, will not lay hold on it and raise [it]? <verse eid="MAT 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 12:12"/>How much better, therefore, is a man than a sheep? So that it is lawful on the Sabbaths to do good.” <verse eid="MAT 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 12:13"/>Then He says to the man, “Stretch forth your hand,” and he stretched [it] forth, and it was restored whole as the other. <verse eid="MAT 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 12:14"/>And the Pharisees having gone forth, held a consultation against Him, how they might destroy Him, <verse eid="MAT 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 12:15"/>and Jesus having known, withdrew from there, and there followed Him great multitudes, and He healed them all, <verse eid="MAT 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 12:16"/>and charged them that they might not make Him apparent, <verse eid="MAT 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 12:17"/>that it might be fulfilled that was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying, <verse eid="MAT 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 12:18"/>“Behold, My Servant, whom I chose, || My Beloved, in whom My soul delighted, || I will put My Spirit on Him, || And He will declare judgment to the nations; <verse eid="MAT 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 12:19"/>He will not strive nor cry, || Nor will any hear His voice in the broad places; <verse eid="MAT 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 12:20"/>A bruised reed He will not break, || And smoking flax He will not quench, || Until He may put forth judgment to victory, <verse eid="MAT 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 12:21"/>And in His Name will nations hope.” <verse eid="MAT 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 12:22"/>Then was brought to Him a demoniac, blind and mute, and He healed him, so that the blind and mute both spoke and saw. <verse eid="MAT 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 12:23"/>And all the multitudes were amazed and said, “Is this the Son of David?” <verse eid="MAT 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 12:24"/>But the Pharisees having heard, said, “This One does not cast out demons, except by Beelzebul, ruler of the demons.” <verse eid="MAT 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 12:25"/>And Jesus, knowing their thoughts, said to them, “Every kingdom having been divided against itself is desolated, and no city or house having been divided against itself stands, <verse eid="MAT 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 12:26"/>and if Satan casts out Satan, against himself he was divided, how then does his kingdom stand? <verse eid="MAT 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 12:27"/>And if I, by Beelzebul, cast out the demons, your sons—by whom do they cast out? Because of this they will be your judges. <verse eid="MAT 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 12:28"/>But if I, by the Spirit of God, cast out the demons, then the Kingdom of God has already come to you. <verse eid="MAT 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 12:29"/>Or how is one able to go into the house of the strong man, and to snatch his goods, if first he may not bind the strong man? And then his house he will plunder. <verse eid="MAT 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 12:30"/>He who is not with Me is against Me, and he who is not gathering with Me, scatters. <verse eid="MAT 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 12:31"/>Because of this I say to you, all sin and slander will be forgiven to men, but the slander of the Spirit will not be forgiven to men. <verse eid="MAT 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 12:32"/>And whoever may speak a word against the Son of Man it will be forgiven to him, but whoever may speak against the Holy Spirit, it will not be forgiven him, neither in this age, nor in that which is coming. <verse eid="MAT 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 12:33"/>Either make the tree good, and its fruit good, or make the tree bad, and its fruit bad, for from the fruit is the tree known. <verse eid="MAT 12:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 12:34"/>Brood of vipers! How are you able to speak good things—being evil? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks. <verse eid="MAT 12:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 12:35"/>The good man out of the good treasure of the heart puts forth the good things, and the evil man out of the evil treasure puts forth evil things. <verse eid="MAT 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 12:36"/>And I say to you that every idle word that men may speak, they will give for it a reckoning in [the] day of judgment; <verse eid="MAT 12:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 12:37"/>for from your words you will be declared righteous, and from your words you will be declared unrighteous.” <verse eid="MAT 12:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 12:38"/>Then certain of the scribes and Pharisees answered, saying, “Teacher, we will to see a sign from You.” <verse eid="MAT 12:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 12:39"/>And He answering said to them, “A generation, evil and adulterous, seeks a sign, and a sign will not be given to it, except the sign of Jonah the prophet; <verse eid="MAT 12:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 12:40"/>for as Jonah was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights, so will the Son of Man be in the heart of the earth three days and three nights. <verse eid="MAT 12:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 12:41"/>Men of Nineveh will stand up in the judgment with this generation, and will condemn it, for they converted at the proclamation of Jonah, and behold, [One] greater than Jonah [is] here! <verse eid="MAT 12:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 12:42"/>A queen of the south will rise up in the judgment with this generation, and will condemn it, for she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon, and behold, [One] greater than Solomon [is] here! <verse eid="MAT 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 12:43"/>And when the unclean spirit may go forth from the man, it walks through dry places seeking rest and does not find; <verse eid="MAT 12:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 12:44"/>then it says, I will return to my house from where I came forth; and having come, it finds [it] unoccupied, swept, and adorned: <verse eid="MAT 12:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 12:45"/>then it goes, and takes with itself seven other spirits more evil than itself, and having gone in they dwell there, and the last of that man becomes worse than the first; so will it also be to this evil generation.” <verse eid="MAT 12:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 12:46"/>And while He was yet speaking to the multitudes, behold, His mother and brothers had stood outside, seeking to speak to Him, <verse eid="MAT 12:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MAT 12:47"/>and one said to Him, “Behold, Your mother and Your brothers stand outside, seeking to speak to You.” <verse eid="MAT 12:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MAT 12:48"/>And He answering said to him who spoke to Him, “Who is My mother? And who are My brothers?” <verse eid="MAT 12:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MAT 12:49"/>And having stretched forth His hand toward His disciples, He said, “Behold, My mother and My brothers! <verse eid="MAT 12:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MAT 12:50"/>For whoever may do the will of My Father who is in the heavens, He is My brother, and sister, and mother.”<verse eid="MAT 12:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="MAT 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 13:1"/>And in that day Jesus, having gone forth from the house, was sitting by the sea, <verse eid="MAT 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 13:2"/>and gathered together to Him were many multitudes, so that He having gone into the boat sat down, and all the multitude on the beach stood, <verse eid="MAT 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 13:3"/>and He spoke to them many things in allegories, saying, “Behold, the sower went forth to sow, <verse eid="MAT 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 13:4"/>and in his sowing, some indeed fell by the way, and the birds having come, devoured them, <verse eid="MAT 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 13:5"/>and others fell on the rocky places where they did not have much earth, and immediately they sprang forth, through having no depth of earth, <verse eid="MAT 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 13:6"/>and the sun having risen they were scorched, and through having no root, they withered, <verse eid="MAT 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 13:7"/>and others fell on the thorns, and the thorns came up and choked them, <verse eid="MAT 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 13:8"/>and others fell on the good ground, and were giving fruit, some indeed a hundredfold, and some sixty, and some thirty. <verse eid="MAT 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 13:9"/>He who is having ears to hear—let him hear.” <verse eid="MAT 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 13:10"/>And the disciples having come near, said to Him, “Why do You speak to them in allegories?” <verse eid="MAT 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 13:11"/>And He answering said to them that, “To you it has been given to know the secrets of the kingdom of the heavens, and to these it has not been given, <verse eid="MAT 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 13:12"/>for whoever has, it will be given to him, and he will have overabundance, and whoever has not, even that which he has will be taken from him. <verse eid="MAT 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 13:13"/>Because of this, in allegories I speak to them, because seeing they do not see, and hearing they do not hear, nor understand, <verse eid="MAT 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 13:14"/>and fulfilled on them is the prophecy of Isaiah that says, With hearing you will hear, and you will not understand, and seeing you will see, and you will not perceive, <verse eid="MAT 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 13:15"/>for the heart of this people was made obtuse, and with the ears they barely heard, and they closed their eyes, lest they might see with the eyes, and might hear with the ears, and understand with the heart, and turn back, and I might heal them. <verse eid="MAT 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 13:16"/>And blessed are your eyes because they see, and your ears because they hear, <verse eid="MAT 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 13:17"/>for truly I say to you that many prophets and righteous men desired to see that which you look on, and they did not see, and to hear that which you hear, and they did not hear. <verse eid="MAT 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 13:18"/>You, therefore, hear the allegory of the sower: <verse eid="MAT 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 13:19"/>Everyone hearing the word of the kingdom, and not understanding—the evil one comes, and snatches that which has been sown in his heart; this is that sown by the way. <verse eid="MAT 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 13:20"/>And that sown on the rocky places, this is he who is hearing the word, and immediately with joy is receiving it, <verse eid="MAT 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 13:21"/>and he has no root in himself, but is temporary, and persecution or tribulation having happened because of the word, immediately he is stumbled. <verse eid="MAT 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 13:22"/>And that sown toward the thorns, this is he who is hearing the word, and the anxiety of this age, and the deceitfulness of the riches, chokes the word, and it becomes unfruitful. <verse eid="MAT 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 13:23"/>And that sown on the good ground: this is he who is hearing the word, and is understanding, who indeed bears fruit, and makes, some indeed a hundredfold, and some sixty, and some thirty.” <verse eid="MAT 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 13:24"/>Another allegory He set before them, saying, “The kingdom of the heavens was likened to a man sowing good seed in his field, <verse eid="MAT 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 13:25"/>and while men are sleeping, his enemy came and sowed darnel in the midst of the wheat, and went away, <verse eid="MAT 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 13:26"/>and when the herb sprang up, and yielded fruit, then appeared also the darnel. <verse eid="MAT 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 13:27"/>And the servants of the householder, having come near, said to him, Lord, did you not sow good seed in your field? From where then does it have the darnel? <verse eid="MAT 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 13:28"/>And he says to them, A man, an enemy, did this; and the servants said to him, Will you, then, [that] having gone away we may gather it up? <verse eid="MAT 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 13:29"/>And he said, No, lest—gathering up the darnel—you root up with it the wheat; <verse eid="MAT 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 13:30"/>permit both to grow together until the harvest, and in the time of the harvest I will say to the reapers, Gather up first the darnel, and bind it in bundles, to burn it, and the wheat gather up into my storehouse.” <verse eid="MAT 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 13:31"/>Another allegory He set before them, saying, “The kingdom of the heavens is like to a grain of mustard, which a man having taken, sowed in his field, <verse eid="MAT 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 13:32"/>which less, indeed, is than all the seeds, but when it may be grown, is greatest of the herbs, and becomes a tree, so that the birds of the sky come and rest in its branches.” <verse eid="MAT 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 13:33"/>Another allegory He spoke to them: “The kingdom of the heavens is like to leaven, which a woman having taken, hid in three measures of meal, until the whole was leavened.” <verse eid="MAT 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 13:34"/>All these things Jesus spoke in allegories to the multitudes, and without an allegory He was not speaking to them, <verse eid="MAT 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 13:35"/>that it might be fulfilled that was spoken through the prophet, saying, “I will open in allegories My mouth, || I will utter things having been hidden from the foundation of the world.” <verse eid="MAT 13:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 13:36"/>Then having let away the multitudes, Jesus came into the house, and His disciples came near to Him, saying, “Explain to us the allegory of the darnel of the field.” <verse eid="MAT 13:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 13:37"/>And He answering said to them, “He who is sowing the good seed is the Son of Man, <verse eid="MAT 13:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 13:38"/>and the field is the world, and the good seed, these are the sons of the kingdom, and the darnel are the sons of the evil one, <verse eid="MAT 13:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 13:39"/>and the enemy who sowed them is the Devil, and the harvest is [the] full end of the age, and the reapers are messengers. <verse eid="MAT 13:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 13:40"/>As, then, the darnel is gathered up, and is burned with fire, so will it be in the full end of this age; <verse eid="MAT 13:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 13:41"/>the Son of Man will send forth His messengers, and they will gather up out of His kingdom all the stumbling-blocks, and those doing the lawlessness, <verse eid="MAT 13:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 13:42"/>and will cast them into the furnace of the fire; there will be the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth. <verse eid="MAT 13:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 13:43"/>Then will the righteous shine forth as the sun in the kingdom of their Father. He who is having ears to hear—let him hear. <verse eid="MAT 13:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 13:44"/>Again, the kingdom of the heavens is like to treasure hid in the field, which a man having found, hid, and from his joy goes, and all, as much as he has, he sells, and buys that field. <verse eid="MAT 13:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 13:45"/>Again, the kingdom of the heavens is like to a man, a merchant, seeking good pearls, <verse eid="MAT 13:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 13:46"/>who having found one pearl of great price, having gone away, has sold all, as much as he had, and bought it. <verse eid="MAT 13:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MAT 13:47"/>Again, the kingdom of the heavens is like to a net that was cast into the sea, and gathered together of every kind, <verse eid="MAT 13:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MAT 13:48"/>which, when it was filled, having drawn up again on the beach, and having sat down, they gathered the good into vessels, and the bad they cast out, <verse eid="MAT 13:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MAT 13:49"/>so will it be in the full end of the age, the messengers will come forth and separate the evil out of the midst of the righteous, <verse eid="MAT 13:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MAT 13:50"/>and will cast them into the furnace of the fire; there will be the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth.” <verse eid="MAT 13:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MAT 13:51"/>Jesus says to them, “Did you understand all these?” They say to Him, “Yes, Lord.” <verse eid="MAT 13:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MAT 13:52"/>And He said to them, “Because of this, every scribe having been discipled in regard to the kingdom of the heavens is like to a man, a householder, who brings forth out of his treasure things new and old.” <verse eid="MAT 13:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="MAT 13:53"/>And it came to pass, when Jesus finished these allegories, He removed from there, <verse eid="MAT 13:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MAT 13:54"/>and having come to His own country, He was teaching them in their synagogue, so that they were astonished, and were saying, “From where to this One this wisdom and the mighty works? <verse eid="MAT 13:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MAT 13:55"/>Is this not the carpenter’s Son? Is His mother not called Mary, and His brothers James, and Joses, and Simon, and Judas? <verse eid="MAT 13:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MAT 13:56"/>And His sisters—are they not all with us? From where, then, to this One all these?” <verse eid="MAT 13:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="MAT 13:57"/>And they were stumbled at Him. And Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not without honor except in his own country, and in his own house”: <verse eid="MAT 13:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="MAT 13:58"/>and He did not do many mighty works there, because of their unbelief.<verse eid="MAT 13:58"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="MAT 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 14:1"/>At that time Herod the tetrarch heard the fame of Jesus, <verse eid="MAT 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 14:2"/>and said to his servants, “This is John the Immerser, he rose from the dead, and because of this the mighty energies are working in him.” <verse eid="MAT 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 14:3"/>For Herod having laid hold on John, bound him, and put him in prison, because of Herodias, his brother Philip’s wife, <verse eid="MAT 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 14:4"/>for John was saying to him, “It is not lawful to you to have her,” <verse eid="MAT 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 14:5"/>and willing to kill him, he feared the multitude, because as a prophet they were holding him. <verse eid="MAT 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 14:6"/>But the birthday of Herod being kept, the daughter of Herodias danced in the midst, and pleased Herod, <verse eid="MAT 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 14:7"/>after which with an oath he professed to give her whatever she might ask. <verse eid="MAT 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 14:8"/>And she, having been instigated by her mother, says, “Give me here on a plate the head of John the Immerser”; <verse eid="MAT 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 14:9"/>and the king was grieved, but because of the oaths and of those dining with him, he commanded [it] to be given; <verse eid="MAT 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 14:10"/>and having sent, he beheaded John in the prison, <verse eid="MAT 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 14:11"/>and his head was brought on a plate, and was given to the girl, and she brought [it] near to her mother. <verse eid="MAT 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 14:12"/>And his disciples having come, took up the body, and buried it, and having come, they told Jesus, <verse eid="MAT 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 14:13"/>and Jesus having heard, withdrew from there in a boat to a desolate place by Himself, and the multitudes having heard followed Him on land from the cities. <verse eid="MAT 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 14:14"/>And Jesus having come forth, saw a great multitude, and was moved with compassion on them, and healed their sick; <verse eid="MAT 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 14:15"/>and evening having come, His disciples came to Him, saying, “The place is desolate, and the hour has now past, let away the multitudes that, having gone into the villages, they may buy food for themselves.” <verse eid="MAT 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 14:16"/>And Jesus said to them, “They have no need to go away—you give them to eat.” <verse eid="MAT 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 14:17"/>And they say to Him, “We have nothing here except five loaves and two fishes.” <verse eid="MAT 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 14:18"/>And He said, “Bring them to Me here.” <verse eid="MAT 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 14:19"/>And having commanded the multitudes to recline on the grass, and having taken the five loaves and the two fishes, having looked up to the sky, He blessed, and having broken, He gave the loaves to the disciples, and the disciples [gave] to the multitudes, <verse eid="MAT 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 14:20"/>and they all ate, and were filled, and they took up what was over of the broken pieces twelve hand-baskets full; <verse eid="MAT 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 14:21"/>and those eating were about five thousand men, apart from women and children. <verse eid="MAT 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 14:22"/>And immediately Jesus constrained His disciples to go into the boat, and to go before Him to the other side, until He might let away the multitudes; <verse eid="MAT 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 14:23"/>and having let away the multitudes, He went up to the mountain by Himself to pray, and evening having come, He was there alone, <verse eid="MAT 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 14:24"/>and the boat was now in the midst of the sea, distressed by the waves, for the wind was contrary. <verse eid="MAT 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 14:25"/>And in the fourth watch of the night Jesus went away to them, walking on the sea, <verse eid="MAT 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 14:26"/>and the disciples having seen Him walking on the sea, were troubled, saying, “It is an apparition,” and from the fear they cried out; <verse eid="MAT 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 14:27"/>and immediately Jesus spoke to them, saying, “Take courage! I AM; do not be afraid.” <verse eid="MAT 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 14:28"/>And Peter answering Him said, “Lord, if it is You, command me to come to You on the waters”; <verse eid="MAT 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 14:29"/>and He said, “Come”; and having gone down from the boat, Peter walked on the waters to come to Jesus, <verse eid="MAT 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 14:30"/>but seeing the vehement wind, he was afraid, and having begun to sink, he cried out, saying, “Lord, save me!” <verse eid="MAT 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 14:31"/>And immediately Jesus, having stretched forth the hand, laid hold of him and says to him, “Little faith! For why did you waver?” <verse eid="MAT 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 14:32"/>And they having gone into the boat, the wind stilled, <verse eid="MAT 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 14:33"/>and those in the boat having come, worshiped Him, saying, “You are truly God’s Son.” <verse eid="MAT 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 14:34"/>And having passed over, they came into the land of Gennesaret, <verse eid="MAT 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 14:35"/>and having recognized Him, the men of that place sent forth to all that surrounding region, and they brought to Him all who were ill, <verse eid="MAT 14:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 14:36"/>and were calling on Him that they might only touch the fringe of His garment, and as many as touched were saved.<verse eid="MAT 14:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="MAT 15"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 15:1"/>Then they come to Jesus from Jerusalem—scribes and Pharisees—saying, <verse eid="MAT 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 15:2"/>“Why do Your disciples transgress the tradition of the elders? For they do not wash their hands when they may eat bread.” <verse eid="MAT 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 15:3"/>And He answering said to them, “Why also do you transgress the command of God because of your tradition? <verse eid="MAT 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 15:4"/>For God commanded, saying, Honor your father and mother; and, He who is speaking evil of father or mother—let him die the death; <verse eid="MAT 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 15:5"/>but you say, Whoever may say to father or mother, An offering [is] whatever you may be profited by me— <verse eid="MAT 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 15:6"/>and he may not honor his father or his mother, and you set aside the command of God because of your tradition. <verse eid="MAT 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 15:7"/>Hypocrites, Isaiah prophesied well of you, saying, <verse eid="MAT 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 15:8"/>This people draws near to Me with their mouth, and with the lips it honors Me, but their heart is far off from Me; <verse eid="MAT 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 15:9"/>and in vain they worship Me, teaching teachings—commands of men.” <verse eid="MAT 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 15:10"/>And having called near the multitude, He said to them, “Hear and understand: <verse eid="MAT 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 15:11"/>[it is] not that which is coming into the mouth [that] defiles the man, but that which is coming forth from the mouth, this defiles the man.” <verse eid="MAT 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 15:12"/>Then His disciples having come near, said to Him, “Have You known that the Pharisees, having heard the word, were stumbled?” <verse eid="MAT 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 15:13"/>And He answering said, “Every plant that My heavenly Father did not plant will be rooted up; <verse eid="MAT 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 15:14"/>leave them alone, they are guides—blind of blind; and if blind may guide blind, both will fall into a ditch.” <verse eid="MAT 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 15:15"/>And Peter answering said to Him, “Explain to us this allegory.” <verse eid="MAT 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 15:16"/>And Jesus said, “Are you also yet without understanding? <verse eid="MAT 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 15:17"/>Do you not understand that all that is going into the mouth passes into the belly, and is cast forth into the drain? <verse eid="MAT 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 15:18"/>But the things coming forth from the mouth come forth from the heart, and these defile the man; <verse eid="MAT 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 15:19"/>for out of the heart come forth evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, whoredoms, thefts, false witnessings, slanders: <verse eid="MAT 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 15:20"/>these are the things defiling the man; but to eat with unwashed hands does not defile the man.” <verse eid="MAT 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 15:21"/>And Jesus having come forth from there, withdrew to the parts of Tyre and Sidon, <verse eid="MAT 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 15:22"/>and behold, a woman, a Canaanite, having come forth from those borders, called to Him, saying, “Deal kindly with me, Lord, Son of David; my daughter is miserably demonized.” <verse eid="MAT 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 15:23"/>And He did not answer her a word; and His disciples having come to Him, were asking Him, saying, “Let her away, because she cries after us”; <verse eid="MAT 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 15:24"/>and He answering said, “I was not sent except to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.” <verse eid="MAT 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 15:25"/>And having come, she was worshiping Him, saying, “Lord, help me”; <verse eid="MAT 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 15:26"/>and He answering said, “It is not good to take the children’s bread, and to cast to the little dogs.” <verse eid="MAT 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 15:27"/>And she said, “Yes, Lord, for even the little dogs eat of the crumbs that are falling from their lords’ table”; <verse eid="MAT 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 15:28"/>then answering, Jesus said to her, “O woman, great [is] your faith, let it be to you as you will”; and her daughter was healed from that hour. <verse eid="MAT 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 15:29"/>And having departed from there, Jesus came near to the Sea of Galilee, and having gone up to the mountain, He was sitting there, <verse eid="MAT 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 15:30"/>and there came to Him great multitudes, having with them lame, blind, mute, maimed, and many others, and they cast them at the feet of Jesus, and He healed them, <verse eid="MAT 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 15:31"/>so that the multitudes wondered, seeing mute ones speaking, maimed whole, lame walking, and blind seeing; and they glorified the God of Israel. <verse eid="MAT 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 15:32"/>And Jesus having called near His disciples, said, “I have compassion on the multitude, because now three days they continue with Me, and they do not have what they may eat; and to let them away fasting I will not, lest they faint in the way.” <verse eid="MAT 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 15:33"/>And His disciples say to Him, “From where to us in a wilderness [will we get] so many loaves, as to fill so great a multitude?” <verse eid="MAT 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 15:34"/>And Jesus says to them, “How many loaves do you have?” And they said, “Seven, and a few little fishes.” <verse eid="MAT 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 15:35"/>And He commanded the multitudes to sit down on the ground, <verse eid="MAT 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 15:36"/>and having taken the seven loaves and the fishes, having given thanks, He broke, and gave to His disciples, and the disciples [gave] to the multitude. <verse eid="MAT 15:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 15:37"/>And they all ate, and were filled, and they took up what was over of the broken pieces seven baskets full, <verse eid="MAT 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 15:38"/>and those eating were four thousand men, apart from women and children. <verse eid="MAT 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 15:39"/>And having let away the multitudes, He went into the boat, and came to the borders of Magdala.<verse eid="MAT 15:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="MAT 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 16:1"/>And the Pharisees and Sadducees having come, tempting, questioned Him, to show to them a sign from Heaven, <verse eid="MAT 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 16:2"/>and He answering said to them, “Evening having come, you say, Fair weather, for the sky is red, <verse eid="MAT 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 16:3"/>and at morning, Foul weather today, for the sky is red—gloomy; hypocrites, you indeed know to discern the face of the sky, but the signs of the times you are not able! <verse eid="MAT 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 16:4"/>An evil and adulterous generation seeks a sign, and a sign will not be given to it, except the sign of Jonah the prophet”; and having left them He went away. <verse eid="MAT 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 16:5"/>And His disciples having come to the other side, forgot to take loaves, <verse eid="MAT 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 16:6"/>and Jesus said to them, “Beware, and take heed of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees”; <verse eid="MAT 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 16:7"/>and they were reasoning in themselves, saying, “Because we took no loaves.” <verse eid="MAT 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 16:8"/>And Jesus having known, said to them, “Why reason you in yourselves, you of little faith, because you took no loaves? <verse eid="MAT 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 16:9"/>Do you not yet understand, nor remember the five loaves of the five thousand, and how many hand-baskets you took up? <verse eid="MAT 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 16:10"/>Nor the seven loaves of the four thousand, and how many baskets you took up? <verse eid="MAT 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 16:11"/>How do you not understand that I did not speak to you of bread—to take heed of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees?” <verse eid="MAT 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 16:12"/>Then they understood that He did not say to take heed of the leaven of the bread, but of the teaching of the Pharisees and Sadducees. <verse eid="MAT 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 16:13"/>And Jesus, having come to the parts of Caesarea Philippi, was asking His disciples, saying, “Who do men say I am—the Son of Man?” <verse eid="MAT 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 16:14"/>And they said, “Some, John the Immerser, and others, Elijah, and others, Jeremiah, or one of the prophets.” <verse eid="MAT 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 16:15"/>He says to them, “And you—who do you say I am?” <verse eid="MAT 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 16:16"/>And Simon Peter answering said, “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.” <verse eid="MAT 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 16:17"/>And Jesus answering said to him, “Blessed are you, Simon Bar-Jona, because flesh and blood did not reveal [it] to you, but My Father who is in the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 16:18"/>And I also say to you that you are Peter, and on this rock I will build My Assembly, and [the] gates of Hades will not prevail against it; <verse eid="MAT 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 16:19"/>and I will give to you the keys of the kingdom of the heavens, and whatever you may bind on the earth will be having been bound in the heavens, and whatever you may loose on the earth will be having been loosed in the heavens.” <verse eid="MAT 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 16:20"/>Then He charged His disciples that they may say to no one that He is Jesus the Christ. <verse eid="MAT 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 16:21"/>From that time Jesus began to show to His disciples that it is necessary for Him to go away to Jerusalem, and to suffer many things from the elders, and chief priests, and scribes, and to be put to death, and the third day to rise. <verse eid="MAT 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 16:22"/>And having taken Him aside, Peter began to rebuke Him, saying, “Be kind to Yourself, Lord; this will not be to You”; <verse eid="MAT 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 16:23"/>and He having turned, said to Peter, “Get behind Me, Satan! You are a stumbling-block to Me, for you do not mind the things of God, but the things of men.” <verse eid="MAT 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 16:24"/>Then Jesus said to His disciples, “If anyone wills to come after Me, let him disown himself, and take up his cross, and follow Me, <verse eid="MAT 16:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 16:25"/>for whoever may will to save his life will lose it, and whoever may lose his life for My sake will find it; <verse eid="MAT 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 16:26"/>for what is a man profited if he may gain the whole world, but of his life suffer loss? Or what will a man give as an exchange for his life? <verse eid="MAT 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 16:27"/>For the Son of Man is about to come in the glory of His Father, with His messengers, and then He will reward each according to his work. <verse eid="MAT 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 16:28"/>Truly I say to you, there are certain of those standing here who will not taste of death until they may see the Son of Man coming in His kingdom.”<verse eid="MAT 16:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="MAT 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 17:1"/>And after six days Jesus takes Peter, and James, and his brother John, and brings them up to a high mountain by themselves, <verse eid="MAT 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 17:2"/>and He was transfigured before them, and His face shone as the sun, and His garments became white as the light, <verse eid="MAT 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 17:3"/>and behold, Moses and Elijah appeared to them, talking together with Him. <verse eid="MAT 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 17:4"/>And Peter answering said to Jesus, “Lord, it is good to us to be here; if You will, we may make three shelters here: one for You, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah.” <verse eid="MAT 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 17:5"/>While he is yet speaking, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them, and behold, a voice out of the cloud, saying, “This is My Son, the Beloved, in whom I delighted; hear Him.” <verse eid="MAT 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 17:6"/>And the disciples having heard, fell on their face, and were exceedingly afraid, <verse eid="MAT 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 17:7"/>and Jesus having come near, touched them, and said, “Rise, do not be afraid,” <verse eid="MAT 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 17:8"/>and having lifted up their eyes, they saw no one, except Jesus only. <verse eid="MAT 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 17:9"/>And as they are coming down from the mountain, Jesus charged them, saying, “Say to no one the vision, until the Son of Man may rise out of the dead.” <verse eid="MAT 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 17:10"/>And His disciples questioned Him, saying, “Why then do the scribes say that Elijah must come first?” <verse eid="MAT 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 17:11"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “Elijah does indeed come first, and will restore all things, <verse eid="MAT 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 17:12"/>and I say to you, Elijah already came, and they did not know him, but did with him whatever they would, so also the Son of Man is about to suffer by them.” <verse eid="MAT 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 17:13"/>Then the disciples understood that He spoke to them concerning John the Immerser. <verse eid="MAT 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 17:14"/>And when they came to the multitude, there came to Him a man, kneeling down to Him, <verse eid="MAT 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 17:15"/>and saying, “Lord, deal kindly with my son, for he is [a] lunatic, and suffers miserably, for he often falls into the fire, and often into the water, <verse eid="MAT 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 17:16"/>and I brought him near to Your disciples, and they were not able to heal him.” <verse eid="MAT 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 17:17"/>And Jesus answering said, “O generation, unsteadfast and perverse, until when will I be with you? Until when will I bear you? Bring him to Me here”; <verse eid="MAT 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 17:18"/>and Jesus rebuked him, and the demon went out of him, and the boy was healed from that hour. <verse eid="MAT 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 17:19"/>Then the disciples having come to Jesus by Himself, said, “Why were we not able to cast him out?” <verse eid="MAT 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 17:20"/>And Jesus said to them, “Through your want of faith; for truly I say to you, if you may have faith as a grain of mustard, you will say to this mountain, Move from here to there, and it will move, and nothing will be impossible to you, <verse eid="MAT 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 17:21"/><char style="bd">[[</char>and this kind does not go forth except in prayer and fasting.”<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MAT 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 17:22"/>And while they are living in Galilee, Jesus said to them, “The Son of Man is about to be delivered up into the hands of men, <verse eid="MAT 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 17:23"/>and they will kill Him, and the third day He will rise,” and they were exceedingly sorry. <verse eid="MAT 17:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 17:24"/>And they having come to Capernaum, those receiving the didrachmas came near to Peter and said, “Your teacher—does He not pay the didrachmas?” He says, “Yes.” <verse eid="MAT 17:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 17:25"/>And when he came into the house, Jesus anticipated him, saying, “What do you think, Simon? The kings of the earth—from whom do they receive custom or poll-tax? From their sons or from the strangers?” <verse eid="MAT 17:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 17:26"/>Peter says to Him, “From the strangers.” Jesus said to him, “Then the sons are free; <verse eid="MAT 17:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 17:27"/>but that we may not cause them to stumble, having gone to the sea, cast a hook, and the fish that has come up first take up, and having opened its mouth, you will find a stater, that having taken, give to them for Me and you.”<verse eid="MAT 17:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="MAT 18"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 18:1"/>At that hour the disciples came near to Jesus, saying, “Who, now, is greater in the kingdom of the heavens?” <verse eid="MAT 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 18:2"/>And Jesus having called near a child, set him in the midst of them, <verse eid="MAT 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 18:3"/>and said, “Truly I say to you, if you may not be turned and become as the children, you may not enter into the kingdom of the heavens; <verse eid="MAT 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 18:4"/>whoever then may humble himself as this child, he is the greater in the kingdom of the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 18:5"/>And he who may receive one such child in My Name, receives Me, <verse eid="MAT 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 18:6"/>and whoever may cause to stumble one of those little ones who are believing in Me, it is better for him that a weighty millstone may be hanged on his neck, and he may be sunk in the depth of the sea. <verse eid="MAT 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 18:7"/>Woe to the world from the stumbling-blocks! For there is necessity for the stumbling-blocks to come, but woe to that man through whom the stumbling-block comes! <verse eid="MAT 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 18:8"/>And if your hand or your foot causes you to stumble, cut them off and cast [them] from you; it is good for you to enter into life lame or maimed, rather than having two hands or two feet, to be cast into the continuous fire. <verse eid="MAT 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 18:9"/>And if your eye causes you to stumble, pluck it out and cast from you; it is good for you to enter into life one-eyed, rather than having two eyes to be cast into the Gehenna of fire. <verse eid="MAT 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 18:10"/>Beware! You may not despise one of these little ones, for I say to you that their messengers in the heavens always behold the face of My Father who is in the heavens, <verse eid="MAT 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 18:11"/><char style="bd">[[</char>for the Son of Man came to save the lost.<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MAT 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 18:12"/>What do you think? If a man may have one hundred sheep, and there may go astray one of them, does he not—having left the ninety-nine, having gone on the mountains—seek that which is gone astray? <verse eid="MAT 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 18:13"/>And if it may come to pass that he finds it, truly I say to you that he rejoices over it more than over the ninety-nine that have not gone astray; <verse eid="MAT 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 18:14"/>so it is not [the] will in [the] presence of your Father who is in the heavens that one of these little ones may perish. <verse eid="MAT 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 18:15"/>And if your brother may sin against you, go and show him his fault between you and him alone, if he may hear you, you gained your brother; <verse eid="MAT 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 18:16"/>and if he may not hear, take with you yet one or two, that by the mouth of two witnesses or three every word may stand. <verse eid="MAT 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 18:17"/>And if he may not hear them, say [it] to the assembly, and if also the assembly he may not hear, let him be to you as the heathen man and the tax collector. <verse eid="MAT 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 18:18"/>Truly I say to you, whatever things you may bind on the earth will be having been bound in the heavens, and whatever things you may loose on the earth will be having been loosed in the heavens. <verse eid="MAT 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 18:19"/>Again, I say to you that if two of you may agree on the earth concerning anything, whatever they may ask—it will be done to them from My Father who is in the heavens, <verse eid="MAT 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 18:20"/>for where there are two or three gathered together—to My Name, there am I in the midst of them.” <verse eid="MAT 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 18:21"/>Then Peter having come near to Him, said, “Lord, how often will my brother sin against me, and I forgive him—until seven times?” <verse eid="MAT 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 18:22"/>Jesus says to him, “I do not say to you until seven times, but until seventy times seven. <verse eid="MAT 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 18:23"/>Because of this was the kingdom of the heavens likened to a man, a king, who willed to take reckoning with his servants, <verse eid="MAT 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 18:24"/>and he having begun to take account, there was brought near to him one debtor of a myriad of talents, <verse eid="MAT 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 18:25"/>and he having nothing to pay, his lord commanded him to be sold, and his wife, and the children, and all, whatever he had, and payment to be made. <verse eid="MAT 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 18:26"/>The servant then, having fallen down, was prostrating to him, saying, Lord, have patience with me, and I will pay you all; <verse eid="MAT 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 18:27"/>and the lord of that servant having been moved with compassion released him, and the debt he forgave him. <verse eid="MAT 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 18:28"/>And that servant having come forth, found one of his fellow-servants who was owing him one hundred denarii, and having laid hold, he took him by the throat, saying, Pay me that which you owe. <verse eid="MAT 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 18:29"/>His fellow-servant then, having fallen down at his feet, was calling on him, saying, Have patience with me, and I will pay you all; <verse eid="MAT 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 18:30"/>and he would not, but having gone away, he cast him into prison, until he might pay that which was owing. <verse eid="MAT 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 18:31"/>And his fellow-servants having seen the things that were done, were grieved exceedingly, and having come, showed fully to their lord all the things that were done; <verse eid="MAT 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 18:32"/>then having called him, his lord says to him, Evil servant! All that debt I forgave you, seeing you called on me; <verse eid="MAT 18:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 18:33"/>did it not seem necessary to you to have dealt kindly with your fellow servant, as I also dealt kindly with you? <verse eid="MAT 18:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 18:34"/>And having been angry, his lord delivered him to the inquisitors, until he might pay all that was owing to him; <verse eid="MAT 18:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 18:35"/>so also My heavenly Father will do to you, if you may not forgive each one his brother from your hearts their trespasses.”<verse eid="MAT 18:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="MAT 19"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 19:1"/>And it came to pass, when Jesus finished these words, He removed from Galilee, and came to the borders of Judea, beyond the Jordan, <verse eid="MAT 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 19:2"/>and great multitudes followed Him, and He healed them there. <verse eid="MAT 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 19:3"/>And the Pharisees came near to Him, tempting Him, and saying to Him, “Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife for every cause?” <verse eid="MAT 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 19:4"/>And He answering said to them, “Did you not read that He who made [them] from the beginning, made them a male and a female, <verse eid="MAT 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 19:5"/>and said, For this cause will a man leave father and mother, and cleave to his wife, and they will be—the two—for one flesh? <verse eid="MAT 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 19:6"/>So that they are no longer two, but one flesh; what therefore God joined together, let no man separate.” <verse eid="MAT 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 19:7"/>They say to Him, “Why then did Moses command to give a roll of divorce, and to put her away?” <verse eid="MAT 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 19:8"/>He says to them, “Moses for your stiffness of heart permitted you to put away your wives, but from the beginning it has not been so. <verse eid="MAT 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 19:9"/>And I say to you that whoever may put away his wife, if not for whoredom, and may marry another, commits adultery; and he who married her that has been put away, commits adultery.” <verse eid="MAT 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 19:10"/>His disciples say to Him, “If the case of the man with the woman is so, it is not good to marry.” <verse eid="MAT 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 19:11"/>And He said to them, “All do not receive this word, but those to whom it has been given; <verse eid="MAT 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 19:12"/>for there are eunuchs who from the mother’s womb were so born; and there are eunuchs who were made eunuchs by men; and there are eunuchs who kept themselves eunuchs because of the kingdom of the heavens: he who is able to receive [it]—let him receive.” <verse eid="MAT 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 19:13"/>Then were brought near to Him children that He might put hands on them and pray, and the disciples rebuked them. <verse eid="MAT 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 19:14"/>But Jesus said, “Permit the children, and do not forbid them to come to Me, for of such is the kingdom of the heavens”; <verse eid="MAT 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 19:15"/>and having laid [His] hands on them, He departed from there. <verse eid="MAT 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 19:16"/>And behold, one having come near, said to Him, “Good Teacher, what good thing will I do that I may have continuous life?” <verse eid="MAT 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 19:17"/>And He said to him, “Why do you call Me good? No one [is] good except one—God; but if you will to enter into life, keep the commands.” <verse eid="MAT 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 19:18"/>He says to Him, “What kind?” And Jesus said, “You will not murder, You will not commit adultery, You will not steal, You will not bear false witness, <verse eid="MAT 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 19:19"/>Honor your father and mother, and, You will love your neighbor as yourself.” <verse eid="MAT 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 19:20"/>The young man says to Him, “All these I kept from my youth; what yet do I lack?” <verse eid="MAT 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 19:21"/>Jesus said to him, “If you will to be perfect, go away, sell what you have, and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in Heaven, and come, follow Me.” <verse eid="MAT 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 19:22"/>And the young man, having heard the word, went away sorrowful, for he had many possessions; <verse eid="MAT 19:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 19:23"/>and Jesus said to His disciples, “Truly I say to you that hardly will a rich man enter into the kingdom of the heavens; <verse eid="MAT 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 19:24"/>and again I say to you, it is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God.” <verse eid="MAT 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 19:25"/>And His disciples having heard, were exceedingly amazed, saying, “Who, then, is able to be saved?” <verse eid="MAT 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 19:26"/>And Jesus having earnestly beheld, said to them, “With men this is impossible, but with God all things are possible.” <verse eid="MAT 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 19:27"/>Then Peter answering said to Him, “Behold, we left all, and followed You, what then will we have?” <verse eid="MAT 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 19:28"/>And Jesus said to them, “Truly I say to you that you who followed Me, in the regeneration, when the Son of Man may sit on a throne of His glory, will sit—you also—on twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel; <verse eid="MAT 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 19:29"/>and everyone who left houses, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or fields, for My Name’s sake, will receive a hundredfold, and will inherit continuous life; <verse eid="MAT 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 19:30"/>and many first will be last, and last first.”<verse eid="MAT 19:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="MAT 20"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 20:1"/>“For the kingdom of the heavens is like to a man, a householder, who went forth with the morning to hire workmen for his vineyard, <verse eid="MAT 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 20:2"/>and having agreed with the workmen for a denarius a day, he sent them into his vineyard. <verse eid="MAT 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 20:3"/>And having gone forth about the third hour, he saw others standing in the marketplace idle, <verse eid="MAT 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 20:4"/>and to these he said, Go—also you—to the vineyard, and whatever may be righteous I will give you; <verse eid="MAT 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 20:5"/>and they went away. Again, having gone forth about the sixth and the ninth hour, he did in like manner. <verse eid="MAT 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 20:6"/>And about the eleventh hour, having gone forth, he found others standing idle and says to them, Why have you stood here idle all day? <verse eid="MAT 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 20:7"/>They say to him, Because no one hired us; he says to them, Go—you also—to the vineyard, and whatever may be righteous you will receive. <verse eid="MAT 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 20:8"/>And evening having come, the lord of the vineyard says to his steward, Call the workmen, and pay them the reward, having begun from the last—to the first. <verse eid="MAT 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 20:9"/>And they of about the eleventh hour having come, each received a denarius. <verse eid="MAT 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 20:10"/>And the first having come, supposed that they will receive more, and they received, they also, each a denarius, <verse eid="MAT 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 20:11"/>and having received [it], they were murmuring against the householder, saying, <verse eid="MAT 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 20:12"/>that, These, the last, worked one hour, and you made them equal to us, who were bearing the burden of the day—and the heat. <verse eid="MAT 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 20:13"/>And he answering said to one of them, Friend, I do no unrighteousness to you; did you not agree with me for a denarius? <verse eid="MAT 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 20:14"/>Take that which is yours, and go; and I will to give to this, the last, also as to you; <verse eid="MAT 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 20:15"/>is it not lawful to me to do what I will in my own? Is your eye evil because I am good? <verse eid="MAT 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 20:16"/>So the last will be first, and the first last, for many are called, and few chosen.” <verse eid="MAT 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 20:17"/>And Jesus going up to Jerusalem, took the twelve disciples by themselves in the way and said to them, <verse eid="MAT 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 20:18"/>“Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be delivered to the chief priests and scribes, <verse eid="MAT 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 20:19"/>and they will condemn Him to death, and will deliver Him to the nations to mock, and to scourge, and to crucify, and the third day He will rise again.” <verse eid="MAT 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 20:20"/>Then came near to Him the mother of the sons of Zebedee, with her sons, prostrating and asking something from Him, <verse eid="MAT 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 20:21"/>and He said to her, “What do you will?” She says to Him, “Say that they may sit—these two sons of mine—one on Your right hand and one on the left, in Your kingdom.” <verse eid="MAT 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 20:22"/>And Jesus answering said, “You have not known what you ask for yourselves; are you able to drink of the cup that I am about to drink? And with the immersion that I am immersed with, to be immersed?” They say to Him, “We are able.” <verse eid="MAT 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 20:23"/>And He says to them, “Of My cup indeed you will drink, and with the immersion that I am immersed with you will be immersed; but to sit on My right hand and on My left is not Mine to give, but—to those for whom it has been prepared by My Father.” <verse eid="MAT 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 20:24"/>And the ten having heard, were much displeased with the two brothers, <verse eid="MAT 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 20:25"/>and Jesus having called them near, said, “You have known that the rulers of the nations exercise lordship over them, and those [who are] great exercise authority over them, <verse eid="MAT 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 20:26"/>but not so will it be among you, but whoever may will among you to become great, let him be your servant; <verse eid="MAT 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 20:27"/>and whoever may will among you to be first, let him be your servant; <verse eid="MAT 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 20:28"/>even as the Son of Man did not come to be ministered to, but to minister, and to give His life [as] a ransom for many.” <verse eid="MAT 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 20:29"/>And they going forth from Jericho, there followed Him a great multitude, <verse eid="MAT 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 20:30"/>and behold, two blind men sitting by the way, having heard that Jesus passes by, cried, saying, “Deal kindly with us, Lord—Son of David.” <verse eid="MAT 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 20:31"/>And the multitude charged them that they might be silent, and they cried out the more, saying, “Deal kindly with us Lord—Son of David.” <verse eid="MAT 20:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 20:32"/>And having stood, Jesus called them and said, “What do you will [that] I may do to you?” <verse eid="MAT 20:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 20:33"/>They say to Him, “Lord, that our eyes may be opened”; <verse eid="MAT 20:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 20:34"/>and having been moved with compassion, Jesus touched their eyes, and immediately their eyes received sight, and they followed Him.<verse eid="MAT 20:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="MAT 21"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 21:1"/>And when they came near to Jerusalem, and came to Bethphage, to the Mount of Olives, then Jesus sent two disciples, <verse eid="MAT 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 21:2"/>saying to them, “Go on into the village in front of you, and immediately you will find a donkey bound, and a colt with her—having loosed, you bring to Me; <verse eid="MAT 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 21:3"/>and if anyone may say anything to you, you will say that the LORD has need of them, and immediately He will send them.” <verse eid="MAT 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 21:4"/>And all this came to pass, that it might be fulfilled that was spoken through the prophet, saying, <verse eid="MAT 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 21:5"/>“Tell the daughter of Zion, Behold, your King comes to you, meek, and mounted on a donkey, and a colt, a foal of a beast of burden.” <verse eid="MAT 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 21:6"/>And the disciples having gone and having done as Jesus commanded them, <verse eid="MAT 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 21:7"/>brought the donkey and the colt, and put on them their garments, and set [Him] on them; <verse eid="MAT 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 21:8"/>and the very great multitude spread their own garments in the way, and others were cutting branches from the trees, and were strewing in the way, <verse eid="MAT 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 21:9"/>and the multitudes who were going before, and who were following, were crying, saying, “Hosanna to the Son of David, blessed is He who is coming in the Name of the LORD; Hosanna in the highest!” <verse eid="MAT 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 21:10"/>And He having entered into Jerusalem, all the city was moved, saying, “Who is this?” <verse eid="MAT 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 21:11"/>And the multitudes said, “This is Jesus the prophet, who [is] from Nazareth of Galilee.” <verse eid="MAT 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 21:12"/>And Jesus entered into the temple of God, and cast forth all those selling and buying in the temple, and the tables of the money-changers He overturned, and the seats of those selling the doves, <verse eid="MAT 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 21:13"/>and He says to them, “It has been written: My house will be called a house of prayer; but you made it a den of robbers.” <verse eid="MAT 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 21:14"/>And there came to Him blind and lame men in the temple, and He healed them, <verse eid="MAT 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 21:15"/>and the chief priests and the scribes having seen the wonderful things that He did, and the children crying in the temple, and saying, “Hosanna to the Son of David,” were much displeased; <verse eid="MAT 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 21:16"/>and they said to Him, “Do You hear what these say?” And Jesus says to them, “Yes, did you never read, that, Out of the mouth of babies and sucklings You prepared praise?” <verse eid="MAT 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 21:17"/>And having left them, He went forth out of the city to Bethany, and lodged there, <verse eid="MAT 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 21:18"/>and in the morning turning back to the city, He hungered, <verse eid="MAT 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 21:19"/>and having seen a certain fig tree on the way, He came to it, and found nothing in it except leaves only, and He says to it, “No more fruit may be from you—throughout the age”; and instantly the fig tree withered. <verse eid="MAT 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 21:20"/>And the disciples having seen, wondered, saying, “How did the fig tree instantly wither?” <verse eid="MAT 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 21:21"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “Truly I say to you, if you may have faith, and may not doubt, not only this of the fig tree will you do, but even if to this mountain you may say, Be lifted up and be cast into the sea, it will come to pass; <verse eid="MAT 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 21:22"/>and all—as much as you may ask in the prayer, believing, you will receive.” <verse eid="MAT 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 21:23"/>And He having come into the temple, there came to Him when teaching the chief priests and the elders of the people, saying, “By what authority do You do these things? And who gave You this authority?” <verse eid="MAT 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 21:24"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “I will ask you—I also—one word, which if you may tell Me, I also will tell you by what authority I do these things; <verse eid="MAT 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 21:25"/>the immersion of John, from where was it? From Heaven, or from men?” And they were reasoning with themselves, saying, “If we should say, From Heaven, He will say to us, Why, then, did you not believe him? <verse eid="MAT 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 21:26"/>And if we should say, From men, we fear the multitude, for all hold John as a prophet.” <verse eid="MAT 21:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 21:27"/>And answering Jesus they said, “We have not known.” He said to them—He also, “Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things. <verse eid="MAT 21:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 21:28"/>And what do you think? A man had two children, and having come to the first, he said, Child, go, today be working in my vineyard. <verse eid="MAT 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 21:29"/>And he answering said, I will not, but at last, having regretted, he went. <verse eid="MAT 21:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 21:30"/>And having come to the second, he said in the same manner, and he answering said, I [go], lord, and did not go; <verse eid="MAT 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 21:31"/>which of the two did the will of the father?” They say to Him, “The first.” Jesus says to them, “Truly I say to you that the tax collectors and the prostitutes go before you into the Kingdom of God, <verse eid="MAT 21:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 21:32"/>for John came to you in the way of righteousness, and you did not believe him, and the tax collectors and the prostitutes believed him, and you, having seen, did not regret at last—to believe him. <verse eid="MAT 21:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 21:33"/>Hear another allegory: There was a certain man, a householder, who planted a vineyard, and put a hedge around it, and dug in it a winepress, and built a tower, and gave it out to farmers, and went abroad. <verse eid="MAT 21:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 21:34"/>And when the season of the fruits came near, he sent his servants to the farmers, to receive the fruits of it, <verse eid="MAT 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 21:35"/>and the farmers having taken his servants, one they scourged, and one they killed, and one they stoned. <verse eid="MAT 21:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 21:36"/>Again he sent other servants more than the first, and they did to them in the same manner. <verse eid="MAT 21:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 21:37"/>And at last he sent to them his son, saying, They will respect my son; <verse eid="MAT 21:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 21:38"/>and the farmers having seen the son, said among themselves, This is the heir, come, we may kill him, and may possess his inheritance; <verse eid="MAT 21:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 21:39"/>and having taken him, they cast [him] out of the vineyard, and killed him; <verse eid="MAT 21:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 21:40"/>whenever therefore the lord of the vineyard may come, what will he do to these farmers?” <verse eid="MAT 21:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 21:41"/>They say to Him, “Evil men—he will grievously destroy them, and will give out the vineyard to other farmers who will give back to him the fruits in their seasons.” <verse eid="MAT 21:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 21:42"/>Jesus says to them, “Did you never read in the Writings: A stone that the builders disallowed, it became head of a corner; from the LORD has this come to pass, and it is wonderful in our eyes? <verse eid="MAT 21:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 21:43"/>Because of this I say to you that the Kingdom of God will be taken from you, and given to a nation bringing forth its fruit; <verse eid="MAT 21:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 21:44"/>and he who is falling on this stone will be broken, and on whomsoever it may fall it will crush him to pieces.” <verse eid="MAT 21:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 21:45"/>And the chief priests and the Pharisees having heard His allegories, knew that He speaks of them, <verse eid="MAT 21:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 21:46"/>and seeking to lay hold on Him, they feared the multitudes, seeing they were holding Him as a prophet.<verse eid="MAT 21:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="MAT 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 22:1"/>And Jesus answering, again spoke to them in allegories, saying, <verse eid="MAT 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 22:2"/>“The kingdom of the heavens was likened to a man, a king, who made wedding feasts for his son, <verse eid="MAT 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 22:3"/>and he sent forth his servants to call those having been called to the wedding feasts, and they were not willing to come. <verse eid="MAT 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 22:4"/>Again he sent forth other servants, saying, Say to those who have been called: Behold, I prepared my early meal, my oxen and the fatlings have been killed, and all things [are] ready, come to the wedding feasts; <verse eid="MAT 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 22:5"/>and they, having disregarded [it], went away, one to his own field, and the other to his merchandise; <verse eid="MAT 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 22:6"/>and the rest, having laid hold on his servants, mistreated and slew [them]. <verse eid="MAT 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 22:7"/>And the king having heard, was angry, and having sent forth his soldiers, he destroyed those murderers, and their city he set on fire; <verse eid="MAT 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 22:8"/>then he says to his servants, The wedding feast indeed is ready, and those called were not worthy, <verse eid="MAT 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 22:9"/>be going, then, on to the cross-ways, and as many as you may find, call to the wedding feasts. <verse eid="MAT 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 22:10"/>And those servants, having gone forth to the ways, gathered all, as many as they found, both bad and good, and the wedding was filled with those reclining. <verse eid="MAT 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 22:11"/>And the king having come in to view those reclining, saw there a man not clothed with wedding clothes, <verse eid="MAT 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 22:12"/>and he says to him, Friend, how did you come in here, not having wedding clothes? And he was speechless. <verse eid="MAT 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 22:13"/>Then the king said to the servants, Having bound his feet and hands, take him up and cast forth into the outer darkness, there will be the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth; <verse eid="MAT 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 22:14"/>for many are called, and few chosen.” <verse eid="MAT 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 22:15"/>Then the Pharisees having gone, took counsel how they might ensnare Him in words, <verse eid="MAT 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 22:16"/>and they send to Him their disciples with the Herodians, saying, “Teacher, we have known that You are true, and the way of God in truth You teach, and You are not caring for anyone, for You do not look to the face of men; <verse eid="MAT 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 22:17"/>tell us, therefore, what do You think? Is it lawful to give tribute to Caesar or not?” <verse eid="MAT 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 22:18"/>And Jesus having known their wickedness, said, “Why do you tempt Me, hypocrites? <verse eid="MAT 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 22:19"/>Show Me the tribute-coin.” And they brought to Him a denarius; <verse eid="MAT 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 22:20"/>and He says to them, “Whose [is] this image and the inscription?” <verse eid="MAT 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 22:21"/>They say to Him, “Caesar’s”; then He says to them, “Render therefore the things of Caesar to Caesar, and the things of God to God”; <verse eid="MAT 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 22:22"/>and having heard they wondered, and having left Him they went away. <verse eid="MAT 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 22:23"/>In that day there came near to Him Sadducees who are saying there is not a resurrection, and they questioned Him, saying, <verse eid="MAT 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 22:24"/>“Teacher, Moses said if anyone may die having no children, his brother will marry his wife, and will raise up seed to his brother. <verse eid="MAT 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 22:25"/>And there were with us seven brothers, and the first having married died, and having no seed, he left his wife to his brother; <verse eid="MAT 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 22:26"/>in like manner also the second, and the third, to the seventh, <verse eid="MAT 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 22:27"/>and last of all the woman also died; <verse eid="MAT 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 22:28"/>therefore in the resurrection, of which of the seven will she be wife—for all had her?” <verse eid="MAT 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 22:29"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “You go astray, not knowing the Writings, nor the power of God; <verse eid="MAT 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 22:30"/>for in the resurrection they do not marry, nor are they given in marriage, but are as messengers of God in Heaven. <verse eid="MAT 22:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 22:31"/>And concerning the resurrection of the dead, did you not read that which was spoken to you by God, saying, <verse eid="MAT 22:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 22:32"/>I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? God is not a God of dead men, but of living.” <verse eid="MAT 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 22:33"/>And having heard, the multitudes were astonished at His teaching; <verse eid="MAT 22:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 22:34"/>and the Pharisees, having heard that He silenced the Sadducees, were gathered together to Him; <verse eid="MAT 22:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 22:35"/>and one of them, a lawyer, questioned, tempting Him, and saying, <verse eid="MAT 22:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 22:36"/>“Teacher, which [is] the great command in the Law?” <verse eid="MAT 22:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 22:37"/>And Jesus said to him, “You will love the LORD your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your understanding— <verse eid="MAT 22:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 22:38"/>this is a first and great command; <verse eid="MAT 22:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 22:39"/>and the second [is] like to it: You will love your neighbor as yourself; <verse eid="MAT 22:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 22:40"/>on these—the two commands—all the Law and the Prophets hang.” <verse eid="MAT 22:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 22:41"/>And the Pharisees having been gathered together, Jesus questioned them, <verse eid="MAT 22:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 22:42"/>saying, “What do you think concerning the Christ? Of whom is He Son?” They say to Him, “Of David.” <verse eid="MAT 22:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 22:43"/>He says to them, “How then does David in the Spirit call Him Lord, saying, <verse eid="MAT 22:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 22:44"/>The LORD said to my Lord, || Sit at My right hand, || Until I may make Your enemies Your footstool? <verse eid="MAT 22:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 22:45"/>If then David calls Him Lord, how is He his son?” <verse eid="MAT 22:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 22:46"/>And no one was able to answer Him a word, nor did any dare question Him from that day [on].<verse eid="MAT 22:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="MAT 23"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 23:1"/>Then Jesus spoke to the multitudes, and to His disciples, <verse eid="MAT 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 23:2"/>saying, “On the seat of Moses sat down the scribes and the Pharisees; <verse eid="MAT 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 23:3"/>all, then, as much as they may say to you to observe, observe and do, but according to their works do not do, for they say, and do not do; <verse eid="MAT 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 23:4"/>for they bind together burdens [too] heavy and grievous to bear, and lay [them] on the shoulders of men, but with their finger they will not move them. <verse eid="MAT 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 23:5"/>And all their works they do to be seen by men, and they make broad their phylacteries, and enlarge the fringes of their garments, <verse eid="MAT 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 23:6"/>they also cherish the first couches at the banquets, and the first seats in the synagogues, <verse eid="MAT 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 23:7"/>and the salutations in the marketplaces, and to be called by men, Rabbi, Rabbi. <verse eid="MAT 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 23:8"/>And you may not be called Rabbi, for one is your teacher—the Christ, and you are all brothers; <verse eid="MAT 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 23:9"/>and you may not call [any] your father on the earth, for one is your Father, who is in the heavens, <verse eid="MAT 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 23:10"/>nor may you be called teachers, for one is your teacher—the Christ. <verse eid="MAT 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 23:11"/>And the greater of you will be your servant, <verse eid="MAT 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 23:12"/>and whoever will exalt himself will be humbled, and whoever will humble himself will be exalted. <verse eid="MAT 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 23:13"/>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you shut up the kingdom of the heavens before men, for you do not go in, nor do you permit those going in to enter. <verse eid="MAT 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 23:14"/><char style="bd">[[</char>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you eat up the houses of the widows, and for a pretense make long prayers, because of this you will receive more abundant judgment.<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MAT 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 23:15"/>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you go around the sea and the dry land to make one proselyte, and whenever it may happen—you make him a son of Gehenna twofold more than yourselves. <verse eid="MAT 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 23:16"/>Woe to you, blind guides, who are saying, Whoever may swear by the temple, it is nothing, but whoever may swear by the gold of the temple—is debtor! <verse eid="MAT 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 23:17"/>Fools and blind! For which [is] greater, the gold, or the temple that is sanctifying the gold? <verse eid="MAT 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 23:18"/>And, Whoever may swear by the altar, it is nothing, but whoever may swear by the gift that is on it—is debtor! <verse eid="MAT 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 23:19"/>Fools and blind! For which [is] greater, the gift, or the altar that is sanctifying the gift? <verse eid="MAT 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 23:20"/>He therefore who swore by the altar, swears by it, and by all things on it; <verse eid="MAT 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 23:21"/>and he who swore by the temple, swears by it, and by Him who is dwelling in it; <verse eid="MAT 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 23:22"/>and he who swore by Heaven, swears by the throne of God, and by Him who is sitting on it. <verse eid="MAT 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 23:23"/>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you give tithe of the mint, and the dill, and the cumin, and neglected the weightier things of the Law—judgment, and kindness, and faith; these it was necessary to do, and those not to neglect. <verse eid="MAT 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 23:24"/>Blind guides! Who are straining out the gnat, and are swallowing the camel. <verse eid="MAT 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 23:25"/>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you make clean the outside of the cup and the plate, and within they are full of robbery and self-indulgence. <verse eid="MAT 23:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 23:26"/>Blind Pharisee! First cleanse the inside of the cup and the plate, that the outside of them may also become clean. <verse eid="MAT 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 23:27"/>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you are like to whitewashed graves, which outwardly indeed appear beautiful, and within are full of bones of dead men, and of all uncleanness; <verse eid="MAT 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 23:28"/>so also you outwardly indeed appear to men righteous, and within you are full of hypocrisy and lawlessness. <verse eid="MAT 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 23:29"/>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you build the graves of the prophets, and adorn the tombs of the righteous, <verse eid="MAT 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 23:30"/>and say, If we had been in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets. <verse eid="MAT 23:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 23:31"/>So that you testify to yourselves that you are sons of them who murdered the prophets; <verse eid="MAT 23:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 23:32"/>and you fill up the measure of your fathers. <verse eid="MAT 23:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 23:33"/>Serpents! Brood of vipers! How may you escape from the judgment of Gehenna? <verse eid="MAT 23:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 23:34"/>Because of this, behold, I send to you prophets, and wise men, and scribes, and of them you will kill and crucify, and of them you will scourge in your synagogues, and will pursue from city to city, <verse eid="MAT 23:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 23:35"/>that on you may come all the righteous blood being poured out on the earth from the blood of Abel the righteous, to the blood of Zacharias son of Barachias, whom you murdered between the temple and the altar: <verse eid="MAT 23:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 23:36"/>truly I say to you, all these things will come on this generation. <verse eid="MAT 23:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 23:37"/>Jerusalem, Jerusalem, that are killing the prophets, and stoning those sent to you, how often I willed to gather your children together, as a hen gathers her own chickens under the wings, and you did not will. <verse eid="MAT 23:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 23:38"/>Behold, your house is left to you desolate; <verse eid="MAT 23:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 23:39"/>for I say to you, you may not see Me from now on, until you may say, Blessed [is] He who is coming in the Name of the LORD.”<verse eid="MAT 23:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="MAT 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 24:1"/>And having gone forth, Jesus departed from the temple, and His disciples came near to show Him the buildings of the temple, <verse eid="MAT 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 24:2"/>and Jesus said to them, “Do you not see all these? Truly I say to you, there may not be left here a stone on a stone that will not be thrown down.” <verse eid="MAT 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 24:3"/>And when He is sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples came near to Him by Himself, saying, “Tell us, when will these be? And what [is] the sign of Your coming, and of the full end of the age?” <verse eid="MAT 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 24:4"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “Take heed that no one may lead you astray, <verse eid="MAT 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 24:5"/>for many will come in My Name, saying, I am the Christ, and they will lead many astray, <verse eid="MAT 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 24:6"/>and you will begin to hear of wars, and reports of wars; see, do not be troubled, for it is necessary for all [these] to come to pass, but the end is not yet. <verse eid="MAT 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 24:7"/>For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be famines, and pestilences, and earthquakes, in various places; <verse eid="MAT 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 24:8"/>and all these [are the] beginning of travails; <verse eid="MAT 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 24:9"/>then they will deliver you up to tribulation, and will kill you, and you will be hated by all the nations because of My Name; <verse eid="MAT 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 24:10"/>and then will many be stumbled, and they will deliver up one another, and will hate one another. <verse eid="MAT 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 24:11"/>And many false prophets will arise, and will lead many astray; <verse eid="MAT 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 24:12"/>and because of the abounding of the lawlessness, the love of the many will become cold; <verse eid="MAT 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 24:13"/>but he who endured to the end, he will be saved; <verse eid="MAT 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 24:14"/>and this good news of the kingdom will be proclaimed in all the world, for a testimony to all the nations, and then will the end arrive. <verse eid="MAT 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 24:15"/>Whenever, therefore, you may see the abomination of the desolation, that was spoken of through Daniel the prophet, standing in the holy place (whoever is reading let him observe) <verse eid="MAT 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 24:16"/>then those in Judea—let them flee to the mountains; <verse eid="MAT 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 24:17"/>he on the housetop—do not let him come down to take up anything out of his house; <verse eid="MAT 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 24:18"/>and he in the field—do not let him turn back to take his garments. <verse eid="MAT 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 24:19"/>And woe to those with child, and to those giving suck in those days; <verse eid="MAT 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 24:20"/>and pray that your flight may not be in winter, nor on a Sabbath; <verse eid="MAT 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 24:21"/>for there will then be great tribulation, such as was not from the beginning of the world until now, no, nor may be. <verse eid="MAT 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 24:22"/>And if those days were not shortened, no flesh would have been saved; but because of the chosen will those days be shortened. <verse eid="MAT 24:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 24:23"/>Then if anyone may say to you, Behold, here [is] the Christ! Or, Here! You may not believe; <verse eid="MAT 24:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 24:24"/>for there will arise false Christs, and false prophets, and they will give great signs and wonders, so as to lead astray, if possible, also the chosen. <verse eid="MAT 24:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 24:25"/>Behold, I told you beforehand. <verse eid="MAT 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 24:26"/>If therefore they may say to you, Behold, He is in the wilderness, you may not go forth; Behold, in the inner chambers, you may not believe; <verse eid="MAT 24:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 24:27"/>for as the lightning comes forth from the east, and appears to the west, so will also be the coming of the Son of Man; <verse eid="MAT 24:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 24:28"/>for wherever the carcass may be, there the eagles will be gathered together. <verse eid="MAT 24:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 24:29"/>And immediately after the tribulation of those days, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give her light, and the stars will fall from the sky, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken; <verse eid="MAT 24:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 24:30"/>and then will appear the sign of the Son of Man in the sky; and then will all the tribes of the earth strike the breast, and they will see the Son of Man coming on the clouds of Heaven, with power and much glory; <verse eid="MAT 24:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 24:31"/>and He will send His messengers with a great sound of a trumpet, and they will gather together His chosen from the four winds, from the ends of the heavens to the ends thereof. <verse eid="MAT 24:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 24:32"/>And from the fig tree learn the allegory: when its branch may have already become tender, and it may put forth the leaves, you know that summer [is] near, <verse eid="MAT 24:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 24:33"/>so also you, when you may see all these, you know that it is near—at the doors. <verse eid="MAT 24:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 24:34"/>Truly I say to you, this generation may not pass away until all these may come to pass. <verse eid="MAT 24:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 24:35"/>The heaven and the earth will pass away, but My words will not pass away. <verse eid="MAT 24:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 24:36"/>And concerning that day and the hour no one has known—not even the messengers of the heavens—except My Father only; <verse eid="MAT 24:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 24:37"/>and as the days of Noah—so will also be the coming of the Son of Man; <verse eid="MAT 24:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 24:38"/>for as they were, in the days before the flood, eating, and drinking, marrying, and giving in marriage, until the day Noah entered into the Ark, <verse eid="MAT 24:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 24:39"/>and they did not know until the flood came and took all away, so will also be the coming of the Son of Man. <verse eid="MAT 24:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 24:40"/>Then two [men] will be in the field: one is received, and one is left; <verse eid="MAT 24:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 24:41"/>two [women] will be grinding in the mill: one is received, and one is left. <verse eid="MAT 24:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 24:42"/>Watch therefore, because you have not known in what hour your Lord comes; <verse eid="MAT 24:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 24:43"/>and know this, that if the master of the house had known in what watch the thief comes, he had watched, and did not permit his house to be broken through; <verse eid="MAT 24:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 24:44"/>because of this also you, become ready, because in what hour you do not think, the Son of Man comes. <verse eid="MAT 24:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 24:45"/>Who, then, is the servant, faithful and wise, whom his lord set over his household, to give them the nourishment in season? <verse eid="MAT 24:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 24:46"/>Blessed that servant, whom his lord, having come, will find doing so; <verse eid="MAT 24:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MAT 24:47"/>truly I say to you that he will set him over all his substance. <verse eid="MAT 24:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MAT 24:48"/>And if that evil servant may say in his heart, My lord delays to come, <verse eid="MAT 24:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MAT 24:49"/>and may begin to beat the fellow-servants, and to eat and to drink with the drunken, <verse eid="MAT 24:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MAT 24:50"/>the lord of that servant will arrive in a day when he does not expect, and in an hour of which he does not know, <verse eid="MAT 24:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MAT 24:51"/>and will cut him off, and will appoint his portion with the hypocrites; there will be the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth.”<verse eid="MAT 24:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="MAT 25"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 25:1"/>“Then will the kingdom of the heavens be likened to ten virgins, who, having taken their lamps, went forth to meet the bridegroom; <verse eid="MAT 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 25:2"/>and five of them were prudent, and five foolish; <verse eid="MAT 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 25:3"/>they who were foolish having taken their lamps, did not take with themselves oil; <verse eid="MAT 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 25:4"/>and the prudent took oil in their vessels, with their lamps. <verse eid="MAT 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 25:5"/>And the bridegroom lingering, they all nodded and were sleeping, <verse eid="MAT 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 25:6"/>and in the middle of the night a cry was made, Behold, the bridegroom comes; go forth to meet him! <verse eid="MAT 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 25:7"/>Then all those virgins rose, and trimmed their lamps, <verse eid="MAT 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 25:8"/>and the foolish said to the prudent, Give us of your oil, because our lamps are going out; <verse eid="MAT 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 25:9"/>and the prudent answered, saying, Lest there may not be sufficient for us and you, go rather to those selling, and buy for yourselves. <verse eid="MAT 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 25:10"/>And while they are going away to buy, the bridegroom came, and those ready went in with him to the wedding feasts, and the door was shut; <verse eid="MAT 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 25:11"/>and afterward come also the rest of the virgins, saying, Lord, lord, open to us; <verse eid="MAT 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 25:12"/>and he answering said, Truly I say to you, I have not known you. <verse eid="MAT 25:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 25:13"/>Watch therefore, for you have not known the day nor the hour in which the Son of Man comes. <verse eid="MAT 25:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 25:14"/>For—as a man going abroad called his own servants, and delivered to them his substance, <verse eid="MAT 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 25:15"/>and to one he gave five talents, and to another two, and to another one, to each according to his several ability, went abroad immediately. <verse eid="MAT 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 25:16"/>And he who received the five talents, having gone, worked with them, and made five other talents; <verse eid="MAT 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 25:17"/>in like manner also he who [received] the two, he gained, also he, other two; <verse eid="MAT 25:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 25:18"/>and he who received the one, having gone away, dug in the earth, and hid his lord’s money. <verse eid="MAT 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 25:19"/>And after a long time comes the lord of those servants, and takes reckoning with them; <verse eid="MAT 25:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 25:20"/>and he who received the five talents, having come, brought five other talents, saying, Lord, you delivered five talents to me; behold, I gained five other talents besides them. <verse eid="MAT 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 25:21"/>And his lord said to him, Well done, good and faithful servant, you were faithful over a few things, I will set you over many things; enter into the joy of your lord. <verse eid="MAT 25:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 25:22"/>And he also, who received the two talents, having come, said, Lord, you delivered to me two talents; behold, I gained two other talents besides them. <verse eid="MAT 25:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 25:23"/>His lord said to him, Well done, good and faithful servant, you were faithful over a few things, I will set you over many things; enter into the joy of your lord. <verse eid="MAT 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 25:24"/>And he also who has received the one talent, having come, said, Lord, I knew you, that you are a hard man, reaping where you did not sow, and gathering from where you did not scatter; <verse eid="MAT 25:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 25:25"/>and having been afraid, having gone away, I hid your talent in the earth; behold, you have your own! <verse eid="MAT 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 25:26"/>And his lord answering said to him, Evil servant, and slothful, you had known that I reap where I did not sow, and I gather from where I did not scatter! <verse eid="MAT 25:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 25:27"/>It was necessary [for] you then to put my money to the money-lenders, and having come I had received my own with increase. <verse eid="MAT 25:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 25:28"/>Take therefore from him the talent, and give to him having the ten talents, <verse eid="MAT 25:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 25:29"/>for to everyone having will be given, and he will have overabundance, and from him who is not having, even that which he has will be taken from him; <verse eid="MAT 25:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 25:30"/>and cast forth the unprofitable servant into the outer darkness; there will be the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth. <verse eid="MAT 25:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 25:31"/>And whenever the Son of Man may come in His glory, and all the holy messengers with Him, then He will sit on a throne of His glory; <verse eid="MAT 25:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 25:32"/>and all the nations will be gathered together before Him, and He will separate them from one another, as the shepherd separates the sheep from the goats, <verse eid="MAT 25:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 25:33"/>and He will set the sheep indeed on His right hand, and the goats on the left. <verse eid="MAT 25:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 25:34"/>Then the King will say to those on His right hand, Come, the blessed of My Father, inherit the kingdom that has been prepared for you from the foundation of the world; <verse eid="MAT 25:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 25:35"/>for I hungered, and you gave Me to eat; I thirsted, and you gave Me to drink; I was a stranger, and you received Me; <verse eid="MAT 25:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 25:36"/>naked, and you clothed Me; I was sick, and you looked after Me; I was in prison, and you came to Me. <verse eid="MAT 25:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 25:37"/>Then will the righteous answer Him, saying, Lord, when did we see You hungering, and we nourished? Or thirsting, and we gave to drink? <verse eid="MAT 25:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 25:38"/>And when did we see You a stranger, and we received? Or naked, and we clothed? <verse eid="MAT 25:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 25:39"/>And when did we see You ailing or in prison, and we came to You? <verse eid="MAT 25:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 25:40"/>And the King answering, will say to them, Truly I say to you, inasmuch as you did [it] to one of these My brothers—the least—you did [it] to Me. <verse eid="MAT 25:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 25:41"/>Then will He say also to those on the left hand, Go from Me, the cursed, into the continuous fire that has been prepared for the Devil and his messengers; <verse eid="MAT 25:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 25:42"/>for I hungered, and you gave Me nothing to eat; I thirsted, and you gave Me nothing to drink; <verse eid="MAT 25:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 25:43"/>I was a stranger, and you did not receive Me; naked, and you did not clothe Me; sick and in prison, and you did not look after Me. <verse eid="MAT 25:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 25:44"/>Then they will answer, they also, saying, Lord, when did we see You hungering, or thirsting, or a stranger, or naked, or sick, or in prison, and we did not minister to You? <verse eid="MAT 25:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 25:45"/>Then will He answer them, saying, Truly I say to you, inasmuch as you did [it] not to one of these, the least, you did [it] not to Me. <verse eid="MAT 25:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 25:46"/>And these will go away into continuous punishment, but the righteous into continuous life.”<verse eid="MAT 25:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="MAT 26"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 26:1"/>And it came to pass, when Jesus finished all these words, He said to His disciples, <verse eid="MAT 26:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 26:2"/>“You have known that after two days the Passover comes, and the Son of Man is delivered up to be crucified.” <verse eid="MAT 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 26:3"/>Then were gathered together the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders of the people, into the court of the chief priest who was called Caiaphas; <verse eid="MAT 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 26:4"/>and they consulted together that they might take Jesus by guile, and kill [Him], <verse eid="MAT 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 26:5"/>and they said, “Not in the celebration, that there may not be a tumult among the people.” <verse eid="MAT 26:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 26:6"/>And Jesus having been in Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper, <verse eid="MAT 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 26:7"/>there came to Him a woman having an alabaster box of ointment, very precious, and she poured on His head as He is reclining. <verse eid="MAT 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 26:8"/>And having seen [it], His disciples were much displeased, saying, “To what purpose [is] this waste? <verse eid="MAT 26:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 26:9"/>For this ointment could have been sold for much, and given to the poor.” <verse eid="MAT 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 26:10"/>And Jesus having known, said to them, “Why do you give trouble to the woman? For a good work she worked for Me; <verse eid="MAT 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 26:11"/>for you always have the poor with you, and you do not always have Me; <verse eid="MAT 26:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 26:12"/>for she having put this ointment on My body—for My burial she did [it]. <verse eid="MAT 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 26:13"/>Truly I say to you, wherever this good news may be proclaimed in the whole world, what this [one] did will also be spoken of—for a memorial of her.” <verse eid="MAT 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 26:14"/>Then one of the Twelve, who is called Judas Iscariot, having gone to the chief priests, said, <verse eid="MAT 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 26:15"/>“What are you willing to give me, and I will deliver Him up to you?” And they weighed out to him thirty pieces of silver, <verse eid="MAT 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 26:16"/>and from that time he was seeking a convenient season to deliver Him up. <verse eid="MAT 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 26:17"/>And on the first [day] of the Unleavened [Bread] the disciples came near to Jesus, saying to Him, “Where will You [that] we may prepare for You to eat the Passover?” <verse eid="MAT 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 26:18"/>And He said, “Go away into the city, to such a one, and say to him, The Teacher says, My time is near; near you I keep the Passover with My disciples”; <verse eid="MAT 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 26:19"/>and the disciples did as Jesus appointed them, and prepared the Passover. <verse eid="MAT 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 26:20"/>And evening having come, He was reclining with the Twelve, <verse eid="MAT 26:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 26:21"/>and while they are eating, He said, “Truly I say to you that one of you will deliver Me up.” <verse eid="MAT 26:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 26:22"/>And being grieved exceedingly, they began to say to Him, each of them, “Is it I, Lord?” <verse eid="MAT 26:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 26:23"/>And He answering said, “He who dipped with Me the hand in the dish, he will deliver Me up; <verse eid="MAT 26:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 26:24"/>the Son of Man indeed goes, as it has been written concerning Him, but woe to that man through whom the Son of Man is delivered up! It were good for him if that man had not been born.” <verse eid="MAT 26:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 26:25"/>And Judas—he who delivered Him up—answering said, “Is it I, Rabbi?” He says to him, “You have said.” <verse eid="MAT 26:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 26:26"/>And while they were eating, Jesus having taken the bread, and having blessed, broke, and was giving [it] to the disciples, and said, “Take, eat, this is My body”; <verse eid="MAT 26:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 26:27"/>and having taken the cup, and having given thanks, He gave to them, saying, “Drink of it—all; <verse eid="MAT 26:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 26:28"/>for this is My blood of the New Covenant, that is being poured out for many, for forgiveness of sins; <verse eid="MAT 26:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 26:29"/>and I say to you that I may not drink from now on this produce of the vine, until that day when I may drink it with you new in the kingdom of My Father.” <verse eid="MAT 26:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 26:30"/>And having sung a hymn, they went forth to the Mount of Olives; <verse eid="MAT 26:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 26:31"/>then Jesus says to them, “All you will be stumbled at Me this night; for it has been written: I will strike the Shepherd, and the sheep of the flock will be scattered abroad; <verse eid="MAT 26:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 26:32"/>but after My having risen, I will go before you to Galilee.” <verse eid="MAT 26:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 26:33"/>And Peter answering said to Him, “Even if all will be stumbled at You, I will never be stumbled.” <verse eid="MAT 26:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 26:34"/>Jesus said to him, “Truly I say to you that this night, before rooster-crowing, three times you will deny Me.” <verse eid="MAT 26:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 26:35"/>Peter says to Him, “Even if it may be necessary for me to die with You, I will not deny You”; in like manner also said all the disciples. <verse eid="MAT 26:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 26:36"/>Then Jesus comes with them to a place called Gethsemane, and He says to the disciples, “Sit here, until having gone away, I will pray over there.” <verse eid="MAT 26:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 26:37"/>And having taken Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, He began to be sorrowful, and to be very heavy; <verse eid="MAT 26:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 26:38"/>then He says to them, “Exceedingly sorrowful is My soul—to death; abide here, and watch with Me.” <verse eid="MAT 26:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 26:39"/>And having gone forward a little, He fell on His face, praying, and saying, “My Father, if it be possible, let this cup pass from Me; nevertheless, not as I will, but as You.” <verse eid="MAT 26:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 26:40"/>And He comes to the disciples, and finds them sleeping, and He says to Peter, “So! You were not able to watch with Me one hour! <verse eid="MAT 26:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 26:41"/>Watch, and pray, that you may not enter into temptation: the spirit indeed is forward, but the flesh weak.” <verse eid="MAT 26:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 26:42"/>Again, a second time, having gone away, He prayed, saying, “My Father, if this cup cannot pass away from Me except I drink it, Your will be done”; <verse eid="MAT 26:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 26:43"/>and having come, He finds them again sleeping, for their eyes were heavy. <verse eid="MAT 26:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 26:44"/>And having left them, having gone away again, He prayed a third time, saying the same word; <verse eid="MAT 26:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 26:45"/>then He comes to His disciples and says to them, “Sleep on from now on, and rest! Behold, the hour has come near, and the Son of Man is delivered up into the hands of sinners. <verse eid="MAT 26:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 26:46"/>Rise, let us go; behold, he who is delivering Me up has come near.” <verse eid="MAT 26:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MAT 26:47"/>And while He is yet speaking, behold, Judas, one of the Twelve came, and with him a great multitude, with swords and sticks, from the chief priests and elders of the people. <verse eid="MAT 26:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MAT 26:48"/>And he who delivered Him up gave them a sign, saying, “Whomsoever I will kiss, it is He, lay hold on Him”; <verse eid="MAT 26:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MAT 26:49"/>and immediately, having come to Jesus, he said, “Greetings, Rabbi,” and kissed Him; <verse eid="MAT 26:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MAT 26:50"/>and Jesus said to him, “Friend, for what are you present?” Then having come near, they laid hands on Jesus, and took hold on Him. <verse eid="MAT 26:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MAT 26:51"/>And behold, one of those with Jesus, having stretched forth the hand, drew his sword, and having struck the servant of the chief priest, he took off his ear. <verse eid="MAT 26:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MAT 26:52"/>Then Jesus says to him, “Turn back your sword to its place; for all who took the sword will perish by the sword; <verse eid="MAT 26:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="MAT 26:53"/>do you think that I am not able now to call on My Father, and He will place beside Me more than twelve legions of messengers? <verse eid="MAT 26:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MAT 26:54"/>How then may the Writings be fulfilled, that thus it must happen?” <verse eid="MAT 26:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MAT 26:55"/>In that hour Jesus said to the multitudes, “Did you come forth as against a robber, with swords and sticks, to take Me? Daily I was with you sitting, teaching in the temple, and you did not lay hold on Me; <verse eid="MAT 26:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MAT 26:56"/>but all this has come to pass, that the Writings of the prophets may be fulfilled”; then all the disciples, having left Him, fled. <verse eid="MAT 26:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="MAT 26:57"/>And those laying hold on Jesus led [Him] away to Caiaphas the chief priest, where the scribes and the elders were gathered together, <verse eid="MAT 26:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="MAT 26:58"/>and Peter was following Him far off, to the court of the chief priest, and having gone in within, he was sitting with the officers, to see the end. <verse eid="MAT 26:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="MAT 26:59"/>And the chief priests, and the elders, and all the council, were seeking false witness against Jesus, that they might put Him to death, <verse eid="MAT 26:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="MAT 26:60"/>and they did not find; and many false witnesses having come near, they did not find; and at last two false witnesses having come near, <verse eid="MAT 26:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="MAT 26:61"/>said, “This One said, I am able to throw down the temple of God, and after three days to build it.” <verse eid="MAT 26:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="MAT 26:62"/>And the chief priest having stood up, said to Him, “Nothing You answer? What do these witness against You?” <verse eid="MAT 26:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="MAT 26:63"/>And Jesus was silent. And the chief priest answering said to Him, “I adjure You, by the living God, that You may say to us if You are the Christ—the Son of God.” <verse eid="MAT 26:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="MAT 26:64"/>Jesus says to him, “You have said; nevertheless I say to you, hereafter you will see the Son of Man sitting on the right hand of the Power and coming on the clouds of Heaven.” <verse eid="MAT 26:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="MAT 26:65"/>Then the chief priest tore his garments, saying, “He has slandered; what need have we yet of witnesses? Behold, now you heard His slander; <verse eid="MAT 26:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="MAT 26:66"/>what do you think?” And they answering said, “He is worthy of death.” <verse eid="MAT 26:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="MAT 26:67"/>Then they spit in His face and punched Him, and others slapped, <verse eid="MAT 26:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="MAT 26:68"/>saying, “Declare to us, O Christ, who he is that struck You?” <verse eid="MAT 26:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="MAT 26:69"/>And Peter was sitting in the court outside, and there came near to him a certain maid, saying, “And you were with Jesus of Galilee!” <verse eid="MAT 26:69"/><verse number="70" style="v" sid="MAT 26:70"/>And he denied before all, saying, “I have not known what you say.” <verse eid="MAT 26:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="MAT 26:71"/>And he having gone forth to the porch, another female saw him, and says to those there, “And this one was with Jesus of Nazareth”; <verse eid="MAT 26:71"/><verse number="72" style="v" sid="MAT 26:72"/>and again he denied with an oath, “I have not known the Man.” <verse eid="MAT 26:72"/><verse number="73" style="v" sid="MAT 26:73"/>And after a while those standing near having come, said to Peter, “Truly you also are of them, for even your speech makes you evident.” <verse eid="MAT 26:73"/><verse number="74" style="v" sid="MAT 26:74"/>Then he began to curse, and to swear, “I have not known the Man”; and immediately a rooster crowed, <verse eid="MAT 26:74"/><verse number="75" style="v" sid="MAT 26:75"/>and Peter remembered the saying of Jesus, He having said to him, “Before rooster-crowing, you will deny Me three times”; and having gone outside, he wept bitterly.<verse eid="MAT 26:75"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="MAT 27"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 27:1"/>And morning having come, all the chief priests and the elders of the people took counsel against Jesus, so as to put Him to death; <verse eid="MAT 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 27:2"/>and having bound Him, they led [Him] away, and delivered Him up to Pontius Pilate, the governor. <verse eid="MAT 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 27:3"/>Then Judas—he who delivered Him up—having seen that He was condemned, having regretted, brought back the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and to the elders, saying, <verse eid="MAT 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 27:4"/>“I sinned, having delivered up innocent blood”; and they said, “What [is that] to us? You will see!” <verse eid="MAT 27:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 27:5"/>And having cast down the pieces of silver in the temple, he departed, and having gone away, he strangled himself. <verse eid="MAT 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 27:6"/>And the chief priests having taken the pieces of silver, said, “It is not lawful to put them into the treasury, seeing it is the price of blood”; <verse eid="MAT 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 27:7"/>and having taken counsel, they bought the potter’s field with them, for the burial of strangers; <verse eid="MAT 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 27:8"/>therefore that field was called, “Field of Blood,” to this day. <verse eid="MAT 27:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 27:9"/>Then was fulfilled that spoken through Jeremiah the prophet, saying, “And I took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of Him who has been priced, whom they of the sons of Israel priced, <verse eid="MAT 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 27:10"/>and gave them for the potter’s field, as the LORD appointed to me.” <verse eid="MAT 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 27:11"/>And Jesus stood before the governor, and the governor questioned Him, saying, “Are You the King of the Jews?” And Jesus said to him, “You say [it].” <verse eid="MAT 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 27:12"/>And in His being accused by the chief priests and the elders, He did not answer anything; <verse eid="MAT 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 27:13"/>then Pilate says to Him, “Do You not hear how many things they witness against You?” <verse eid="MAT 27:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 27:14"/>And He did not answer him, not even to one word, so that the governor wondered greatly. <verse eid="MAT 27:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 27:15"/>And at the celebration the governor had been accustomed to release one to the multitude, a prisoner, whom they willed, <verse eid="MAT 27:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 27:16"/>and they had a noted prisoner then, called Barabbas, <verse eid="MAT 27:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 27:17"/>therefore they having been gathered together, Pilate said to them, “Whom do you will [that] I may release to you? Barabbas or Jesus who is called Christ?” <verse eid="MAT 27:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 27:18"/>For he had known that they had delivered Him up because of envy. <verse eid="MAT 27:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 27:19"/>And as he is sitting on the judgment seat, his wife sent to him, saying, “Nothing—to you and to that Righteous One, for I suffered many things today in a dream because of Him.” <verse eid="MAT 27:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 27:20"/>And the chief priests and the elders persuaded the multitudes that they might ask for themselves Barabbas, and might destroy Jesus; <verse eid="MAT 27:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MAT 27:21"/>and the governor answering said to them, “Which of the two will you [that] I may release to you?” And they said, “Barabbas.” <verse eid="MAT 27:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MAT 27:22"/>Pilate says to them, “What then will I do with Jesus who is called Christ?” They all say to him, “Let [Him] be crucified!” <verse eid="MAT 27:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MAT 27:23"/>And the governor said, “Why, what evil did He do?” And they were crying out the more, saying, “Let [Him] be crucified!” <verse eid="MAT 27:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MAT 27:24"/>And Pilate having seen that it profits nothing, but rather a tumult is made, having taken water, he washed the hands before the multitude, saying, “I am innocent from the blood of this Righteous One; you will see [to it] yourselves”; <verse eid="MAT 27:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MAT 27:25"/>and all the people answering said, “His blood [is] on us, and on our children!” <verse eid="MAT 27:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MAT 27:26"/>Then he released Barabbas to them, and having scourged Jesus, he delivered [Him] up that He may be crucified; <verse eid="MAT 27:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MAT 27:27"/>then the soldiers of the governor having taken Jesus to the Praetorium, gathered to Him all the band; <verse eid="MAT 27:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MAT 27:28"/>and having unclothed Him, they put a crimson cloak around Him, <verse eid="MAT 27:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MAT 27:29"/>and having plaited Him a garland out of thorns they put [it] on His head, and [put] a reed in His right hand, and having kneeled before Him, they were mocking Him, saying, “Hail, the King of the Jews!” <verse eid="MAT 27:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MAT 27:30"/>And having spit on Him, they took the reed, and were striking on His head; <verse eid="MAT 27:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MAT 27:31"/>and when they had mocked Him, they took off the cloak from Him, and put His own garments on Him, and led Him away to crucify [Him]. <verse eid="MAT 27:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MAT 27:32"/>And coming forth, they found a man, a Cyrenian, by name Simon: they impressed him that he might carry His cross; <verse eid="MAT 27:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MAT 27:33"/>and having come to a place called Golgotha, which is called “Place of [the] Skull,” <verse eid="MAT 27:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MAT 27:34"/>they gave Him vinegar mixed with gall to drink, and having tasted, He would not drink. <verse eid="MAT 27:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MAT 27:35"/>And having crucified Him, they divided His garments, casting a lot, <char style="bd">[[</char>that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet: “They divided My garments to themselves, and they cast a lot over My clothing”;<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MAT 27:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MAT 27:36"/>and sitting down, they were watching Him there, <verse eid="MAT 27:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MAT 27:37"/>and they put up over His head, His accusation written: “THIS IS JESUS, THE KING OF THE JEWS.” <verse eid="MAT 27:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MAT 27:38"/>Then two robbers are crucified with Him, one on the right hand and one on the left, <verse eid="MAT 27:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MAT 27:39"/>and those passing by kept slandering Him, wagging their heads, <verse eid="MAT 27:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MAT 27:40"/>and saying, “You that are throwing down the temple, and in three days building [it], save Yourself; if You are the Son of God, come down from the cross.” <verse eid="MAT 27:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MAT 27:41"/>And in like manner also the chief priests mocking, with the scribes and elders, said, <verse eid="MAT 27:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MAT 27:42"/>“He saved others; He is not able to save Himself! If He is King of Israel, let Him come down now from the cross, and we will believe Him; <verse eid="MAT 27:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MAT 27:43"/>He has trusted on God, let Him now deliver Him if He wants Him, because He said, I am [the] Son of God”; <verse eid="MAT 27:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MAT 27:44"/>with the same also the robbers, who were crucified with Him, were reproaching Him. <verse eid="MAT 27:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MAT 27:45"/>And from the sixth hour darkness came over all the land to the ninth hour, <verse eid="MAT 27:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MAT 27:46"/>and about the ninth hour Jesus cried out with a great voice, saying, “Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani?” That is, “My God, My God, why did You forsake Me?” <verse eid="MAT 27:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MAT 27:47"/>And certain of those standing there having heard, said, “He calls Elijah”; <verse eid="MAT 27:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MAT 27:48"/>and immediately, one of them having run, and having taken a sponge, having filled [it] with vinegar, and having put [it] on a reed, was giving Him to drink, <verse eid="MAT 27:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MAT 27:49"/>but the rest said, “Let alone, let us see if Elijah comes—about to save Him.” <verse eid="MAT 27:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MAT 27:50"/>And Jesus having again cried with a great voice, yielded the spirit; <verse eid="MAT 27:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MAT 27:51"/>and behold, the veil of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom, and the earth quaked, and the rocks were split, <verse eid="MAT 27:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MAT 27:52"/>and the tombs were opened, and many bodies of the holy ones who have fallen asleep, arose, <verse eid="MAT 27:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="MAT 27:53"/>and having come forth out of the tombs after His rising, they went into the holy city, and appeared to many. <verse eid="MAT 27:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MAT 27:54"/>And the centurion, and those with him watching Jesus, having seen the earthquake, and the things that were done, were exceedingly afraid, saying, “Truly this was God’s Son.” <verse eid="MAT 27:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MAT 27:55"/>And there were there many women beholding from afar, who followed Jesus from Galilee, ministering to Him, <verse eid="MAT 27:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MAT 27:56"/>among whom was Mary the Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James and of Joses, and the mother of the sons of Zebedee. <verse eid="MAT 27:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="MAT 27:57"/>And evening having come, there came a rich man from Arimathea named Joseph, who also himself was discipled to Jesus, <verse eid="MAT 27:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="MAT 27:58"/>he having gone near to Pilate, asked for himself the body of Jesus; then Pilate commanded the body to be given back. <verse eid="MAT 27:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="MAT 27:59"/>And having taken the body, Joseph wrapped it in clean linen, <verse eid="MAT 27:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="MAT 27:60"/>and laid it in his new tomb that he hewed in the rock, and having rolled a great stone to the door of the tomb, he went away; <verse eid="MAT 27:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="MAT 27:61"/>now Mary the Magdalene was there, and the other Mary, sitting opposite the grave. <verse eid="MAT 27:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="MAT 27:62"/>And on the next day that is after the Preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees were gathered together to Pilate, <verse eid="MAT 27:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="MAT 27:63"/>saying, “Lord, we have remembered that this deceiver said while yet living, After three days I rise; <verse eid="MAT 27:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="MAT 27:64"/>command, then, the grave to be made secure until the third day, lest His disciples, having come by night, may steal Him away, and may say to the people, He rose from the dead, and the last deceit will be worse than the first.” <verse eid="MAT 27:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="MAT 27:65"/>And Pilate said to them, “You have a guard, go away, make [it] secure—as you have known”; <verse eid="MAT 27:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="MAT 27:66"/>and they, having gone, made the grave secure, having sealed the stone, together with the guard.<verse eid="MAT 27:66"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="MAT 28"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MAT 28:1"/>Now after [the] Sabbaths, it being dawn, toward the first [day] of the weeks, Mary the Magdalene came, and the other Mary, to see the grave, <verse eid="MAT 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MAT 28:2"/>and behold, there came a great earthquake, for a messenger of the LORD, having come down out of Heaven, having come, rolled away the stone from the door, and was sitting on it, <verse eid="MAT 28:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MAT 28:3"/>and his countenance was as lightning, and his clothing white as snow, <verse eid="MAT 28:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MAT 28:4"/>and from the fear of him the keepers shook, and they became as dead men. <verse eid="MAT 28:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MAT 28:5"/>And the messenger answering said to the women, “Do not fear, for I have known that you seek Jesus who has been crucified; <verse eid="MAT 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MAT 28:6"/>He is not here, for He rose, as He said; come, see the place where the LORD was lying; <verse eid="MAT 28:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MAT 28:7"/>and having gone quickly, say to His disciples that He rose from the dead; and behold, He goes before you to Galilee, there you will see Him; behold, I have told you.” <verse eid="MAT 28:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MAT 28:8"/>And having gone forth quickly from the tomb, with fear and great joy, they ran to tell His disciples; <verse eid="MAT 28:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MAT 28:9"/>and as they were going to tell His disciples, then behold, Jesus met them, saying, “Greetings!” And having come near, they laid hold of His feet, and worshiped Him. <verse eid="MAT 28:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MAT 28:10"/>Then Jesus says to them, “Do not fear, go away, tell My brothers that they may go away to Galilee, and there they will see Me.” <verse eid="MAT 28:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MAT 28:11"/>And while they are going on, behold, certain of the guard having come into the city, reported to the chief priests all the things that happened, <verse eid="MAT 28:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MAT 28:12"/>and having been gathered together with the elders, having also taken counsel, they gave much money to the soldiers, <verse eid="MAT 28:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MAT 28:13"/>saying, “Say that His disciples having come by night, stole Him—we being asleep; <verse eid="MAT 28:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MAT 28:14"/>and if this is heard by the governor, we will persuade him, and you keep free from anxiety.” <verse eid="MAT 28:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MAT 28:15"/>And they, having received the money, did as they were taught, and this account was spread abroad among Jews until this day. <verse eid="MAT 28:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MAT 28:16"/>And the eleven disciples went to Galilee, to the mountain where Jesus appointed them, <verse eid="MAT 28:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MAT 28:17"/>and having seen Him, they worshiped Him, but some wavered. <verse eid="MAT 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MAT 28:18"/>And having come near, Jesus spoke to them, saying, “All authority in Heaven and on earth was given to Me; <verse eid="MAT 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MAT 28:19"/>having gone, then, disciple all the nations, immersing them into the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, <verse eid="MAT 28:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MAT 28:20"/>teaching them to observe all, whatever I commanded you, and behold, I am with you all the days—until the full end of the age.”<verse eid="MAT 28:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MAT 28"/>
</usx>
