<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="MRK" style="id">- Literal Standard Version</book>
  <para style="usfm">3.0</para>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Mark</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Gospel of Mark</para>
  <para style="toc2">Mark</para>
  <para style="toc3">Mrk</para>
  <para style="mt">Mark</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="MRK 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 1:1"/>A beginning of the good news of Jesus Christ, Son of God. <verse eid="MRK 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 1:2"/>As it has been written in the Prophets: “Behold, I send My messenger before Your face, || Who will prepare Your way before You. <verse eid="MRK 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 1:3"/>A voice of one calling in the wilderness: Prepare the way of the LORD, || Make His paths straight.” <verse eid="MRK 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 1:4"/>John came immersing in the wilderness, and proclaiming an immersion of conversion for forgiveness of sins, <verse eid="MRK 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 1:5"/>and there were going forth to him all the region of Judea, and they of Jerusalem, and they were all immersed by him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins. <verse eid="MRK 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 1:6"/>And John was clothed with camel’s hair, and a girdle of skin around his loins, and eating locusts and honey of the field, <verse eid="MRK 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 1:7"/>and he proclaimed, saying, “He comes—who is mightier than I—after me, of whom I am not worthy—having stooped down—to loose the strap of His sandals; <verse eid="MRK 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 1:8"/>I indeed immersed you in water, but He will immerse you in the Holy Spirit.” <verse eid="MRK 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 1:9"/>And it came to pass in those days, Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and was immersed by John in the Jordan; <verse eid="MRK 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 1:10"/>and immediately coming up from the water, He saw the heavens dividing, and the Spirit coming down on Him as a dove; <verse eid="MRK 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 1:11"/>and a voice came out of the heavens, “You are My Son, the Beloved, in whom I delighted.” <verse eid="MRK 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 1:12"/>And immediately the Spirit puts Him forth into the wilderness, <verse eid="MRK 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 1:13"/>and He was there in the wilderness forty days, being tempted by Satan, and He was with the beasts, and the messengers were ministering to Him. <verse eid="MRK 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 1:14"/>And after the delivering up of John, Jesus came to Galilee, proclaiming the good news of the Kingdom of God, <verse eid="MRK 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 1:15"/>and saying, “The time has been fulfilled, and the Kingdom of God has come near, convert and believe in the good news.” <verse eid="MRK 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 1:16"/>And walking by the Sea of Galilee, He saw Simon, and his brother Andrew, casting a drag into the sea, for they were fishers, <verse eid="MRK 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 1:17"/>and Jesus said to them, “Come after Me, and I will make you to become fishers of men”; <verse eid="MRK 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 1:18"/>and immediately, having left their nets, they followed Him. <verse eid="MRK 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 1:19"/>And having gone on there a little, He saw James of Zebedee, and his brother John, and they were in the boat refitting the nets, <verse eid="MRK 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 1:20"/>and immediately He called them, and having left their father Zebedee in the boat with the hired servants, they went away after Him. <verse eid="MRK 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 1:21"/>And they go on to Capernaum, and immediately, on the Sabbaths, having gone into the synagogue, He was teaching, <verse eid="MRK 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 1:22"/>and they were astonished at His teaching, for He was teaching them as having authority, and not as the scribes. <verse eid="MRK 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 1:23"/>And there was in their synagogue a man with an unclean spirit, and he cried out, <verse eid="MRK 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 1:24"/>saying, “What [regards] us and You, Jesus the Nazarene? You came to destroy us; I have known You, who You are—the Holy One of God.” <verse eid="MRK 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 1:25"/>And Jesus rebuked him, saying, “Be silenced, and come forth out of him,” <verse eid="MRK 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 1:26"/>and the unclean spirit having convulsed him, and having cried with a great voice, came forth out of him, <verse eid="MRK 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 1:27"/>and they were all amazed, so as to reason among themselves, saying, “What is this? What new teaching [is] this? That with authority He also commands the unclean spirits, and they obey Him!” <verse eid="MRK 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 1:28"/>And the fame of Him went forth immediately to all the region of Galilee. <verse eid="MRK 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 1:29"/>And immediately, having come forth out of the synagogue, they went into the house of Simon and Andrew, with James and John, <verse eid="MRK 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 1:30"/>and the mother-in-law of Simon was lying fevered, and immediately they tell Him about her, <verse eid="MRK 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 1:31"/>and having come near, He raised her up, having laid hold of her hand, and the fever left her immediately, and she was ministering to them. <verse eid="MRK 1:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 1:32"/>And evening having come, when the sun set, they brought to Him all who were ill and who were demoniacs, <verse eid="MRK 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 1:33"/>and the whole city was gathered together near the door, <verse eid="MRK 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 1:34"/>and He healed many who were ill of manifold diseases, and He cast forth many demons, and was not permitting the demons to speak, because they knew Him. <verse eid="MRK 1:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 1:35"/>And very early, it being yet night, having risen, He went forth, and went away to a desolate place, and was praying there; <verse eid="MRK 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 1:36"/>and Simon and those with him went in quest of Him, <verse eid="MRK 1:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 1:37"/>and having found Him, they say to Him, “All seek You”; <verse eid="MRK 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 1:38"/>and He says to them, “We may go into the next towns, that there also I may preach, for—for this I came forth.” <verse eid="MRK 1:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 1:39"/>And He was preaching in their synagogues, in all Galilee, and is casting out the demons, <verse eid="MRK 1:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 1:40"/>and there comes to Him a leper, calling on Him, and kneeling to Him, and saying to Him, “If You may will, You are able to cleanse me.” <verse eid="MRK 1:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 1:41"/>And Jesus having been moved with compassion, having stretched forth the hand, touched him and says to him, “I will, be cleansed”; <verse eid="MRK 1:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 1:42"/>and He having spoken, immediately the leprosy went away from him, and he was cleansed. <verse eid="MRK 1:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 1:43"/>And having sternly charged him, immediately He put him forth, <verse eid="MRK 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 1:44"/>and says to him, “See [that] you may say nothing to anyone, but go away, show yourself to the priest, and bring near for your cleansing the things Moses directed, for a testimony to them.” <verse eid="MRK 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 1:45"/>And he, having gone forth, began to proclaim much, and to spread the thing abroad, so that He was no longer able to openly enter into the city, but He was outside in desolate places, and they were coming to Him from every quarter.<verse eid="MRK 1:45"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="MRK 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 2:1"/>And again He entered into Capernaum, after [some] days, and it was heard that He is in the house, <verse eid="MRK 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 2:2"/>and immediately many were gathered together, so that there was no more room, not even at the door, and He was speaking to them the word. <verse eid="MRK 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 2:3"/>And they come to Him, bringing a paralytic, carried by four, <verse eid="MRK 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 2:4"/>and not being able to come near to Him because of the multitude, they uncovered the roof where He was, and having broken [it] up, they let down the pallet on which the paralytic was lying, <verse eid="MRK 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 2:5"/>and Jesus having seen their faith, says to the paralytic, “Child, your sins have been forgiven you.” <verse eid="MRK 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 2:6"/>And there were certain of the scribes sitting there, and reasoning in their hearts, <verse eid="MRK 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 2:7"/>“Why does this One thus speak evil words? Who is able to forgive sins except one—God?” <verse eid="MRK 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 2:8"/>And immediately Jesus, having known in His spirit that they thus reason in themselves, said to them, “Why do you reason these things in your hearts? <verse eid="MRK 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 2:9"/>Which is easier? To say to the paralytic, Your sins are forgiven; or to say, Rise, and take up your pallet, and walk? <verse eid="MRK 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 2:10"/>And that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on the earth to forgive sins—(He says to the paralytic)— <verse eid="MRK 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 2:11"/>I say to you, rise, and take up your pallet, and go away to your house”; <verse eid="MRK 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 2:12"/>and he rose immediately, and having taken up the pallet, he went forth before all, so that all were astonished, and glorify God, saying, “Never thus did we see.” <verse eid="MRK 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 2:13"/>And He went forth again by the sea, and all the multitude was coming to Him, and He was teaching them, <verse eid="MRK 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 2:14"/>and passing by, He saw Levi of Alpheus sitting at the tax office, and says to him, “Follow Me,” and he, having risen, followed Him. <verse eid="MRK 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 2:15"/>And it came to pass, in His reclining in his house, that many tax collectors and sinners were dining with Jesus and His disciples, for there were many, and they followed Him. <verse eid="MRK 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 2:16"/>And the scribes and the Pharisees, having seen Him eating with the tax collectors and sinners, said to His disciples, “Why—that with the tax collectors and sinners He eats and drinks?” <verse eid="MRK 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 2:17"/>And Jesus, having heard, says to them, “They who are strong have no need of a physician, but they who are ill; I did not come to call righteous men, but sinners.” <verse eid="MRK 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 2:18"/>And the disciples of John and those of the Pharisees were fasting, and they come and say to Him, “Why do the disciples of John and those of the Pharisees fast, and Your disciples do not fast?” <verse eid="MRK 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 2:19"/>And Jesus said to them, “Are the sons of the bride-chamber able, while the bridegroom is with them, to fast? As long a time [as] they have the bridegroom with them they are not able to fast; <verse eid="MRK 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 2:20"/>but days will come when the bridegroom may be taken from them, and then they will fast—in those days. <verse eid="MRK 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 2:21"/>And no one sews a patch of undressed cloth on an old garment, and if not—the new, filling it up, takes from the old and the split becomes worse; <verse eid="MRK 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 2:22"/>and no one puts new wine into old skins, and if not—the new wine bursts the skins, and the wine is poured out, and the skins will be destroyed; but new wine is to be put into new skins.” <verse eid="MRK 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 2:23"/>And it came to pass—He is going along on the Sabbaths through the grainfields—and His disciples began to make a way, plucking the ears, <verse eid="MRK 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 2:24"/>and the Pharisees said to Him, “Behold, why do they do on the Sabbaths that which is not lawful?” <verse eid="MRK 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 2:25"/>And He said to them, “Did you never read what David did when he had need and was hungry, he and those with him? <verse eid="MRK 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 2:26"/>How he went into the house of God, in [the days of] Abiathar the chief priest, and ate the Bread of the Presentation, which it is not lawful to eat, except to the priests, and he also gave to those who were with him?” <verse eid="MRK 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 2:27"/>And He said to them, “The Sabbath was made for man, not man for the Sabbath, <verse eid="MRK 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 2:28"/>so that the Son of Man is also Lord of the Sabbath.”<verse eid="MRK 2:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="MRK 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 3:1"/>And He entered again into the synagogue, and there was there a man having the hand withered, <verse eid="MRK 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 3:2"/>and they were watching Him, whether on the Sabbaths He will heal him, that they might accuse Him. <verse eid="MRK 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 3:3"/>And He says to the man having the hand withered, “Rise up in the midst.” <verse eid="MRK 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 3:4"/>And He says to them, “Is it lawful on the Sabbaths to do good, or to do evil? To save life, or to kill?” But they were silent. <verse eid="MRK 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 3:5"/>And having looked around on them with anger, being grieved for the hardness of their heart, He says to the man, “Stretch forth your hand”; and he stretched forth, and his hand was restored whole as the other; <verse eid="MRK 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 3:6"/>and the Pharisees having gone forth, immediately, with the Herodians, were taking counsel against Him how they might destroy Him. <verse eid="MRK 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 3:7"/>And Jesus withdrew with His disciples to the sea, and a great multitude from Galilee followed Him, and from Judea, <verse eid="MRK 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 3:8"/>and from Jerusalem, and from Idumea and beyond the Jordan; and they around Tyre and Sidon—a great multitude—having heard how He was doing great things, came to Him. <verse eid="MRK 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 3:9"/>And He said to His disciples that a little boat may wait on Him, because of the multitude, that they may not press on Him, <verse eid="MRK 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 3:10"/>for He healed many, so that they threw themselves on Him, in order to touch Him—as many as had plagues; <verse eid="MRK 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 3:11"/>and the unclean spirits, when they were seeing Him, were falling down before Him, and were crying, saying, “You are the Son of God”; <verse eid="MRK 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 3:12"/>and many times He was charging them that they might not make Him apparent. <verse eid="MRK 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 3:13"/>And He goes up to the mountain, and calls near whom He willed, and they went away to Him; <verse eid="MRK 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 3:14"/>and He appointed twelve, that they may be with Him, and that He may send them forth to preach, <verse eid="MRK 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 3:15"/>and to have power to heal the sicknesses, and to cast out the demons. <verse eid="MRK 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 3:16"/>And He put on Simon the name Peter; <verse eid="MRK 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 3:17"/>and James of Zebedee, and John the brother of James, and He put on them names—Boanerges, that is, “Sons of thunder”; <verse eid="MRK 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 3:18"/>and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James of Alpheus, and Thaddeus, and Simon the Zealot, <verse eid="MRK 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 3:19"/>and Judas Iscariot, who also delivered Him up; and they come into a house. <verse eid="MRK 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 3:20"/>And a multitude comes together again, so that they are not even able to eat bread; <verse eid="MRK 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 3:21"/>and those alongside Him having heard, went forth to lay hold on Him, for they said that He was beside Himself, <verse eid="MRK 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 3:22"/>and the scribes who [are] from Jerusalem having come down, said, “He has Beelzebul,” and, “By the ruler of the demons He casts out the demons.” <verse eid="MRK 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 3:23"/>And having called them near, He said to them in allegories, “How is Satan able to cast out Satan? <verse eid="MRK 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 3:24"/>And if a kingdom is divided against itself, that kingdom cannot be made to stand; <verse eid="MRK 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 3:25"/>and if a house is divided against itself, that house cannot be made to stand; <verse eid="MRK 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 3:26"/>and if Satan rose against himself, and has been divided, he cannot be made to stand, but has an end. <verse eid="MRK 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 3:27"/>No one is able to spoil the vessels of the strong man, having entered into his house, if first he may not bind the strong man, and then he will spoil his house. <verse eid="MRK 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 3:28"/>Truly I say to you that all sins will be forgiven to the sons of men, and slanders with which they might have slandered, <verse eid="MRK 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 3:29"/>but whoever may slander in regard to the Holy Spirit has no forgiveness—throughout the age, but is in danger of continuous judgment; <verse eid="MRK 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 3:30"/>because they said, He has an unclean spirit.” <verse eid="MRK 3:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 3:31"/>Then His brothers and mother come, and standing outside, they sent to Him, calling Him, <verse eid="MRK 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 3:32"/>and a multitude was sitting around Him, and they said to Him, “Behold, Your mother and Your brothers seek You outside.” <verse eid="MRK 3:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 3:33"/>And He answered them, saying, “Who is My mother, or My brothers?” <verse eid="MRK 3:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 3:34"/>And having looked around in a circle to those sitting around Him, He says, “Behold, My mother and My brothers! <verse eid="MRK 3:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 3:35"/>For whoever may do the will of God, he is My brother, and My sister, and mother.”<verse eid="MRK 3:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="MRK 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 4:1"/>And again He began to teach by the sea, and there was gathered to Him a great multitude, so that He, having gone into the boat, sat in the sea, and all the multitude was near the sea, on the land, <verse eid="MRK 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 4:2"/>and He taught them many things in allegories, and He said to them in His teaching: <verse eid="MRK 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 4:3"/>“Listen, behold, the sower went forth to sow; <verse eid="MRK 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 4:4"/>and it came to pass, in the sowing, some fell by the way, and the birds of the sky came and devoured it; <verse eid="MRK 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 4:5"/>and other fell on the rocky ground, where it did not have much earth, and immediately it sprang forth, because of having no depth of earth, <verse eid="MRK 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 4:6"/>and the sun having risen, it was scorched, and because of having no root it withered; <verse eid="MRK 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 4:7"/>and other fell toward the thorns, and the thorns came up and choked it, and it gave no fruit; <verse eid="MRK 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 4:8"/>and other fell to the good ground, and was giving fruit, coming up and increasing, and it was bearing, one thirty-fold, and one sixty, and one a hundred.” <verse eid="MRK 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 4:9"/>And He said to them, “He who is having ears to hear—let him hear.” <verse eid="MRK 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 4:10"/>And when He was alone, those around Him, with the Twelve, asked Him of the allegory, <verse eid="MRK 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 4:11"/>and He said to them, “To you it has been given to know the secret of the Kingdom of God, but to those who are outside, in allegories are all the things done, <verse eid="MRK 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 4:12"/>that seeing they may see and not perceive, and hearing they may hear and not understand, lest they may turn, and the sins may be forgiven them.” <verse eid="MRK 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 4:13"/>And He says to them, “Have you not known this allegory? And how will you know all the allegories? <verse eid="MRK 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 4:14"/>He who is sowing sows the word; <verse eid="MRK 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 4:15"/>and these are they by the way where the word is sown: and whenever they may hear, Satan immediately comes, and he takes away the word that has been sown in their hearts. <verse eid="MRK 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 4:16"/>And these are they, in like manner, who are sown on the rocky ground: who, whenever they may hear the word, immediately receive it with joy, <verse eid="MRK 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 4:17"/>and have no root in themselves, but are temporary; afterward tribulation or persecution having come because of the word, immediately they are stumbled. <verse eid="MRK 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 4:18"/>And these are they who are sown toward the thorns: these are they who are hearing the word, <verse eid="MRK 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 4:19"/>and the anxieties of this age, and the deceitfulness of the riches, and the desires concerning the other things, entering in, choke the word, and it becomes unfruitful. <verse eid="MRK 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 4:20"/>And these are they who on the good ground have been sown: who hear the word, and receive, and bear fruit, one thirty-fold, and one sixty, and one a hundred.” <verse eid="MRK 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 4:21"/>And He said to them, “Does the lamp come that it may be put under the measure, or under the bed—not that it may be put on the lampstand? <verse eid="MRK 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 4:22"/>For there is not anything hid that may not be revealed, nor was anything kept hid but that it may come to light. <verse eid="MRK 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 4:23"/>If any has ears to hear—let him hear.” <verse eid="MRK 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 4:24"/>And He said to them, “Take heed what you hear; in what measure you measure, it will be measured to you; and to you who hear it will be added; <verse eid="MRK 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 4:25"/>for whoever may have, there will be given to him, and whoever has not, also that which he has will be taken from him.” <verse eid="MRK 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 4:26"/>And He said, “Thus is the Kingdom of God: as if a man may cast the seed on the earth, <verse eid="MRK 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 4:27"/>and may sleep, and may rise night and day, and the seed springs up and grows, he has not known how; <verse eid="MRK 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 4:28"/>for of itself the earth bears fruit, first a blade, afterward an ear, afterward full grain in the ear; <verse eid="MRK 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 4:29"/>and whenever the fruit may yield itself, immediately he sends forth the sickle, because the harvest has come.” <verse eid="MRK 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 4:30"/>And He said, “To what may we liken the Kingdom of God, or in what allegory may we compare it? <verse eid="MRK 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 4:31"/>As a grain of mustard, which, whenever it may be sown on the earth, is less than any of the seeds that are on the earth; <verse eid="MRK 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 4:32"/>and whenever it may be sown, it comes up, and becomes greater than any of the herbs, and makes great branches, so that under its shade the birds of the sky are able to rest.” <verse eid="MRK 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 4:33"/>And with many such allegories He was speaking to them the word, as they were able to hear, <verse eid="MRK 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 4:34"/>and without an allegory He was not speaking to them, and by themselves, to His disciples He was expounding all. <verse eid="MRK 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 4:35"/>And He says to them on that day, evening having come, “We may pass over to the other side”; <verse eid="MRK 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 4:36"/>and having let away the multitude, they take Him up as He was in the boat, and other little boats were also with Him. <verse eid="MRK 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 4:37"/>And there comes a great storm of wind, and the waves were beating on the boat, so that it is now being filled, <verse eid="MRK 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 4:38"/>and He Himself was on the stern, sleeping on the pillow, and they wake Him up, and say to Him, “Teacher, are You not caring that we perish?” <verse eid="MRK 4:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 4:39"/>And having awoken, He rebuked the wind and said to the sea, “Peace, be stilled”; and the wind stilled, and there was a great calm; <verse eid="MRK 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 4:40"/>and He said to them, “Why are you so fearful? How have you no faith?” <verse eid="MRK 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 4:41"/>And they feared a great fear and said to one another, “Who, then, is this, that even the wind and the sea obey Him?”<verse eid="MRK 4:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="MRK 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 5:1"/>And they came to the other side of the sea, to the region of the Gadarenes, <verse eid="MRK 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 5:2"/>and He having come forth out of the boat, immediately there met Him out of the tombs a man with an unclean spirit, <verse eid="MRK 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 5:3"/>who had his dwelling in the tombs, and not even with chains was anyone able to bind him, <verse eid="MRK 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 5:4"/>because that many times he had been bound with shackles and chains, and the chains had been pulled in pieces by him, and the shackles broken in pieces, and none was able to tame him, <verse eid="MRK 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 5:5"/>and always, night and day, he was in the mountains, and in the tombs, crying and cutting himself with stones. <verse eid="MRK 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 5:6"/>And having seen Jesus from afar, he ran and prostrated to Him, <verse eid="MRK 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 5:7"/>and having called with a loud voice, he said, “What [regards] me and You, Jesus, Son of God the Most High? I adjure You by God, may You not afflict me!” <verse eid="MRK 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 5:8"/>For He said to him, “Come forth, unclean spirit, out of the man!” <verse eid="MRK 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 5:9"/>And He was questioning him, “What [is] your name?” And he answered, saying, “Legion [is] my name, because we are many”; <verse eid="MRK 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 5:10"/>and he was calling on Him much, that He may not send them out of the region. <verse eid="MRK 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 5:11"/>And there was there, near the mountains, a great herd of pigs feeding, <verse eid="MRK 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 5:12"/>and all the demons called on Him, saying, “Send us to the pigs, that into them we may enter”; <verse eid="MRK 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 5:13"/>and immediately Jesus gave them leave, and having come forth, the unclean spirits entered into the pigs, and the herd rushed down the steep place to the sea—and they were about two thousand—and they were choked in the sea. <verse eid="MRK 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 5:14"/>And those feeding the pigs fled, and told in the city, and in the fields, and they came forth to see what it is that has been done; <verse eid="MRK 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 5:15"/>and they come to Jesus, and see the demoniac, sitting, and clothed, and right-minded—him having had the legion—and they were afraid; <verse eid="MRK 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 5:16"/>and those having seen [it], declared to them how it had come to pass to the demoniac, and about the pigs; <verse eid="MRK 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 5:17"/>and they began to call on Him to go away from their borders. <verse eid="MRK 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 5:18"/>And He having gone into the boat, the demoniac was calling on Him that he may be with Him, <verse eid="MRK 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 5:19"/>and Jesus did not permit him, but says to him, “Go away to your house, to your own [friends], and tell them how the LORD did great things to you, and dealt kindly with you”; <verse eid="MRK 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 5:20"/>and he went away, and began to proclaim in the Decapolis how Jesus did great things to him, and all were wondering. <verse eid="MRK 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 5:21"/>And Jesus having passed over in the boat again to the other side, there was gathered a great multitude to Him, and He was near the sea, <verse eid="MRK 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 5:22"/>and behold, there comes one of the chiefs of the synagogue, by name Jairus, and having seen Him, he falls at His feet, <verse eid="MRK 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 5:23"/>and he was calling on Him much, saying, “My little daughter is at the last extremity—that having come, You may lay on her [Your] hands, so that she may be saved, and she will live”; <verse eid="MRK 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 5:24"/>and He went away with him. And there was following Him a great multitude, and they were thronging Him, <verse eid="MRK 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 5:25"/>and a certain woman, being with a flow of blood [for] twelve years, <verse eid="MRK 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 5:26"/>and having suffered many things under many physicians, and having spent all that she had, and having profited nothing, but rather having come to the worse, <verse eid="MRK 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 5:27"/>having heard about Jesus, having come in the multitude behind, she touched His garment, <verse eid="MRK 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 5:28"/>for she said, “If I may even touch His garments, I will be saved”; <verse eid="MRK 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 5:29"/>and immediately the fountain of her blood was dried up, and she knew in the body that she has been healed of the plague. <verse eid="MRK 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 5:30"/>And immediately Jesus having known in Himself that power had gone forth out of Him, having turned in the multitude, said, “Who touched My garments?” <verse eid="MRK 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 5:31"/>And His disciples said to Him, “You see the multitude thronging You, and You say, Who touched Me!” <verse eid="MRK 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 5:32"/>And He was looking around to see her who did this, <verse eid="MRK 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 5:33"/>and the woman, having been afraid, and trembling, knowing what was done on her, came, and fell down before Him, and told Him all the truth, <verse eid="MRK 5:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 5:34"/>and He said to her, “Daughter, your faith has saved you; go away in peace, and be whole from your plague.” <verse eid="MRK 5:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 5:35"/>As He is yet speaking, there come from the chief of the synagogue’s [house, certain], saying, “Your daughter died, why do you still harass the Teacher?” <verse eid="MRK 5:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 5:36"/>And Jesus immediately, having heard the word that is spoken, says to the chief of the synagogue, “Do not be afraid, only believe.” <verse eid="MRK 5:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 5:37"/>And He did not permit anyone to follow with Him, except Peter, and James, and John the brother of James; <verse eid="MRK 5:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 5:38"/>and He comes into the house of the chief of the synagogue, and sees a tumult, much weeping and wailing; <verse eid="MRK 5:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 5:39"/>and having gone in He says to them, “Why do you make a tumult, and weep? The child did not die, but sleeps”; <verse eid="MRK 5:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 5:40"/>and they were laughing at Him. And He, having put all forth, takes the father of the child, and the mother, and those with Him, and goes in where the child is lying, <verse eid="MRK 5:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 5:41"/>and having taken the hand of the child, He says to her, “Talitha cumi”; which is, being interpreted, “Girl (I say to you), arise.” <verse eid="MRK 5:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 5:42"/>And immediately the girl arose, and was walking, for she was twelve years [old]; and they were amazed with a great amazement, <verse eid="MRK 5:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 5:43"/>and He charged them much, that no one may know this thing, and He said that there be given to her to eat.<verse eid="MRK 5:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="MRK 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 6:1"/>And He went forth from there, and came to His own country, and His disciples follow Him, <verse eid="MRK 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 6:2"/>and Sabbath having come, He began to teach in the synagogue, and many hearing were astonished, saying, “From where [did] this One [hear] these things? And what [is] the wisdom that was given to Him, that also such mighty works are done through His hands? <verse eid="MRK 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 6:3"/>Is this not the carpenter, the Son of Mary, and brother of James, and Joses, and Judas, and Simon? And are His sisters not here with us?” And they were being stumbled at Him. <verse eid="MRK 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 6:4"/>And Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not without honor, except in his own country, and among his relatives, and in his own house”; <verse eid="MRK 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 6:5"/>and He was not able to do any mighty work there, except having put hands on a few sick, He healed [them]; <verse eid="MRK 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 6:6"/>and He wondered because of their unbelief. And He was going around the villages, in a circle, teaching, <verse eid="MRK 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 6:7"/>and He calls near the Twelve, and He began to send them forth two by two, and He was giving them power over the unclean spirits, <verse eid="MRK 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 6:8"/>and He commanded them that they may take nothing for the way, except a staff only—no leather pouch, no bread, no brass in the girdle, <verse eid="MRK 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 6:9"/>but having been shod with sandals, and you may not put on two coats. <verse eid="MRK 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 6:10"/>And He said to them, “Whenever you may enter into a house, remain there until you may depart from there, <verse eid="MRK 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 6:11"/>and as many as may not receive you nor hear you, going out from there, shake off the dust that is under your feet for a testimony to them; <char style="bd">[[</char>truly I say to you, it will be more tolerable for Sodom or Gomorrah in [the] day of judgment than for that city.”<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MRK 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 6:12"/>And having gone forth they were preaching that [men] might convert, <verse eid="MRK 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 6:13"/>and they were casting out many demons, and they were anointing many sick with oil, and they were healing [them]. <verse eid="MRK 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 6:14"/>And King Herod heard (for His Name became public), and he said, “John the Immerser was raised out of the dead, and because of this the mighty powers are working in him.” <verse eid="MRK 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 6:15"/>Others said, “It is Elijah,” and others said, “It is a prophet, or as one of the prophets.” <verse eid="MRK 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 6:16"/>And Herod having heard, said, “He whom I beheaded—John—this is he; he was raised out of the dead.” <verse eid="MRK 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 6:17"/>For Herod himself, having sent forth, laid hold on John, and bound him in the prison, because of Herodias, the wife of his brother Philip, because he married her, <verse eid="MRK 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 6:18"/>for John said to Herod, “It is not lawful for you to have the wife of your brother”; <verse eid="MRK 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 6:19"/>and Herodias was having a quarrel with him, and was willing to kill him, and was not able, <verse eid="MRK 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 6:20"/>for Herod was fearing John, knowing him [to be] a righteous and holy man, and was keeping watch over him, and having heard him, was doing many things, and hearing him gladly. <verse eid="MRK 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 6:21"/>And a seasonable day having come when Herod on his birthday was making a banquet to his great men, and to the chiefs of thousands, and to the first men of Galilee, <verse eid="MRK 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 6:22"/>and the daughter of that Herodias having come in, and having danced, and having pleased Herod and those dining with him, the king said to the girl, “Ask of me whatever you will, and I will give to you,” <verse eid="MRK 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 6:23"/>and he swore to her, “Whatever you may ask me, I will give to you—to the half of my kingdom.” <verse eid="MRK 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 6:24"/>And she, having gone forth, said to her mother, “What will I ask for myself?” And she said, “The head of John the Immerser”; <verse eid="MRK 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 6:25"/>and having come in immediately with haste to the king, she asked, saying, “I will that you may immediately give me the head of John the Immerser on a plate.” <verse eid="MRK 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 6:26"/>And the king, made very sorrowful because of the oaths and of those reclining with him, would not put her away, <verse eid="MRK 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 6:27"/>and immediately the king having sent a guardsman, commanded his head to be brought, <verse eid="MRK 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 6:28"/>and he having gone, beheaded him in the prison, and brought his head on a plate, and gave it to the girl, and the girl gave it to her mother; <verse eid="MRK 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 6:29"/>and having heard, his disciples came and took up his corpse, and laid it in the tomb. <verse eid="MRK 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 6:30"/>And the apostles are gathered together to Jesus, and they told Him all, and how many things they did, and how many things they taught, <verse eid="MRK 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 6:31"/>and He said to them, “Come yourselves apart to a desolate place, and rest a little,” for those coming and those going were many, and not even to eat had they opportunity, <verse eid="MRK 6:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 6:32"/>and they went away to a desolate place, in the boat, by themselves. <verse eid="MRK 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 6:33"/>And the multitudes saw them going away, and many recognized Him, and they ran there by land from all the cities, and went before them, and came together to Him, <verse eid="MRK 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 6:34"/>and having come forth, Jesus saw a great multitude, and was moved with compassion on them, that they were as sheep not having a shepherd, and He began to teach many things. <verse eid="MRK 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 6:35"/>And now the hour being advanced, His disciples having come near to Him, say, “The place is desolate, and the hour is now advanced, <verse eid="MRK 6:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 6:36"/>let them away, that having gone away into the surrounding fields and villages, they may buy loaves for themselves, for they do not have what they may eat.” <verse eid="MRK 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 6:37"/>And He answering said to them, “You give them to eat,” and they say to Him, “Having gone away, may we buy two hundred denarii worth of loaves, and give to them to eat?” <verse eid="MRK 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 6:38"/>And He says to them, “How many loaves do you have? Go and see”; and having known, they say, “Five, and two fishes.” <verse eid="MRK 6:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 6:39"/>And He commanded them to make all recline in companies on the green grass, <verse eid="MRK 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 6:40"/>and they sat down in squares, by hundreds, and by fifties. <verse eid="MRK 6:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 6:41"/>And having taken the five loaves and the two fishes, having looked up to the sky, He blessed, and broke the loaves, and was giving [them] to His disciples, that they may set [them] before them, and the two fishes He divided to all, <verse eid="MRK 6:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 6:42"/>and they all ate, and were filled, <verse eid="MRK 6:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 6:43"/>and they took up of broken pieces twelve hand-baskets full, and of the fishes, <verse eid="MRK 6:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 6:44"/>and those eating of the loaves were about five thousand men. <verse eid="MRK 6:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 6:45"/>And immediately He constrained His disciples to go into the boat, and to go before [Him] to the other side, to Bethsaida, until He may let the multitude away, <verse eid="MRK 6:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 6:46"/>and having taken leave of them, He went away to the mountain to pray. <verse eid="MRK 6:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 6:47"/>And evening having come, the boat was in the midst of the sea, and He alone on the land; <verse eid="MRK 6:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 6:48"/>and He saw them harassed in the rowing, for the wind was against them, and about the fourth watch of the night He comes to them walking on the sea, and wished to pass by them. <verse eid="MRK 6:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 6:49"/>And they having seen Him walking on the sea, thought [it] to be an apparition, and cried out, <verse eid="MRK 6:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 6:50"/>for they all saw Him, and were troubled, and immediately He spoke with them, and says to them, “Take courage! I AM; do not be afraid.” <verse eid="MRK 6:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 6:51"/>And He went up to them into the boat, and the wind stilled, and greatly out of measure they were amazed in themselves, and were wondering, <verse eid="MRK 6:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 6:52"/>for they did not understand concerning the loaves, for their heart has been hard. <verse eid="MRK 6:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 6:53"/>And having passed over, they came on the land of Gennesaret, and drew to the shore, <verse eid="MRK 6:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 6:54"/>and they having come forth out of the boat, immediately having recognized Him, <verse eid="MRK 6:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 6:55"/>they ran around through all that surrounding region, and they began to carry around on the pallets those being ill, where they were hearing that He is, <verse eid="MRK 6:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 6:56"/>and wherever He was going, to villages, or cities, or fields, in the marketplaces they were laying the ailing, and were calling on Him, that they may touch if it were but the fringe of His garment, and as many as were touching Him were saved.<verse eid="MRK 6:56"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="MRK 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 7:1"/>And gathered together to Him are the Pharisees, and certain of the scribes, having come from Jerusalem, <verse eid="MRK 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 7:2"/>and having seen certain of His disciples with defiled hands—that is, unwashed—eating bread, they found fault; <verse eid="MRK 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 7:3"/>for the Pharisees, and all the Jews, if they do not wash the hands to the wrist, do not eat, holding the tradition of the elders, <verse eid="MRK 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 7:4"/>and [coming] from the marketplace, if they do not immerse themselves, they do not eat; and many other things there are that they received to hold, immersions of cups, and pots, and bronze vessels, and couches. <verse eid="MRK 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 7:5"/>Then the Pharisees and the scribes question Him, “Why do Your disciples not walk according to the tradition of the elders, but eat the bread with unwashed hands?” <verse eid="MRK 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 7:6"/>And He answering said to them, “Well did Isaiah prophesy concerning you, hypocrites, as it has been written: This people honors Me with the lips, and their heart is far from Me; <verse eid="MRK 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 7:7"/>and in vain they worship Me, teaching teachings, commands of men; <verse eid="MRK 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 7:8"/>for having put away the command of God, you hold the tradition of men, immersions of pots and cups; and many other such like things you do.” <verse eid="MRK 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 7:9"/>And He said to them, “Well do you put away the command of God that you may keep your tradition; <verse eid="MRK 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 7:10"/>for Moses said, Honor your father and your mother; and, He who is speaking evil of father or mother—let him die the death; <verse eid="MRK 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 7:11"/>and you say, If a man may say to father or to mother, Korban (that is, a gift), [is] whatever you may be profited out of mine, <verse eid="MRK 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 7:12"/>and you no longer permit him to do anything for his father or for his mother, <verse eid="MRK 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 7:13"/>setting aside the word of God for your tradition that you delivered; and many such like things you do.” <verse eid="MRK 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 7:14"/>And having called near all the multitude, He said to them, “Listen to Me, you all, and understand; <verse eid="MRK 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 7:15"/>there is nothing from outside the man entering into him that is able to defile him, but the things coming out from him, those are the things defiling the man. <verse eid="MRK 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 7:16"/><char style="bd">[[</char>If any has ears to hear—let him hear.”<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 7:17"/>And when He entered into a house from the multitude, His disciples were questioning Him about the allegory, <verse eid="MRK 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 7:18"/>and He says to them, “So also you are without understanding! Do you not perceive that nothing from outside entering into the man is able to defile him? <verse eid="MRK 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 7:19"/>Because it does not enter into his heart, but into the belly, and into the drain it goes out, purifying all the meats.” <verse eid="MRK 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 7:20"/>And He said, “That which is coming out from the man, that defiles the man; <verse eid="MRK 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 7:21"/>for from within, out of the heart of men, the evil reasonings come forth, adulteries, whoredoms, murders, <verse eid="MRK 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 7:22"/>thefts, covetous desires, wickedness, deceit, arrogance, an evil eye, slander, pride, foolishness; <verse eid="MRK 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 7:23"/>all these evils come forth from within, and they defile the man.” <verse eid="MRK 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 7:24"/>And from there having risen, He went away to the borders of Tyre and Sidon, and having entered into the house, He wished none to know, and He was not able to be hid, <verse eid="MRK 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 7:25"/>for a woman having heard about Him, whose little daughter had an unclean spirit, having come, fell at His feet— <verse eid="MRK 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 7:26"/>and the woman was a Greek, a Syro-Phoenician by nation—and was asking Him that He may cast forth the demon out of her daughter. <verse eid="MRK 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 7:27"/>And Jesus said to her, “First permit the children to be filled, for it is not good to take the children’s bread, and to cast [it] to the little dogs.” <verse eid="MRK 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 7:28"/>And she answered and says to Him, “Yes, Lord; for the little dogs under the table also eat of the children’s crumbs.” <verse eid="MRK 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 7:29"/>And He said to her, “Because of this word, go; the demon has gone forth out of your daughter”; <verse eid="MRK 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 7:30"/>and having come away to her house, she found the demon gone forth, and the daughter laid on the bed. <verse eid="MRK 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 7:31"/>And again, having gone forth from the coasts of Tyre and Sidon, He came to the Sea of Galilee, through the midst of the coasts of Decapolis, <verse eid="MRK 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 7:32"/>and they bring to Him a deaf, stuttering man, and they call on Him that He may put the hand on him. <verse eid="MRK 7:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 7:33"/>And having taken him away from the multitude by Himself, He put His fingers to his ears, and having spit, He touched his tongue, <verse eid="MRK 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 7:34"/>and having looked to the sky, He sighed, and says to him, “Ephphatha,” that is, “Be opened”; <verse eid="MRK 7:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 7:35"/>and immediately his ears were opened, and the string of his tongue was loosed, and he was speaking plain. <verse eid="MRK 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 7:36"/>He charged them that they may tell no one, but the more He was charging them, the more abundantly they were proclaiming [it], <verse eid="MRK 7:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 7:37"/>and they were being astonished beyond measure, saying, “He has done all things well; He makes both the deaf to hear, and the mute to speak.”<verse eid="MRK 7:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="MRK 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 8:1"/>In those days the multitude being very great, and not having what they may eat, Jesus having called near His disciples, says to them, <verse eid="MRK 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 8:2"/>“I have compassion on the multitude, because now three days they continue with Me, and they have not what they may eat; <verse eid="MRK 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 8:3"/>and if I will let them away fasting to their home, they will faint in the way, for certain of them are come from far.” <verse eid="MRK 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 8:4"/>And His disciples answered Him, “From where will anyone be able to feed these here in a wilderness with bread?” <verse eid="MRK 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 8:5"/>And He was questioning them, “How many loaves do you have?” And they said, “Seven.” <verse eid="MRK 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 8:6"/>And He commanded the multitude to sit down on the ground, and having taken the seven loaves, having given thanks, He broke, and was giving to His disciples that they may set before [them]; and they set before the multitude. <verse eid="MRK 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 8:7"/>And they had a few small fishes, and having blessed, He said to set them also before [them]; <verse eid="MRK 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 8:8"/>and they ate and were filled, and they took up that which was over of broken pieces—seven baskets; <verse eid="MRK 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 8:9"/>and those eating were about four thousand. And He let them away, <verse eid="MRK 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 8:10"/>and immediately having entered into the boat with His disciples, He came to the parts of Dalmanutha, <verse eid="MRK 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 8:11"/>and the Pharisees came forth, and began to dispute with Him, seeking from Him a sign from Heaven, tempting Him; <verse eid="MRK 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 8:12"/>and having sighed deeply in His spirit, He says, “Why does this generation seek after a sign? Truly I say to you, no sign will be given to this generation.” <verse eid="MRK 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 8:13"/>And having left them, having entered again into the boat, He went away to the other side; <verse eid="MRK 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 8:14"/>and they forgot to take loaves, and except one loaf they had nothing with them in the boat, <verse eid="MRK 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 8:15"/>and He was charging them, saying, “Take heed, beware of the leaven of the Pharisees, and of the leaven of Herod,” <verse eid="MRK 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 8:16"/>and they were reasoning with one another, saying, “Because we have no loaves.” <verse eid="MRK 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 8:17"/>And Jesus having known, says to them, “Why do you reason, because you have no loaves? Do you not yet perceive, nor understand, yet have you hardened your heart? <verse eid="MRK 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 8:18"/>Having eyes, do you not see? And having ears, do you not hear? And do you not remember? <verse eid="MRK 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 8:19"/>When I broke the five loaves to the five thousand, how many hand-baskets full of broken pieces did you take up?” They say to Him, “Twelve.” <verse eid="MRK 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 8:20"/>“And when the seven to the four thousand, how many hand-baskets full of broken pieces did you take up?” And they said, “Seven.” <verse eid="MRK 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 8:21"/>And He said to them, “How do you not understand?” <verse eid="MRK 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 8:22"/>And He comes to Bethsaida, and they bring to Him one blind, and call on Him that He may touch him, <verse eid="MRK 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 8:23"/>and having taken the hand of the blind man, He led him forth outside the village, and having spit on his eyes, having put [His] hands on him, He was questioning him if he beholds anything: <verse eid="MRK 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 8:24"/>and he, having looked up, said, “I behold men, as I see trees, walking.” <verse eid="MRK 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 8:25"/>Afterward again He put [His] hands on his eyes, and made him look up, and he was restored, and discerned all things clearly, <verse eid="MRK 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 8:26"/>and He sent him away to his house, saying, “Neither may you go into the village, nor tell [it] to any in the village.” <verse eid="MRK 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 8:27"/>And Jesus went forth, and His disciples, into the villages of Caesarea Philippi, and in the way He was questioning His disciples, saying to them, “Who do men say I am?” <verse eid="MRK 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 8:28"/>And they answered, “John the Immerser, and others Elijah, but others one of the prophets.” <verse eid="MRK 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 8:29"/>And He says to them, “And you—who do you say I am?” And Peter answering says to him, “You are the Christ.” <verse eid="MRK 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 8:30"/>And He strictly charged them that they may tell no one about it, <verse eid="MRK 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 8:31"/>and began to teach them that it is necessary for the Son of Man to suffer many things, and to be rejected by the elders, and chief priests, and scribes, and to be killed, and to rise again after three days; <verse eid="MRK 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 8:32"/>and openly He was speaking the word. And Peter having taken Him aside, began to rebuke Him, <verse eid="MRK 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 8:33"/>and He, having turned, and having looked on His disciples, rebuked Peter, saying, “Get behind Me, Satan, because you do not mind the things of God, but the things of men.” <verse eid="MRK 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 8:34"/>And having called near the multitude, with His disciples, He said to them, “Whoever wills to come after Me—let him disown himself, and take up his cross, and follow Me; <verse eid="MRK 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 8:35"/>for whoever may will to save his life will lose it; and whoever may lose his life for My sake and for the good news’ sake, he will save it; <verse eid="MRK 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 8:36"/>for what will it profit a man, if he may gain the whole world, and forfeit his life? <verse eid="MRK 8:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 8:37"/>Or what will a man give as an exchange for his life? <verse eid="MRK 8:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 8:38"/>For whoever may be ashamed of Me, and of My words, in this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of Man will also be ashamed of him when He may come in the glory of His Father with the holy messengers.”<verse eid="MRK 8:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="MRK 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 9:1"/>And He said to them, “Truly I say to you that there are certain of those standing here, who may not taste of death until they see the Kingdom of God having come in power.” <verse eid="MRK 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 9:2"/>And after six days Jesus takes Peter, and James, and John, and brings them up to a high mountain by themselves, alone, and He was transfigured before them, <verse eid="MRK 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 9:3"/>and His garments became glittering, exceedingly white, as snow, so as a launderer on the earth is not able to whiten [them]. <verse eid="MRK 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 9:4"/>And there appeared to them Elijah with Moses, and they were talking with Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 9:5"/>And Peter answering says to Jesus, “Rabbi, it is good to us to be here; and we may make three shelters, for You one, and for Moses one, and for Elijah one”: <verse eid="MRK 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 9:6"/>for he was not knowing what he might say, for they were greatly afraid. <verse eid="MRK 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 9:7"/>And there came a cloud overshadowing them, and there came a voice out of the cloud, saying, “This is My Son, the Beloved, hear Him”; <verse eid="MRK 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 9:8"/>and suddenly, having looked around, they saw no one anymore, but Jesus only with themselves. <verse eid="MRK 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 9:9"/>And as they are coming down from the mountain, He charged them that they may declare to no one the things that they saw, except when the Son of Man may rise out of the dead; <verse eid="MRK 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 9:10"/>and the thing they kept to themselves, questioning together what the rising out of the dead is. <verse eid="MRK 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 9:11"/>And they were questioning Him, saying that the scribes say that Elijah must come first. <verse eid="MRK 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 9:12"/>And He answering said to them, “Elijah indeed, having come first, restores all things; and how has it been written concerning the Son of Man, that He may suffer many things, and be set at nothing? <verse eid="MRK 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 9:13"/>But I say to you that also Elijah has come, and they did to him what they willed, as it has been written of him.” <verse eid="MRK 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 9:14"/>And having come to the disciples, He saw a great multitude around them, and scribes questioning with them, <verse eid="MRK 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 9:15"/>and immediately, all the multitude having seen Him, were amazed, and running near, were greeting Him. <verse eid="MRK 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 9:16"/>And He questioned the scribes, “What do you dispute with them?” <verse eid="MRK 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 9:17"/>And one out of the multitude answering said, “Teacher, I brought my son to You, having a mute spirit; <verse eid="MRK 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 9:18"/>and wherever it seizes him, it tears him, and he foams, and gnashes his teeth, and pines away; and I spoke to Your disciples that they may cast it out, and they were not able.” <verse eid="MRK 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 9:19"/>And He answering him, said, “O generation unbelieving, until when will I be with you? Until when will I suffer you? Bring him to Me”; <verse eid="MRK 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 9:20"/>and they brought him to Him, and he having seen Him, immediately the spirit convulsed him, and he, having fallen on the earth, was wallowing—foaming. <verse eid="MRK 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 9:21"/>And He questioned his father, “How much time is it since this came to him?” And he said, “From childhood, <verse eid="MRK 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 9:22"/>and many times it also cast him into fire, and into water, that it might destroy him; but if You are able to do anything, help us, having compassion on us.” <verse eid="MRK 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 9:23"/>And Jesus said to him, “If you are able to believe! All things are possible to the one that is believing”; <verse eid="MRK 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 9:24"/>and immediately the father of the child, having cried out with tears, said, “I believe, Lord; be helping my unbelief.” <verse eid="MRK 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 9:25"/>Jesus having seen that a multitude runs together, rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to it, “Spirit—mute and deaf—I charge you, come forth out of him, and you may no longer enter into him”; <verse eid="MRK 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 9:26"/>and having cried, and convulsed him much, it came forth, and he became as dead, so that many said that he was dead, <verse eid="MRK 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 9:27"/>but Jesus, having taken him by the hand, lifted him up, and he arose. <verse eid="MRK 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 9:28"/>And He having come into the house, His disciples were questioning Him by Himself, “Why were we not able to cast it forth?” <verse eid="MRK 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 9:29"/>And He said to them, “This kind is able to come forth with nothing except with prayer and fasting.” <verse eid="MRK 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 9:30"/>And having gone forth there, they were passing through Galilee, and He did not wish that any may know, <verse eid="MRK 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 9:31"/>for He was teaching His disciples, and He said to them, “The Son of Man is being delivered into the hands of men, and they will kill Him, and having been killed, the third day He will rise,” <verse eid="MRK 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 9:32"/>but they were not understanding the saying, and they were afraid to question Him. <verse eid="MRK 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 9:33"/>And He came to Capernaum, and being in the house, He was questioning them, “What were you reasoning in the way among yourselves?” <verse eid="MRK 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 9:34"/>And they were silent, for they reasoned with one another in the way who is greater; <verse eid="MRK 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 9:35"/>and having sat down He called the Twelve, and He says to them, “If any wills to be first, he will be last of all, and minister of all.” <verse eid="MRK 9:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 9:36"/>And having taken a child, He set him in the midst of them, and having taken him in His arms, said to them, <verse eid="MRK 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 9:37"/>“Whoever may receive one of such children in My Name, receives Me, and whoever may receive Me, does not receive Me, but Him who sent Me.” <verse eid="MRK 9:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 9:38"/>And John answered Him, saying, “Teacher, we saw a certain one casting out demons in Your Name, who does not follow us, and we forbade him, because he does not follow us.” <verse eid="MRK 9:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 9:39"/>And Jesus said, “Do not forbid him, for there is no one who will do a mighty work in My Name, and will be readily able to speak evil of Me: <verse eid="MRK 9:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 9:40"/>for he who is not against us is for us; <verse eid="MRK 9:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 9:41"/>for whoever may give you to drink a cup of water in My Name, because you are Christ’s, truly I say to you, he may not lose his reward; <verse eid="MRK 9:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 9:42"/>and whoever may cause to stumble one of the little ones believing in Me, better is it for him if a millstone is hanged around his neck, and he has been cast into the sea. <verse eid="MRK 9:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 9:43"/>And if your hand may cause you to stumble, cut it off; it is better for you to enter into life maimed, than having the two hands, to go away into Gehenna, into the fire—the unquenchable— <verse eid="MRK 9:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 9:44"/><char style="bd">[[</char>where their worm is not dying, and the fire is not being quenched.<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 9:45"/>And if your foot may cause you to stumble, cut it off; it is better for you to enter into life lame, than having the two feet to be cast into Gehenna, into the fire—the unquenchable— <verse eid="MRK 9:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 9:46"/><char style="bd">[[</char>where their worm is not dying, and the fire is not being quenched.<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 9:47"/>And if your eye may cause you to stumble, cast it out; it is better for you to enter into the Kingdom of God one-eyed, than having two eyes, to be cast into the Gehenna of fire— <verse eid="MRK 9:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 9:48"/>where their worm is not dying, and the fire is not being quenched; <verse eid="MRK 9:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 9:49"/>for everyone will be salted with fire, and every sacrifice will be salted with salt. <verse eid="MRK 9:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 9:50"/>The salt [is] good, but if the salt may become saltless, in what will you season [it]? Have in yourselves salt, and have peace in one another.”<verse eid="MRK 9:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="MRK 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 10:1"/>And having risen from there, He comes to the coasts of Judea, through the other side of the Jordan, and again multitudes come together to Him, and as He had been accustomed, again He was teaching them. <verse eid="MRK 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 10:2"/>And the Pharisees, having come near, questioned Him if it is lawful for a husband to put away a wife, tempting Him, <verse eid="MRK 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 10:3"/>and He answering said to them, “What did Moses command you?” <verse eid="MRK 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 10:4"/>And they said, “Moses permitted to write a bill of divorce, and to put away.” <verse eid="MRK 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 10:5"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “For the stiffness of your heart he wrote you this command, <verse eid="MRK 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 10:6"/>but from the beginning of the creation God made them a male and a female; <verse eid="MRK 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 10:7"/>on this account will a man leave his father and mother, and will cleave to his wife, <verse eid="MRK 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 10:8"/>and they will be—the two—for one flesh, so that they are no longer two, but one flesh; <verse eid="MRK 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 10:9"/>what God therefore joined together, do not let man separate.” <verse eid="MRK 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 10:10"/>And in the house His disciples again questioned Him of the same thing, <verse eid="MRK 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 10:11"/>and He says to them, “Whoever may put away his wife, and may marry another, commits adultery against her; <verse eid="MRK 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 10:12"/>and if a woman may put away her husband, and is married to another, she commits adultery.” <verse eid="MRK 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 10:13"/>And they were bringing to Him children that He might touch them, and the disciples were rebuking those bringing them, <verse eid="MRK 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 10:14"/>and Jesus having seen, was much displeased, and He said to them, “Permit the children to come to Me, and do not forbid them, for of such is the Kingdom of God; <verse eid="MRK 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 10:15"/>truly I say to you, whoever may not receive the Kingdom of God as a child—he may not enter into it”; <verse eid="MRK 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 10:16"/>and having taken them in His arms, having put [His] hands on them, He was blessing them. <verse eid="MRK 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 10:17"/>And as He is going forth into the way, one having run and having kneeled to Him, was questioning Him, “Good Teacher, what may I do that I may inherit continuous life?” <verse eid="MRK 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 10:18"/>And Jesus said to him, “Why do you call Me good? No one [is] good except one—God; <verse eid="MRK 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 10:19"/>you have known the commands: You may not commit adultery, You may not murder, You may not steal, You may not bear false witness, You may not defraud, Honor your father and mother.” <verse eid="MRK 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 10:20"/>And he answering said to Him, “Teacher, all these I have kept from my youth.” <verse eid="MRK 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 10:21"/>And Jesus having looked on him, loved him, and said to him, “One thing you lack: go away, whatever you have—sell, and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in Heaven, and come, follow Me, having taken up the cross.” <verse eid="MRK 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 10:22"/>And he—gloomy at the word—went away sorrowing, for he was having many possessions. <verse eid="MRK 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 10:23"/>And Jesus having looked around, says to His disciples, “How hardly will they who have riches enter into the Kingdom of God!” <verse eid="MRK 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 10:24"/>And the disciples were astonished at His words, and Jesus again answering says to them, “Children, how hard it is to those trusting on riches to enter into the Kingdom of God! <verse eid="MRK 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 10:25"/>It is easier for a camel to enter through the eye of the needle, than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God.” <verse eid="MRK 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 10:26"/>And they were astonished beyond measure, saying to themselves, “And who is able to be saved?” <verse eid="MRK 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 10:27"/>And Jesus, having looked on them, says, “With men it is impossible, but not with God; for all things are possible with God.” <verse eid="MRK 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 10:28"/>And Peter began to say to Him, “Behold, we left all, and we followed You.” <verse eid="MRK 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 10:29"/>And Jesus answering said, “Truly I say to you, there is no one who left house, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or fields, for My sake, and for the good news’, <verse eid="MRK 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 10:30"/>who may not receive a hundredfold now in this time, houses, and brothers, and sisters, and mothers, and children, and fields, with persecutions, and in the age that is coming, continuous life; <verse eid="MRK 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 10:31"/>and many first will be last, and the last first.” <verse eid="MRK 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 10:32"/>And they were in the way going up to Jerusalem, and Jesus was going before them, and they were amazed, and following they were afraid. And having again taken the Twelve, He began to tell them the things about to happen to Him: <verse eid="MRK 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 10:33"/>“Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be delivered to the chief priests, and to the scribes, and they will condemn Him to death, and will deliver Him to the nations, <verse eid="MRK 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 10:34"/>and they will mock Him, and scourge Him, and spit on Him, and kill Him, and the third day He will rise again.” <verse eid="MRK 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 10:35"/>And there come near to Him James and John, the sons of Zebedee, saying, “Teacher, we wish that whatever we may ask for ourselves, You may do for us”; <verse eid="MRK 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 10:36"/>and He said to them, “What do you wish Me to do for you?” <verse eid="MRK 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 10:37"/>And they said to Him, “Grant to us that, one on Your right hand and one on Your left, we may sit in Your glory”; <verse eid="MRK 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 10:38"/>and Jesus said to them, “You have not known what you ask; are you able to drink of the cup that I drink of, and with the immersion that I am immersed with—to be immersed?” <verse eid="MRK 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 10:39"/>And they said to Him, “We are able”; and Jesus said to them, “Of the cup indeed that I drink of, you will drink, and with the immersion that I am immersed with, you will be immersed; <verse eid="MRK 10:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 10:40"/>but to sit on My right and on My left is not Mine to give, but—to those for whom it has been prepared.” <verse eid="MRK 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 10:41"/>And the ten having heard, began to be much displeased at James and John, <verse eid="MRK 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 10:42"/>but Jesus having called them near, says to them, “You have known that they who are considered to rule the nations exercise lordship over them, and their great ones exercise authority on them; <verse eid="MRK 10:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 10:43"/>but not so will it be among you; but whoever may will to become great among you, he will be your minister, <verse eid="MRK 10:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 10:44"/>and whoever of you may will to become first, he will be servant of all; <verse eid="MRK 10:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 10:45"/>for even the Son of Man did not come to be ministered to, but to minister, and to give His life [as] a ransom for many.” <verse eid="MRK 10:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 10:46"/>And they come to Jericho, and as He is going forth from Jericho with His disciples and a great multitude, a son of Timaeus—Bartimaeus the blind—was sitting beside the way begging, <verse eid="MRK 10:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 10:47"/>and having heard that it is Jesus the Nazarene, he began to cry out, and to say, “The Son of David—Jesus! Deal kindly with me”; <verse eid="MRK 10:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 10:48"/>and many were rebuking him that he might keep silent, but the more abundantly he cried out, “Son of David, deal kindly with me.” <verse eid="MRK 10:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 10:49"/>And Jesus having stood, He commanded him to be called, and they call the blind man, saying to him, “Take courage, rise, He calls you”; <verse eid="MRK 10:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 10:50"/>and he, having cast away his garment, having risen, came to Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 10:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 10:51"/>And answering, Jesus says to him, “What do you will I may do to you?” And the blind man said to Him, “Rabboni, that I may see again”; <verse eid="MRK 10:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 10:52"/>and Jesus said to him, “Go, your faith has saved you”: and immediately he saw again, and was following Jesus in the way.<verse eid="MRK 10:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="MRK 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 11:1"/>And when they come near to Jerusalem, to Bethphage, and Bethany, to the Mount of Olives, He sends forth two of His disciples, <verse eid="MRK 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 11:2"/>and says to them, “Go away into the village that is in front of you, and immediately, entering into it, you will find a colt tied, on which no one of men has sat, having loosed it, bring [it]: <verse eid="MRK 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 11:3"/>and if anyone may say to you, Why do you do this? Say that the LORD has need of it, and immediately He will send it here.” <verse eid="MRK 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 11:4"/>And they went away, and found the colt tied at the door outside, by the two ways, and they loose it, <verse eid="MRK 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 11:5"/>and certain of those standing there said to them, “What do you—loosing the colt?” <verse eid="MRK 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 11:6"/>And they said to them as Jesus commanded, and they permitted them. <verse eid="MRK 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 11:7"/>And they brought the colt to Jesus, and cast their garments on it, and He sat on it, <verse eid="MRK 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 11:8"/>and many spread their garments in the way, and others were cutting down branches from the trees, and were strewing in the way. <verse eid="MRK 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 11:9"/>And those going before and those following were crying out, saying, “Hosanna! Blessed [is] He who is coming in the Name of the LORD; <verse eid="MRK 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 11:10"/>blessed is the coming kingdom, in the Name of the LORD, of our father David; Hosanna in the highest!” <verse eid="MRK 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 11:11"/>And Jesus entered into Jerusalem, and into the temple, and having looked around on all things, it being now evening, He went forth to Bethany with the Twelve. <verse eid="MRK 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 11:12"/>And on the next day, they having come forth from Bethany, He hungered, <verse eid="MRK 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 11:13"/>and having seen a fig tree far off having leaves, He came, if perhaps He will find anything in it, and having come to it, He found nothing except leaves, for it was not a time of figs, <verse eid="MRK 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 11:14"/>and Jesus answering said to it, “No longer from you—throughout the age—may any eat fruit”; and His disciples were hearing. <verse eid="MRK 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 11:15"/>And they come to Jerusalem, and Jesus having gone into the temple, began to cast forth those selling and buying in the temple, and He overthrew the tables of the money-changers and the seats of those selling the doves, <verse eid="MRK 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 11:16"/>and He did not permit that any might carry a vessel through the temple, <verse eid="MRK 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 11:17"/>and He was teaching, saying to them, “Has it not been written: My house will be called a house of prayer for all the nations? And you made it a den of robbers!” <verse eid="MRK 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 11:18"/>And the scribes and the chief priests heard, and they were seeking how they will destroy Him, for they were afraid of Him, because all the multitude was astonished at His teaching; <verse eid="MRK 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 11:19"/>and when evening came, He was going forth outside the city. <verse eid="MRK 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 11:20"/>And in the morning, passing by, they saw the fig tree having been dried up from the roots, <verse eid="MRK 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 11:21"/>and Peter having remembered says to Him, “Rabbi, behold, the fig tree that You cursed is dried up.” <verse eid="MRK 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 11:22"/>And Jesus answering says to them, “Have faith from God; <verse eid="MRK 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 11:23"/>for truly I say to you that whoever may say to this mountain, Be taken up, and be cast into the sea, and may not doubt in his heart, but may believe that the things that he says come to pass, it will be to him whatever he may say. <verse eid="MRK 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 11:24"/>Because of this I say to you, all whatever—praying—you ask, believe that you receive, and it will be to you. <verse eid="MRK 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 11:25"/>And whenever you may stand praying, forgive, if you have anything against anyone, that your Father who is in the heavens may also forgive you your trespasses; <verse eid="MRK 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 11:26"/><char style="bd">[[</char>and, if you do not forgive, neither will your Father who is in the heavens forgive your trespasses.”<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 11:27"/>And they come again to Jerusalem, and in the temple, as He is walking, there come to Him the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders, <verse eid="MRK 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 11:28"/>and they say to Him, “By what authority do You do these things? And who gave You this authority that You may do these things?” <verse eid="MRK 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 11:29"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “I will question you—I also—one word; and answer Me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things; <verse eid="MRK 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 11:30"/>the immersion of John—was it from Heaven or from men? Answer Me.” <verse eid="MRK 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 11:31"/>And they were reasoning with themselves, saying, “If we may say, From Heaven, He will say, Why then did you not believe him? <verse eid="MRK 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 11:32"/>But if we may say, From men…” They were fearing the people, for all were holding that John was indeed a prophet; <verse eid="MRK 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 11:33"/>and answering they say to Jesus, “We have not known”; and Jesus answering says to them, “Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.”<verse eid="MRK 11:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="MRK 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 12:1"/>And He began to speak to them in allegories: “A man planted a vineyard, and put a hedge around, and dug a wine vat, and built a tower, and gave it out to farmers, and went abroad; <verse eid="MRK 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 12:2"/>and he sent to the farmers at the due time a servant, that from the farmers he may receive from the fruit of the vineyard, <verse eid="MRK 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 12:3"/>and they, having taken him, severely beat [him], and sent him away empty. <verse eid="MRK 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 12:4"/>And again he sent to them another servant, and having cast stones at that one, they wounded [him] in the head, and sent [him] away—dishonored. <verse eid="MRK 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 12:5"/>And again he sent another, and that one they killed; and many others, some beating, and some killing. <verse eid="MRK 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 12:6"/>Having yet therefore one son—his beloved—he also sent him to them last, saying, They will respect my son; <verse eid="MRK 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 12:7"/>and those farmers said among themselves, This is the heir, come, we may kill him, and the inheritance will be ours; <verse eid="MRK 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 12:8"/>and having taken him, they killed, and cast [him] forth outside the vineyard. <verse eid="MRK 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 12:9"/>What therefore will the lord of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the farmers, and will give the vineyard to others. <verse eid="MRK 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 12:10"/>And this Writing you did not read: A stone that the builders rejected, it became the head of a corner; <verse eid="MRK 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 12:11"/>this was from the LORD, and it is wonderful in our eyes.” <verse eid="MRK 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 12:12"/>And they were seeking to lay hold on Him, and they feared the multitude, for they knew that He spoke the allegory against them, and having left Him, they went away; <verse eid="MRK 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 12:13"/>and they send to Him certain of the Pharisees and of the Herodians, that they may ensnare Him in discourse, <verse eid="MRK 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 12:14"/>and they having come, say to Him, “Teacher, we have known that You are true, and You are not caring for anyone, for You do not look to the face of men, but in truth teach the way of God; is it lawful to give tribute to Caesar or not? May we give, or may we not give?” <verse eid="MRK 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 12:15"/>And He, knowing their hypocrisy, said to them, “Why do you tempt Me? Bring Me a denarius, that I may see”; <verse eid="MRK 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 12:16"/>and they brought, and He says to them, “Whose [is] this image, and the inscription?” And they said to Him, “Caesar’s”; <verse eid="MRK 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 12:17"/>and Jesus answering said to them, “Give back the things of Caesar to Caesar, and the things of God to God”; and they wondered at Him. <verse eid="MRK 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 12:18"/>And the Sadducees come to Him, who say there is not a resurrection, and they questioned Him, saying, <verse eid="MRK 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 12:19"/>“Teacher, Moses wrote to us that if anyone’s brother may die, and may leave a wife, and may leave no children, that his brother may take his wife, and raise up seed to his brother. <verse eid="MRK 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 12:20"/>There were then seven brothers, and the first took a wife, and dying, he left no seed; <verse eid="MRK 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 12:21"/>and the second took her, and died, not having left seed, and the third in like manner, <verse eid="MRK 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 12:22"/>and the seven took her, and left no seed, last of all the woman also died; <verse eid="MRK 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 12:23"/>in the resurrection, then, whenever they may rise, of which of them will she be wife—for the seven had her as wife?” <verse eid="MRK 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 12:24"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “Do you not go astray because of this, not knowing the Writings, nor the power of God? <verse eid="MRK 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 12:25"/>For when they may rise out of the dead, they neither marry nor are they given in marriage, but are as messengers who are in the heavens. <verse eid="MRK 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 12:26"/>And concerning the dead, that they rise: have you not read in the Scroll of Moses (at the bush), how God spoke to him, saying, I [am] the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob; <verse eid="MRK 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 12:27"/>He is not the God of dead men, but a God of living men; you then go greatly astray.” <verse eid="MRK 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 12:28"/>And one of the scribes having come near, having heard them disputing, knowing that He answered them well, questioned Him, “Which is the first command of all?” <verse eid="MRK 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 12:29"/>And Jesus answered him, “The first of all the commands—Hear, O Israel: The LORD is our God, the LORD is one; <verse eid="MRK 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 12:30"/>and you will love the LORD your God out of all your heart, and out of all your soul, and out of all your understanding, and out of all your strength—this [is] the first command; <verse eid="MRK 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 12:31"/>and the second [is] like [it], this, You will love your neighbor as yourself—there is no other command greater than these.” <verse eid="MRK 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 12:32"/>And the scribe said to Him, “Well, Teacher, in truth You have spoken that there is one God, and there is none other but He; <verse eid="MRK 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 12:33"/>and to love Him out of all the heart, and out of all the understanding, and out of all the soul, and out of all the strength, and to love one’s neighbor as one’s self, is more than all the whole burnt-offerings and the sacrifices.” <verse eid="MRK 12:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 12:34"/>And Jesus, having seen him that he answered with understanding, said to him, “You are not far from the Kingdom of God”; and no one dared question Him anymore. <verse eid="MRK 12:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 12:35"/>And Jesus answering said, teaching in the temple, “How do the scribes say that the Christ is son of David? <verse eid="MRK 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 12:36"/>For David himself said in the Holy Spirit, The LORD said to my Lord, || Sit on My right hand, || Until I place Your enemies—Your footstool; <verse eid="MRK 12:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 12:37"/>therefore David himself calls Him Lord, and from where is He his son?” And the great multitude were hearing Him gladly, <verse eid="MRK 12:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 12:38"/>and He was saying to them in His teaching, “Beware of the scribes who will to walk in long robes, and love salutations in the marketplaces, <verse eid="MRK 12:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 12:39"/>and first seats in the synagogues, and first couches at the banquets, <verse eid="MRK 12:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 12:40"/>who are devouring the widows’ houses, and for a pretense are making long prayers; these will receive more abundant judgment.” <verse eid="MRK 12:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 12:41"/>And Jesus having sat down opposite the treasury, was beholding how the multitude puts brass into the treasury, and many rich were putting in much, <verse eid="MRK 12:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 12:42"/>and having come, a poor widow put in two mites, which are a penny. <verse eid="MRK 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 12:43"/>And having called near His disciples, He says to them, “Truly I say to you that this poor widow has put in more than all those putting into the treasury; <verse eid="MRK 12:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 12:44"/>for all, out of their abundance, put in, but she, out of her want, put in all that she had—all her living.”<verse eid="MRK 12:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="MRK 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 13:1"/>And as He is going forth out of the temple, one of His disciples says to Him, “Teacher, see! What stones! And what buildings!” <verse eid="MRK 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 13:2"/>And Jesus answering said to him, “See these great buildings? There may not be left a stone on a stone that may not be thrown down.” <verse eid="MRK 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 13:3"/>And as He is sitting at the Mount of Olives, opposite the temple, Peter, and James, and John, and Andrew, were questioning Him by Himself, <verse eid="MRK 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 13:4"/>“Tell us when these things will be? And what [is] the sign when all these may be about to be fulfilled?” <verse eid="MRK 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 13:5"/>And Jesus answering them, began to say, “Take heed lest anyone may lead you astray, <verse eid="MRK 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 13:6"/>for many will come in My Name, saying, I am [He], and many they will lead astray; <verse eid="MRK 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 13:7"/>and when you may hear of wars and reports of wars, do not be troubled, for these ought to be, but the end [is] not yet; <verse eid="MRK 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 13:8"/>for nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be earthquakes in various places, and there will be famines and troubles; these [are the] beginning of travails. <verse eid="MRK 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 13:9"/>And take heed to yourselves, for they will deliver you up to Sanhedrins, and to synagogues, you will be beaten, and before governors and kings you will be set for My sake, for a testimony to them; <verse eid="MRK 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 13:10"/>and to all the nations it is first necessary that the good news be proclaimed. <verse eid="MRK 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 13:11"/>And when they may lead you, delivering up, do not be anxious beforehand what you may speak, nor premeditate, but whatever may be given to you in that hour, that speak, for it is not you who are speaking, but the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="MRK 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 13:12"/>And brother will deliver up brother to death, and father child, and children will rise up against parents, and will put them to death, <verse eid="MRK 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 13:13"/>and you will be hated by all because of My Name, but he who has endured to the end—he will be saved. <verse eid="MRK 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 13:14"/>And when you may see the abomination of the desolation, that was spoken of by Daniel the prophet, standing where it should not (whoever is reading let him understand), then those in Judea, let them flee to the mountains; <verse eid="MRK 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 13:15"/>and he on the housetop, do not let him come down into the house, nor come in to take anything out of his house; <verse eid="MRK 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 13:16"/>and he who is in the field, do not let him turn to the things behind, to take up his garment. <verse eid="MRK 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 13:17"/>And woe to those with child, and to those giving suck, in those days; <verse eid="MRK 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 13:18"/>and pray that your flight may not be in winter, <verse eid="MRK 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 13:19"/>for those days will be tribulation, such as has not been from the beginning of the creation that God created, until now, and may not be [again]; <verse eid="MRK 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 13:20"/>and if the LORD did not shorten the days, no flesh had been saved; but because of the chosen, whom He chose to Himself, He shortened the days. <verse eid="MRK 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 13:21"/>And then, if any may say to you, Behold, here [is] the Christ, or, Behold, there, you may not believe; <verse eid="MRK 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 13:22"/>for there will rise false Christs and false prophets, and they will give signs and wonders, to seduce, if possible, also the chosen; <verse eid="MRK 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 13:23"/>and you, take heed; behold, I have foretold you all things. <verse eid="MRK 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 13:24"/>But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give her light, <verse eid="MRK 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 13:25"/>and the stars of the sky will be falling, and the powers that are in the heavens will be shaken. <verse eid="MRK 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 13:26"/>And then they will see the Son of Man coming in clouds with much power and glory, <verse eid="MRK 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 13:27"/>and then He will send His messengers, and gather together His chosen from the four winds, from the end of the earth to the end of heaven. <verse eid="MRK 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 13:28"/>And from the fig tree learn the allegory: when the branch may already become tender, and may put forth the leaves, you know that the summer is near; <verse eid="MRK 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 13:29"/>so you, also, when you may see these coming to pass, you know that it is near, at the doors. <verse eid="MRK 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 13:30"/>Truly I say to you that this generation may not pass away until all these things may come to pass; <verse eid="MRK 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 13:31"/>the heaven and the earth will pass away, but My words will not pass away. <verse eid="MRK 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 13:32"/>And concerning that day and the hour no one has known—not even the messengers who are in Heaven, not even the Son—except the Father. <verse eid="MRK 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 13:33"/>Take heed, watch and pray, for you have not known when the time is; <verse eid="MRK 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 13:34"/>as a man who is gone abroad, having left his house, and given to his servants the authority, and to each one his work, also commanded the doorkeeper that he may watch; <verse eid="MRK 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 13:35"/>watch, therefore, for you have not known when the lord of the house comes, at evening, or at midnight, or at rooster-crowing, or at the morning; <verse eid="MRK 13:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 13:36"/>lest, having come suddenly, he may find you sleeping; <verse eid="MRK 13:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 13:37"/>and what I say to you, I say to all, Watch!”<verse eid="MRK 13:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="MRK 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 14:1"/>And the Passover and the Unleavened [Bread] were after two days, and the chief priests and the scribes were seeking how, by guile, having taken hold of Him, they might kill Him; <verse eid="MRK 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 14:2"/>and they said, “Not in the celebration, lest there will be a tumult of the people.” <verse eid="MRK 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 14:3"/>And He, being in Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper, at His reclining, there came a woman having an alabaster box of ointment, of spikenard, very precious, and having broken the alabaster box, poured [it] on His head; <verse eid="MRK 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 14:4"/>and there were certain much displeased within themselves, and saying, “For what has this waste of the ointment been made? <verse eid="MRK 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 14:5"/>For this could have been sold for more than three hundred denarii, and given to the poor”; and they were murmuring at her. <verse eid="MRK 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 14:6"/>And Jesus said, “Leave her alone; why are you giving her trouble? She worked a good work on Me; <verse eid="MRK 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 14:7"/>for you always have the poor with you, and whenever you may will you are able to do them good, but you do not always have Me; <verse eid="MRK 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 14:8"/>she did what she could, she anticipated to anoint My body for the embalming. <verse eid="MRK 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 14:9"/>Truly I say to you, wherever this good news may be proclaimed in the whole world, what this woman did will also be spoken of—for a memorial of her.” <verse eid="MRK 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 14:10"/>And Judas the Iscariot, one of the Twelve, went away to the chief priests that he might deliver Him up to them, <verse eid="MRK 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 14:11"/>and having heard, they were glad, and promised to give him money, and he was seeking how, conveniently, he might deliver Him up. <verse eid="MRK 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 14:12"/>And the first day of the Unleavened [Bread], when they were killing the Passover, His disciples say to Him, “Where will You, [that] having gone, we may prepare, that You may eat the Passover?” <verse eid="MRK 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 14:13"/>And He sends forth two of His disciples and says to them, “Go away into the city, and there a man carrying a pitcher of water will meet you, follow him; <verse eid="MRK 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 14:14"/>and wherever he may go in, say to the master of the house: The Teacher says, Where is the guest-chamber, where the Passover, with My disciples, I may eat? <verse eid="MRK 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 14:15"/>And he will show you a large upper room, furnished, prepared—make ready for us there.” <verse eid="MRK 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 14:16"/>And His disciples went forth, and came into the city, and found as He said to them, and they made ready the Passover. <verse eid="MRK 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 14:17"/>And evening having come, He comes with the Twelve, <verse eid="MRK 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 14:18"/>and as they are reclining, and eating, Jesus said, “Truly I say to you that one of you who is eating with Me will deliver Me up.” <verse eid="MRK 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 14:19"/>And they began to be sorrowful, and to say to Him one by one, “Is it I?” And another, “Is it I?” <verse eid="MRK 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 14:20"/>And He answering said to them, “One of the Twelve who is dipping with Me in the dish; <verse eid="MRK 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 14:21"/>the Son of Man indeed goes, as it has been written concerning Him, but woe to that man through whom the Son of Man is delivered up; it were good to him if that man had not been born.” <verse eid="MRK 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 14:22"/>And as they are eating, Jesus having taken bread, having blessed, broke, and gave to them, and said, “Take, eat; this is My body.” <verse eid="MRK 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 14:23"/>And having taken the cup, having given thanks, He gave to them, and they drank of it—all; <verse eid="MRK 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 14:24"/>and He said to them, “This is My blood of the New Covenant, which is being poured out for many; <verse eid="MRK 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 14:25"/>truly I say to you that I may drink no more of the produce of the vine until that day when I may drink it new in the Kingdom of God.” <verse eid="MRK 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 14:26"/>And having sung a hymn, they went forth to the Mount of Olives, <verse eid="MRK 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 14:27"/>and Jesus says to them, “All of you will be stumbled at Me this night, because it has been written: I will strike the Shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered abroad; <verse eid="MRK 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 14:28"/>but after My having risen I will go before you to Galilee.” <verse eid="MRK 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 14:29"/>And Peter said to Him, “And if all will be stumbled, yet not I.” <verse eid="MRK 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 14:30"/>And Jesus said to him, “Truly I say to you that today, this night, before a rooster will crow twice, three times you will deny Me.” <verse eid="MRK 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 14:31"/>And he spoke the more vehemently, “If it may be necessary for me to die with You—I will in no way deny You”; and in like manner also said they all. <verse eid="MRK 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 14:32"/>And they come to a spot, the name of which [is] Gethsemane, and He says to His disciples, “Sit here until I may pray”; <verse eid="MRK 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 14:33"/>and He takes Peter, and James, and John with Him, and began to be amazed, and to be very heavy, <verse eid="MRK 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 14:34"/>and He says to them, “My soul is exceedingly sorrowful—to death; remain here, and watch.” <verse eid="MRK 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 14:35"/>And having gone forward a little, He fell on the earth, and was praying that, if it be possible, the hour may pass from Him, <verse eid="MRK 14:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 14:36"/>and He said, “Abba, Father; all things are possible to You; make this cup pass from Me; but not what I will, but what You [will].” <verse eid="MRK 14:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 14:37"/>And He comes, and finds them sleeping, and says to Peter, “Simon, you sleep! You were not able to watch one hour! <verse eid="MRK 14:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 14:38"/>Watch and pray, that you may not enter into temptation; the spirit indeed is forward, but the flesh weak.” <verse eid="MRK 14:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 14:39"/>And again having gone away, He prayed, saying the same word; <verse eid="MRK 14:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 14:40"/>and having returned, He found them sleeping again, for their eyes were heavy, and they had not known what they might answer Him. <verse eid="MRK 14:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 14:41"/>And He comes the third time and says to them, “Sleep on from now on, and rest—it is over; the hour came; behold, the Son of Man is delivered up into the hands of the sinful; <verse eid="MRK 14:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 14:42"/>rise, we may go, behold, he who is delivering Me up has come near.” <verse eid="MRK 14:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 14:43"/>And immediately—while He is yet speaking—Judas comes near, one of the Twelve, and with him a great multitude with swords and sticks, from the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders; <verse eid="MRK 14:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 14:44"/>and he who is delivering Him up had given a token to them, saying, “Whomsoever I will kiss, it is He, lay hold on Him, and lead Him away safely,” <verse eid="MRK 14:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 14:45"/>and having come, immediately, having gone near Him, he says, “Rabbi, Rabbi,” and kissed Him. <verse eid="MRK 14:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 14:46"/>And they laid on Him their hands, and kept hold on Him; <verse eid="MRK 14:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 14:47"/>and a certain one of those standing by, having drawn the sword, struck the servant of the chief priest, and took off his ear. <verse eid="MRK 14:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 14:48"/>And Jesus answering said to them, “As against a robber you came out, with swords and sticks, to take Me! <verse eid="MRK 14:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 14:49"/>Daily I was with you teaching in the temple, and you did not lay hold on Me—but that the Writings may be fulfilled.” <verse eid="MRK 14:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 14:50"/>And having left Him they all fled; <verse eid="MRK 14:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 14:51"/>and a certain young man was following Him, having cast a linen cloth on [his] naked [body], and the young men lay hold on him, <verse eid="MRK 14:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 14:52"/>and he, having left the linen cloth, fled from them naked. <verse eid="MRK 14:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 14:53"/>And they led Jesus away to the chief priest, and all the chief priests, and the elders, and the scribes come together; <verse eid="MRK 14:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 14:54"/>and Peter followed Him far off, to the inside of the hall of the chief priest, and he was sitting with the officers, and warming himself near the fire. <verse eid="MRK 14:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 14:55"/>And the chief priests and all the Sanhedrin were seeking testimony against Jesus—to put Him to death, and they were not finding, <verse eid="MRK 14:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 14:56"/>for many were bearing false testimony against Him, and their testimonies were not alike. <verse eid="MRK 14:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="MRK 14:57"/>And certain having risen up, were bearing false testimony against Him, saying, <verse eid="MRK 14:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="MRK 14:58"/>“We heard Him saying, I will throw down this temple made with hands, and by three days, I will build another made without hands”; <verse eid="MRK 14:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="MRK 14:59"/>and neither so was their testimony alike. <verse eid="MRK 14:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="MRK 14:60"/>And the chief priest, having risen up in the midst, questioned Jesus, saying, “You do not answer anything! Why do these testify against You?” <verse eid="MRK 14:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="MRK 14:61"/>And He was keeping silent and did not answer anything. Again the chief priest was questioning Him and says to Him, “Are You the Christ—the Son of the Blessed?” <verse eid="MRK 14:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="MRK 14:62"/>And Jesus said, “I AM; and you will see the Son of Man sitting on the right hand of the Power and coming with the clouds of Heaven.” <verse eid="MRK 14:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="MRK 14:63"/>And the chief priest, having torn his garments, says, “What need have we yet of witnesses? <verse eid="MRK 14:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="MRK 14:64"/>You heard the slander, what appears to you?” And they all condemned Him to be worthy of death, <verse eid="MRK 14:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="MRK 14:65"/>and certain began to spit on Him, and to cover His face, and to punch Him, and to say to Him, “Prophesy”; and the officers were striking Him with their palms. <verse eid="MRK 14:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="MRK 14:66"/>And Peter being in the hall beneath, there comes one of the maids of the chief priest, <verse eid="MRK 14:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="MRK 14:67"/>and having seen Peter warming himself, having looked on him, she said, “And you were with Jesus of Nazareth!” <verse eid="MRK 14:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="MRK 14:68"/>And he denied, saying, “I have not known [Him], neither do I understand what you say”; and he went forth outside to the porch, and a rooster crowed. <verse eid="MRK 14:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="MRK 14:69"/>And the maid having seen him again, began to say to those standing near, “This is of them”; <verse eid="MRK 14:69"/><verse number="70" style="v" sid="MRK 14:70"/>and he was again denying. And after a while again, those standing near said to Peter, “Truly you are of them, for you also are a Galilean, and your speech is alike”; <verse eid="MRK 14:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="MRK 14:71"/>and he began to curse, and to swear, “I have not known this Man of whom you speak”; <verse eid="MRK 14:71"/><verse number="72" style="v" sid="MRK 14:72"/>and a second time a rooster crowed, and Peter remembered the saying that Jesus said to him, “Before a rooster crows twice, you may deny Me three times”; and having thought thereon—he was weeping.<verse eid="MRK 14:72"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="MRK 15"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 15:1"/>And immediately, in the morning, the chief priests having made a consultation with the elders, and scribes, and the whole Sanhedrin, having bound Jesus, led [Him] away, and delivered [Him] to Pilate; <verse eid="MRK 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 15:2"/>and Pilate questioned Him, “Are You the King of the Jews?” And He answering said to him, “You say [it].” <verse eid="MRK 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 15:3"/>And the chief priests were accusing Him of many things, [but He answered nothing.] <verse eid="MRK 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 15:4"/>And Pilate again questioned Him, saying, “You do not answer anything? Behold, how many things they testify against You!” <verse eid="MRK 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 15:5"/>And Jesus no longer answered anything, so that Pilate wondered. <verse eid="MRK 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 15:6"/>And at every celebration he was releasing to them one prisoner, whomsoever they were asking for; <verse eid="MRK 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 15:7"/>and there was [one] named Barabbas, bound with those making insurrection with him, who had committed murder in the insurrection. <verse eid="MRK 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 15:8"/>And the multitude having cried out, began to ask for themselves as he was always doing to them, <verse eid="MRK 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 15:9"/>and Pilate answered them, saying, “Will you [that] I will release to you the King of the Jews?” <verse eid="MRK 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 15:10"/>For he knew that the chief priests had delivered Him up because of envy; <verse eid="MRK 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 15:11"/>and the chief priests moved the multitude that he might rather release Barabbas to them. <verse eid="MRK 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 15:12"/>And Pilate answering, again said to them, “What, then, will you [that] I will do to Him whom you call King of the Jews?” <verse eid="MRK 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 15:13"/>And they again cried out, “Crucify Him!” <verse eid="MRK 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 15:14"/>And Pilate said to them, “Why—what evil did He do?” And they cried out the more vehemently, “Crucify Him!” <verse eid="MRK 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 15:15"/>And Pilate, resolving to do that which [was] satisfactory to the multitude, released Barabbas to them, and delivered up Jesus—having scourged [Him]—that He might be crucified. <verse eid="MRK 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 15:16"/>And the soldiers led Him away into the hall, which is [the] Praetorium, and call together the whole band, <verse eid="MRK 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 15:17"/>and clothe Him with purple, and having plaited a garland of thorns, they put [it] on Him, <verse eid="MRK 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 15:18"/>and began to greet Him, “Hail, King of the Jews!” <verse eid="MRK 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 15:19"/>And they were striking Him on the head with a reed, and were spitting on Him, and having bent the knee, were prostrating to Him, <verse eid="MRK 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 15:20"/>and when they [had] mocked Him, they took the purple from off Him, and clothed Him in His own garments, and they led Him forth, that they may crucify Him. <verse eid="MRK 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 15:21"/>And they impress a certain one passing by—Simon, a Cyrenian, coming from the field, the father of Alexander and Rufus—that he may carry His cross, <verse eid="MRK 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 15:22"/>and they bring Him to the place [called] Golgotha, which is, being interpreted, “Place of [the] Skull”; <verse eid="MRK 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 15:23"/>and they were giving Him wine mingled with myrrh to drink, and He did not receive [it]. <verse eid="MRK 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 15:24"/>And having crucified Him, they were dividing His garments, casting a lot on them, what each may take; <verse eid="MRK 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 15:25"/>and it was the third hour, and they crucified Him; <verse eid="MRK 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 15:26"/>and the inscription of His accusation was written above: “THE KING OF THE JEWS.” <verse eid="MRK 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 15:27"/>And they crucify two robbers with Him, one on the right hand and one on His left, <verse eid="MRK 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 15:28"/><char style="bd">[[</char>and the Writing was fulfilled that is saying, “And He was numbered with lawless ones.”<char style="bd">]]</char> <verse eid="MRK 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 15:29"/>And those passing by were slandering Him, shaking their heads, and saying, “Ha! The [One] throwing down the temple, and building [it] in three days! <verse eid="MRK 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 15:30"/>Save Yourself, and come down from the cross!” <verse eid="MRK 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 15:31"/>And in like manner also the chief priests, mocking with one another, with the scribes, said, “He saved others; He is not able to save Himself. <verse eid="MRK 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 15:32"/>The Christ! The King of Israel—let Him come down now from the cross, that we may see and believe”; and those crucified with Him were reproaching Him. <verse eid="MRK 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 15:33"/>And the sixth hour having come, darkness came over the whole land until the ninth hour, <verse eid="MRK 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 15:34"/>and at the ninth hour Jesus cried with a great voice, saying, “Eloi, Eloi, lamma sabachthani?” Which is, being interpreted, “My God, My God, why did You forsake Me?” <verse eid="MRK 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 15:35"/>And certain of those standing by, having heard, said, “Behold, He calls Elijah”; <verse eid="MRK 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 15:36"/>and one having run, and having filled a sponge with vinegar, having also put [it] on a reed, was giving Him to drink, saying, “Let alone, let us see if Elijah comes to take Him down.” <verse eid="MRK 15:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 15:37"/>And Jesus having uttered a loud cry, yielded the spirit, <verse eid="MRK 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 15:38"/>and the veil of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom, <verse eid="MRK 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 15:39"/>and the centurion who was standing opposite Him, having seen that, having so cried out, He yielded the spirit, said, “Truly this Man was [the] Son of God.” <verse eid="MRK 15:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 15:40"/>And there were also women beholding far off, among whom was also Mary the Magdalene, and Mary of James the less, and of Joses, and Salome, <verse eid="MRK 15:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 15:41"/>who also, when He was in Galilee, were following Him and were ministering to Him, and many other women who came up with Him to Jerusalem. <verse eid="MRK 15:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 15:42"/>And now evening having come, seeing it was the Preparation, that is, before Sabbath, <verse eid="MRK 15:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 15:43"/>Joseph of Arimathea, an honorable counselor, who also himself was waiting for the Kingdom of God, came, boldly entered in to Pilate, and asked for the body of Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 15:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 15:44"/>And Pilate wondered if He were already dead, and having called near the centurion, questioned him if He were long dead, <verse eid="MRK 15:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 15:45"/>and having known [it] from the centurion, he granted the body to Joseph. <verse eid="MRK 15:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 15:46"/>And he, having brought fine linen, and having taken Him down, wrapped Him in the linen, and laid Him in a tomb that had been hewn out of a rock, and he rolled a stone to the door of the tomb, <verse eid="MRK 15:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 15:47"/>and Mary the Magdalene, and Mary of Joses, were beholding where He is laid.<verse eid="MRK 15:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="MRK 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 16:1"/>And the Sabbath having past, Mary the Magdalene, and Mary of James, and Salome, bought spices, that having come, they may anoint Him, <verse eid="MRK 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 16:2"/>and early in the morning of the first [day] of the weeks, they come to the tomb, at the rising of the sun, <verse eid="MRK 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 16:3"/>and they said among themselves, “Who will roll away the stone out of the door of the tomb for us?” <verse eid="MRK 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 16:4"/>And having looked, they see that the stone has been rolled away—for it was very great, <verse eid="MRK 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 16:5"/>and having entered into the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right hand, clothed in a long white robe, and they were amazed. <verse eid="MRK 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 16:6"/>And he says to them, “Do not be amazed, you seek Jesus the Nazarene, the crucified [One]: He rose—He is not here; behold the place where they laid Him! <verse eid="MRK 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 16:7"/>And go, say to His disciples and Peter that He goes before you to Galilee; there you will see Him, as He said to you.” <verse eid="MRK 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 16:8"/>And having come forth quickly, they fled from the tomb, and trembling and amazement had seized them, and they said to no one anything, for they were afraid. <char style="bd">[[</char> <verse eid="MRK 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 16:9"/>And He, having risen in the morning of the first of the week, appeared first to Mary the Magdalene, out of whom He had cast seven demons; <verse eid="MRK 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 16:10"/>she having gone, told those who had been with Him, mourning and weeping; <verse eid="MRK 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 16:11"/>and they, having heard that He is alive, and was seen by her, did not believe. <verse eid="MRK 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 16:12"/>And after these things, to two of them, as they are going into a field, walking, He appeared in another form, <verse eid="MRK 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 16:13"/>and they having gone, told [it] to the rest; not even them did they believe. <verse eid="MRK 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 16:14"/>Afterward, as they are reclining, He appeared to the Eleven, and reproached their unbelief and stiffness of heart, because they did not believe those having seen Him being raised; <verse eid="MRK 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 16:15"/>and He said to them, “Having gone into all the world, proclaim the good news to all the creation; <verse eid="MRK 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 16:16"/>he who has believed and has been immersed will be saved; and he who has not believed will be condemned. <verse eid="MRK 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 16:17"/>And signs will accompany those believing these things: they will cast out demons in My Name; they will speak with new tongues; <verse eid="MRK 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 16:18"/>they will take up serpents; and if they may drink any deadly thing, it will not hurt them; they will lay hands on the ailing, and they will be well.” <verse eid="MRK 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 16:19"/>The LORD, then, indeed, after speaking to them, was received up to Heaven, and sat on the right hand of God; <verse eid="MRK 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 16:20"/>and they, having gone forth, preached everywhere, the LORD working with [them], and confirming the word, through the signs following. Amen.<char style="bd">]]</char><verse eid="MRK 16:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 16"/>
</usx>
