<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2CH" style="id">The Second Book of Chronicles</book>
  <para style="h">2 Chronicles</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Second Book of the Chronicles</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Chronicles</para>
  <para style="toc3">2Ch</para>
  <para style="mt1">The Second Book of the Chronicles</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2CH 1" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 1:1" />And Solomon the son of David was strengthened in his kingdom, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God <char style="add">was</char> with him, and magnified him exceedingly. <verse eid="2CH 1:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 1:2" />Then Solomon spake unto all Israel, to the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and to the judges, and to every governor in all Israel, the chief of the fathers. <verse eid="2CH 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 1:3" />So Solomon, and all the congregation with him, went to the high place that <char style="add">was</char> at Gibeon; for there was the tabernacle of the congregation of God, which Moses the servant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had made in the wilderness. <verse eid="2CH 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 1:4" />But the ark of God had David brought up from Kirjath-jearim to <char style="add">the place which</char> David had prepared for it: for he had pitched a tent for it at Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 1:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 1:5" />Moreover the brasen altar, that Bezaleel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, had made, he put before the tabernacle of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: and Solomon and the congregation sought unto it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he put: or, was there</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 1:6" />And Solomon went up thither to the brasen altar before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, which <char style="add">was</char> at the tabernacle of the congregation, and offered a thousand burnt offerings upon it.<verse eid="2CH 1:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 1:7" />¶ In that night did God appear unto Solomon, and said unto him, Ask what I shall give thee. <verse eid="2CH 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 1:8" />And Solomon said unto God, Thou hast shewed great mercy unto David my father, and hast made me to reign in his stead. <verse eid="2CH 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 1:9" />Now, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God, let thy promise unto David my father be established: for thou hast made me king over a people like the dust of the earth in multitude.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">like…: Heb. much as the dust of the earth</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 1:10" />Give me now wisdom and knowledge, that I may go out and come in before this people: for who can judge this thy people, <char style="add">that is so</char> great? <verse eid="2CH 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 1:11" />And God said to Solomon, Because this was in thine heart, and thou hast not asked riches, wealth, or honour, nor the life of thine enemies, neither yet hast asked long life; but hast asked wisdom and knowledge for thyself, that thou mayest judge my people, over whom I have made thee king: <verse eid="2CH 1:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 1:12" />Wisdom and knowledge <char style="add">is</char> granted unto thee; and I will give thee riches, and wealth, and honour, such as none of the kings have had that <char style="add">have been</char> before thee, neither shall there any after thee have the like.<verse eid="2CH 1:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 1:13" />¶ Then Solomon came <char style="add">from his journey</char> to the high place that <char style="add">was</char> at Gibeon to Jerusalem, from before the tabernacle of the congregation, and reigned over Israel. <verse eid="2CH 1:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 1:14" />And Solomon gathered chariots and horsemen: and he had a thousand and four hundred chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, which he placed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 1:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 1:15" />And the king made silver and gold at Jerusalem <char style="add">as plenteous</char> as stones, and cedar trees made he as the sycomore trees that <char style="add">are</char> in the vale for abundance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">made: Heb. gave</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 1:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 1:16" />And Solomon had horses brought out of Egypt, and linen yarn: the king’s merchants received the linen yarn at a price.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Solomon…: Heb. the going forth of the horses which was Solomon’s</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 1:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 1:17" />And they fetched up, and brought forth out of Egypt a chariot for six hundred <char style="add">shekels</char> of silver, and an horse for an hundred and fifty: and so brought they out <char style="add">horses</char> for all the kings of the Hittites, and for the kings of Syria, by their means.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means: Heb. hand</char></note><verse eid="2CH 1:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2CH 2" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 2:1" />And Solomon determined to build an house for the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and an house for his kingdom. <verse eid="2CH 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 2:2" />And Solomon told out threescore and ten thousand men to bear burdens, and fourscore thousand to hew in the mountain, and three thousand and six hundred to oversee them.<verse eid="2CH 2:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 2:3" />¶ And Solomon sent to Huram the king of Tyre, saying, As thou didst deal with David my father, and didst send him cedars to build him an house to dwell therein, <char style="add">even so deal with me</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Huram: or, Hiram</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 2:4" />Behold, I build an house to the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> my God, to dedicate <char style="add">it</char> to him, <char style="add">and</char> to burn before him sweet incense, and for the continual shewbread, and for the burnt offerings morning and evening, on the sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the solemn feasts of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God. This <char style="add">is an ordinance</char> for ever to Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sweet…: Heb. incense of spices</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 2:5" />And the house which I build <char style="add">is</char> great: for great <char style="add">is</char> our God above all gods. <verse eid="2CH 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 2:6" />But who is able to build him an house, seeing the heaven and heaven of heavens cannot contain him? who <char style="add">am</char> I then, that I should build him an house, save only to burn sacrifice before him?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is able: Heb. hath retained, or, obtained strength</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 2:7" />Send me now therefore a man cunning to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, and in iron, and in purple, and crimson, and blue, and that can skill to grave with the cunning men that <char style="add">are</char> with me in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom David my father did provide.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to grave: Heb. to grave gravings</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 2:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 2:8" />Send me also cedar trees, fir trees, and algum trees, out of Lebanon: for I know that thy servants can skill to cut timber in Lebanon; and, behold, my servants <char style="add">shall be</char> with thy servants,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">algum: also called, almuggim</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 2:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 2:9" />Even to prepare me timber in abundance: for the house which I am about to build <char style="add">shall be</char> wonderful great.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wonderful…: Heb. great and wonderful</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 2:10" />And, behold, I will give to thy servants, the hewers that cut timber, twenty thousand measures of beaten wheat, and twenty thousand measures of barley, and twenty thousand baths of wine, and twenty thousand baths of oil.<verse eid="2CH 2:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 2:11" />¶ Then Huram the king of Tyre answered in writing, which he sent to Solomon, Because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath loved his people, he hath made thee king over them. <verse eid="2CH 2:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 2:12" />Huram said moreover, Blessed <char style="add">be</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, that made heaven and earth, who hath given to David the king a wise son, endued with prudence and understanding, that might build an house for the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and an house for his kingdom.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">endued…: Heb. knowing prudence and understanding</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 2:13" />And now I have sent a cunning man, endued with understanding, of Huram my father’s, <verse eid="2CH 2:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 2:14" />The son of a woman of the daughters of Dan, and his father <char style="add">was</char> a man of Tyre, skilful to work in gold, and in silver, in brass, in iron, in stone, and in timber, in purple, in blue, and in fine linen, and in crimson; also to grave any manner of graving, and to find out every device which shall be put to him, with thy cunning men, and with the cunning men of my lord David thy father. <verse eid="2CH 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 2:15" />Now therefore the wheat, and the barley, the oil, and the wine, which my lord hath spoken of, let him send unto his servants: <verse eid="2CH 2:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 2:16" />And we will cut wood out of Lebanon, as much as thou shalt need: and we will bring it to thee in floats by sea to Joppa; and thou shalt carry it up to Jerusalem.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as much…: Heb according to all thy need</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Joppa: Heb. Japho</char></note><verse eid="2CH 2:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 2:17" />¶ And Solomon numbered all the strangers that <char style="add">were</char> in the land of Israel, after the numbering wherewith David his father had numbered them; and they were found an hundred and fifty thousand and three thousand and six hundred.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the strangers: Heb. the men the strangers</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 2:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 2:18" />And he set threescore and ten thousand of them <char style="add">to be</char> bearers of burdens, and fourscore thousand <char style="add">to be</char> hewers in the mountain, and three thousand and six hundred overseers to set the people a work.<verse eid="2CH 2:18" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2CH 3" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 3:1" />Then Solomon began to build the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> at Jerusalem in mount Moriah, where <char style="add">the <char style="nd">Lord</char></char> appeared unto David his father, in the place that David had prepared in the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">where…: or, which was seen of David his father</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ornan: also called, Araunah</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 3:2" />And he began to build in the second <char style="add">day</char> of the second month, in the fourth year of his reign.<verse eid="2CH 3:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 3:3" />¶ Now these <char style="add">are the things wherein</char> Solomon was instructed for the building of the house of God. The length by cubits after the first measure <char style="add">was</char> threescore cubits, and the breadth twenty cubits.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">instructed: Heb. founded</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 3:4" />And the porch that <char style="add">was</char> in the front <char style="add">of the house</char>, the length <char style="add">of it was</char> according to the breadth of the house, twenty cubits, and the height <char style="add">was</char> an hundred and twenty: and he overlaid it within with pure gold. <verse eid="2CH 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 3:5" />And the greater house he cieled with fir tree, which he overlaid with fine gold, and set thereon palm trees and chains. <verse eid="2CH 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 3:6" />And he garnished the house with precious stones for beauty: and the gold <char style="add">was</char> gold of Parvaim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">garnished: Heb. covered</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 3:7" />He overlaid also the house, the beams, the posts, and the walls thereof, and the doors thereof, with gold; and graved cherubims on the walls. <verse eid="2CH 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 3:8" />And he made the most holy house, the length whereof <char style="add">was</char> according to the breadth of the house, twenty cubits, and the breadth thereof twenty cubits: and he overlaid it with fine gold, <char style="add">amounting</char> to six hundred talents. <verse eid="2CH 3:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 3:9" />And the weight of the nails <char style="add">was</char> fifty shekels of gold. And he overlaid the upper chambers with gold.<verse eid="2CH 3:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 3:10" />And in the most holy house he made two cherubims of image work, and overlaid them with gold.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">image…: or, (as some think) of moveable work</char></note><verse eid="2CH 3:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 3:11" />¶ And the wings of the cherubims <char style="add">were</char> twenty cubits long: one wing <char style="add">of the one cherub was</char> five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house: and the other wing <char style="add">was likewise</char> five cubits, reaching to the wing of the other cherub. <verse eid="2CH 3:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 3:12" />And <char style="add">one</char> wing of the other cherub <char style="add">was</char> five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house: and the other wing <char style="add">was</char> five cubits <char style="add">also</char>, joining to the wing of the other cherub. <verse eid="2CH 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 3:13" />The wings of these cherubims spread themselves forth twenty cubits: and they stood on their feet, and their faces <char style="add">were</char> inward.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">inward: or, toward the house</char></note><verse eid="2CH 3:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 3:14" />¶ And he made the vail <char style="add">of</char> blue, and purple, and crimson, and fine linen, and wrought cherubims thereon.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wrought: Heb. caused to ascend</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 3:15" />Also he made before the house two pillars of thirty and five cubits high, and the chapiter that <char style="add">was</char> on the top of each of them <char style="add">was</char> five cubits.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">high: Heb. long</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 3:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 3:16" />And he made chains, <char style="add">as</char> in the oracle, and put <char style="add">them</char> on the heads of the pillars; and made an hundred pomegranates, and put <char style="add">them</char> on the chains. <verse eid="2CH 3:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 3:17" />And he reared up the pillars before the temple, one on the right hand, and the other on the left; and called the name of that on the right hand Jachin, and the name of that on the left Boaz.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Jachin: that is, He shall establish</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Boaz: that is, In it is strength</char></note><verse eid="2CH 3:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="2CH 4" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 4:1" />Moreover he made an altar of brass, twenty cubits the length thereof, and twenty cubits the breadth thereof, and ten cubits the height thereof.<verse eid="2CH 4:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 4:2" />¶ Also he made a molten sea of ten cubits from brim to brim, round in compass, and five cubits the height thereof; and a line of thirty cubits did compass it round about.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from…: Heb. from his brim to his brim</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 4:3" />And under it <char style="add">was</char> the similitude of oxen, which did compass it round about: ten in a cubit, compassing the sea round about. Two rows of oxen <char style="add">were</char> cast, when it was cast. <verse eid="2CH 4:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 4:4" />It stood upon twelve oxen, three looking toward the north, and three looking toward the west, and three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east: and the sea <char style="add">was set</char> above upon them, and all their hinder parts <char style="add">were</char> inward. <verse eid="2CH 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 4:5" />And the thickness of it <char style="add">was</char> an handbreadth, and the brim of it like the work of the brim of a cup, with flowers of lilies; <char style="add">and</char> it received and held three thousand baths.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">with flowers…: or, like a lilyflower</char></note><verse eid="2CH 4:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 4:6" />¶ He made also ten lavers, and put five on the right hand, and five on the left, to wash in them: such things as they offered for the burnt offering they washed in them; but the sea <char style="add">was</char> for the priests to wash in.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">such…: Heb. the work of burnt offering</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 4:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 4:7" />And he made ten candlesticks of gold according to their form, and set <char style="add">them</char> in the temple, five on the right hand, and five on the left. <verse eid="2CH 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 4:8" />He made also ten tables, and placed <char style="add">them</char> in the temple, five on the right side, and five on the left. And he made an hundred basons of gold.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">basons: or, bowls</char></note><verse eid="2CH 4:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 4:9" />¶ Furthermore he made the court of the priests, and the great court, and doors for the court, and overlaid the doors of them with brass. <verse eid="2CH 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 4:10" />And he set the sea on the right side of the east end, over against the south.<verse eid="2CH 4:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 4:11" />And Huram made the pots, and the shovels, and the basons. And Huram finished the work that he was to make for king Solomon for the house of God;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">basons: or, bowls</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">finished: Heb. finished to make</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 4:12" /><char style="add">To wit</char>, the two pillars, and the pommels, and the chapiters <char style="add">which were</char> on the top of the two pillars, and the two wreaths to cover the two pommels of the chapiters which <char style="add">were</char> on the top of the pillars; <verse eid="2CH 4:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 4:13" />And four hundred pomegranates on the two wreaths; two rows of pomegranates on each wreath, to cover the two pommels of the chapiters which <char style="add">were</char> upon the pillars.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">upon: Heb. upon the face of</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 4:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 4:14" />He made also bases, and lavers made he upon the bases;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">lavers: or, caldrons</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 4:15" />One sea, and twelve oxen under it. <verse eid="2CH 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 4:16" />The pots also, and the shovels, and the fleshhooks, and all their instruments, did Huram his father make to king Solomon for the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> of bright brass.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">bright: Heb. made bright, or, scoured</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 4:17" />In the plain of Jordan did the king cast them, in the clay ground between Succoth and Zeredathah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">clay…: Heb. thicknesses of the ground</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 4:18" />Thus Solomon made all these vessels in great abundance: for the weight of the brass could not be found out.<verse eid="2CH 4:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 4:19" />¶ And Solomon made all the vessels that <char style="add">were for</char> the house of God, the golden altar also, and the tables whereon the shewbread <char style="add">was set;</char> <verse eid="2CH 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 4:20" />Moreover the candlesticks with their lamps, that they should burn after the manner before the oracle, of pure gold; <verse eid="2CH 4:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 4:21" />And the flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs, <char style="add">made he of</char> gold, <char style="add">and</char> that perfect gold;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">perfect…: Heb. perfections of gold</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 4:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 4:22" />And the snuffers, and the basons, and the spoons, and the censers, <char style="add">of</char> pure gold: and the entry of the house, the inner doors thereof for the most holy <char style="add">place</char>, and the doors of the house of the temple, <char style="add">were of</char> gold.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">basons: or, bowls</char></note><verse eid="2CH 4:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="2CH 5" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 5:1" />Thus all the work that Solomon made for the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was finished: and Solomon brought in <char style="add">all</char> the things that David his father had dedicated; and the silver, and the gold, and all the instruments, put he among the treasures of the house of God.<verse eid="2CH 5:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 5:2" />¶ Then Solomon assembled the elders of Israel, and all the heads of the tribes, the chief of the fathers of the children of Israel, unto Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> out of the city of David, which <char style="add">is</char> Zion. <verse eid="2CH 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 5:3" />Wherefore all the men of Israel assembled themselves unto the king in the feast which <char style="add">was</char> in the seventh month. <verse eid="2CH 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 5:4" />And all the elders of Israel came; and the Levites took up the ark. <verse eid="2CH 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 5:5" />And they brought up the ark, and the tabernacle of the congregation, and all the holy vessels that <char style="add">were</char> in the tabernacle, these did the priests <char style="add">and</char> the Levites bring up. <verse eid="2CH 5:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 5:6" />Also king Solomon, and all the congregation of Israel that were assembled unto him before the ark, sacrificed sheep and oxen, which could not be told nor numbered for multitude. <verse eid="2CH 5:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 5:7" />And the priests brought in the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> unto his place, to the oracle of the house, into the most holy <char style="add">place, even</char> under the wings of the cherubims: <verse eid="2CH 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 5:8" />For the cherubims spread forth <char style="add">their</char> wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubims covered the ark and the staves thereof above. <verse eid="2CH 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 5:9" />And they drew out the staves <char style="add">of the ark</char>, that the ends of the staves were seen from the ark before the oracle; but they were not seen without. And there it is unto this day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">there…: or, they are there</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 5:10" /><char style="add">There was</char> nothing in the ark save the two tables which Moses put <char style="add">therein</char> at Horeb, when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> made <char style="add">a covenant</char> with the children of Israel, when they came out of Egypt.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">when the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: or, where, etc</char></note><verse eid="2CH 5:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 5:11" />¶ And it came to pass, when the priests were come out of the holy <char style="add">place:</char> (for all the priests <char style="add">that were</char> present were sanctified, <char style="add">and</char> did not <char style="add">then</char> wait by course:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 5:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 5:12" />Also the Levites <char style="add">which were</char> the singers, all of them of Asaph, of Heman, of Jeduthun, with their sons and their brethren, <char style="add">being</char> arrayed in white linen, having cymbals and psalteries and harps, stood at the east end of the altar, and with them an hundred and twenty priests sounding with trumpets:) <verse eid="2CH 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 5:13" />It came even to pass, as the trumpeters and singers <char style="add">were</char> as one, to make one sound to be heard in praising and thanking the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; and when they lifted up <char style="add">their</char> voice with the trumpets and cymbals and instruments of musick, and praised the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, <char style="add">saying</char>, For <char style="add">he is</char> good; for his mercy <char style="add">endureth</char> for ever: that <char style="add">then</char> the house was filled with a cloud, <char style="add">even</char> the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; <verse eid="2CH 5:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 5:14" />So that the priests could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud: for the glory of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had filled the house of God.<verse eid="2CH 5:14" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 5" />
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="2CH 6" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 6:1" />Then said Solomon, The <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath said that he would dwell in the thick darkness. <verse eid="2CH 6:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 6:2" />But I have built an house of habitation for thee, and a place for thy dwelling for ever. <verse eid="2CH 6:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 6:3" />And the king turned his face, and blessed the whole congregation of Israel: and all the congregation of Israel stood. <verse eid="2CH 6:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 6:4" />And he said, Blessed <char style="add">be</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, who hath with his hands fulfilled <char style="add">that</char> which he spake with his mouth to my father David, saying, <verse eid="2CH 6:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 6:5" />Since the day that I brought forth my people out of the land of Egypt I chose no city among all the tribes of Israel to build an house in, that my name might be there; neither chose I any man to be a ruler over my people Israel: <verse eid="2CH 6:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 6:6" />But I have chosen Jerusalem, that my name might be there; and have chosen David to be over my people Israel. <verse eid="2CH 6:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 6:7" />Now it was in the heart of David my father to build an house for the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 6:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 6:8" />But the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said to David my father, Forasmuch as it was in thine heart to build an house for my name, thou didst well in that it was in thine heart: <verse eid="2CH 6:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 6:9" />Notwithstanding thou shalt not build the house; but thy son which shall come forth out of thy loins, he shall build the house for my name. <verse eid="2CH 6:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 6:10" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> therefore hath performed his word that he hath spoken: for I am risen up in the room of David my father, and am set on the throne of Israel, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> promised, and have built the house for the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 6:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 6:11" />And in it have I put the ark, wherein <char style="add">is</char> the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, that he made with the children of Israel.<verse eid="2CH 6:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 6:12" />¶ And he stood before the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> in the presence of all the congregation of Israel, and spread forth his hands: <verse eid="2CH 6:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 6:13" />For Solomon had made a brasen scaffold, of five cubits long, and five cubits broad, and three cubits high, and had set it in the midst of the court: and upon it he stood, and kneeled down upon his knees before all the congregation of Israel, and spread forth his hands toward heaven,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">long…: Heb. the length thereof, etc</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 6:14" />And said, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, <char style="add">there is</char> no God like thee in the heaven, nor in the earth; which keepest covenant, and <char style="add">shewest</char> mercy unto thy servants, that walk before thee with all their hearts: <verse eid="2CH 6:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 6:15" />Thou which hast kept with thy servant David my father that which thou hast promised him; and spakest with thy mouth, and hast fulfilled <char style="add">it</char> with thine hand, as <char style="add">it is</char> this day. <verse eid="2CH 6:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 6:16" />Now therefore, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, keep with thy servant David my father that which thou hast promised him, saying, There shall not fail thee a man in my sight to sit upon the throne of Israel; yet so that thy children take heed to their way to walk in my law, as thou hast walked before me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">There…: Heb. There shall not a man be cut off</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 6:17" />Now then, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, let thy word be verified, which thou hast spoken unto thy servant David. <verse eid="2CH 6:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 6:18" />But will God in very deed dwell with men on the earth? behold, heaven and the heaven of heavens cannot contain thee; how much less this house which I have built! <verse eid="2CH 6:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 6:19" />Have respect therefore to the prayer of thy servant, and to his supplication, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> my God, to hearken unto the cry and the prayer which thy servant prayeth before thee: <verse eid="2CH 6:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 6:20" />That thine eyes may be open upon this house day and night, upon the place whereof thou hast said that thou wouldest put thy name there; to hearken unto the prayer which thy servant prayeth toward this place.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">toward…: or, in this place</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 6:21" />Hearken therefore unto the supplications of thy servant, and of thy people Israel, which they shall make toward this place: hear thou from thy dwelling place, <char style="add">even</char> from heaven; and when thou hearest, forgive.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">make: Heb. pray</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">toward…: or, in this place</char></note><verse eid="2CH 6:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 6:22" />¶ If a man sin against his neighbour, and an oath be laid upon him to make him swear, and the oath come before thine altar in this house;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and an oath…: Heb. and he require an oath of him</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 6:23" />Then hear thou from heaven, and do, and judge thy servants, by requiting the wicked, by recompensing his way upon his own head; and by justifying the righteous, by giving him according to his righteousness.<verse eid="2CH 6:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 6:24" />¶ And if thy people Israel be put to the worse before the enemy, because they have sinned against thee; and shall return and confess thy name, and pray and make supplication before thee in this house;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">be put…: or, be smitten</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in: or, toward</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 6:25" />Then hear thou from the heavens, and forgive the sin of thy people Israel, and bring them again unto the land which thou gavest to them and to their fathers.<verse eid="2CH 6:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 6:26" />¶ When the heaven is shut up, and there is no rain, because they have sinned against thee; <char style="add">yet</char> if they pray toward this place, and confess thy name, and turn from their sin, when thou dost afflict them;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">toward…: or, in this place</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 6:27" />Then hear thou from heaven, and forgive the sin of thy servants, and of thy people Israel, when thou hast taught them the good way, wherein they should walk; and send rain upon thy land, which thou hast given unto thy people for an inheritance.<verse eid="2CH 6:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 6:28" />¶ If there be dearth in the land, if there be pestilence, if there be blasting, or mildew, locusts, or caterpillers; if their enemies besiege them in the cities of their land; whatsoever sore or whatsoever sickness <char style="add">there be:</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in the cities…: Heb. in the land of their gates</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 6:29" /><char style="add">Then</char> what prayer <char style="add">or</char> what supplication soever shall be made of any man, or of all thy people Israel, when every one shall know his own sore and his own grief, and shall spread forth his hands in this house:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in: or, toward</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">toward…: or, in this place</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 6:30" />Then hear thou from heaven thy dwelling place, and forgive, and render unto every man according unto all his ways, whose heart thou knowest; (for thou only knowest the hearts of the children of men:) <verse eid="2CH 6:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 6:31" />That they may fear thee, to walk in thy ways, so long as they live in the land which thou gavest unto our fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">so long…: Heb. all the days which</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in the land: Heb. upon the face of the land</char></note><verse eid="2CH 6:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 6:32" />¶ Moreover concerning the stranger, which is not of thy people Israel, but is come from a far country for thy great name’s sake, and thy mighty hand, and thy stretched out arm; if they come and pray in this house;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">toward…: or, in this place</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 6:33" />Then hear thou from the heavens, <char style="add">even</char> from thy dwelling place, and do according to all that the stranger calleth to thee for; that all people of the earth may know thy name, and fear thee, as <char style="add">doth</char> thy people Israel, and may know that this house which I have built is called by thy name.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">this…: Heb. thy name is called upon this house</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 6:34" />If thy people go out to war against their enemies by the way that thou shalt send them, and they pray unto thee toward this city which thou hast chosen, and the house which I have built for thy name; <verse eid="2CH 6:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 6:35" />Then hear thou from the heavens their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cause: or, right</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 6:36" />If they sin against thee, (for <char style="add">there is</char> no man which sinneth not,) and thou be angry with them, and deliver them over before <char style="add">their</char> enemies, and they carry them away captives unto a land far off or near;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">they carry them away captives: Heb. they that take them captives carry them away</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2CH 6:37" />Yet <char style="add">if</char> they bethink themselves in the land whither they are carried captive, and turn and pray unto thee in the land of their captivity, saying, We have sinned, we have done amiss, and have dealt wickedly;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.37 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">bethink…: Heb. bring back to their heart</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="2CH 6:38" />If they return to thee with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their captivity, whither they have carried them captives, and pray toward their land, which thou gavest unto their fathers, and <char style="add">toward</char> the city which thou hast chosen, and toward the house which I have built for thy name: <verse eid="2CH 6:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="2CH 6:39" />Then hear thou from the heavens, <char style="add">even</char> from thy dwelling place, their prayer and their supplications, and maintain their cause, and forgive thy people which have sinned against thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.39 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cause: or, right</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="2CH 6:40" />Now, my God, let, I beseech thee, thine eyes be open, and <char style="add">let</char> thine ears <char style="add">be</char> attent unto the prayer <char style="add">that is made</char> in this place.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.40 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">unto…: Heb. to the prayer of this place</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 6:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="2CH 6:41" />Now therefore arise, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God, into thy resting place, thou, and the ark of thy strength: let thy priests, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God, be clothed with salvation, and let thy saints rejoice in goodness. <verse eid="2CH 6:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="2CH 6:42" />O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God, turn not away the face of thine anointed: remember the mercies of David thy servant.<verse eid="2CH 6:42" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 6" />
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="2CH 7" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 7:1" />Now when Solomon had made an end of praying, the fire came down from heaven, and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices; and the glory of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> filled the house. <verse eid="2CH 7:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 7:2" />And the priests could not enter into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, because the glory of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had filled the <char style="nd">LORD’s</char> house. <verse eid="2CH 7:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 7:3" />And when all the children of Israel saw how the fire came down, and the glory of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> upon the house, they bowed themselves with their faces to the ground upon the pavement, and worshipped, and praised the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, <char style="add">saying</char>, For <char style="add">he is</char> good; for his mercy <char style="add">endureth</char> for ever.<verse eid="2CH 7:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 7:4" />¶ Then the king and all the people offered sacrifices before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 7:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 7:5" />And king Solomon offered a sacrifice of twenty and two thousand oxen, and an hundred and twenty thousand sheep: so the king and all the people dedicated the house of God. <verse eid="2CH 7:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 7:6" />And the priests waited on their offices: the Levites also with instruments of musick of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, which David the king had made to praise the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, because his mercy <char style="add">endureth</char> for ever, when David praised by their ministry; and the priests sounded trumpets before them, and all Israel stood.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by their…: Heb. by their hand</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 7:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 7:7" />Moreover Solomon hallowed the middle of the court that <char style="add">was</char> before the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: for there he offered burnt offerings, and the fat of the peace offerings, because the brasen altar which Solomon had made was not able to receive the burnt offerings, and the meat offerings, and the fat.<verse eid="2CH 7:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 7:8" />¶ Also at the same time Solomon kept the feast seven days, and all Israel with him, a very great congregation, from the entering in of Hamath unto the river of Egypt. <verse eid="2CH 7:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 7:9" />And in the eighth day they made a solemn assembly: for they kept the dedication of the altar seven days, and the feast seven days.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a solemn…: Heb. a restraint</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 7:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 7:10" />And on the three and twentieth day of the seventh month he sent the people away into their tents, glad and merry in heart for the goodness that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had shewed unto David, and to Solomon, and to Israel his people. <verse eid="2CH 7:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 7:11" />Thus Solomon finished the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and the king’s house: and all that came into Solomon’s heart to make in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and in his own house, he prosperously effected.<verse eid="2CH 7:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 7:12" />¶ And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> appeared to Solomon by night, and said unto him, I have heard thy prayer, and have chosen this place to myself for an house of sacrifice. <verse eid="2CH 7:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 7:13" />If I shut up heaven that there be no rain, or if I command the locusts to devour the land, or if I send pestilence among my people; <verse eid="2CH 7:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 7:14" />If my people, which are called by my name, shall humble themselves, and pray, and seek my face, and turn from their wicked ways; then will I hear from heaven, and will forgive their sin, and will heal their land.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">which…: Heb. upon whom my name is called</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 7:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 7:15" />Now mine eyes shall be open, and mine ears attent unto the prayer <char style="add">that is made</char> in this place.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">unto…: Heb. to the prayer of this place</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 7:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 7:16" />For now have I chosen and sanctified this house, that my name may be there for ever: and mine eyes and mine heart shall be there perpetually. <verse eid="2CH 7:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 7:17" />And as for thee, if thou wilt walk before me, as David thy father walked, and do according to all that I have commanded thee, and shalt observe my statutes and my judgments; <verse eid="2CH 7:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 7:18" />Then will I stablish the throne of thy kingdom, according as I have covenanted with David thy father, saying, There shall not fail thee a man <char style="add">to be</char> ruler in Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">There…: Heb. There shall not be cut off to thee</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 7:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 7:19" />But if ye turn away, and forsake my statutes and my commandments, which I have set before you, and shall go and serve other gods, and worship them; <verse eid="2CH 7:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 7:20" />Then will I pluck them up by the roots out of my land which I have given them; and this house, which I have sanctified for my name, will I cast out of my sight, and will make it <char style="add">to be</char> a proverb and a byword among all nations. <verse eid="2CH 7:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 7:21" />And this house, which is high, shall be an astonishment to every one that passeth by it; so that he shall say, Why hath the <char style="nd">LORD</char> done thus unto this land, and unto this house? <verse eid="2CH 7:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 7:22" />And it shall be answered, Because they forsook the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers, which brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, and laid hold on other gods, and worshipped them, and served them: therefore hath he brought all this evil upon them.<verse eid="2CH 7:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 7" />
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="2CH 8" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 8:1" />And it came to pass at the end of twenty years, wherein Solomon had built the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and his own house, <verse eid="2CH 8:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 8:2" />That the cities which Huram had restored to Solomon, Solomon built them, and caused the children of Israel to dwell there. <verse eid="2CH 8:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 8:3" />And Solomon went to Hamath-zobah, and prevailed against it. <verse eid="2CH 8:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 8:4" />And he built Tadmor in the wilderness, and all the store cities, which he built in Hamath. <verse eid="2CH 8:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 8:5" />Also he built Beth-horon the upper, and Beth-horon the nether, fenced cities, with walls, gates, and bars; <verse eid="2CH 8:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 8:6" />And Baalath, and all the store cities that Solomon had, and all the chariot cities, and the cities of the horsemen, and all that Solomon desired to build in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and throughout all the land of his dominion.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">all that…: Heb. all the desire of Solomon which he desired to build</char></note><verse eid="2CH 8:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 8:7" />¶ <char style="add">As for</char> all the people <char style="add">that were</char> left of the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, which <char style="add">were</char> not of Israel, <verse eid="2CH 8:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 8:8" /><char style="add">But</char> of their children, who were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel consumed not, them did Solomon make to pay tribute until this day. <verse eid="2CH 8:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 8:9" />But of the children of Israel did Solomon make no servants for his work; but they <char style="add">were</char> men of war, and chief of his captains, and captains of his chariots and horsemen. <verse eid="2CH 8:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 8:10" />And these <char style="add">were</char> the chief of king Solomon’s officers, <char style="add">even</char> two hundred and fifty, that bare rule over the people.<verse eid="2CH 8:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 8:11" />¶ And Solomon brought up the daughter of Pharaoh out of the city of David unto the house that he had built for her: for he said, My wife shall not dwell in the house of David king of Israel, because <char style="add">the places are</char> holy, whereunto the ark of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath come.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">holy: Heb. holiness</char></note><verse eid="2CH 8:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 8:12" />¶ Then Solomon offered burnt offerings unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> on the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, which he had built before the porch, <verse eid="2CH 8:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 8:13" />Even after a certain rate every day, offering according to the commandment of Moses, on the sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the solemn feasts, three times in the year, <char style="add">even</char> in the feast of unleavened bread, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of tabernacles.<verse eid="2CH 8:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 8:14" />¶ And he appointed, according to the order of David his father, the courses of the priests to their service, and the Levites to their charges, to praise and minister before the priests, as the duty of every day required: the porters also by their courses at every gate: for so had David the man of God commanded.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">so had David…: Heb. so was the commandment of David the man of God</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 8:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 8:15" />And they departed not from the commandment of the king unto the priests and Levites concerning any matter, or concerning the treasures. <verse eid="2CH 8:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 8:16" />Now all the work of Solomon was prepared unto the day of the foundation of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and until it was finished. <char style="add">So</char> the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was perfected.<verse eid="2CH 8:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 8:17" />¶ Then went Solomon to Ezion-geber, and to Eloth, at the sea side in the land of Edom.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Eloth: also called, Elath</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 8:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 8:18" />And Huram sent him by the hands of his servants ships, and servants that had knowledge of the sea; and they went with the servants of Solomon to Ophir, and took thence four hundred and fifty talents of gold, and brought <char style="add">them</char> to king Solomon.<verse eid="2CH 8:18" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 8" />
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="2CH 9" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 9:1" />And when the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, she came to prove Solomon with hard questions at Jerusalem, with a very great company, and camels that bare spices, and gold in abundance, and precious stones: and when she was come to Solomon, she communed with him of all that was in her heart. <verse eid="2CH 9:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 9:2" />And Solomon told her all her questions: and there was nothing hid from Solomon which he told her not. <verse eid="2CH 9:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 9:3" />And when the queen of Sheba had seen the wisdom of Solomon, and the house that he had built, <verse eid="2CH 9:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 9:4" />And the meat of his table, and the sitting of his servants, and the attendance of his ministers, and their apparel; his cupbearers also, and their apparel; and his ascent by which he went up into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; there was no more spirit in her.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cupbearers: or, butlers</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 9:5" />And she said to the king, <char style="add">It was</char> a true report which I heard in mine own land of thine acts, and of thy wisdom:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">report: Heb. word</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">acts: or, sayings</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 9:6" />Howbeit I believed not their words, until I came, and mine eyes had seen <char style="add">it:</char> and, behold, the one half of the greatness of thy wisdom was not told me: <char style="add">for</char> thou exceedest the fame that I heard. <verse eid="2CH 9:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 9:7" />Happy <char style="add">are</char> thy men, and happy <char style="add">are</char> these thy servants, which stand continually before thee, and hear thy wisdom. <verse eid="2CH 9:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 9:8" />Blessed be the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, which delighted in thee to set thee on his throne, <char style="add">to be</char> king for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: because thy God loved Israel, to establish them for ever, therefore made he thee king over them, to do judgment and justice. <verse eid="2CH 9:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 9:9" />And she gave the king an hundred and twenty talents of gold, and of spices great abundance, and precious stones: neither was there any such spice as the queen of Sheba gave king Solomon. <verse eid="2CH 9:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 9:10" />And the servants also of Huram, and the servants of Solomon, which brought gold from Ophir, brought algum trees and precious stones.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">algum…: also called, almug trees</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 9:11" />And the king made <char style="add">of</char> the algum trees terraces to the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and to the king’s palace, and harps and psalteries for singers: and there were none such seen before in the land of Judah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">terraces: or, stairs: Heb. highways</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 9:12" />And king Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all her desire, whatsoever she asked, beside <char style="add">that</char> which she had brought unto the king. So she turned, and went away to her own land, she and her servants.<verse eid="2CH 9:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 9:13" />¶ Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was six hundred and threescore and six talents of gold; <verse eid="2CH 9:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 9:14" />Beside <char style="add">that which</char> chapmen and merchants brought. And all the kings of Arabia and governors of the country brought gold and silver to Solomon.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">governors: or, captains</char></note><verse eid="2CH 9:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 9:15" />¶ And king Solomon made two hundred targets <char style="add">of</char> beaten gold: six hundred <char style="add">shekels</char> of beaten gold went to one target. <verse eid="2CH 9:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 9:16" />And three hundred shields <char style="add">made he of</char> beaten gold: three hundred <char style="add">shekels</char> of gold went to one shield. And the king put them in the house of the forest of Lebanon. <verse eid="2CH 9:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 9:17" />Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with pure gold. <verse eid="2CH 9:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 9:18" />And <char style="add">there were</char> six steps to the throne, with a footstool of gold, <char style="add">which were</char> fastened to the throne, and stays on each side of the sitting place, and two lions standing by the stays:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">stays: Heb. hands</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 9:19" />And twelve lions stood there on the one side and on the other upon the six steps. There was not the like made in any kingdom.<verse eid="2CH 9:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 9:20" />¶ And all the drinking vessels of king Solomon <char style="add">were of</char> gold, and all the vessels of the house of the forest of Lebanon <char style="add">were of</char> pure gold: none <char style="add">were of</char> silver; it was <char style="add">not</char> any thing accounted of in the days of Solomon.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">pure: Heb. shut up</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">none were of silver: or, there was no silver in them</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 9:21" />For the king’s ships went to Tarshish with the servants of Huram: every three years once came the ships of Tarshish bringing gold, and silver, ivory, and apes, and peacocks.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">ivory: or, elephants’ teeth</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 9:22" />And king Solomon passed all the kings of the earth in riches and wisdom.<verse eid="2CH 9:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 9:23" />¶ And all the kings of the earth sought the presence of Solomon, to hear his wisdom, that God had put in his heart. <verse eid="2CH 9:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 9:24" />And they brought every man his present, vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and raiment, harness, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate year by year.<verse eid="2CH 9:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 9:25" />¶ And Solomon had four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen; whom he bestowed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 9:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 9:26" />¶ And he reigned over all the kings from the river even unto the land of the Philistines, and to the border of Egypt.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">river: that is, Euphrates</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 9:27" />And the king made silver in Jerusalem as stones, and cedar trees made he as the sycomore trees that <char style="add">are</char> in the low plains in abundance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">made silver: Heb. gave silver</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 9:28" />And they brought unto Solomon horses out of Egypt, and out of all lands.<verse eid="2CH 9:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 9:29" />¶ Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, first and last, <char style="add">are</char> they not written in the book of Nathan the prophet, and in the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the seer against Jeroboam the son of Nebat?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">book: Heb. words</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 9:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 9:30" />And Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years. <verse eid="2CH 9:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 9:31" />And Solomon slept with his fathers, and he was buried in the city of David his father: and Rehoboam his son reigned in his stead.<verse eid="2CH 9:31" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 9" />
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="2CH 10" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 10:1" />And Rehoboam went to Shechem: for to Shechem were all Israel come to make him king. <verse eid="2CH 10:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 10:2" />And it came to pass, when Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who <char style="add">was</char> in Egypt, whither he had fled from the presence of Solomon the king, heard <char style="add">it</char>, that Jeroboam returned out of Egypt. <verse eid="2CH 10:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 10:3" />And they sent and called him. So Jeroboam and all Israel came and spake to Rehoboam, saying, <verse eid="2CH 10:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 10:4" />Thy father made our yoke grievous: now therefore ease thou somewhat the grievous servitude of thy father, and his heavy yoke that he put upon us, and we will serve thee. <verse eid="2CH 10:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 10:5" />And he said unto them, Come again unto me after three days. And the people departed.<verse eid="2CH 10:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 10:6" />¶ And king Rehoboam took counsel with the old men that had stood before Solomon his father while he yet lived, saying, What counsel give ye <char style="add">me</char> to return answer to this people? <verse eid="2CH 10:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 10:7" />And they spake unto him, saying, If thou be kind to this people, and please them, and speak good words to them, they will be thy servants for ever. <verse eid="2CH 10:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 10:8" />But he forsook the counsel which the old men gave him, and took counsel with the young men that were brought up with him, that stood before him. <verse eid="2CH 10:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 10:9" />And he said unto them, What advice give ye that we may return answer to this people, which have spoken to me, saying, Ease somewhat the yoke that thy father did put upon us? <verse eid="2CH 10:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 10:10" />And the young men that were brought up with him spake unto him, saying, Thus shalt thou answer the people that spake unto thee, saying, Thy father made our yoke heavy, but make thou <char style="add">it</char> somewhat lighter for us; thus shalt thou say unto them, My little <char style="add">finger</char> shall be thicker than my father’s loins. <verse eid="2CH 10:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 10:11" />For whereas my father put a heavy yoke upon you, I will put more to your yoke: my father chastised you with whips, but I <char style="add">will chastise you</char> with scorpions.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my father put: Heb. my father laded</char></note><verse eid="2CH 10:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 10:12" />So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam on the third day, as the king bade, saying, Come again to me on the third day. <verse eid="2CH 10:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 10:13" />And the king answered them roughly; and king Rehoboam forsook the counsel of the old men, <verse eid="2CH 10:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 10:14" />And answered them after the advice of the young men, saying, My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add thereto: my father chastised you with whips, but I <char style="add">will chastise you</char> with scorpions. <verse eid="2CH 10:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 10:15" />So the king hearkened not unto the people: for the cause was of God, that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> might perform his word, which he spake by the hand of Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat.<verse eid="2CH 10:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 10:16" />¶ And when all Israel <char style="add">saw </char> that the king would not hearken unto them, the people answered the king, saying, What portion have we in David? and <char style="add">we have</char> none inheritance in the son of Jesse: every man to your tents, O Israel: <char style="add">and</char> now, David, see to thine own house. So all Israel went to their tents. <verse eid="2CH 10:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 10:17" />But <char style="add">as for</char> the children of Israel that dwelt in the cities of Judah, Rehoboam reigned over them. <verse eid="2CH 10:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 10:18" />Then king Rehoboam sent Hadoram that <char style="add">was</char> over the tribute; and the children of Israel stoned him with stones, that he died. But king Rehoboam made speed to get him up to <char style="add">his</char> chariot, to flee to Jerusalem.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">made speed: Heb. strengthened himself</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 10:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 10:19" />And Israel rebelled against the house of David unto this day.<verse eid="2CH 10:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 10" />
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="2CH 11" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 11:1" />And when Rehoboam was come to Jerusalem, he gathered of the house of Judah and Benjamin an hundred and fourscore thousand chosen <char style="add">men</char>, which were warriors, to fight against Israel, that he might bring the kingdom again to Rehoboam. <verse eid="2CH 11:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 11:2" />But the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> came to Shemaiah the man of God, saying, <verse eid="2CH 11:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 11:3" />Speak unto Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, saying, <verse eid="2CH 11:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 11:4" />Thus saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, Ye shall not go up, nor fight against your brethren: return every man to his house: for this thing is done of me. And they obeyed the words of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and returned from going against Jeroboam.<verse eid="2CH 11:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 11:5" />¶ And Rehoboam dwelt in Jerusalem, and built cities for defence in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 11:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 11:6" />He built even Beth-lehem, and Etam, and Tekoa, <verse eid="2CH 11:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 11:7" />And Beth-zur, and Shoco, and Adullam, <verse eid="2CH 11:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 11:8" />And Gath, and Mareshah, and Ziph, <verse eid="2CH 11:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 11:9" />And Adoraim, and Lachish, and Azekah, <verse eid="2CH 11:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 11:10" />And Zorah, and Aijalon, and Hebron, which <char style="add">are</char> in Judah and in Benjamin fenced cities. <verse eid="2CH 11:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 11:11" />And he fortified the strong holds, and put captains in them, and store of victual, and of oil and wine. <verse eid="2CH 11:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 11:12" />And in every several city <char style="add">he put</char> shields and spears, and made them exceeding strong, having Judah and Benjamin on his side.<verse eid="2CH 11:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 11:13" />¶ And the priests and the Levites that <char style="add">were</char> in all Israel resorted to him out of all their coasts.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">resorted…: Heb. presented themselves to him</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 11:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 11:14" />For the Levites left their suburbs and their possession, and came to Judah and Jerusalem: for Jeroboam and his sons had cast them off from executing the priest’s office unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: <verse eid="2CH 11:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 11:15" />And he ordained him priests for the high places, and for the devils, and for the calves which he had made. <verse eid="2CH 11:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 11:16" />And after them out of all the tribes of Israel such as set their hearts to seek the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel came to Jerusalem, to sacrifice unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers. <verse eid="2CH 11:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 11:17" />So they strengthened the kingdom of Judah, and made Rehoboam the son of Solomon strong, three years: for three years they walked in the way of David and Solomon.<verse eid="2CH 11:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 11:18" />¶ And Rehoboam took him Mahalath the daughter of Jerimoth the son of David to wife, <char style="add">and</char> Abihail the daughter of Eliab the son of Jesse; <verse eid="2CH 11:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 11:19" />Which bare him children; Jeush, and Shamariah, and Zaham. <verse eid="2CH 11:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 11:20" />And after her he took Maachah the daughter of Absalom; which bare him Abijah, and Attai, and Ziza, and Shelomith.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Maachah: she is also called Michaiah the daughter of Uriel</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 11:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 11:21" />And Rehoboam loved Maachah the daughter of Absalom above all his wives and his concubines: (for he took eighteen wives, and threescore concubines; and begat twenty and eight sons, and threescore daughters.) <verse eid="2CH 11:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 11:22" />And Rehoboam made Abijah the son of Maachah the chief, <char style="add">to be</char> ruler among his brethren: for <char style="add">he thought</char> to make him king. <verse eid="2CH 11:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 11:23" />And he dealt wisely, and dispersed of all his children throughout all the countries of Judah and Benjamin, unto every fenced city: and he gave them victual in abundance. And he desired many wives.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">many wives: Heb. a multitude of wives</char></note><verse eid="2CH 11:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 11" />
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="2CH 12" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 12:1" />And it came to pass, when Rehoboam had established the kingdom, and had strengthened himself, he forsook the law of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and all Israel with him. <verse eid="2CH 12:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 12:2" />And it came to pass, <char style="add">that</char> in the fifth year of king Rehoboam Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, because they had transgressed against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, <verse eid="2CH 12:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 12:3" />With twelve hundred chariots, and threescore thousand horsemen: and the people <char style="add">were</char> without number that came with him out of Egypt; the Lubims, the Sukkiims, and the Ethiopians. <verse eid="2CH 12:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 12:4" />And he took the fenced cities which <char style="add">pertained</char> to Judah, and came to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 12:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 12:5" />¶ Then came Shemaiah the prophet to Rehoboam, and <char style="add">to</char> the princes of Judah, that were gathered together to Jerusalem because of Shishak, and said unto them, Thus saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, Ye have forsaken me, and therefore have I also left you in the hand of Shishak. <verse eid="2CH 12:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 12:6" />Whereupon the princes of Israel and the king humbled themselves; and they said, The <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">is</char> righteous. <verse eid="2CH 12:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 12:7" />And when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> saw that they humbled themselves, the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> came to Shemaiah, saying, They have humbled themselves; <char style="add">therefore</char> I will not destroy them, but I will grant them some deliverance; and my wrath shall not be poured out upon Jerusalem by the hand of Shishak.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">some: or, a little while</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 12:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 12:8" />Nevertheless they shall be his servants; that they may know my service, and the service of the kingdoms of the countries. <verse eid="2CH 12:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 12:9" />So Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, and took away the treasures of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and the treasures of the king’s house; he took all: he carried away also the shields of gold which Solomon had made. <verse eid="2CH 12:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 12:10" />Instead of which king Rehoboam made shields of brass, and committed <char style="add">them</char> to the hands of the chief of the guard, that kept the entrance of the king’s house. <verse eid="2CH 12:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 12:11" />And when the king entered into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, the guard came and fetched them, and brought them again into the guard chamber. <verse eid="2CH 12:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 12:12" />And when he humbled himself, the wrath of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> turned from him, that he would not destroy <char style="add">him</char> altogether: and also in Judah things went well.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and also…: or, and yet in Judah there were good things</char></note><verse eid="2CH 12:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 12:13" />¶ So king Rehoboam strengthened himself in Jerusalem, and reigned: for Rehoboam <char style="add">was</char> one and forty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, to put his name there. And his mother’s name <char style="add">was</char> Naamah an Ammonitess. <verse eid="2CH 12:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 12:14" />And he did evil, because he prepared not his heart to seek the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">prepared: or, fixed</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 12:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 12:15" />Now the acts of Rehoboam, first and last, <char style="add">are</char> they not written in the book of Shemaiah the prophet, and of Iddo the seer concerning genealogies? And <char style="add">there were</char> wars between Rehoboam and Jeroboam continually.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">book: Heb. words</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 12:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 12:16" />And Rehoboam slept with his fathers, and was buried in the city of David: and Abijah his son reigned in his stead.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Abijah: also called, Abijam</char></note><verse eid="2CH 12:16" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 12" />
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="2CH 13" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 13:1" />Now in the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam began Abijah to reign over Judah. <verse eid="2CH 13:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 13:2" />He reigned three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also <char style="add">was</char> Michaiah the daughter of Uriel of Gibeah. And there was war between Abijah and Jeroboam. <verse eid="2CH 13:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 13:3" />And Abijah set the battle in array with an army of valiant men of war, <char style="add">even</char> four hundred thousand chosen men: Jeroboam also set the battle in array against him with eight hundred thousand chosen men, <char style="add">being</char> mighty men of valour.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Abijah set: Heb. Abijah bound together</char></note><verse eid="2CH 13:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 13:4" />¶ And Abijah stood up upon mount Zemaraim, which <char style="add">is</char> in mount Ephraim, and said, Hear me, thou Jeroboam, and all Israel; <verse eid="2CH 13:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 13:5" />Ought ye not to know that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel gave the kingdom over Israel to David for ever, <char style="add">even</char> to him and to his sons by a covenant of salt? <verse eid="2CH 13:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 13:6" />Yet Jeroboam the son of Nebat, the servant of Solomon the son of David, is risen up, and hath rebelled against his lord. <verse eid="2CH 13:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 13:7" />And there are gathered unto him vain men, the children of Belial, and have strengthened themselves against Rehoboam the son of Solomon, when Rehoboam was young and tenderhearted, and could not withstand them. <verse eid="2CH 13:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 13:8" />And now ye think to withstand the kingdom of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> in the hand of the sons of David; and ye <char style="add">be</char> a great multitude, and <char style="add">there are</char> with you golden calves, which Jeroboam made you for gods. <verse eid="2CH 13:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 13:9" />Have ye not cast out the priests of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites, and have made you priests after the manner of the nations of <char style="add">other</char> lands? so that whosoever cometh to consecrate himself with a young bullock and seven rams, <char style="add">the same</char> may be a priest of <char style="add">them that are</char> no gods.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to consecrate…: Heb. to fill his hand</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 13:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 13:10" />But as for us, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">is</char> our God, and we have not forsaken him; and the priests, which minister unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, <char style="add">are</char> the sons of Aaron, and the Levites <char style="add">wait</char> upon <char style="add">their</char> business: <verse eid="2CH 13:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 13:11" />And they burn unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> every morning and every evening burnt sacrifices and sweet incense: the shewbread also <char style="add">set they in order</char> upon the pure table; and the candlestick of gold with the lamps thereof, to burn every evening: for we keep the charge of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God; but ye have forsaken him. <verse eid="2CH 13:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 13:12" />And, behold, God himself <char style="add">is</char> with us for <char style="add">our</char> captain, and his priests with sounding trumpets to cry alarm against you. O children of Israel, fight ye not against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of your fathers; for ye shall not prosper.<verse eid="2CH 13:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 13:13" />¶ But Jeroboam caused an ambushment to come about behind them: so they were before Judah, and the ambushment <char style="add">was</char> behind them. <verse eid="2CH 13:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 13:14" />And when Judah looked back, behold, the battle <char style="add">was</char> before and behind: and they cried unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and the priests sounded with the trumpets. <verse eid="2CH 13:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 13:15" />Then the men of Judah gave a shout: and as the men of Judah shouted, it came to pass, that God smote Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah. <verse eid="2CH 13:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 13:16" />And the children of Israel fled before Judah: and God delivered them into their hand. <verse eid="2CH 13:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 13:17" />And Abijah and his people slew them with a great slaughter: so there fell down slain of Israel five hundred thousand chosen men. <verse eid="2CH 13:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 13:18" />Thus the children of Israel were brought under at that time, and the children of Judah prevailed, because they relied upon the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers. <verse eid="2CH 13:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 13:19" />And Abijah pursued after Jeroboam, and took cities from him, Beth-el with the towns thereof, and Jeshanah with the towns thereof, and Ephrain with the towns thereof. <verse eid="2CH 13:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 13:20" />Neither did Jeroboam recover strength again in the days of Abijah: and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> struck him, and he died.<verse eid="2CH 13:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 13:21" />¶ But Abijah waxed mighty, and married fourteen wives, and begat twenty and two sons, and sixteen daughters. <verse eid="2CH 13:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 13:22" />And the rest of the acts of Abijah, and his ways, and his sayings, <char style="add">are</char> written in the story of the prophet Iddo.<verse eid="2CH 13:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 13" />
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="2CH 14" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 14:1" />So Abijah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David: and Asa his son reigned in his stead. In his days the land was quiet ten years. <verse eid="2CH 14:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 14:2" />And Asa did <char style="add">that which was</char> good and right in the eyes of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God: <verse eid="2CH 14:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 14:3" />For he took away the altars of the strange <char style="add">gods</char>, and the high places, and brake down the images, and cut down the groves:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">images: Heb. statues</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 14:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 14:4" />And commanded Judah to seek the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers, and to do the law and the commandment. <verse eid="2CH 14:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 14:5" />Also he took away out of all the cities of Judah the high places and the images: and the kingdom was quiet before him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">images: Heb. sun images</char></note><verse eid="2CH 14:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 14:6" />¶ And he built fenced cities in Judah: for the land had rest, and he had no war in those years; because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had given him rest. <verse eid="2CH 14:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 14:7" />Therefore he said unto Judah, Let us build these cities, and make about <char style="add">them</char> walls, and towers, gates, and bars, <char style="add">while</char> the land <char style="add">is</char> yet before us; because we have sought the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God, we have sought <char style="add">him</char>, and he hath given us rest on every side. So they built and prospered. <verse eid="2CH 14:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 14:8" />And Asa had an army <char style="add">of men</char> that bare targets and spears, out of Judah three hundred thousand; and out of Benjamin, that bare shields and drew bows, two hundred and fourscore thousand: all these <char style="add">were</char> mighty men of valour.<verse eid="2CH 14:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 14:9" />¶ And there came out against them Zerah the Ethiopian with an host of a thousand thousand, and three hundred chariots; and came unto Mareshah. <verse eid="2CH 14:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 14:10" />Then Asa went out against him, and they set the battle in array in the valley of Zephathah at Mareshah. <verse eid="2CH 14:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 14:11" />And Asa cried unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God, and said, <char style="nd">LORD</char>, <char style="add">it is</char> nothing with thee to help, whether with many, or with them that have no power: help us, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God; for we rest on thee, and in thy name we go against this multitude. O <char style="nd">LORD</char>, thou <char style="add">art</char> our God; let not man prevail against thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">man: or, mortal man</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 14:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 14:12" />So the <char style="nd">LORD</char> smote the Ethiopians before Asa, and before Judah; and the Ethiopians fled. <verse eid="2CH 14:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 14:13" />And Asa and the people that <char style="add">were</char> with him pursued them unto Gerar: and the Ethiopians were overthrown, that they could not recover themselves; for they were destroyed before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and before his host; and they carried away very much spoil.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">destroyed: Heb. broken</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 14:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 14:14" />And they smote all the cities round about Gerar; for the fear of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> came upon them: and they spoiled all the cities; for there was exceeding much spoil in them. <verse eid="2CH 14:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 14:15" />They smote also the tents of cattle, and carried away sheep and camels in abundance, and returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 14:15" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 14" />
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="2CH 15" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 15:1" />And the Spirit of God came upon Azariah the son of Oded: <verse eid="2CH 15:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 15:2" />And he went out to meet Asa, and said unto him, Hear ye me, Asa, and all Judah and Benjamin; The <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">is</char> with you, while ye be with him; and if ye seek him, he will be found of you; but if ye forsake him, he will forsake you.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to meet…: Heb. before Asa</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 15:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 15:3" />Now for a long season Israel <char style="add">hath been</char> without the true God, and without a teaching priest, and without law. <verse eid="2CH 15:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 15:4" />But when they in their trouble did turn unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, and sought him, he was found of them. <verse eid="2CH 15:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 15:5" />And in those times <char style="add">there was</char> no peace to him that went out, nor to him that came in, but great vexations <char style="add">were</char> upon all the inhabitants of the countries. <verse eid="2CH 15:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 15:6" />And nation was destroyed of nation, and city of city: for God did vex them with all adversity.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">destroyed: Heb. beaten in pieces</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 15:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 15:7" />Be ye strong therefore, and let not your hands be weak: for your work shall be rewarded.<verse eid="2CH 15:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 15:8" />And when Asa heard these words, and the prophecy of Oded the prophet, he took courage, and put away the abominable idols out of all the land of Judah and Benjamin, and out of the cities which he had taken from mount Ephraim, and renewed the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, that <char style="add">was</char> before the porch of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">abominable…: Heb. abominations</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 15:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 15:9" />And he gathered all Judah and Benjamin, and the strangers with them out of Ephraim and Manasseh, and out of Simeon: for they fell to him out of Israel in abundance, when they saw that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God <char style="add">was</char> with him. <verse eid="2CH 15:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 15:10" />So they gathered themselves together at Jerusalem in the third month, in the fifteenth year of the reign of Asa. <verse eid="2CH 15:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 15:11" />And they offered unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> the same time, of the spoil <char style="add">which</char> they had brought, seven hundred oxen and seven thousand sheep.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the same…: Heb. in that day</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 15:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 15:12" />And they entered into a covenant to seek the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers with all their heart and with all their soul; <verse eid="2CH 15:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 15:13" />That whosoever would not seek the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel should be put to death, whether small or great, whether man or woman. <verse eid="2CH 15:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 15:14" />And they sware unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> with a loud voice, and with shouting, and with trumpets, and with cornets. <verse eid="2CH 15:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 15:15" />And all Judah rejoiced at the oath: for they had sworn with all their heart, and sought him with their whole desire; and he was found of them: and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> gave them rest round about.<verse eid="2CH 15:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 15:16" />¶ And also <char style="add">concerning</char> Maachah the mother of Asa the king, he removed her from <char style="add">being</char> queen, because she had made an idol in a grove: and Asa cut down her idol, and stamped <char style="add">it</char>, and burnt <char style="add">it</char> at the brook Kidron.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mother: that is, grandmother</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">idol: Heb. horror</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 15:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 15:17" />But the high places were not taken away out of Israel: nevertheless the heart of Asa was perfect all his days.<verse eid="2CH 15:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 15:18" />¶ And he brought into the house of God the things that his father had dedicated, and that he himself had dedicated, silver, and gold, and vessels. <verse eid="2CH 15:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 15:19" />And there was no <char style="add">more</char> war unto the five and thirtieth year of the reign of Asa.<verse eid="2CH 15:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 15" />
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="2CH 16" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 16:1" />In the six and thirtieth year of the reign of Asa Baasha king of Israel came up against Judah, and built Ramah, to the intent that he might let none go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 16:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 16:2" />Then Asa brought out silver and gold out of the treasures of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> and of the king’s house, and sent to Ben-hadad king of Syria, that dwelt at Damascus, saying,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Damascus: Heb. Darmesek</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 16:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 16:3" /><char style="add">There is</char> a league between me and thee, as <char style="add">there was</char> between my father and thy father: behold, I have sent thee silver and gold; go, break thy league with Baasha king of Israel, that he may depart from me. <verse eid="2CH 16:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 16:4" />And Ben-hadad hearkened unto king Asa, and sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel; and they smote Ijon, and Dan, and Abel-maim, and all the store cities of Naphtali.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">his: Heb. which were his</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 16:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 16:5" />And it came to pass, when Baasha heard <char style="add">it</char>, that he left off building of Ramah, and let his work cease. <verse eid="2CH 16:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 16:6" />Then Asa the king took all Judah; and they carried away the stones of Ramah, and the timber thereof, wherewith Baasha was building; and he built therewith Geba and Mizpah.<verse eid="2CH 16:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 16:7" />¶ And at that time Hanani the seer came to Asa king of Judah, and said unto him, Because thou hast relied on the king of Syria, and not relied on the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, therefore is the host of the king of Syria escaped out of thine hand. <verse eid="2CH 16:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 16:8" />Were not the Ethiopians and the Lubims a huge host, with very many chariots and horsemen? yet, because thou didst rely on the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, he delivered them into thine hand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a huge: Heb. in abundance</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 16:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 16:9" />For the eyes of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> run to and fro throughout the whole earth, to shew himself strong in the behalf of <char style="add">them</char> whose heart <char style="add">is</char> perfect toward him. Herein thou hast done foolishly: therefore from henceforth thou shalt have wars.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to shew…: or, strongly to hold with them, etc</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 16:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 16:10" />Then Asa was wroth with the seer, and put him in a prison house; for <char style="add">he was</char> in a rage with him because of this <char style="add">thing</char>. And Asa oppressed <char style="add">some</char> of the people the same time.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">oppressed: Heb. crushed</char></note><verse eid="2CH 16:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 16:11" />¶ And, behold, the acts of Asa, first and last, lo, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse eid="2CH 16:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 16:12" />And Asa in the thirty and ninth year of his reign was diseased in his feet, until his disease <char style="add">was</char> exceeding <char style="add">great:</char> yet in his disease he sought not to the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, but to the physicians.<verse eid="2CH 16:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 16:13" />¶ And Asa slept with his fathers, and died in the one and fortieth year of his reign. <verse eid="2CH 16:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 16:14" />And they buried him in his own sepulchres, which he had made for himself in the city of David, and laid him in the bed which was filled with sweet odours and divers kinds <char style="add">of spices</char> prepared by the apothecaries’ art: and they made a very great burning for him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">had made: Heb. had digged</char></note><verse eid="2CH 16:14" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 16" />
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="2CH 17" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 17:1" />And Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his stead, and strengthened himself against Israel. <verse eid="2CH 17:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 17:2" />And he placed forces in all the fenced cities of Judah, and set garrisons in the land of Judah, and in the cities of Ephraim, which Asa his father had taken. <verse eid="2CH 17:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 17:3" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was with Jehoshaphat, because he walked in the first ways of his father David, and sought not unto Baalim;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of…: or, of his father, and of David</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 17:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 17:4" />But sought to the <char style="add"><char style="nd">Lord</char></char> God of his father, and walked in his commandments, and not after the doings of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 17:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 17:5" />Therefore the <char style="nd">LORD</char> stablished the kingdom in his hand; and all Judah brought to Jehoshaphat presents; and he had riches and honour in abundance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">brought: Heb. gave</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 17:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 17:6" />And his heart was lifted up in the ways of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: moreover he took away the high places and groves out of Judah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was…: that is, was encouraged</char></note><verse eid="2CH 17:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 17:7" />¶ Also in the third year of his reign he sent to his princes, <char style="add">even</char> to Ben-hail, and to Obadiah, and to Zechariah, and to Nethaneel, and to Michaiah, to teach in the cities of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 17:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 17:8" />And with them <char style="add">he sent</char> Levites, <char style="add">even</char> Shemaiah, and Nethaniah, and Zebadiah, and Asahel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehonathan, and Adonijah, and Tobijah, and Tob-adonijah, Levites; and with them Elishama and Jehoram, priests. <verse eid="2CH 17:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 17:9" />And they taught in Judah, and <char style="add">had</char> the book of the law of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> with them, and went about throughout all the cities of Judah, and taught the people.<verse eid="2CH 17:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 17:10" />¶ And the fear of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> fell upon all the kingdoms of the lands that <char style="add">were</char> round about Judah, so that they made no war against Jehoshaphat.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fell: Heb. was</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 17:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 17:11" />Also <char style="add">some</char> of the Philistines brought Jehoshaphat presents, and tribute silver; and the Arabians brought him flocks, seven thousand and seven hundred rams, and seven thousand and seven hundred he goats.<verse eid="2CH 17:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 17:12" />¶ And Jehoshaphat waxed great exceedingly; and he built in Judah castles, and cities of store.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">castles: or, palaces</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 17:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 17:13" />And he had much business in the cities of Judah: and the men of war, mighty men of valour, <char style="add">were</char> in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 17:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 17:14" />And these <char style="add">are</char> the numbers of them according to the house of their fathers: Of Judah, the captains of thousands; Adnah the chief, and with him mighty men of valour three hundred thousand. <verse eid="2CH 17:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 17:15" />And next to him <char style="add">was</char> Jehohanan the captain, and with him two hundred and fourscore thousand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">next…: Heb. at his hand</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 17:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 17:16" />And next him <char style="add">was</char> Amasiah the son of Zichri, who willingly offered himself unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; and with him two hundred thousand mighty men of valour. <verse eid="2CH 17:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 17:17" />And of Benjamin; Eliada a mighty man of valour, and with him armed men with bow and shield two hundred thousand. <verse eid="2CH 17:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 17:18" />And next him <char style="add">was</char> Jehozabad, and with him an hundred and fourscore thousand ready prepared for the war. <verse eid="2CH 17:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 17:19" />These waited on the king, beside <char style="add">those</char> whom the king put in the fenced cities throughout all Judah.<verse eid="2CH 17:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 17" />
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="2CH 18" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 18:1" />Now Jehoshaphat had riches and honour in abundance, and joined affinity with Ahab. <verse eid="2CH 18:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 18:2" />And after <char style="add">certain</char> years he went down to Ahab to Samaria. And Ahab killed sheep and oxen for him in abundance, and for the people that <char style="add">he had</char> with him, and persuaded him to go up <char style="add">with him</char> to Ramoth-gilead.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">after…: Heb. at the end of years</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 18:3" />And Ahab king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat king of Judah, Wilt thou go with me to Ramoth-gilead? And he answered him, I <char style="add">am</char> as thou <char style="add">art</char>, and my people as thy people; and <char style="add">we will be</char> with thee in the war.<verse eid="2CH 18:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 18:4" />¶ And Jehoshaphat said unto the king of Israel, Enquire, I pray thee, at the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> to day. <verse eid="2CH 18:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 18:5" />Therefore the king of Israel gathered together of prophets four hundred men, and said unto them, Shall we go to Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I forbear? And they said, Go up; for God will deliver <char style="add">it</char> into the king’s hand. <verse eid="2CH 18:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 18:6" />But Jehoshaphat said, <char style="add">Is there</char> not here a prophet of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> besides, that we might enquire of him?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">besides: Heb. yet, or, more</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 18:7" />And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, <char style="add">There is</char> yet one man, by whom we may enquire of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: but I hate him; for he never prophesied good unto me, but always evil: the same <char style="add">is</char> Micaiah the son of Imla. And Jehoshaphat said, Let not the king say so. <verse eid="2CH 18:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 18:8" />And the king of Israel called for one <char style="add">of his</char> officers, and said, Fetch quickly Micaiah the son of Imla.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">officers: or, eunuchs</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Fetch…: Heb. Hasten</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 18:9" />And the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat king of Judah sat either of them on his throne, clothed in <char style="add">their</char> robes, and they sat in a void place at the entering in of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets prophesied before them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">void…: or, floor</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 18:10" />And Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah had made him horns of iron, and said, Thus saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, With these thou shalt push Syria until they be consumed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">they…: Heb. thou consume them</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 18:11" />And all the prophets prophesied so, saying, Go up to Ramoth-gilead, and prosper: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall deliver <char style="add">it</char> into the hand of the king. <verse eid="2CH 18:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 18:12" />And the messenger that went to call Micaiah spake to him, saying, Behold, the words of the prophets <char style="add">declare</char> good to the king with one assent; let thy word therefore, I pray thee, be like one of theirs, and speak thou good.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">with…: Heb. with one mouth</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 18:13" />And Micaiah said, <char style="add">As</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> liveth, even what my God saith, that will I speak. <verse eid="2CH 18:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 18:14" />And when he was come to the king, the king said unto him, Micaiah, shall we go to Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I forbear? And he said, Go ye up, and prosper, and they shall be delivered into your hand. <verse eid="2CH 18:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 18:15" />And the king said to him, How many times shall I adjure thee that thou say nothing but the truth to me in the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>? <verse eid="2CH 18:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 18:16" />Then he said, I did see all Israel scattered upon the mountains, as sheep that have no shepherd: and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said, These have no master; let them return <char style="add">therefore</char> every man to his house in peace. <verse eid="2CH 18:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 18:17" />And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, Did I not tell thee <char style="add">that</char> he would not prophesy good unto me, but evil?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">but evil: or, but for evil</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 18:18" />Again he said, Therefore hear the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; I saw the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sitting upon his throne, and all the host of heaven standing on his right hand and <char style="add">on</char> his left. <verse eid="2CH 18:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 18:19" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said, Who shall entice Ahab king of Israel, that he may go up and fall at Ramoth-gilead? And one spake saying after this manner, and another saying after that manner. <verse eid="2CH 18:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 18:20" />Then there came out a spirit, and stood before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and said, I will entice him. And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto him, Wherewith? <verse eid="2CH 18:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 18:21" />And he said, I will go out, and be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets. And <char style="add">the <char style="nd">Lord</char></char> said, Thou shalt entice <char style="add">him</char>, and thou shalt also prevail: go out, and do <char style="add">even</char> so. <verse eid="2CH 18:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 18:22" />Now therefore, behold, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath put a lying spirit in the mouth of these thy prophets, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath spoken evil against thee. <verse eid="2CH 18:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 18:23" />Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah came near, and smote Micaiah upon the cheek, and said, Which way went the Spirit of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> from me to speak unto thee? <verse eid="2CH 18:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 18:24" />And Micaiah said, Behold, thou shalt see on that day when thou shalt go into an inner chamber to hide thyself.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">into…: or, from chamber to chamber: Heb. a chamber in a chamber</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 18:25" />Then the king of Israel said, Take ye Micaiah, and carry him back to Amon the governor of the city, and to Joash the king’s son; <verse eid="2CH 18:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 18:26" />And say, Thus saith the king, Put this <char style="add">fellow</char> in the prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction, until I return in peace. <verse eid="2CH 18:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 18:27" />And Micaiah said, If thou certainly return in peace, <char style="add">then</char> hath not the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spoken by me. And he said, Hearken, all ye people.<verse eid="2CH 18:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 18:28" />So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth-gilead. <verse eid="2CH 18:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 18:29" />And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, I will disguise myself, and will go to the battle; but put thou on thy robes. So the king of Israel disguised himself; and they went to the battle. <verse eid="2CH 18:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 18:30" />Now the king of Syria had commanded the captains of the chariots that <char style="add">were</char> with him, saying, Fight ye not with small or great, save only with the king of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 18:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 18:31" />And it came to pass, when the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, that they said, It <char style="add">is</char> the king of Israel. Therefore they compassed about him to fight: but Jehoshaphat cried out, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> helped him; and God moved them <char style="add">to depart</char> from him. <verse eid="2CH 18:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 18:32" />For it came to pass, that, when the captains of the chariots perceived that it was not the king of Israel, they turned back again from pursuing him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from…: Heb. from after him</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 18:33" />And a <char style="add">certain</char> man drew a bow at a venture, and smote the king of Israel between the joints of the harness: therefore he said to his chariot man, Turn thine hand, that thou mayest carry me out of the host; for I am wounded.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">at a venture: Heb. in his simplicity</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">between…: Heb. between the joints and between the breastplate</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wounded: Heb. made sick</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 18:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 18:34" />And the battle increased that day: howbeit the king of Israel stayed <char style="add">himself</char> up in <char style="add">his</char> chariot against the Syrians until the even: and about the time of the sun going down he died.<verse eid="2CH 18:34" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 18" />
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="2CH 19" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 19:1" />And Jehoshaphat the king of Judah returned to his house in peace to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 19:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 19:2" />And Jehu the son of Hanani the seer went out to meet him, and said to king Jehoshaphat, Shouldest thou help the ungodly, and love them that hate the <char style="nd">LORD</char>? therefore <char style="add">is</char> wrath upon thee from before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 19:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 19:3" />Nevertheless there are good things found in thee, in that thou hast taken away the groves out of the land, and hast prepared thine heart to seek God. <verse eid="2CH 19:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 19:4" />And Jehoshaphat dwelt at Jerusalem: and he went out again through the people from Beer-sheba to mount Ephraim, and brought them back unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he went…: Heb. he returned and went out</char></note><verse eid="2CH 19:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 19:5" />¶ And he set judges in the land throughout all the fenced cities of Judah, city by city, <verse eid="2CH 19:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 19:6" />And said to the judges, Take heed what ye do: for ye judge not for man, but for the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, who <char style="add">is</char> with you in the judgment.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: Heb. in the matter of judgment</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 19:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 19:7" />Wherefore now let the fear of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> be upon you; take heed and do <char style="add">it:</char> for <char style="add">there is</char> no iniquity with the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God, nor respect of persons, nor taking of gifts.<verse eid="2CH 19:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 19:8" />¶ Moreover in Jerusalem did Jehoshaphat set of the Levites, and <char style="add">of</char> the priests, and of the chief of the fathers of Israel, for the judgment of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and for controversies, when they returned to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 19:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 19:9" />And he charged them, saying, Thus shall ye do in the fear of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, faithfully, and with a perfect heart. <verse eid="2CH 19:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 19:10" />And what cause soever shall come to you of your brethren that dwell in their cities, between blood and blood, between law and commandment, statutes and judgments, ye shall even warn them that they trespass not against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and <char style="add">so</char> wrath come upon you, and upon your brethren: this do, and ye shall not trespass. <verse eid="2CH 19:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 19:11" />And, behold, Amariah the chief priest <char style="add">is</char> over you in all matters of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; and Zebadiah the son of Ishmael, the ruler of the house of Judah, for all the king’s matters: also the Levites <char style="add">shall be</char> officers before you. Deal courageously, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall be with the good.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Deal…: Heb. Take courage and do</char></note><verse eid="2CH 19:11" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 19" />
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="2CH 20" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 20:1" />It came to pass after this also, <char style="add">that</char> the children of Moab, and the children of Ammon, and with them <char style="add">other</char> beside the Ammonites, came against Jehoshaphat to battle. <verse eid="2CH 20:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 20:2" />Then there came some that told Jehoshaphat, saying, There cometh a great multitude against thee from beyond the sea on this side Syria; and, behold, they <char style="add">be</char> in Hazazon-tamar, which <char style="add">is</char> En-gedi. <verse eid="2CH 20:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 20:3" />And Jehoshaphat feared, and set himself to seek the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and proclaimed a fast throughout all Judah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">himself: Heb. his face</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 20:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 20:4" />And Judah gathered themselves together, to ask <char style="add">help</char> of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: even out of all the cities of Judah they came to seek the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<verse eid="2CH 20:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 20:5" />¶ And Jehoshaphat stood in the congregation of Judah and Jerusalem, in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, before the new court, <verse eid="2CH 20:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 20:6" />And said, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of our fathers, <char style="add">art</char> not thou God in heaven? and rulest <char style="add">not</char> thou over all the kingdoms of the heathen? and in thine hand <char style="add">is there not</char> power and might, so that none is able to withstand thee? <verse eid="2CH 20:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 20:7" /><char style="add">Art</char> not thou our God, <char style="add">who</char> didst drive out the inhabitants of this land before thy people Israel, and gavest it to the seed of Abraham thy friend for ever?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">who: Heb. thou</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 20:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 20:8" />And they dwelt therein, and have built thee a sanctuary therein for thy name, saying, <verse eid="2CH 20:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 20:9" />If, <char style="add">when</char> evil cometh upon us, <char style="add">as</char> the sword, judgment, or pestilence, or famine, we stand before this house, and in thy presence, (for thy name <char style="add">is</char> in this house,) and cry unto thee in our affliction, then thou wilt hear and help. <verse eid="2CH 20:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 20:10" />And now, behold, the children of Ammon and Moab and mount Seir, whom thou wouldest not let Israel invade, when they came out of the land of Egypt, but they turned from them, and destroyed them not; <verse eid="2CH 20:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 20:11" />Behold, <char style="add">I say, how</char> they reward us, to come to cast us out of thy possession, which thou hast given us to inherit. <verse eid="2CH 20:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 20:12" />O our God, wilt thou not judge them? for we have no might against this great company that cometh against us; neither know we what to do: but our eyes <char style="add">are</char> upon thee. <verse eid="2CH 20:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 20:13" />And all Judah stood before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, with their little ones, their wives, and their children.<verse eid="2CH 20:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 20:14" />¶ Then upon Jahaziel the son of Zechariah, the son of Benaiah, the son of Jeiel, the son of Mattaniah, a Levite of the sons of Asaph, came the Spirit of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> in the midst of the congregation; <verse eid="2CH 20:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 20:15" />And he said, Hearken ye, all Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem, and thou king Jehoshaphat, Thus saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char> unto you, Be not afraid nor dismayed by reason of this great multitude; for the battle <char style="add">is</char> not yours, but God’s. <verse eid="2CH 20:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 20:16" />To morrow go ye down against them: behold, they come up by the cliff of Ziz; and ye shall find them at the end of the brook, before the wilderness of Jeruel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cliff: Heb. ascent</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">brook: or, valley</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 20:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 20:17" />Ye shall not <char style="add">need</char> to fight in this <char style="add">battle:</char> set yourselves, stand ye <char style="add">still</char>, and see the salvation of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> with you, O Judah and Jerusalem: fear not, nor be dismayed; to morrow go out against them: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">will be</char> with you. <verse eid="2CH 20:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 20:18" />And Jehoshaphat bowed his head with <char style="add">his</char> face to the ground: and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, worshipping the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 20:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 20:19" />And the Levites, of the children of the Kohathites, and of the children of the Korhites, stood up to praise the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel with a loud voice on high.<verse eid="2CH 20:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 20:20" />¶ And they rose early in the morning, and went forth into the wilderness of Tekoa: and as they went forth, Jehoshaphat stood and said, Hear me, O Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem; Believe in the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, so shall ye be established; believe his prophets, so shall ye prosper. <verse eid="2CH 20:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 20:21" />And when he had consulted with the people, he appointed singers unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and that should praise the beauty of holiness, as they went out before the army, and to say, Praise the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; for his mercy <char style="add">endureth</char> for ever.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: Heb. praisers</char></note><verse eid="2CH 20:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 20:22" />¶ And when they began to sing and to praise, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> set ambushments against the children of Ammon, Moab, and mount Seir, which were come against Judah; and they were smitten.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">And when…: Heb. And in the time that they, etc</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to sing…: Heb. in singing and praise</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">they were…: or, they smote one another</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 20:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 20:23" />For the children of Ammon and Moab stood up against the inhabitants of mount Seir, utterly to slay and destroy <char style="add">them:</char> and when they had made an end of the inhabitants of Seir, every one helped to destroy another.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to destroy: Heb. for the destruction</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 20:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 20:24" />And when Judah came toward the watch tower in the wilderness, they looked unto the multitude, and, behold, they <char style="add">were</char> dead bodies fallen to the earth, and none escaped.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">none…: Heb. there was not an escaping</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 20:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 20:25" />And when Jehoshaphat and his people came to take away the spoil of them, they found among them in abundance both riches with the dead bodies, and precious jewels, which they stripped off for themselves, more than they could carry away: and they were three days in gathering of the spoil, it was so much.<verse eid="2CH 20:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 20:26" />¶ And on the fourth day they assembled themselves in the valley of Berachah; for there they blessed the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: therefore the name of the same place was called, The valley of Berachah, unto this day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Berachah: that is, blessing</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 20:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 20:27" />Then they returned, every man of Judah and Jerusalem, and Jehoshaphat in the forefront of them, to go again to Jerusalem with joy; for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had made them to rejoice over their enemies.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">forefront: Heb. head</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 20:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 20:28" />And they came to Jerusalem with psalteries and harps and trumpets unto the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 20:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 20:29" />And the fear of God was on all the kingdoms of <char style="add">those</char> countries, when they had heard that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> fought against the enemies of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 20:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 20:30" />So the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet: for his God gave him rest round about.<verse eid="2CH 20:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 20:31" />¶ And Jehoshaphat reigned over Judah: <char style="add">he was</char> thirty and five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty and five years in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name <char style="add">was</char> Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. <verse eid="2CH 20:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 20:32" />And he walked in the way of Asa his father, and departed not from it, doing <char style="add">that which was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 20:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 20:33" />Howbeit the high places were not taken away: for as yet the people had not prepared their hearts unto the God of their fathers. <verse eid="2CH 20:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 20:34" />Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, first and last, behold, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the book of Jehu the son of Hanani, who <char style="add">is</char> mentioned in the book of the kings of Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">book of Jehu: Heb. words, etc</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is mentioned: Heb. was made to ascend</char></note><verse eid="2CH 20:34" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 20:35" />¶ And after this did Jehoshaphat king of Judah join himself with Ahaziah king of Israel, who did very wickedly: <verse eid="2CH 20:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 20:36" />And he joined himself with him to make ships to go to Tarshish: and they made the ships in Ezion-geber. <verse eid="2CH 20:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2CH 20:37" />Then Eliezer the son of Dodavah of Mareshah prophesied against Jehoshaphat, saying, Because thou hast joined thyself with Ahaziah, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath broken thy works. And the ships were broken, that they were not able to go to Tarshish.<verse eid="2CH 20:37" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 20" />
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="2CH 21" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 21:1" />Now Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David. And Jehoram his son reigned in his stead. <verse eid="2CH 21:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 21:2" />And he had brethren the sons of Jehoshaphat, Azariah, and Jehiel, and Zechariah, and Azariah, and Michael, and Shephatiah: all these <char style="add">were</char> the sons of Jehoshaphat king of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 21:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 21:3" />And their father gave them great gifts of silver, and of gold, and of precious things, with fenced cities in Judah: but the kingdom gave he to Jehoram; because he <char style="add">was</char> the firstborn. <verse eid="2CH 21:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 21:4" />Now when Jehoram was risen up to the kingdom of his father, he strengthened himself, and slew all his brethren with the sword, and <char style="add">divers</char> also of the princes of Israel.<verse eid="2CH 21:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 21:5" />¶ Jehoram <char style="add">was</char> thirty and two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 21:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 21:6" />And he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, like as did the house of Ahab: for he had the daughter of Ahab to wife: and he wrought <char style="add">that which was</char> evil in the eyes of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 21:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 21:7" />Howbeit the <char style="nd">LORD</char> would not destroy the house of David, because of the covenant that he had made with David, and as he promised to give a light to him and to his sons for ever.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">light: Heb. lamp, or, candle</char></note><verse eid="2CH 21:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 21:8" />¶ In his days the Edomites revolted from under the dominion of Judah, and made themselves a king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">dominion: Heb. hand</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 21:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 21:9" />Then Jehoram went forth with his princes, and all his chariots with him: and he rose up by night, and smote the Edomites which compassed him in, and the captains of the chariots. <verse eid="2CH 21:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 21:10" />So the Edomites revolted from under the hand of Judah unto this day. The same time <char style="add">also</char> did Libnah revolt from under his hand; because he had forsaken the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of his fathers. <verse eid="2CH 21:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 21:11" />Moreover he made high places in the mountains of Judah, and caused the inhabitants of Jerusalem to commit fornication, and compelled Judah <char style="add">thereto</char>.<verse eid="2CH 21:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 21:12" />¶ And there came a writing to him from Elijah the prophet, saying, Thus saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of David thy father, Because thou hast not walked in the ways of Jehoshaphat thy father, nor in the ways of Asa king of Judah, <verse eid="2CH 21:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 21:13" />But hast walked in the way of the kings of Israel, and hast made Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to go a whoring, like to the whoredoms of the house of Ahab, and also hast slain thy brethren of thy father’s house, <char style="add">which were</char> better than thyself: <verse eid="2CH 21:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 21:14" />Behold, with a great plague will the <char style="nd">LORD</char> smite thy people, and thy children, and thy wives, and all thy goods:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a great…: Heb. a great stroke</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 21:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 21:15" />And thou <char style="add">shalt have</char> great sickness by disease of thy bowels, until thy bowels fall out by reason of the sickness day by day.<verse eid="2CH 21:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 21:16" />¶ Moreover the <char style="nd">LORD</char> stirred up against Jehoram the spirit of the Philistines, and of the Arabians, that <char style="add">were</char> near the Ethiopians: <verse eid="2CH 21:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 21:17" />And they came up into Judah, and brake into it, and carried away all the substance that was found in the king’s house, and his sons also, and his wives; so that there was never a son left him, save Jehoahaz, the youngest of his sons.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">carried…: Heb. carried captive</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Jehoahaz: also called, Ahaziah, or, Azariah</char></note><verse eid="2CH 21:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 21:18" />¶ And after all this the <char style="nd">LORD</char> smote him in his bowels with an incurable disease. <verse eid="2CH 21:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 21:19" />And it came to pass, that in process of time, after the end of two years, his bowels fell out by reason of his sickness: so he died of sore diseases. And his people made no burning for him, like the burning of his fathers. <verse eid="2CH 21:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 21:20" />Thirty and two years old was he when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem eight years, and departed without being desired. Howbeit they buried him in the city of David, but not in the sepulchres of the kings.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">without…: Heb. without desire</char></note><verse eid="2CH 21:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 21" />
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="2CH 22" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 22:1" />And the inhabitants of Jerusalem made Ahaziah his youngest son king in his stead: for the band of men that came with the Arabians to the camp had slain all the eldest. So Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah reigned. <verse eid="2CH 22:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 22:2" />Forty and two years old <char style="add">was</char> Ahaziah when he began to reign, and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also <char style="add">was</char> Athaliah the daughter of Omri. <verse eid="2CH 22:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 22:3" />He also walked in the ways of the house of Ahab: for his mother was his counsellor to do wickedly. <verse eid="2CH 22:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 22:4" />Wherefore he did evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> like the house of Ahab: for they were his counsellors after the death of his father to his destruction.<verse eid="2CH 22:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 22:5" />¶ He walked also after their counsel, and went with Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth-gilead: and the Syrians smote Joram. <verse eid="2CH 22:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 22:6" />And he returned to be healed in Jezreel because of the wounds which were given him at Ramah, when he fought with Hazael king of Syria. And Azariah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Jehoram the son of Ahab at Jezreel, because he was sick.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">which…: Heb. wherewith they wounded him</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Azariah: also called, Ahaziah, or, Jehoahaz</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 22:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 22:7" />And the destruction of Ahaziah was of God by coming to Joram: for when he was come, he went out with Jehoram against Jehu the son of Nimshi, whom the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had anointed to cut off the house of Ahab.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">destruction: Heb. treading down</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 22:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 22:8" />And it came to pass, that, when Jehu was executing judgment upon the house of Ahab, and found the princes of Judah, and the sons of the brethren of Ahaziah, that ministered to Ahaziah, he slew them. <verse eid="2CH 22:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 22:9" />And he sought Ahaziah: and they caught him, (for he was hid in Samaria,) and brought him to Jehu: and when they had slain him, they buried him: Because, said they, he <char style="add">is</char> the son of Jehoshaphat, who sought the <char style="nd">LORD</char> with all his heart. So the house of Ahaziah had no power to keep still the kingdom.<verse eid="2CH 22:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 22:10" />¶ But when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the seed royal of the house of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 22:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 22:11" />But Jehoshabeath, the daughter of the king, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him from among the king’s sons that were slain, and put him and his nurse in a bedchamber. So Jehoshabeath, the daughter of king Jehoram, the wife of Jehoiada the priest, (for she was the sister of Ahaziah,) hid him from Athaliah, so that she slew him not.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Jehoshabeath: also called, Jehosheba</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 22:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 22:12" />And he was with them hid in the house of God six years: and Athaliah reigned over the land.<verse eid="2CH 22:12" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 22" />
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="2CH 23" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 23:1" />And in the seventh year Jehoiada strengthened himself, and took the captains of hundreds, Azariah the son of Jeroham, and Ishmael the son of Jehohanan, and Azariah the son of Obed, and Maaseiah the son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat the son of Zichri, into covenant with him. <verse eid="2CH 23:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 23:2" />And they went about in Judah, and gathered the Levites out of all the cities of Judah, and the chief of the fathers of Israel, and they came to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 23:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 23:3" />And all the congregation made a covenant with the king in the house of God. And he said unto them, Behold, the king’s son shall reign, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath said of the sons of David. <verse eid="2CH 23:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 23:4" />This <char style="add">is</char> the thing that ye shall do; A third part of you entering on the sabbath, of the priests and of the Levites, <char style="add">shall be</char> porters of the doors;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">doors: Heb. thresholds</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 23:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 23:5" />And a third part <char style="add">shall be</char> at the king’s house; and a third part at the gate of the foundation: and all the people <char style="add">shall be</char> in the courts of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 23:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 23:6" />But let none come into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, save the priests, and they that minister of the Levites; they shall go in, for they <char style="add">are</char> holy: but all the people shall keep the watch of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 23:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 23:7" />And the Levites shall compass the king round about, every man with his weapons in his hand; and whosoever <char style="add">else</char> cometh into the house, he shall be put to death: but be ye with the king when he cometh in, and when he goeth out. <verse eid="2CH 23:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 23:8" />So the Levites and all Judah did according to all things that Jehoiada the priest had commanded, and took every man his men that were to come in on the sabbath, with them that were to go <char style="add">out</char> on the sabbath: for Jehoiada the priest dismissed not the courses. <verse eid="2CH 23:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 23:9" />Moreover Jehoiada the priest delivered to the captains of hundreds spears, and bucklers, and shields, that <char style="add">had been</char> king David’s, which <char style="add">were</char> in the house of God. <verse eid="2CH 23:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 23:10" />And he set all the people, every man having his weapon in his hand, from the right side of the temple to the left side of the temple, along by the altar and the temple, by the king round about.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">side: Heb. shoulder</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">temple: Heb. house</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 23:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 23:11" />Then they brought out the king’s son, and put upon him the crown, and <char style="add">gave him</char> the testimony, and made him king. And Jehoiada and his sons anointed him, and said, God save the king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">God…: Heb. Let the king live</char></note><verse eid="2CH 23:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 23:12" />¶ Now when Athaliah heard the noise of the people running and praising the king, she came to the people into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: <verse eid="2CH 23:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 23:13" />And she looked, and, behold, the king stood at his pillar at the entering in, and the princes and the trumpets by the king: and all the people of the land rejoiced, and sounded with trumpets, also the singers with instruments of musick, and such as taught to sing praise. Then Athaliah rent her clothes, and said, Treason, Treason.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Treason: Heb. Conspiracy</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 23:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 23:14" />Then Jehoiada the priest brought out the captains of hundreds that were set over the host, and said unto them, Have her forth of the ranges: and whoso followeth her, let him be slain with the sword. For the priest said, Slay her not in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 23:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 23:15" />So they laid hands on her; and when she was come to the entering of the horse gate by the king’s house, they slew her there.<verse eid="2CH 23:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 23:16" />¶ And Jehoiada made a covenant between him, and between all the people, and between the king, that they should be the <char style="nd">LORD’s</char> people. <verse eid="2CH 23:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 23:17" />Then all the people went to the house of Baal, and brake it down, and brake his altars and his images in pieces, and slew Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. <verse eid="2CH 23:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 23:18" />Also Jehoiada appointed the offices of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> by the hand of the priests the Levites, whom David had distributed in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to offer the burnt offerings of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, as <char style="add">it is</char> written in the law of Moses, with rejoicing and with singing, <char style="add">as it was ordained</char> by David.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as it was…: Heb. by the hands of David</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 23:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 23:19" />And he set the porters at the gates of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, that none <char style="add">which was</char> unclean in any thing should enter in. <verse eid="2CH 23:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 23:20" />And he took the captains of hundreds, and the nobles, and the governors of the people, and all the people of the land, and brought down the king from the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: and they came through the high gate into the king’s house, and set the king upon the throne of the kingdom. <verse eid="2CH 23:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 23:21" />And all the people of the land rejoiced: and the city was quiet, after that they had slain Athaliah with the sword.<verse eid="2CH 23:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 23" />
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="2CH 24" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 24:1" />Joash <char style="add">was</char> seven years old when he began to reign, and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also <char style="add">was</char> Zibiah of Beer-sheba. <verse eid="2CH 24:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 24:2" />And Joash did <char style="add">that which was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> all the days of Jehoiada the priest. <verse eid="2CH 24:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 24:3" />And Jehoiada took for him two wives; and he begat sons and daughters.<verse eid="2CH 24:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 24:4" />¶ And it came to pass after this, <char style="add">that</char> Joash was minded to repair the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to repair: Heb. to renew</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 24:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 24:5" />And he gathered together the priests and the Levites, and said to them, Go out unto the cities of Judah, and gather of all Israel money to repair the house of your God from year to year, and see that ye hasten the matter. Howbeit the Levites hastened <char style="add">it</char> not. <verse eid="2CH 24:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 24:6" />And the king called for Jehoiada the chief, and said unto him, Why hast thou not required of the Levites to bring in out of Judah and out of Jerusalem the collection, <char style="add">according to the commandment</char> of Moses the servant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and of the congregation of Israel, for the tabernacle of witness? <verse eid="2CH 24:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 24:7" />For the sons of Athaliah, that wicked woman, had broken up the house of God; and also all the dedicated things of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> did they bestow upon Baalim. <verse eid="2CH 24:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 24:8" />And at the king’s commandment they made a chest, and set it without at the gate of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 24:9" />And they made a proclamation through Judah and Jerusalem, to bring in to the <char style="nd">LORD</char> the collection <char style="add">that</char> Moses the servant of God <char style="add">laid</char> upon Israel in the wilderness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a proclamation: Heb. a voice</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 24:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 24:10" />And all the princes and all the people rejoiced, and brought in, and cast into the chest, until they had made an end. <verse eid="2CH 24:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 24:11" />Now it came to pass, that at what time the chest was brought unto the king’s office by the hand of the Levites, and when they saw that <char style="add">there was</char> much money, the king’s scribe and the high priest’s officer came and emptied the chest, and took it, and carried it to his place again. Thus they did day by day, and gathered money in abundance. <verse eid="2CH 24:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 24:12" />And the king and Jehoiada gave it to such as did the work of the service of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and hired masons and carpenters to repair the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and also such as wrought iron and brass to mend the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 24:13" />So the workmen wrought, and the work was perfected by them, and they set the house of God in his state, and strengthened it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the work…: Heb. the healing went up upon the work</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 24:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 24:14" />And when they had finished <char style="add">it</char>, they brought the rest of the money before the king and Jehoiada, whereof were made vessels for the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, <char style="add">even</char> vessels to minister, and to offer <char style="add">withal</char>, and spoons, and vessels of gold and silver. And they offered burnt offerings in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> continually all the days of Jehoiada.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to offer…: or, pestils</char></note><verse eid="2CH 24:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 24:15" />¶ But Jehoiada waxed old, and was full of days when he died; an hundred and thirty years old <char style="add">was he</char> when he died. <verse eid="2CH 24:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 24:16" />And they buried him in the city of David among the kings, because he had done good in Israel, both toward God, and toward his house. <verse eid="2CH 24:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 24:17" />Now after the death of Jehoiada came the princes of Judah, and made obeisance to the king. Then the king hearkened unto them. <verse eid="2CH 24:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 24:18" />And they left the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers, and served groves and idols: and wrath came upon Judah and Jerusalem for this their trespass. <verse eid="2CH 24:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 24:19" />Yet he sent prophets to them, to bring them again unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; and they testified against them: but they would not give ear. <verse eid="2CH 24:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 24:20" />And the Spirit of God came upon Zechariah the son of Jehoiada the priest, which stood above the people, and said unto them, Thus saith God, Why transgress ye the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, that ye cannot prosper? because ye have forsaken the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, he hath also forsaken you.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">came…: Heb. clothed</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 24:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 24:21" />And they conspired against him, and stoned him with stones at the commandment of the king in the court of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 24:22" />Thus Joash the king remembered not the kindness which Jehoiada his father had done to him, but slew his son. And when he died, he said, The <char style="nd">LORD</char> look upon <char style="add">it</char>, and require <char style="add">it</char>.<verse eid="2CH 24:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 24:23" />¶ And it came to pass at the end of the year, <char style="add">that</char> the host of Syria came up against him: and they came to Judah and Jerusalem, and destroyed all the princes of the people from among the people, and sent all the spoil of them unto the king of Damascus.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">at the…: Heb. in the revolution of the year</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Damascus: Heb. Darmesek</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 24:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 24:24" />For the army of the Syrians came with a small company of men, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> delivered a very great host into their hand, because they had forsaken the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers. So they executed judgment against Joash. <verse eid="2CH 24:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 24:25" />And when they were departed from him, (for they left him in great diseases,) his own servants conspired against him for the blood of the sons of Jehoiada the priest, and slew him on his bed, and he died: and they buried him in the city of David, but they buried him not in the sepulchres of the kings. <verse eid="2CH 24:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 24:26" />And these are they that conspired against him; Zabad the son of Shimeath an Ammonitess, and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith a Moabitess.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Zabad: or, Jozacher</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Shimrith: or, Shomer</char></note><verse eid="2CH 24:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 24:27" />¶ Now <char style="add">concerning</char> his sons, and the greatness of the burdens <char style="add">laid</char> upon him, and the repairing of the house of God, behold, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the story of the book of the kings. And Amaziah his son reigned in his stead.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">repairing: Heb. founding</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">story: or, commentary</char></note><verse eid="2CH 24:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 24" />
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="2CH 25" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 25:1" />Amaziah <char style="add">was</char> twenty and five years old <char style="add">when</char> he began to reign, and he reigned twenty and nine years in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name <char style="add">was</char> Jehoaddan of Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 25:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 25:2" />And he did <char style="add">that which was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, but not with a perfect heart.<verse eid="2CH 25:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 25:3" />¶ Now it came to pass, when the kingdom was established to him, that he slew his servants that had killed the king his father.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">established…: Heb. confirmed upon him</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 25:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 25:4" />But he slew not their children, but <char style="add">did</char> as <char style="add">it is</char> written in the law in the book of Moses, where the <char style="nd">LORD</char> commanded, saying, The fathers shall not die for the children, neither shall the children die for the fathers, but every man shall die for his own sin.<verse eid="2CH 25:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 25:5" />¶ Moreover Amaziah gathered Judah together, and made them captains over thousands, and captains over hundreds, according to the houses of <char style="add">their</char> fathers, throughout all Judah and Benjamin: and he numbered them from twenty years old and above, and found them three hundred thousand choice <char style="add">men, able</char> to go forth to war, that could handle spear and shield. <verse eid="2CH 25:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 25:6" />He hired also an hundred thousand mighty men of valour out of Israel for an hundred talents of silver. <verse eid="2CH 25:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 25:7" />But there came a man of God to him, saying, O king, let not the army of Israel go with thee; for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">is</char> not with Israel, <char style="add">to wit, with</char> all the children of Ephraim. <verse eid="2CH 25:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 25:8" />But if thou wilt go, do <char style="add">it</char>, be strong for the battle: God shall make thee fall before the enemy: for God hath power to help, and to cast down. <verse eid="2CH 25:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 25:9" />And Amaziah said to the man of God, But what shall we do for the hundred talents which I have given to the army of Israel? And the man of God answered, The <char style="nd">LORD</char> is able to give thee much more than this.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">army: Heb. band</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 25:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 25:10" />Then Amaziah separated them, <char style="add">to wit</char>, the army that was come to him out of Ephraim, to go home again: wherefore their anger was greatly kindled against Judah, and they returned home in great anger.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">home again: Heb. to their place</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in great…: Heb. in heat of anger</char></note><verse eid="2CH 25:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 25:11" />¶ And Amaziah strengthened himself, and led forth his people, and went to the valley of salt, and smote of the children of Seir ten thousand. <verse eid="2CH 25:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 25:12" />And <char style="add">other</char> ten thousand <char style="add">left</char> alive did the children of Judah carry away captive, and brought them unto the top of the rock, and cast them down from the top of the rock, that they all were broken in pieces.<verse eid="2CH 25:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 25:13" />¶ But the soldiers of the army which Amaziah sent back, that they should not go with him to battle, fell upon the cities of Judah, from Samaria even unto Beth-horon, and smote three thousand of them, and took much spoil.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the soldiers…: Heb. the sons of the band</char></note><verse eid="2CH 25:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 25:14" />¶ Now it came to pass, after that Amaziah was come from the slaughter of the Edomites, that he brought the gods of the children of Seir, and set them up <char style="add">to be</char> his gods, and bowed down himself before them, and burned incense unto them. <verse eid="2CH 25:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 25:15" />Wherefore the anger of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was kindled against Amaziah, and he sent unto him a prophet, which said unto him, Why hast thou sought after the gods of the people, which could not deliver their own people out of thine hand? <verse eid="2CH 25:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 25:16" />And it came to pass, as he talked with him, that <char style="add">the king</char> said unto him, Art thou made of the king’s counsel? forbear; why shouldest thou be smitten? Then the prophet forbare, and said, I know that God hath determined to destroy thee, because thou hast done this, and hast not hearkened unto my counsel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">determined: Heb. counselled</char></note><verse eid="2CH 25:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 25:17" />¶ Then Amaziah king of Judah took advice, and sent to Joash, the son of Jehoahaz, the son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, Come, let us see one another in the face. <verse eid="2CH 25:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 25:18" />And Joash king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, The thistle that <char style="add">was</char> in Lebanon sent to the cedar that <char style="add">was</char> in Lebanon, saying, Give thy daughter to my son to wife: and there passed by a wild beast that <char style="add">was</char> in Lebanon, and trode down the thistle.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">thistle: or, furze bush, or, thorn</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a wild…: Heb. a beast of the field</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 25:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 25:19" />Thou sayest, Lo, thou hast smitten the Edomites; and thine heart lifteth thee up to boast: abide now at home; why shouldest thou meddle to <char style="add">thine</char> hurt, that thou shouldest fall, <char style="add">even</char> thou, and Judah with thee? <verse eid="2CH 25:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 25:20" />But Amaziah would not hear; for it <char style="add">came</char> of God, that he might deliver them into the hand <char style="add">of their enemies</char>, because they sought after the gods of Edom. <verse eid="2CH 25:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 25:21" />So Joash the king of Israel went up; and they saw one another in the face, <char style="add">both</char> he and Amaziah king of Judah, at Beth-shemesh, which <char style="add">belongeth</char> to Judah. <verse eid="2CH 25:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 25:22" />And Judah was put to the worse before Israel, and they fled every man to his tent.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">put…: Heb. smitten</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 25:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 25:23" />And Joash the king of Israel took Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Joash, the son of Jehoahaz, at Beth-shemesh, and brought him to Jerusalem, and brake down the wall of Jerusalem from the gate of Ephraim to the corner gate, four hundred cubits.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the corner…: Heb. the gate of it that looketh</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 25:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 25:24" />And <char style="add">he took</char> all the gold and the silver, and all the vessels that were found in the house of God with Obed-edom, and the treasures of the king’s house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria.<verse eid="2CH 25:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 25:25" />¶ And Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah lived after the death of Joash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel fifteen years. <verse eid="2CH 25:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 25:26" />Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, first and last, behold, <char style="add">are</char> they not written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel?<verse eid="2CH 25:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 25:27" />¶ Now after the time that Amaziah did turn away from following the <char style="nd">LORD</char> they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem; and he fled to Lachish: but they sent to Lachish after him, and slew him there.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from…: Heb. from after</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">made…: Heb. conspired a conspiracy</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 25:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 25:28" />And they brought him upon horses, and buried him with his fathers in the city of Judah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Judah: that is, the city of David</char></note><verse eid="2CH 25:28" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 25" />
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="2CH 26" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 26:1" />Then all the people of Judah took Uzziah, who <char style="add">was</char> sixteen years old, and made him king in the room of his father Amaziah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Uzziah: or, Azariah</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 26:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 26:2" />He built Eloth, and restored it to Judah, after that the king slept with his fathers. <verse eid="2CH 26:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 26:3" />Sixteen years old <char style="add">was</char> Uzziah when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty and two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also <char style="add">was</char> Jecoliah of Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 26:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 26:4" />And he did <char style="add">that which was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, according to all that his father Amaziah did. <verse eid="2CH 26:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 26:5" />And he sought God in the days of Zechariah, who had understanding in the visions of God: and as long as he sought the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, God made him to prosper.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in the visions…: Heb. in the seeing of God</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 26:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 26:6" />And he went forth and warred against the Philistines, and brake down the wall of Gath, and the wall of Jabneh, and the wall of Ashdod, and built cities about Ashdod, and among the Philistines.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">about…: or, in the country of Ashdod</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 26:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 26:7" />And God helped him against the Philistines, and against the Arabians that dwelt in Gur-baal, and the Mehunims. <verse eid="2CH 26:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 26:8" />And the Ammonites gave gifts to Uzziah: and his name spread abroad <char style="add">even</char> to the entering in of Egypt; for he strengthened <char style="add">himself</char> exceedingly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">spread…: Heb. went</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 26:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 26:9" />Moreover Uzziah built towers in Jerusalem at the corner gate, and at the valley gate, and at the turning <char style="add">of the wall</char>, and fortified them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fortified: or, repaired</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 26:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 26:10" />Also he built towers in the desert, and digged many wells: for he had much cattle, both in the low country, and in the plains: husbandmen <char style="add">also</char>, and vine dressers in the mountains, and in Carmel: for he loved husbandry.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">digged…: or, cut out many cisterns</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Carmel: or, fruitful fields</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">husbandry: Heb. ground</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 26:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 26:11" />Moreover Uzziah had an host of fighting men, that went out to war by bands, according to the number of their account by the hand of Jeiel the scribe and Maaseiah the ruler, under the hand of Hananiah, <char style="add">one</char> of the king’s captains. <verse eid="2CH 26:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 26:12" />The whole number of the chief of the fathers of the mighty men of valour <char style="add">were</char> two thousand and six hundred. <verse eid="2CH 26:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 26:13" />And under their hand <char style="add">was</char> an army, three hundred thousand and seven thousand and five hundred, that made war with mighty power, to help the king against the enemy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">an army: Heb. the power of an army</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 26:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 26:14" />And Uzziah prepared for them throughout all the host shields, and spears, and helmets, and habergeons, and bows, and slings <char style="add">to cast</char> stones.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">slings…: Heb. stones of slings</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 26:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 26:15" />And he made in Jerusalem engines, invented by cunning men, to be on the towers and upon the bulwarks, to shoot arrows and great stones withal. And his name spread far abroad; for he was marvellously helped, till he was strong.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">spread: Heb. went forth</char></note><verse eid="2CH 26:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 26:16" />¶ But when he was strong, his heart was lifted up to <char style="add">his</char> destruction: for he transgressed against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God, and went into the temple of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> to burn incense upon the altar of incense. <verse eid="2CH 26:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 26:17" />And Azariah the priest went in after him, and with him fourscore priests of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, <char style="add">that were</char> valiant men: <verse eid="2CH 26:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 26:18" />And they withstood Uzziah the king, and said unto him, <char style="add">It appertaineth</char> not unto thee, Uzziah, to burn incense unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, but to the priests the sons of Aaron, that are consecrated to burn incense: go out of the sanctuary; for thou hast trespassed; neither <char style="add">shall it be</char> for thine honour from the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God. <verse eid="2CH 26:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 26:19" />Then Uzziah was wroth, and <char style="add">had</char> a censer in his hand to burn incense: and while he was wroth with the priests, the leprosy even rose up in his forehead before the priests in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, from beside the incense altar. <verse eid="2CH 26:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 26:20" />And Azariah the chief priest, and all the priests, looked upon him, and, behold, he <char style="add">was</char> leprous in his forehead, and they thrust him out from thence; yea, himself hasted also to go out, because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had smitten him. <verse eid="2CH 26:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 26:21" />And Uzziah the king was a leper unto the day of his death, and dwelt in a several house, <char style="add">being</char> a leper; for he was cut off from the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: and Jotham his son <char style="add">was</char> over the king’s house, judging the people of the land.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">several: Heb. free</char></note><verse eid="2CH 26:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 26:22" />¶ Now the rest of the acts of Uzziah, first and last, did Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, write. <verse eid="2CH 26:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 26:23" />So Uzziah slept with his fathers, and they buried him with his fathers in the field of the burial which <char style="add">belonged</char> to the kings; for they said, He <char style="add">is</char> a leper: and Jotham his son reigned in his stead.<verse eid="2CH 26:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 26" />
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="2CH 27" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 27:1" />Jotham <char style="add">was</char> twenty and five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also <char style="add">was</char> Jerushah, the daughter of Zadok. <verse eid="2CH 27:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 27:2" />And he did <char style="add">that which was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, according to all that his father Uzziah did: howbeit he entered not into the temple of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. And the people did yet corruptly. <verse eid="2CH 27:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 27:3" />He built the high gate of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and on the wall of Ophel he built much.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ophel: or, the tower</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 27:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 27:4" />Moreover he built cities in the mountains of Judah, and in the forests he built castles and towers.<verse eid="2CH 27:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 27:5" />¶ He fought also with the king of the Ammonites, and prevailed against them. And the children of Ammon gave him the same year an hundred talents of silver, and ten thousand measures of wheat, and ten thousand of barley. So much did the children of Ammon pay unto him, both the second year, and the third.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">So…: Heb. This</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 27:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 27:6" />So Jotham became mighty, because he prepared his ways before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">prepared: or, established</char></note><verse eid="2CH 27:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 27:7" />¶ Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all his wars, and his ways, lo, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. <verse eid="2CH 27:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 27:8" />He was five and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 27:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 27:9" />¶ And Jotham slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David: and Ahaz his son reigned in his stead.<verse eid="2CH 27:9" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 27" />
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="2CH 28" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 28:1" />Ahaz <char style="add">was</char> twenty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem: but he did not <char style="add">that which was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, like David his father: <verse eid="2CH 28:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 28:2" />For he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel, and made also molten images for Baalim. <verse eid="2CH 28:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 28:3" />Moreover he burnt incense in the valley of the son of Hinnom, and burnt his children in the fire, after the abominations of the heathen whom the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had cast out before the children of Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">burnt…: or, offered sacrifice</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 28:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 28:4" />He sacrificed also and burnt incense in the high places, and on the hills, and under every green tree. <verse eid="2CH 28:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 28:5" />Wherefore the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God delivered him into the hand of the king of Syria; and they smote him, and carried away a great multitude of them captives, and brought <char style="add">them</char> to Damascus. And he was also delivered into the hand of the king of Israel, who smote him with a great slaughter.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Damascus: Heb. Darmesek</char></note><verse eid="2CH 28:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 28:6" />¶ For Pekah the son of Remaliah slew in Judah an hundred and twenty thousand in one day, <char style="add">which were</char> all valiant men; because they had forsaken the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">valiant…: Heb. sons of valour</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 28:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 28:7" />And Zichri, a mighty man of Ephraim, slew Maaseiah the king’s son, and Azrikam the governor of the house, and Elkanah <char style="add">that was</char> next to the king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">next…: Heb. the second to the king</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 28:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 28:8" />And the children of Israel carried away captive of their brethren two hundred thousand, women, sons, and daughters, and took also away much spoil from them, and brought the spoil to Samaria. <verse eid="2CH 28:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 28:9" />But a prophet of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was there, whose name <char style="add">was</char> Oded: and he went out before the host that came to Samaria, and said unto them, Behold, because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of your fathers was wroth with Judah, he hath delivered them into your hand, and ye have slain them in a rage <char style="add">that</char> reacheth up unto heaven. <verse eid="2CH 28:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 28:10" />And now ye purpose to keep under the children of Judah and Jerusalem for bondmen and bondwomen unto you: <char style="add">but are there</char> not with you, even with you, sins against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God? <verse eid="2CH 28:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 28:11" />Now hear me therefore, and deliver the captives again, which ye have taken captive of your brethren: for the fierce wrath of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">is</char> upon you. <verse eid="2CH 28:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 28:12" />Then certain of the heads of the children of Ephraim, Azariah the son of Johanan, Berechiah the son of Meshillemoth, and Jehizkiah the son of Shallum, and Amasa the son of Hadlai, stood up against them that came from the war, <verse eid="2CH 28:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 28:13" />And said unto them, Ye shall not bring in the captives hither: for whereas we have offended against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">already</char>, ye intend to add <char style="add">more</char> to our sins and to our trespass: for our trespass is great, and <char style="add">there is</char> fierce wrath against Israel. <verse eid="2CH 28:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 28:14" />So the armed men left the captives and the spoil before the princes and all the congregation. <verse eid="2CH 28:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 28:15" />And the men which were expressed by name rose up, and took the captives, and with the spoil clothed all that were naked among them, and arrayed them, and shod them, and gave them to eat and to drink, and anointed them, and carried all the feeble of them upon asses, and brought them to Jericho, the city of palm trees, to their brethren: then they returned to Samaria.<verse eid="2CH 28:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 28:16" />¶ At that time did king Ahaz send unto the kings of Assyria to help him. <verse eid="2CH 28:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 28:17" />For again the Edomites had come and smitten Judah, and carried away captives.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">captives: Heb. a captivity</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 28:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 28:18" />The Philistines also had invaded the cities of the low country, and of the south of Judah, and had taken Beth-shemesh, and Ajalon, and Gederoth, and Shocho with the villages thereof, and Timnah with the villages thereof, Gimzo also and the villages thereof: and they dwelt there. <verse eid="2CH 28:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 28:19" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> brought Judah low because of Ahaz king of Israel; for he made Judah naked, and transgressed sore against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 28:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 28:20" />And Tilgath-pilneser king of Assyria came unto him, and distressed him, but strengthened him not. <verse eid="2CH 28:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 28:21" />For Ahaz took away a portion <char style="add">out</char> of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and <char style="add">out</char> of the house of the king, and of the princes, and gave <char style="add">it</char> unto the king of Assyria: but he helped him not.<verse eid="2CH 28:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 28:22" />¶ And in the time of his distress did he trespass yet more against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: this <char style="add">is that</char> king Ahaz. <verse eid="2CH 28:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 28:23" />For he sacrificed unto the gods of Damascus, which smote him: and he said, Because the gods of the kings of Syria help them, <char style="add">therefore</char> will I sacrifice to them, that they may help me. But they were the ruin of him, and of all Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Damascus: Heb. Darmesek</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 28:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 28:24" />And Ahaz gathered together the vessels of the house of God, and cut in pieces the vessels of the house of God, and shut up the doors of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and he made him altars in every corner of Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 28:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 28:25" />And in every several city of Judah he made high places to burn incense unto other gods, and provoked to anger the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of his fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to burn: or, to offer</char></note><verse eid="2CH 28:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 28:26" />¶ Now the rest of his acts and of all his ways, first and last, behold, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse eid="2CH 28:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 28:27" />And Ahaz slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city, <char style="add">even</char> in Jerusalem: but they brought him not into the sepulchres of the kings of Israel: and Hezekiah his son reigned in his stead.<verse eid="2CH 28:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 28" />
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="2CH 29" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 29:1" />Hezekiah began to reign <char style="add">when he was</char> five and twenty years old, and he reigned nine and twenty years in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name <char style="add">was</char> Abijah, the daughter of Zechariah. <verse eid="2CH 29:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 29:2" />And he did <char style="add">that which was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, according to all that David his father had done.<verse eid="2CH 29:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 29:3" />¶ He in the first year of his reign, in the first month, opened the doors of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and repaired them. <verse eid="2CH 29:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 29:4" />And he brought in the priests and the Levites, and gathered them together into the east street, <verse eid="2CH 29:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 29:5" />And said unto them, Hear me, ye Levites, sanctify now yourselves, and sanctify the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of your fathers, and carry forth the filthiness out of the holy <char style="add">place</char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 29:6" />For our fathers have trespassed, and done <char style="add">that which was</char> evil in the eyes of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God, and have forsaken him, and have turned away their faces from the habitation of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and turned <char style="add">their</char> backs.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">turned their…: Heb. given the neck</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 29:7" />Also they have shut up the doors of the porch, and put out the lamps, and have not burned incense nor offered burnt offerings in the holy <char style="add">place</char> unto the God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 29:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 29:8" />Wherefore the wrath of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was upon Judah and Jerusalem, and he hath delivered them to trouble, to astonishment, and to hissing, as ye see with your eyes.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">trouble: Heb. commotion</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 29:9" />For, lo, our fathers have fallen by the sword, and our sons and our daughters and our wives <char style="add">are</char> in captivity for this. <verse eid="2CH 29:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 29:10" />Now <char style="add">it is</char> in mine heart to make a covenant with the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, that his fierce wrath may turn away from us. <verse eid="2CH 29:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 29:11" />My sons, be not now negligent: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath chosen you to stand before him, to serve him, and that ye should minister unto him, and burn incense.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">be not…: or, be not now deceived</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">burn…: or, offer sacrifice</char></note><verse eid="2CH 29:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 29:12" />¶ Then the Levites arose, Mahath the son of Amasai, and Joel the son of Azariah, of the sons of the Kohathites: and of the sons of Merari, Kish the son of Abdi, and Azariah the son of Jehalelel: and of the Gershonites; Joah the son of Zimmah, and Eden the son of Joah: <verse eid="2CH 29:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 29:13" />And of the sons of Elizaphan; Shimri, and Jeiel: and of the sons of Asaph; Zechariah, and Mattaniah: <verse eid="2CH 29:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 29:14" />And of the sons of Heman; Jehiel, and Shimei: and of the sons of Jeduthun; Shemaiah, and Uzziel. <verse eid="2CH 29:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 29:15" />And they gathered their brethren, and sanctified themselves, and came, according to the commandment of the king, by the words of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to cleanse the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by the words…: or, in the business of the <char style="nd">LORD</char></char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 29:16" />And the priests went into the inner part of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to cleanse <char style="add">it</char>, and brought out all the uncleanness that they found in the temple of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> into the court of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. And the Levites took <char style="add">it</char>, to carry <char style="add">it</char> out abroad into the brook Kidron. <verse eid="2CH 29:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 29:17" />Now they began on the first <char style="add">day</char> of the first month to sanctify, and on the eighth day of the month came they to the porch of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: so they sanctified the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> in eight days; and in the sixteenth day of the first month they made an end. <verse eid="2CH 29:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 29:18" />Then they went in to Hezekiah the king, and said, We have cleansed all the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and the altar of burnt offering, with all the vessels thereof, and the shewbread table, with all the vessels thereof. <verse eid="2CH 29:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 29:19" />Moreover all the vessels, which king Ahaz in his reign did cast away in his transgression, have we prepared and sanctified, and, behold, they <char style="add">are</char> before the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<verse eid="2CH 29:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 29:20" />¶ Then Hezekiah the king rose early, and gathered the rulers of the city, and went up to the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 29:21" />And they brought seven bullocks, and seven rams, and seven lambs, and seven he goats, for a sin offering for the kingdom, and for the sanctuary, and for Judah. And he commanded the priests the sons of Aaron to offer <char style="add">them</char> on the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 29:22" />So they killed the bullocks, and the priests received the blood, and sprinkled <char style="add">it</char> on the altar: likewise, when they had killed the rams, they sprinkled the blood upon the altar: they killed also the lambs, and they sprinkled the blood upon the altar. <verse eid="2CH 29:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 29:23" />And they brought forth the he goats <char style="add">for</char> the sin offering before the king and the congregation; and they laid their hands upon them:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">forth: Heb. near</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 29:24" />And the priests killed them, and they made reconciliation with their blood upon the altar, to make an atonement for all Israel: for the king commanded <char style="add">that</char> the burnt offering and the sin offering <char style="add">should be made</char> for all Israel. <verse eid="2CH 29:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 29:25" />And he set the Levites in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> with cymbals, with psalteries, and with harps, according to the commandment of David, and of Gad the king’s seer, and Nathan the prophet: for <char style="add">so was</char> the commandment of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> by his prophets.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">commandment of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: Heb. commandment by the hand of the <char style="nd">LORD</char></char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by: Heb. by the hand of</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 29:26" />And the Levites stood with the instruments of David, and the priests with the trumpets. <verse eid="2CH 29:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 29:27" />And Hezekiah commanded to offer the burnt offering upon the altar. And when the burnt offering began, the song of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> began <char style="add">also</char> with the trumpets, and with the instruments <char style="add">ordained</char> by David king of Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">when: Heb. in the time</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the instruments: Heb. hands of instruments</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 29:28" />And all the congregation worshipped, and the singers sang, and the trumpeters sounded: <char style="add">and</char> all <char style="add">this continued</char> until the burnt offering was finished.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">singers: Heb. song</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 29:29" />And when they had made an end of offering, the king and all that were present with him bowed themselves, and worshipped.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 29:30" />Moreover Hezekiah the king and the princes commanded the Levites to sing praise unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> with the words of David, and of Asaph the seer. And they sang praises with gladness, and they bowed their heads and worshipped. <verse eid="2CH 29:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 29:31" />Then Hezekiah answered and said, Now ye have consecrated yourselves unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, come near and bring sacrifices and thank offerings into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. And the congregation brought in sacrifices and thank offerings; and as many as were of a free heart burnt offerings.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">consecrated…: or, filled your hand</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 29:32" />And the number of the burnt offerings, which the congregation brought, was threescore and ten bullocks, an hundred rams, <char style="add">and</char> two hundred lambs: all these <char style="add">were</char> for a burnt offering to the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 29:33" />And the consecrated things <char style="add">were</char> six hundred oxen and three thousand sheep. <verse eid="2CH 29:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 29:34" />But the priests were too few, so that they could not flay all the burnt offerings: wherefore their brethren the Levites did help them, till the work was ended, and until the <char style="add">other</char> priests had sanctified themselves: for the Levites <char style="add">were</char> more upright in heart to sanctify themselves than the priests.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">did help…: Heb. strengthened them</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 29:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 29:35" />And also the burnt offerings <char style="add">were</char> in abundance, with the fat of the peace offerings, and the drink offerings for <char style="add">every</char> burnt offering. So the service of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was set in order. <verse eid="2CH 29:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 29:36" />And Hezekiah rejoiced, and all the people, that God had prepared the people: for the thing was <char style="add">done</char> suddenly.<verse eid="2CH 29:36" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 29" />
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="2CH 30" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 30:1" />And Hezekiah sent to all Israel and Judah, and wrote letters also to Ephraim and Manasseh, that they should come to the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> at Jerusalem, to keep the passover unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 30:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 30:2" />For the king had taken counsel, and his princes, and all the congregation in Jerusalem, to keep the passover in the second month. <verse eid="2CH 30:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 30:3" />For they could not keep it at that time, because the priests had not sanctified themselves sufficiently, neither had the people gathered themselves together to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 30:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 30:4" />And the thing pleased the king and all the congregation.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">pleased…: Heb. was right in the eyes of the king</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 30:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 30:5" />So they established a decree to make proclamation throughout all Israel, from Beer-sheba even to Dan, that they should come to keep the passover unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel at Jerusalem: for they had not done <char style="add">it</char> of a long <char style="add">time in such sort</char> as it was written. <verse eid="2CH 30:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 30:6" />So the posts went with the letters from the king and his princes throughout all Israel and Judah, and according to the commandment of the king, saying, Ye children of Israel, turn again unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, and he will return to the remnant of you, that are escaped out of the hand of the kings of Assyria.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from: Heb. from the hand</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 30:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 30:7" />And be not ye like your fathers, and like your brethren, which trespassed against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers, <char style="add">who</char> therefore gave them up to desolation, as ye see. <verse eid="2CH 30:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 30:8" />Now be ye not stiffnecked, as your fathers <char style="add">were, but</char> yield yourselves unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and enter into his sanctuary, which he hath sanctified for ever: and serve the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, that the fierceness of his wrath may turn away from you.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">be ye…: Heb. harden not your necks</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">yield…: Heb. give the hand</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 30:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 30:9" />For if ye turn again unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, your brethren and your children <char style="add">shall find</char> compassion before them that lead them captive, so that they shall come again into this land: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God <char style="add">is</char> gracious and merciful, and will not turn away <char style="add">his</char> face from you, if ye return unto him. <verse eid="2CH 30:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 30:10" />So the posts passed from city to city through the country of Ephraim and Manasseh even unto Zebulun: but they laughed them to scorn, and mocked them. <verse eid="2CH 30:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 30:11" />Nevertheless divers of Asher and Manasseh and of Zebulun humbled themselves, and came to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 30:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 30:12" />Also in Judah the hand of God was to give them one heart to do the commandment of the king and of the princes, by the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<verse eid="2CH 30:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 30:13" />¶ And there assembled at Jerusalem much people to keep the feast of unleavened bread in the second month, a very great congregation. <verse eid="2CH 30:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 30:14" />And they arose and took away the altars that <char style="add">were</char> in Jerusalem, and all the altars for incense took they away, and cast <char style="add">them</char> into the brook Kidron. <verse eid="2CH 30:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 30:15" />Then they killed the passover on the fourteenth <char style="add">day</char> of the second month: and the priests and the Levites were ashamed, and sanctified themselves, and brought in the burnt offerings into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 30:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 30:16" />And they stood in their place after their manner, according to the law of Moses the man of God: the priests sprinkled the blood, <char style="add">which they received</char> of the hand of the Levites.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">their place: Heb. their standing</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 30:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 30:17" />For <char style="add">there were</char> many in the congregation that were not sanctified: therefore the Levites had the charge of the killing of the passovers for every one <char style="add">that was</char> not clean, to sanctify <char style="add">them</char> unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 30:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 30:18" />For a multitude of the people, <char style="add">even</char> many of Ephraim, and Manasseh, Issachar, and Zebulun, had not cleansed themselves, yet did they eat the passover otherwise than it was written. But Hezekiah prayed for them, saying, The good <char style="nd">LORD</char> pardon every one <verse eid="2CH 30:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 30:19" /><char style="add">That</char> prepareth his heart to seek God, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of his fathers, though <char style="add">he be</char> not <char style="add">cleansed</char> according to the purification of the sanctuary. <verse eid="2CH 30:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 30:20" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hearkened to Hezekiah, and healed the people.<verse eid="2CH 30:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 30:21" />And the children of Israel that were present at Jerusalem kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with great gladness: and the Levites and the priests praised the <char style="nd">LORD</char> day by day, <char style="add">singing</char> with loud instruments unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">loud…: Heb. instruments of strength</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 30:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 30:22" />And Hezekiah spake comfortably unto all the Levites that taught the good knowledge of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: and they did eat throughout the feast seven days, offering peace offerings, and making confession to the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">comfortably…: Heb. to the heart of all</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 30:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 30:23" />And the whole assembly took counsel to keep other seven days: and they kept <char style="add">other</char> seven days with gladness. <verse eid="2CH 30:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 30:24" />For Hezekiah king of Judah did give to the congregation a thousand bullocks and seven thousand sheep; and the princes gave to the congregation a thousand bullocks and ten thousand sheep: and a great number of priests sanctified themselves.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">did give: Heb. lifted up, or, offered</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gave: Heb. lifted up, or, offered</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 30:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 30:25" />And all the congregation of Judah, with the priests and the Levites, and all the congregation that came out of Israel, and the strangers that came out of the land of Israel, and that dwelt in Judah, rejoiced. <verse eid="2CH 30:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 30:26" />So there was great joy in Jerusalem: for since the time of Solomon the son of David king of Israel <char style="add">there was</char> not the like in Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 30:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 30:27" />¶ Then the priests the Levites arose and blessed the people: and their voice was heard, and their prayer came <char style="add">up</char> to his holy dwelling place, <char style="add">even</char> unto heaven.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">his holy…: Heb. the habitation of his holiness</char></note><verse eid="2CH 30:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 30" />
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="2CH 31" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 31:1" />Now when all this was finished, all Israel that were present went out to the cities of Judah, and brake the images in pieces, and cut down the groves, and threw down the high places and the altars out of all Judah and Benjamin, in Ephraim also and Manasseh, until they had utterly destroyed them all. Then all the children of Israel returned, every man to his possession, into their own cities.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">images: Heb. statues</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">until…: Heb. until to make an end</char></note><verse eid="2CH 31:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 31:2" />¶ And Hezekiah appointed the courses of the priests and the Levites after their courses, every man according to his service, the priests and Levites for burnt offerings and for peace offerings, to minister, and to give thanks, and to praise in the gates of the tents of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 31:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 31:3" /><char style="add">He appointed</char> also the king’s portion of his substance for the burnt offerings, <char style="add">to wit</char>, for the morning and evening burnt offerings, and the burnt offerings for the sabbaths, and for the new moons, and for the set feasts, as <char style="add">it is</char> written in the law of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 31:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 31:4" />Moreover he commanded the people that dwelt in Jerusalem to give the portion of the priests and the Levites, that they might be encouraged in the law of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<verse eid="2CH 31:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 31:5" />¶ And as soon as the commandment came abroad, the children of Israel brought in abundance the firstfruits of corn, wine, and oil, and honey, and of all the increase of the field; and the tithe of all <char style="add">things</char> brought they in abundantly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">came…: Heb. brake forth</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">honey: or, dates</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 31:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 31:6" />And <char style="add">concerning</char> the children of Israel and Judah, that dwelt in the cities of Judah, they also brought in the tithe of oxen and sheep, and the tithe of holy things which were consecrated unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> their God, and laid <char style="add">them</char> by heaps.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by heaps: Heb. heaps, heaps</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 31:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 31:7" />In the third month they began to lay the foundation of the heaps, and finished <char style="add">them</char> in the seventh month. <verse eid="2CH 31:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 31:8" />And when Hezekiah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they blessed the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and his people Israel. <verse eid="2CH 31:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 31:9" />Then Hezekiah questioned with the priests and the Levites concerning the heaps. <verse eid="2CH 31:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 31:10" />And Azariah the chief priest of the house of Zadok answered him, and said, Since <char style="add">the people</char> began to bring the offerings into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, we have had enough to eat, and have left plenty: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath blessed his people; and that which is left <char style="add">is</char> this great store.<verse eid="2CH 31:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 31:11" />¶ Then Hezekiah commanded to prepare chambers in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; and they prepared <char style="add">them</char>,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">chambers: or, storehouses</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 31:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 31:12" />And brought in the offerings and the tithes and the dedicated <char style="add">things</char> faithfully: over which Cononiah the Levite <char style="add">was</char> ruler, and Shimei his brother <char style="add">was</char> the next. <verse eid="2CH 31:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 31:13" />And Jehiel, and Azaziah, and Nahath, and Asahel, and Jerimoth, and Jozabad, and Eliel, and Ismachiah, and Mahath, and Benaiah, <char style="add">were</char> overseers under the hand of Cononiah and Shimei his brother, at the commandment of Hezekiah the king, and Azariah the ruler of the house of God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">under…: Heb. at the hand</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 31:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 31:14" />And Kore the son of Imnah the Levite, the porter toward the east, <char style="add">was</char> over the freewill offerings of God, to distribute the oblations of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and the most holy things. <verse eid="2CH 31:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 31:15" />And next him <char style="add">were</char> Eden, and Miniamin, and Jeshua, and Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah, in the cities of the priests, in <char style="add">their</char> set office, to give to their brethren by courses, as well to the great as to the small:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">next…: Heb. at his hand</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">set…: or, trust</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 31:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 31:16" />Beside their genealogy of males, from three years old and upward, <char style="add">even</char> unto every one that entereth into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, his daily portion for their service in their charges according to their courses; <verse eid="2CH 31:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 31:17" />Both to the genealogy of the priests by the house of their fathers, and the Levites from twenty years old and upward, in their charges by their courses; <verse eid="2CH 31:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 31:18" />And to the genealogy of all their little ones, their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, through all the congregation: for in their set office they sanctified themselves in holiness:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">set…: or, trust</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 31:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 31:19" />Also of the sons of Aaron the priests, <char style="add">which were</char> in the fields of the suburbs of their cities, in every several city, the men that were expressed by name, to give portions to all the males among the priests, and to all that were reckoned by genealogies among the Levites.<verse eid="2CH 31:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 31:20" />¶ And thus did Hezekiah throughout all Judah, and wrought <char style="add">that which was</char> good and right and truth before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God. <verse eid="2CH 31:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 31:21" />And in every work that he began in the service of the house of God, and in the law, and in the commandments, to seek his God, he did <char style="add">it</char> with all his heart, and prospered.<verse eid="2CH 31:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 31" />
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="2CH 32" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 32:1" />After these things, and the establishment thereof, Sennacherib king of Assyria came, and entered into Judah, and encamped against the fenced cities, and thought to win them for himself.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to win…: Heb. to break them up</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 32:2" />And when Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib was come, and that he was purposed to fight against Jerusalem,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he was…: Heb. his face was to war</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 32:3" />He took counsel with his princes and his mighty men to stop the waters of the fountains which <char style="add">were</char> without the city: and they did help him. <verse eid="2CH 32:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 32:4" />So there was gathered much people together, who stopped all the fountains, and the brook that ran through the midst of the land, saying, Why should the kings of Assyria come, and find much water?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">ran: Heb. overflowed</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 32:5" />Also he strengthened himself, and built up all the wall that was broken, and raised <char style="add">it</char> up to the towers, and another wall without, and repaired Millo <char style="add">in</char> the city of David, and made darts and shields in abundance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">darts: or, swords, or, weapons</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 32:6" />And he set captains of war over the people, and gathered them together to him in the street of the gate of the city, and spake comfortably to them, saying,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">spake…: Heb. he spoke to their heart</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 32:7" />Be strong and courageous, be not afraid nor dismayed for the king of Assyria, nor for all the multitude that <char style="add">is</char> with him: for <char style="add">there be</char> more with us than with him: <verse eid="2CH 32:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 32:8" />With him <char style="add">is</char> an arm of flesh; but with us <char style="add">is</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God to help us, and to fight our battles. And the people rested themselves upon the words of Hezekiah king of Judah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">rested…: Heb. leaned</char></note><verse eid="2CH 32:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 32:9" />¶ After this did Sennacherib king of Assyria send his servants to Jerusalem, (but he <char style="add">himself laid siege</char> against Lachish, and all his power with him,) unto Hezekiah king of Judah, and unto all Judah that <char style="add">were</char> at Jerusalem, saying,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">power: Heb. dominion</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 32:10" />Thus saith Sennacherib king of Assyria, Whereon do ye trust, that ye abide in the siege in Jerusalem?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">siege: or, strong hold</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 32:11" />Doth not Hezekiah persuade you to give over yourselves to die by famine and by thirst, saying, The <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God shall deliver us out of the hand of the king of Assyria? <verse eid="2CH 32:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 32:12" />Hath not the same Hezekiah taken away his high places and his altars, and commanded Judah and Jerusalem, saying, Ye shall worship before one altar, and burn incense upon it? <verse eid="2CH 32:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 32:13" />Know ye not what I and my fathers have done unto all the people of <char style="add">other</char> lands? were the gods of the nations of those lands any ways able to deliver their lands out of mine hand? <verse eid="2CH 32:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 32:14" />Who <char style="add">was there</char> among all the gods of those nations that my fathers utterly destroyed, that could deliver his people out of mine hand, that your God should be able to deliver you out of mine hand? <verse eid="2CH 32:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 32:15" />Now therefore let not Hezekiah deceive you, nor persuade you on this manner, neither yet believe him: for no god of any nation or kingdom was able to deliver his people out of mine hand, and out of the hand of my fathers: how much less shall your God deliver you out of mine hand? <verse eid="2CH 32:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 32:16" />And his servants spake yet <char style="add">more</char> against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God, and against his servant Hezekiah. <verse eid="2CH 32:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 32:17" />He wrote also letters to rail on the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, and to speak against him, saying, As the gods of the nations of <char style="add">other</char> lands have not delivered their people out of mine hand, so shall not the God of Hezekiah deliver his people out of mine hand. <verse eid="2CH 32:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 32:18" />Then they cried with a loud voice in the Jews’ speech unto the people of Jerusalem that <char style="add">were</char> on the wall, to affright them, and to trouble them; that they might take the city. <verse eid="2CH 32:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 32:19" />And they spake against the God of Jerusalem, as against the gods of the people of the earth, <char style="add">which were</char> the work of the hands of man. <verse eid="2CH 32:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 32:20" />And for this <char style="add">cause</char> Hezekiah the king, and the prophet Isaiah the son of Amoz, prayed and cried to heaven.<verse eid="2CH 32:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 32:21" />¶ And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sent an angel, which cut off all the mighty men of valour, and the leaders and captains in the camp of the king of Assyria. So he returned with shame of face to his own land. And when he was come into the house of his god, they that came forth of his own bowels slew him there with the sword.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">slew…: Heb. made him fall</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 32:22" />Thus the <char style="nd">LORD</char> saved Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of Sennacherib the king of Assyria, and from the hand of all <char style="add">other</char>, and guided them on every side. <verse eid="2CH 32:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 32:23" />And many brought gifts unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> to Jerusalem, and presents to Hezekiah king of Judah: so that he was magnified in the sight of all nations from thenceforth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">presents: Heb. precious things</char></note><verse eid="2CH 32:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 32:24" />¶ In those days Hezekiah was sick to the death, and prayed unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: and he spake unto him, and he gave him a sign.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gave…: or, wrought a miracle for him</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 32:25" />But Hezekiah rendered not again according to the benefit <char style="add">done</char> unto him; for his heart was lifted up: therefore there was wrath upon him, and upon Judah and Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 32:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 32:26" />Notwithstanding Hezekiah humbled himself for the pride of his heart, <char style="add">both</char> he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the wrath of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> came not upon them in the days of Hezekiah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">pride: Heb. lifting up</char></note><verse eid="2CH 32:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 32:27" />¶ And Hezekiah had exceeding much riches and honour: and he made himself treasuries for silver, and for gold, and for precious stones, and for spices, and for shields, and for all manner of pleasant jewels;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">pleasant…: Heb. instruments of desire</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 32:28" />Storehouses also for the increase of corn, and wine, and oil; and stalls for all manner of beasts, and cotes for flocks. <verse eid="2CH 32:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 32:29" />Moreover he provided him cities, and possessions of flocks and herds in abundance: for God had given him substance very much. <verse eid="2CH 32:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 32:30" />This same Hezekiah also stopped the upper watercourse of Gihon, and brought it straight down to the west side of the city of David. And Hezekiah prospered in all his works.<verse eid="2CH 32:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 32:31" />¶ Howbeit in <char style="add">the business of</char> the ambassadors of the princes of Babylon, who sent unto him to enquire of the wonder that was <char style="add">done</char> in the land, God left him, to try him, that he might know all <char style="add">that was</char> in his heart.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">ambassadors: Heb. interpreters</char></note><verse eid="2CH 32:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 32:32" />¶ Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and his goodness, behold, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the vision of Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, <char style="add">and</char> in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">goodness: Heb. kindnesses</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 32:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 32:33" />And Hezekiah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the chiefest of the sepulchres of the sons of David: and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem did him honour at his death. And Manasseh his son reigned in his stead.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">chiefest: or, highest</char></note><verse eid="2CH 32:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 32" />
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="2CH 33" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 33:1" />Manasseh <char style="add">was</char> twelve years old when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty and five years in Jerusalem: <verse eid="2CH 33:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 33:2" />But did <char style="add">that which was</char> evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, like unto the abominations of the heathen, whom the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had cast out before the children of Israel.<verse eid="2CH 33:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 33:3" />¶ For he built again the high places which Hezekiah his father had broken down, and he reared up altars for Baalim, and made groves, and worshipped all the host of heaven, and served them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he built…: Heb. he returned and built</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 33:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 33:4" />Also he built altars in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, whereof the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had said, In Jerusalem shall my name be for ever. <verse eid="2CH 33:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 33:5" />And he built altars for all the host of heaven in the two courts of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 33:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 33:6" />And he caused his children to pass through the fire in the valley of the son of Hinnom: also he observed times, and used enchantments, and used witchcraft, and dealt with a familiar spirit, and with wizards: he wrought much evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to provoke him to anger. <verse eid="2CH 33:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 33:7" />And he set a carved image, the idol which he had made, in the house of God, of which God had said to David and to Solomon his son, In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen before all the tribes of Israel, will I put my name for ever: <verse eid="2CH 33:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 33:8" />Neither will I any more remove the foot of Israel from out of the land which I have appointed for your fathers; so that they will take heed to do all that I have commanded them, according to the whole law and the statutes and the ordinances by the hand of Moses. <verse eid="2CH 33:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 33:9" />So Manasseh made Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to err, <char style="add">and</char> to do worse than the heathen, whom the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had destroyed before the children of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 33:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 33:10" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake to Manasseh, and to his people: but they would not hearken.<verse eid="2CH 33:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 33:11" />¶ Wherefore the <char style="nd">LORD</char> brought upon them the captains of the host of the king of Assyria, which took Manasseh among the thorns, and bound him with fetters, and carried him to Babylon.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of the king: Heb. which were the king’s</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fetters: or, chains</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 33:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 33:12" />And when he was in affliction, he besought the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God, and humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers, <verse eid="2CH 33:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 33:13" />And prayed unto him: and he was intreated of him, and heard his supplication, and brought him again to Jerusalem into his kingdom. Then Manasseh knew that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> he <char style="add">was</char> God. <verse eid="2CH 33:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 33:14" />Now after this he built a wall without the city of David, on the west side of Gihon, in the valley, even to the entering in at the fish gate, and compassed about Ophel, and raised it up a very great height, and put captains of war in all the fenced cities of Judah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ophel: or, the tower</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 33:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 33:15" />And he took away the strange gods, and the idol out of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and all the altars that he had built in the mount of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and in Jerusalem, and cast <char style="add">them</char> out of the city. <verse eid="2CH 33:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 33:16" />And he repaired the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and sacrificed thereon peace offerings and thank offerings, and commanded Judah to serve the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 33:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 33:17" />Nevertheless the people did sacrifice still in the high places, <char style="add">yet</char> unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> their God only.<verse eid="2CH 33:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 33:18" />¶ Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and his prayer unto his God, and the words of the seers that spake to him in the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, behold, they <char style="add">are written</char> in the book of the kings of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 33:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 33:19" />His prayer also, and <char style="add">how God</char> was intreated of him, and all his sin, and his trespass, and the places wherein he built high places, and set up groves and graven images, before he was humbled: behold, they <char style="add">are</char> written among the sayings of the seers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the seers: or, Hosai</char></note><verse eid="2CH 33:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 33:20" />¶ So Manasseh slept with his fathers, and they buried him in his own house: and Amon his son reigned in his stead.<verse eid="2CH 33:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 33:21" />¶ Amon <char style="add">was</char> two and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned two years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 33:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 33:22" />But he did <char style="add">that which was</char> evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, as did Manasseh his father: for Amon sacrificed unto all the carved images which Manasseh his father had made, and served them; <verse eid="2CH 33:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 33:23" />And humbled not himself before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, as Manasseh his father had humbled himself; but Amon trespassed more and more.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">trespassed more and more: Heb. multiplied trespass</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 33:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 33:24" />And his servants conspired against him, and slew him in his own house.<verse eid="2CH 33:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 33:25" />¶ But the people of the land slew all them that had conspired against king Amon; and the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his stead.<verse eid="2CH 33:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 33" />
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="2CH 34" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 34:1" />Josiah <char style="add">was</char> eight years old when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem one and thirty years. <verse eid="2CH 34:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 34:2" />And he did <char style="add">that which was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and walked in the ways of David his father, and declined <char style="add">neither</char> to the right hand, nor to the left.<verse eid="2CH 34:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 34:3" />¶ For in the eighth year of his reign, while he was yet young, he began to seek after the God of David his father: and in the twelfth year he began to purge Judah and Jerusalem from the high places, and the groves, and the carved images, and the molten images. <verse eid="2CH 34:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 34:4" />And they brake down the altars of Baalim in his presence; and the images, that <char style="add">were</char> on high above them, he cut down; and the groves, and the carved images, and the molten images, he brake in pieces, and made dust <char style="add">of them</char>, and strowed <char style="add">it</char> upon the graves of them that had sacrificed unto them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the images: or, the sun images</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">graves: Heb. face of the graves</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 34:5" />And he burnt the bones of the priests upon their altars, and cleansed Judah and Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 34:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 34:6" />And <char style="add">so did he</char> in the cities of Manasseh, and Ephraim, and Simeon, even unto Naphtali, with their mattocks round about.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mattocks: or, mauls</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 34:7" />And when he had broken down the altars and the groves, and had beaten the graven images into powder, and cut down all the idols throughout all the land of Israel, he returned to Jerusalem.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">into…: Heb. to make powder</char></note><verse eid="2CH 34:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 34:8" />¶ Now in the eighteenth year of his reign, when he had purged the land, and the house, he sent Shaphan the son of Azaliah, and Maaseiah the governor of the city, and Joah the son of Joahaz the recorder, to repair the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God. <verse eid="2CH 34:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 34:9" />And when they came to Hilkiah the high priest, they delivered the money that was brought into the house of God, which the Levites that kept the doors had gathered of the hand of Manasseh and Ephraim, and of all the remnant of Israel, and of all Judah and Benjamin; and they returned to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 34:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 34:10" />And they put <char style="add">it</char> in the hand of the workmen that had the oversight of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and they gave it to the workmen that wrought in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to repair and amend the house: <verse eid="2CH 34:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 34:11" />Even to the artificers and builders gave they <char style="add">it</char>, to buy hewn stone, and timber for couplings, and to floor the houses which the kings of Judah had destroyed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to floor: or, to rafter</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 34:12" />And the men did the work faithfully: and the overseers of them <char style="add">were</char> Jahath and Obadiah, the Levites, of the sons of Merari; and Zechariah and Meshullam, of the sons of the Kohathites, to set <char style="add">it</char> forward; and <char style="add">other of</char> the Levites, all that could skill of instruments of musick. <verse eid="2CH 34:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 34:13" />Also <char style="add">they were</char> over the bearers of burdens, and <char style="add">were</char> overseers of all that wrought the work in any manner of service: and of the Levites <char style="add">there were</char> scribes, and officers, and porters.<verse eid="2CH 34:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 34:14" />¶ And when they brought out the money that was brought into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, Hilkiah the priest found a book of the law of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">given</char> by Moses.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by: Heb. by the hand of</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 34:15" />And Hilkiah answered and said to Shaphan the scribe, I have found the book of the law in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. And Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan. <verse eid="2CH 34:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 34:16" />And Shaphan carried the book to the king, and brought the king word back again, saying, All that was committed to thy servants, they do <char style="add">it</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to thy…: Heb. to the hand of, etc</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 34:17" />And they have gathered together the money that was found in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and have delivered it into the hand of the overseers, and to the hand of the workmen.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gathered together: Heb. poured out, or, melted</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 34:18" />Then Shaphan the scribe told the king, saying, Hilkiah the priest hath given me a book. And Shaphan read it before the king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">it: Heb. in it</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 34:19" />And it came to pass, when the king had heard the words of the law, that he rent his clothes. <verse eid="2CH 34:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 34:20" />And the king commanded Hilkiah, and Ahikam the son of Shaphan, and Abdon the son of Micah, and Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah a servant of the king’s, saying,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Abdon: or, Achbor</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 34:21" />Go, enquire of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> for me, and for them that are left in Israel and in Judah, concerning the words of the book that is found: for great <char style="add">is</char> the wrath of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> that is poured out upon us, because our fathers have not kept the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to do after all that is written in this book. <verse eid="2CH 34:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 34:22" />And Hilkiah, and <char style="add">they</char> that the king <char style="add">had appointed</char>, went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tikvath, the son of Hasrah, keeper of the wardrobe; (now she dwelt in Jerusalem in the college:) and they spake to her to that <char style="add">effect</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hasrah: also called, Harhas</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wardrobe: Heb. garments</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in the college: or, in the school, or, in the second part</char></note><verse eid="2CH 34:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 34:23" />¶ And she answered them, Thus saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel, Tell ye the man that sent you to me, <verse eid="2CH 34:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 34:24" />Thus saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, Behold, I will bring evil upon this place, and upon the inhabitants thereof, <char style="add">even</char> all the curses that are written in the book which they have read before the king of Judah: <verse eid="2CH 34:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 34:25" />Because they have forsaken me, and have burned incense unto other gods, that they might provoke me to anger with all the works of their hands; therefore my wrath shall be poured out upon this place, and shall not be quenched. <verse eid="2CH 34:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 34:26" />And as for the king of Judah, who sent you to enquire of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, so shall ye say unto him, Thus saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel <char style="add">concerning</char> the words which thou hast heard; <verse eid="2CH 34:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 34:27" />Because thine heart was tender, and thou didst humble thyself before God, when thou heardest his words against this place, and against the inhabitants thereof, and humbledst thyself before me, and didst rend thy clothes, and weep before me; I have even heard <char style="add">thee</char> also, saith the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 34:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 34:28" />Behold, I will gather thee to thy fathers, and thou shalt be gathered to thy grave in peace, neither shall thine eyes see all the evil that I will bring upon this place, and upon the inhabitants of the same. So they brought the king word again.<verse eid="2CH 34:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 34:29" />¶ Then the king sent and gathered together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 34:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 34:30" />And the king went up into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and all the men of Judah, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and the priests, and the Levites, and all the people, great and small: and he read in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant that was found in the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">great…: Heb. from great even to small</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 34:31" />And the king stood in his place, and made a covenant before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to walk after the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and to keep his commandments, and his testimonies, and his statutes, with all his heart, and with all his soul, to perform the words of the covenant which are written in this book. <verse eid="2CH 34:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 34:32" />And he caused all that were present in Jerusalem and Benjamin to stand <char style="add">to it</char>. And the inhabitants of Jerusalem did according to the covenant of God, the God of their fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 34:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 34:33" />And Josiah took away all the abominations out of all the countries that <char style="add">pertained</char> to the children of Israel, and made all that were present in Israel to serve, <char style="add">even</char> to serve the <char style="nd">LORD</char> their God. <char style="add">And</char> all his days they departed not from following the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, the God of their fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from…: Heb. from after</char></note><verse eid="2CH 34:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 34" />
  <chapter number="35" style="c" sid="2CH 35" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 35:1" />Moreover Josiah kept a passover unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> in Jerusalem: and they killed the passover on the fourteenth <char style="add">day</char> of the first month. <verse eid="2CH 35:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 35:2" />And he set the priests in their charges, and encouraged them to the service of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, <verse eid="2CH 35:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 35:3" />And said unto the Levites that taught all Israel, which were holy unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, Put the holy ark in the house which Solomon the son of David king of Israel did build; <char style="add">it shall</char> not <char style="add">be</char> a burden upon <char style="add">your</char> shoulders: serve now the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, and his people Israel, <verse eid="2CH 35:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 35:4" />And prepare <char style="add">yourselves</char> by the houses of your fathers, after your courses, according to the writing of David king of Israel, and according to the writing of Solomon his son. <verse eid="2CH 35:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 35:5" />And stand in the holy <char style="add">place</char> according to the divisions of the families of the fathers of your brethren the people, and <char style="add">after</char> the division of the families of the Levites.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the families of the fathers: Heb. the house of the fathers</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the people: Heb. the sons of the people</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 35:6" />So kill the passover, and sanctify yourselves, and prepare your brethren, that <char style="add">they</char> may do according to the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> by the hand of Moses. <verse eid="2CH 35:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 35:7" />And Josiah gave to the people, of the flock, lambs and kids, all for the passover offerings, for all that were present, to the number of thirty thousand, and three thousand bullocks: these <char style="add">were</char> of the king’s substance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gave: Heb. offered</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 35:8" />And his princes gave willingly unto the people, to the priests, and to the Levites: Hilkiah and Zechariah and Jehiel, rulers of the house of God, gave unto the priests for the passover offerings two thousand and six hundred <char style="add">small cattle</char>, and three hundred oxen.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gave willingly: Heb. offered, etc</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 35:9" />Conaniah also, and Shemaiah and Nethaneel, his brethren, and Hashabiah and Jeiel and Jozabad, chief of the Levites, gave unto the Levites for passover offerings five thousand <char style="add">small cattle</char>, and five hundred oxen.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gave: Heb. offered</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 35:10" />So the service was prepared, and the priests stood in their place, and the Levites in their courses, according to the king’s commandment. <verse eid="2CH 35:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 35:11" />And they killed the passover, and the priests sprinkled <char style="add">the blood</char> from their hands, and the Levites flayed <char style="add">them</char>. <verse eid="2CH 35:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 35:12" />And they removed the burnt offerings, that they might give according to the divisions of the families of the people, to offer unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, as <char style="add">it is</char> written in the book of Moses. And so <char style="add">did they</char> with the oxen. <verse eid="2CH 35:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 35:13" />And they roasted the passover with fire according to the ordinance: but the <char style="add">other</char> holy <char style="add">offerings</char> sod they in pots, and in caldrons, and in pans, and divided <char style="add">them</char> speedily among all the people.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">divided…: Heb. made them run</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 35:14" />And afterward they made ready for themselves, and for the priests: because the priests the sons of Aaron <char style="add">were busied</char> in offering of burnt offerings and the fat until night; therefore the Levites prepared for themselves, and for the priests the sons of Aaron. <verse eid="2CH 35:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 35:15" />And the singers the sons of Asaph <char style="add">were</char> in their place, according to the commandment of David, and Asaph, and Heman, and Jeduthun the king’s seer; and the porters <char style="add">waited</char> at every gate; they might not depart from their service; for their brethren the Levites prepared for them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">place: Heb. station</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 35:16" />So all the service of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was prepared the same day, to keep the passover, and to offer burnt offerings upon the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, according to the commandment of king Josiah. <verse eid="2CH 35:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 35:17" />And the children of Israel that were present kept the passover at that time, and the feast of unleavened bread seven days.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 35:18" />And there was no passover like to that kept in Israel from the days of Samuel the prophet; neither did all the kings of Israel keep such a passover as Josiah kept, and the priests, and the Levites, and all Judah and Israel that were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 35:19" />In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah was this passover kept.<verse eid="2CH 35:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 35:20" />¶ After all this, when Josiah had prepared the temple, Necho king of Egypt came up to fight against Carchemish by Euphrates: and Josiah went out against him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">temple: Heb. house</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 35:21" />But he sent ambassadors to him, saying, What have I to do with thee, thou king of Judah? <char style="add">I come</char> not against thee this day, but against the house wherewith I have war: for God commanded me to make haste: forbear thee from <char style="add">meddling with</char> God, who <char style="add">is</char> with me, that he destroy thee not.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the house…: Heb. the house of my war</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 35:22" />Nevertheless Josiah would not turn his face from him, but disguised himself, that he might fight with him, and hearkened not unto the words of Necho from the mouth of God, and came to fight in the valley of Megiddo. <verse eid="2CH 35:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 35:23" />And the archers shot at king Josiah; and the king said to his servants, Have me away; for I am sore wounded.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wounded: Heb. made sick</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 35:24" />His servants therefore took him out of that chariot, and put him in the second chariot that he had; and they brought him to Jerusalem, and he died, and was buried in <char style="add">one of</char> the sepulchres of his fathers. And all Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in one…: or, among the sepulchres</char></note><verse eid="2CH 35:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 35:25" />¶ And Jeremiah lamented for Josiah: and all the singing men and the singing women spake of Josiah in their lamentations to this day, and made them an ordinance in Israel: and, behold, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the lamentations. <verse eid="2CH 35:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 35:26" />Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and his goodness, according to <char style="add">that which was</char> written in the law of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">goodness: Heb. kindnesses</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 35:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 35:27" />And his deeds, first and last, behold, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah.<verse eid="2CH 35:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 35" />
  <chapter number="36" style="c" sid="2CH 36" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 36:1" />Then the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and made him king in his father’s stead in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 36:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 36:2" />Jehoahaz <char style="add">was</char> twenty and three years old when he began to reign, and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 36:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 36:3" />And the king of Egypt put him down at Jerusalem, and condemned the land in an hundred talents of silver and a talent of gold.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">put…: Heb. removed him</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 36:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 36:4" />And the king of Egypt made Eliakim his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem, and turned his name to Jehoiakim. And Necho took Jehoahaz his brother, and carried him to Egypt.<verse eid="2CH 36:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 36:5" />¶ Jehoiakim <char style="add">was</char> twenty and five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: and he did <char style="add">that which was</char> evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God. <verse eid="2CH 36:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 36:6" />Against him came up Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and bound him in fetters, to carry him to Babylon.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fetters: or, chains</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 36:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 36:7" />Nebuchadnezzar also carried of the vessels of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> to Babylon, and put them in his temple at Babylon. <verse eid="2CH 36:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 36:8" />Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and his abominations which he did, and that which was found in him, behold, they <char style="add">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah: and Jehoiachin his son reigned in his stead.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Jehoiachin: also called, Jeconiah, or, Coniah</char></note><verse eid="2CH 36:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 36:9" />¶ Jehoiachin <char style="add">was</char> eight years old when he began to reign, and he reigned three months and ten days in Jerusalem: and he did <char style="add">that which was</char> evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 36:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 36:10" />And when the year was expired, king Nebuchadnezzar sent, and brought him to Babylon, with the goodly vessels of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and made Zedekiah his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">when…: Heb. at the return of the year</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">goodly…: Heb. vessels of desire</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Zedekiah…: or, Mattaniah, his father’s brother</char></note><verse eid="2CH 36:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 36:11" />¶ Zedekiah <char style="add">was</char> one and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 36:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 36:12" />And he did <char style="add">that which was</char> evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God, <char style="add">and</char> humbled not himself before Jeremiah the prophet <char style="add">speaking</char> from the mouth of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="2CH 36:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 36:13" />And he also rebelled against king Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear by God: but he stiffened his neck, and hardened his heart from turning unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of Israel.<verse eid="2CH 36:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 36:14" />¶ Moreover all the chief of the priests, and the people, transgressed very much after all the abominations of the heathen; and polluted the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> which he had hallowed in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 36:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 36:15" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers sent to them by his messengers, rising up betimes, and sending; because he had compassion on his people, and on his dwelling place:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by: Heb. by the hand of</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">betimes: that is, continually and carefully</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 36:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 36:16" />But they mocked the messengers of God, and despised his words, and misused his prophets, until the wrath of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> arose against his people, till <char style="add">there was</char> no remedy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">remedy: Heb. healing</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 36:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 36:17" />Therefore he brought upon them the king of the Chaldees, who slew their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary, and had no compassion upon young man or maiden, old man, or him that stooped for age: he gave <char style="add">them</char> all into his hand. <verse eid="2CH 36:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 36:18" />And all the vessels of the house of God, great and small, and the treasures of the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and the treasures of the king, and of his princes; all <char style="add">these</char> he brought to Babylon. <verse eid="2CH 36:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 36:19" />And they burnt the house of God, and brake down the wall of Jerusalem, and burnt all the palaces thereof with fire, and destroyed all the goodly vessels thereof. <verse eid="2CH 36:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 36:20" />And them that had escaped from the sword carried he away to Babylon; where they were servants to him and his sons until the reign of the kingdom of Persia:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">them…: Heb. the remainder from the sword</char></note> <verse eid="2CH 36:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 36:21" />To fulfil the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> by the mouth of Jeremiah, until the land had enjoyed her sabbaths: <char style="add">for</char> as long as she lay desolate she kept sabbath, to fulfil threescore and ten years.<verse eid="2CH 36:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 36:22" />¶ Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">spoken</char> by the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and <char style="add">put it</char> also in writing, saying, <verse eid="2CH 36:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 36:23" />Thus saith Cyrus king of Persia, All the kingdoms of the earth hath the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of heaven given me; and he hath charged me to build him an house in Jerusalem, which <char style="add">is</char> in Judah. Who <char style="add">is there</char> among you of all his people? The <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God <char style="add">be</char> with him, and let him go up.<verse eid="2CH 36:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 36" />
</usx>