<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="DEU" style="id">Deuteronomy</book>
  <para style="h">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Fifth Book of Moses, called Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc2">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc3">Deu</para>
  <para style="mt1">The Fifth Book of Moses, called Deuteronomy</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="DEU 1" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 1:1" />These <char style="add">be</char> the words which Moses spake unto all Israel on this side Jordan in the wilderness, in the plain over against the Red <char style="add">sea</char>, between Paran, and Tophel, and Laban, and Hazeroth, and Dizahab.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the Red…: or, Zuph</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 1:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 1:2" />(<char style="add">There are</char> eleven days’ <char style="add">journey</char> from Horeb by the way of mount Seir unto Kadesh-barnea.) <verse eid="DEU 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 1:3" />And it came to pass in the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first <char style="add">day</char> of the month, <char style="add">that</char> Moses spake unto the children of Israel, according unto all that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had given him in commandment unto them; <verse eid="DEU 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 1:4" />After he had slain Sihon the king of the Amorites, which dwelt in Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, which dwelt at Astaroth in Edrei: <verse eid="DEU 1:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 1:5" />On this side Jordan, in the land of Moab, began Moses to declare this law, saying, <verse eid="DEU 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 1:6" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God spake unto us in Horeb, saying, Ye have dwelt long enough in this mount: <verse eid="DEU 1:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 1:7" />Turn you, and take your journey, and go to the mount of the Amorites, and unto all <char style="add">the places</char> nigh thereunto, in the plain, in the hills, and in the vale, and in the south, and by the sea side, to the land of the Canaanites, and unto Lebanon, unto the great river, the river Euphrates.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">all…: Heb. all his neighbours</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 1:8" />Behold, I have set the land before you: go in and possess the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, to give unto them and to their seed after them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">set: Heb. given</char></note><verse eid="DEU 1:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 1:9" />¶ And I spake unto you at that time, saying, I am not able to bear you myself alone: <verse eid="DEU 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 1:10" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God hath multiplied you, and, behold, ye <char style="add">are</char> this day as the stars of heaven for multitude. <verse eid="DEU 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 1:11" />(The <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of your fathers make you a thousand times so many more as ye <char style="add">are</char>, and bless you, as he hath promised you!) <verse eid="DEU 1:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 1:12" />How can I myself alone bear your cumbrance, and your burden, and your strife? <verse eid="DEU 1:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 1:13" />Take you wise men, and understanding, and known among your tribes, and I will make them rulers over you.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Take: Heb. Give</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 1:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 1:14" />And ye answered me, and said, The thing which thou hast spoken <char style="add">is</char> good <char style="add">for us</char> to do. <verse eid="DEU 1:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 1:15" />So I took the chief of your tribes, wise men, and known, and made them heads over you, captains over thousands, and captains over hundreds, and captains over fifties, and captains over tens, and officers among your tribes.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">made: Heb. gave</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 1:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 1:16" />And I charged your judges at that time, saying, Hear <char style="add">the causes</char> between your brethren, and judge righteously between <char style="add">every</char> man and his brother, and the stranger <char style="add">that is</char> with him. <verse eid="DEU 1:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 1:17" />Ye shall not respect persons in judgment; <char style="add">but</char> ye shall hear the small as well as the great; ye shall not be afraid of the face of man; for the judgment <char style="add">is</char> God’s: and the cause that is too hard for you, bring <char style="add">it</char> unto me, and I will hear it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">respect…: Heb. acknowledge faces</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 1:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 1:18" />And I commanded you at that time all the things which ye should do.<verse eid="DEU 1:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 1:19" />¶ And when we departed from Horeb, we went through all that great and terrible wilderness, which ye saw by the way of the mountain of the Amorites, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God commanded us; and we came to Kadesh-barnea. <verse eid="DEU 1:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 1:20" />And I said unto you, Ye are come unto the mountain of the Amorites, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God doth give unto us. <verse eid="DEU 1:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 1:21" />Behold, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath set the land before thee: go up <char style="add">and</char> possess <char style="add">it</char>, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of thy fathers hath said unto thee; fear not, neither be discouraged.<verse eid="DEU 1:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 1:22" />¶ And ye came near unto me every one of you, and said, We will send men before us, and they shall search us out the land, and bring us word again by what way we must go up, and into what cities we shall come. <verse eid="DEU 1:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 1:23" />And the saying pleased me well: and I took twelve men of you, one of a tribe: <verse eid="DEU 1:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 1:24" />And they turned and went up into the mountain, and came unto the valley of Eshcol, and searched it out. <verse eid="DEU 1:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 1:25" />And they took of the fruit of the land in their hands, and brought <char style="add">it</char> down unto us, and brought us word again, and said, <char style="add">It is</char> a good land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God doth give us. <verse eid="DEU 1:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 1:26" />Notwithstanding ye would not go up, but rebelled against the commandment of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God: <verse eid="DEU 1:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 1:27" />And ye murmured in your tents, and said, Because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hated us, he hath brought us forth out of the land of Egypt, to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites, to destroy us. <verse eid="DEU 1:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 1:28" />Whither shall we go up? our brethren have discouraged our heart, saying, The people <char style="add">is</char> greater and taller than we; the cities <char style="add">are</char> great and walled up to heaven; and moreover we have seen the sons of the Anakims there.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">discouraged: Heb. melted</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 1:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 1:29" />Then I said unto you, Dread not, neither be afraid of them. <verse eid="DEU 1:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 1:30" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God which goeth before you, he shall fight for you, according to all that he did for you in Egypt before your eyes; <verse eid="DEU 1:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 1:31" />And in the wilderness, where thou hast seen how that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God bare thee, as a man doth bear his son, in all the way that ye went, until ye came into this place. <verse eid="DEU 1:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 1:32" />Yet in this thing ye did not believe the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, <verse eid="DEU 1:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 1:33" />Who went in the way before you, to search you out a place to pitch your tents <char style="add">in</char>, in fire by night, to shew you by what way ye should go, and in a cloud by day. <verse eid="DEU 1:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 1:34" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> heard the voice of your words, and was wroth, and sware, saying, <verse eid="DEU 1:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 1:35" />Surely there shall not one of these men of this evil generation see that good land, which I sware to give unto your fathers, <verse eid="DEU 1:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 1:36" />Save Caleb the son of Jephunneh; he shall see it, and to him will I give the land that he hath trodden upon, and to his children, because he hath wholly followed the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wholly…: Heb. fulfilled to go after</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 1:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 1:37" />Also the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was angry with me for your sakes, saying, Thou also shalt not go in thither. <verse eid="DEU 1:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 1:38" /><char style="add">But</char> Joshua the son of Nun, which standeth before thee, he shall go in thither: encourage him: for he shall cause Israel to inherit it. <verse eid="DEU 1:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 1:39" />Moreover your little ones, which ye said should be a prey, and your children, which in that day had no knowledge between good and evil, they shall go in thither, and unto them will I give it, and they shall possess it. <verse eid="DEU 1:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 1:40" />But <char style="add">as for</char> you, turn you, and take your journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red sea. <verse eid="DEU 1:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 1:41" />Then ye answered and said unto me, We have sinned against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, we will go up and fight, according to all that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God commanded us. And when ye had girded on every man his weapons of war, ye were ready to go up into the hill. <verse eid="DEU 1:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 1:42" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Say unto them, Go not up, neither fight; for I <char style="add">am</char> not among you; lest ye be smitten before your enemies. <verse eid="DEU 1:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 1:43" />So I spake unto you; and ye would not hear, but rebelled against the commandment of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and went presumptuously up into the hill.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.43 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">went…: Heb. ye were presumptuous, and went up</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 1:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 1:44" />And the Amorites, which dwelt in that mountain, came out against you, and chased you, as bees do, and destroyed you in Seir, <char style="add">even</char> unto Hormah. <verse eid="DEU 1:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 1:45" />And ye returned and wept before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; but the <char style="nd">LORD</char> would not hearken to your voice, nor give ear unto you. <verse eid="DEU 1:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 1:46" />So ye abode in Kadesh many days, according unto the days that ye abode <char style="add">there</char>.<verse eid="DEU 1:46" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="DEU 2" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 2:1" />Then we turned, and took our journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red sea, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto me: and we compassed mount Seir many days. <verse eid="DEU 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 2:2" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto me, saying, <verse eid="DEU 2:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 2:3" />Ye have compassed this mountain long enough: turn you northward. <verse eid="DEU 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 2:4" />And command thou the people, saying, Ye <char style="add">are</char> to pass through the coast of your brethren the children of Esau, which dwell in Seir; and they shall be afraid of you: take ye good heed unto yourselves therefore: <verse eid="DEU 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 2:5" />Meddle not with them; for I will not give you of their land, no, not so much as a foot breadth; because I have given mount Seir unto Esau <char style="add">for</char> a possession.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">no…: Heb. even to the treading of the sole of the foot</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 2:6" />Ye shall buy meat of them for money, that ye may eat; and ye shall also buy water of them for money, that ye may drink. <verse eid="DEU 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 2:7" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath blessed thee in all the works of thy hand: he knoweth thy walking through this great wilderness: these forty years the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">hath been</char> with thee; thou hast lacked nothing.<verse eid="DEU 2:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 2:8" />And when we passed by from our brethren the children of Esau, which dwelt in Seir, through the way of the plain from Elath, and from Ezion-gaber, we turned and passed by the way of the wilderness of Moab. <verse eid="DEU 2:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 2:9" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Distress not the Moabites, neither contend with them in battle: for I will not give thee of their land <char style="add">for</char> a possession; because I have given Ar unto the children of Lot <char style="add">for</char> a possession.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Distress…: or, Use no hostility against Moab</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 2:10" />The Emims dwelt therein in times past, a people great, and many, and tall, as the Anakims; <verse eid="DEU 2:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 2:11" />Which also were accounted giants, as the Anakims; but the Moabites call them Emims. <verse eid="DEU 2:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 2:12" />The Horims also dwelt in Seir beforetime; but the children of Esau succeeded them, when they had destroyed them from before them, and dwelt in their stead; as Israel did unto the land of his possession, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> gave unto them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">succeeded: Heb. inherited</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">stead: or, room</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 2:13" />Now rise up, <char style="add">said I</char>, and get you over the brook Zered. And we went over the brook Zered.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">brook: or, valley</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 2:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 2:14" />And the space in which we came from Kadesh-barnea, until we were come over the brook Zered, <char style="add">was</char> thirty and eight years; until all the generation of the men of war were wasted out from among the host, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">brook: or, valley</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 2:15" />For indeed the hand of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was against them, to destroy them from among the host, until they were consumed.<verse eid="DEU 2:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 2:16" />¶ So it came to pass, when all the men of war were consumed and dead from among the people, <verse eid="DEU 2:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 2:17" />That the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto me, saying, <verse eid="DEU 2:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 2:18" />Thou art to pass over through Ar, the coast of Moab, this day: <verse eid="DEU 2:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 2:19" />And <char style="add">when</char> thou comest nigh over against the children of Ammon, distress them not, nor meddle with them: for I will not give thee of the land of the children of Ammon <char style="add">any</char> possession; because I have given it unto the children of Lot <char style="add">for</char> a possession. <verse eid="DEU 2:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 2:20" />(That also was accounted a land of giants: giants dwelt therein in old time; and the Ammonites call them Zamzummims;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Zamzummims: also called, Zuzims</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 2:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 2:21" />A people great, and many, and tall, as the Anakims; but the <char style="nd">LORD</char> destroyed them before them; and they succeeded them, and dwelt in their stead: <verse eid="DEU 2:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 2:22" />As he did to the children of Esau, which dwelt in Seir, when he destroyed the Horims from before them; and they succeeded them, and dwelt in their stead even unto this day: <verse eid="DEU 2:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 2:23" />And the Avims which dwelt in Hazerim, <char style="add">even</char> unto Azzah, the Caphtorims, which came forth out of Caphtor, destroyed them, and dwelt in their stead.)<verse eid="DEU 2:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 2:24" />¶ Rise ye up, take your journey, and pass over the river Arnon: behold, I have given into thine hand Sihon the Amorite, king of Heshbon, and his land: begin to possess <char style="add">it</char>, and contend with him in battle.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">begin…: Heb. begin, possess</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 2:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 2:25" />This day will I begin to put the dread of thee and the fear of thee upon the nations <char style="add">that are</char> under the whole heaven, who shall hear report of thee, and shall tremble, and be in anguish because of thee.<verse eid="DEU 2:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 2:26" />¶ And I sent messengers out of the wilderness of Kedemoth unto Sihon king of Heshbon with words of peace, saying, <verse eid="DEU 2:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 2:27" />Let me pass through thy land: I will go along by the high way, I will neither turn unto the right hand nor to the left. <verse eid="DEU 2:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 2:28" />Thou shalt sell me meat for money, that I may eat; and give me water for money, that I may drink: only I will pass through on my feet; <verse eid="DEU 2:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 2:29" />(As the children of Esau which dwell in Seir, and the Moabites which dwell in Ar, did unto me;) until I shall pass over Jordan into the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God giveth us. <verse eid="DEU 2:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 2:30" />But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass by him: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hardened his spirit, and made his heart obstinate, that he might deliver him into thy hand, as <char style="add">appeareth</char> this day. <verse eid="DEU 2:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 2:31" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Behold, I have begun to give Sihon and his land before thee: begin to possess, that thou mayest inherit his land. <verse eid="DEU 2:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 2:32" />Then Sihon came out against us, he and all his people, to fight at Jahaz. <verse eid="DEU 2:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 2:33" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God delivered him before us; and we smote him, and his sons, and all his people. <verse eid="DEU 2:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 2:34" />And we took all his cities at that time, and utterly destroyed the men, and the women, and the little ones, of every city, we left none to remain:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the men…: Heb. every city of men, and women, and little ones</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 2:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 2:35" />Only the cattle we took for a prey unto ourselves, and the spoil of the cities which we took. <verse eid="DEU 2:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 2:36" />From Aroer, which <char style="add">is</char> by the brink of the river of Arnon, and <char style="add">from</char> the city that <char style="add">is</char> by the river, even unto Gilead, there was not one city too strong for us: the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God delivered all unto us: <verse eid="DEU 2:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 2:37" />Only unto the land of the children of Ammon thou camest not, <char style="add">nor</char> unto any place of the river Jabbok, nor unto the cities in the mountains, nor unto whatsoever the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God forbad us.<verse eid="DEU 2:37" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="DEU 3" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 3:1" />Then we turned, and went up the way to Bashan: and Og the king of Bashan came out against us, he and all his people, to battle at Edrei. <verse eid="DEU 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 3:2" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Fear him not: for I will deliver him, and all his people, and his land, into thy hand; and thou shalt do unto him as thou didst unto Sihon king of the Amorites, which dwelt at Heshbon. <verse eid="DEU 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 3:3" />So the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God delivered into our hands Og also, the king of Bashan, and all his people: and we smote him until none was left to him remaining. <verse eid="DEU 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 3:4" />And we took all his cities at that time, there was not a city which we took not from them, threescore cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan. <verse eid="DEU 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 3:5" />All these cities <char style="add">were</char> fenced with high walls, gates, and bars; beside unwalled towns a great many. <verse eid="DEU 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 3:6" />And we utterly destroyed them, as we did unto Sihon king of Heshbon, utterly destroying the men, women, and children, of every city. <verse eid="DEU 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 3:7" />But all the cattle, and the spoil of the cities, we took for a prey to ourselves. <verse eid="DEU 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 3:8" />And we took at that time out of the hand of the two kings of the Amorites the land that <char style="add">was</char> on this side Jordan, from the river of Arnon unto mount Hermon; <verse eid="DEU 3:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 3:9" />(<char style="add">Which</char> Hermon the Sidonians call Sirion; and the Amorites call it Shenir;) <verse eid="DEU 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 3:10" />All the cities of the plain, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, unto Salchah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan. <verse eid="DEU 3:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 3:11" />For only Og king of Bashan remained of the remnant of giants; behold, his bedstead <char style="add">was</char> a bedstead of iron; <char style="add">is</char> it not in Rabbath of the children of Ammon? nine cubits <char style="add">was</char> the length thereof, and four cubits the breadth of it, after the cubit of a man.<verse eid="DEU 3:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 3:12" />And this land, <char style="add">which</char> we possessed at that time, from Aroer, which <char style="add">is</char> by the river Arnon, and half mount Gilead, and the cities thereof, gave I unto the Reubenites and to the Gadites. <verse eid="DEU 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 3:13" />And the rest of Gilead, and all Bashan, <char style="add">being</char> the kingdom of Og, gave I unto the half tribe of Manasseh; all the region of Argob, with all Bashan, which was called the land of giants. <verse eid="DEU 3:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 3:14" />Jair the son of Manasseh took all the country of Argob unto the coasts of Geshuri and Maachathi; and called them after his own name, Bashan-havoth-jair, unto this day. <verse eid="DEU 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 3:15" />And I gave Gilead unto Machir. <verse eid="DEU 3:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 3:16" />And unto the Reubenites and unto the Gadites I gave from Gilead even unto the river Arnon half the valley, and the border even unto the river Jabbok, <char style="add">which is</char> the border of the children of Ammon; <verse eid="DEU 3:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 3:17" />The plain also, and Jordan, and the coast <char style="add">thereof</char>, from Chinnereth even unto the sea of the plain, <char style="add">even</char> the salt sea, under Ashdoth-pisgah eastward.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ashdoth-pisgah: or, the springs of Pisgah, or, the hill</char></note><verse eid="DEU 3:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 3:18" />¶ And I commanded you at that time, saying, The <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God hath given you this land to possess it: ye shall pass over armed before your brethren the children of Israel, all <char style="add">that are</char> meet for the war.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">meet…: Heb. sons of power</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 3:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 3:19" />But your wives, and your little ones, and your cattle, (<char style="add">for</char> I know that ye have much cattle,) shall abide in your cities which I have given you; <verse eid="DEU 3:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 3:20" />Until the <char style="nd">LORD</char> have given rest unto your brethren, as well as unto you, and <char style="add">until</char> they also possess the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God hath given them beyond Jordan: and <char style="add">then</char> shall ye return every man unto his possession, which I have given you.<verse eid="DEU 3:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 3:21" />¶ And I commanded Joshua at that time, saying, Thine eyes have seen all that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God hath done unto these two kings: so shall the <char style="nd">LORD</char> do unto all the kingdoms whither thou passest. <verse eid="DEU 3:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 3:22" />Ye shall not fear them: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God he shall fight for you. <verse eid="DEU 3:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 3:23" />And I besought the <char style="nd">LORD</char> at that time, saying, <verse eid="DEU 3:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 3:24" />O Lord <char style="nd">GOD</char>, thou hast begun to shew thy servant thy greatness, and thy mighty hand: for what God <char style="add">is there</char> in heaven or in earth, that can do according to thy works, and according to thy might? <verse eid="DEU 3:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 3:25" />I pray thee, let me go over, and see the good land that <char style="add">is</char> beyond Jordan, that goodly mountain, and Lebanon. <verse eid="DEU 3:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 3:26" />But the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was wroth with me for your sakes, and would not hear me: and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Let it suffice thee; speak no more unto me of this matter. <verse eid="DEU 3:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 3:27" />Get thee up into the top of Pisgah, and lift up thine eyes westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and behold <char style="add">it</char> with thine eyes: for thou shalt not go over this Jordan.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Pisgah: or, the hill</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 3:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 3:28" />But charge Joshua, and encourage him, and strengthen him: for he shall go over before this people, and he shall cause them to inherit the land which thou shalt see. <verse eid="DEU 3:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 3:29" />So we abode in the valley over against Beth-peor.<verse eid="DEU 3:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="DEU 4" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 4:1" />Now therefore hearken, O Israel, unto the statutes and unto the judgments, which I teach you, for to do <char style="add">them</char>, that ye may live, and go in and possess the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of your fathers giveth you. <verse eid="DEU 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 4:2" />Ye shall not add unto the word which I command you, neither shall ye diminish <char style="add">ought</char> from it, that ye may keep the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God which I command you. <verse eid="DEU 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 4:3" />Your eyes have seen what the <char style="nd">LORD</char> did because of Baal-peor: for all the men that followed Baal-peor, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath destroyed them from among you. <verse eid="DEU 4:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 4:4" />But ye that did cleave unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God <char style="add">are</char> alive every one of you this day. <verse eid="DEU 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 4:5" />Behold, I have taught you statutes and judgments, even as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> my God commanded me, that ye should do so in the land whither ye go to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 4:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 4:6" />Keep therefore and do <char style="add">them;</char> for this <char style="add">is</char> your wisdom and your understanding in the sight of the nations, which shall hear all these statutes, and say, Surely this great nation <char style="add">is</char> a wise and understanding people. <verse eid="DEU 4:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 4:7" />For what nation <char style="add">is there so</char> great, who <char style="add">hath</char> God <char style="add">so</char> nigh unto them, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God <char style="add">is</char> in all <char style="add">things that</char> we call upon him <char style="add">for</char>? <verse eid="DEU 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 4:8" />And what nation <char style="add">is there so</char> great, that hath statutes and judgments <char style="add">so</char> righteous as all this law, which I set before you this day? <verse eid="DEU 4:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 4:9" />Only take heed to thyself, and keep thy soul diligently, lest thou forget the things which thine eyes have seen, and lest they depart from thy heart all the days of thy life: but teach them thy sons, and thy sons’ sons; <verse eid="DEU 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 4:10" /><char style="add">Specially</char> the day that thou stoodest before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God in Horeb, when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Gather me the people together, and I will make them hear my words, that they may learn to fear me all the days that they shall live upon the earth, and <char style="add">that</char> they may teach their children. <verse eid="DEU 4:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 4:11" />And ye came near and stood under the mountain; and the mountain burned with fire unto the midst of heaven, with darkness, clouds, and thick darkness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">midst: Heb. heart</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 4:12" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto you out of the midst of the fire: ye heard the voice of the words, but saw no similitude; only <char style="add">ye heard</char> a voice.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">only…: Heb. save a voice</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 4:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 4:13" />And he declared unto you his covenant, which he commanded you to perform, <char style="add">even</char> ten commandments; and he wrote them upon two tables of stone.<verse eid="DEU 4:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 4:14" />¶ And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and judgments, that ye might do them in the land whither ye go over to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 4:15" />Take ye therefore good heed unto yourselves; for ye saw no manner of similitude on the day <char style="add">that</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto you in Horeb out of the midst of the fire: <verse eid="DEU 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 4:16" />Lest ye corrupt <char style="add">yourselves</char>, and make you a graven image, the similitude of any figure, the likeness of male or female, <verse eid="DEU 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 4:17" />The likeness of any beast that <char style="add">is</char> on the earth, the likeness of any winged fowl that flieth in the air, <verse eid="DEU 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 4:18" />The likeness of any thing that creepeth on the ground, the likeness of any fish that <char style="add">is</char> in the waters beneath the earth: <verse eid="DEU 4:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 4:19" />And lest thou lift up thine eyes unto heaven, and when thou seest the sun, and the moon, and the stars, <char style="add">even</char> all the host of heaven, shouldest be driven to worship them, and serve them, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath divided unto all nations under the whole heaven.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">divided: or, imparted</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 4:20" />But the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath taken you, and brought you forth out of the iron furnace, <char style="add">even</char> out of Egypt, to be unto him a people of inheritance, as <char style="add">ye are</char> this day. <verse eid="DEU 4:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 4:21" />Furthermore the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was angry with me for your sakes, and sware that I should not go over Jordan, and that I should not go in unto that good land, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance: <verse eid="DEU 4:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 4:22" />But I must die in this land, I must not go over Jordan: but ye shall go over, and possess that good land. <verse eid="DEU 4:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 4:23" />Take heed unto yourselves, lest ye forget the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, which he made with you, and make you a graven image, <char style="add">or</char> the likeness of any <char style="add">thing</char>, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath forbidden thee. <verse eid="DEU 4:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 4:24" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">is</char> a consuming fire, <char style="add">even</char> a jealous God.<verse eid="DEU 4:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 4:25" />¶ When thou shalt beget children, and children’s children, and ye shall have remained long in the land, and shall corrupt <char style="add">yourselves</char>, and make a graven image, <char style="add">or</char> the likeness of any <char style="add">thing</char>, and shall do evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to provoke him to anger: <verse eid="DEU 4:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 4:26" />I call heaven and earth to witness against you this day, that ye shall soon utterly perish from off the land whereunto ye go over Jordan to possess it; ye shall not prolong <char style="add">your</char> days upon it, but shall utterly be destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 4:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 4:27" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall scatter you among the nations, and ye shall be left few in number among the heathen, whither the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall lead you. <verse eid="DEU 4:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 4:28" />And there ye shall serve gods, the work of men’s hands, wood and stone, which neither see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell. <verse eid="DEU 4:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 4:29" />But if from thence thou shalt seek the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, thou shalt find <char style="add">him</char>, if thou seek him with all thy heart and with all thy soul. <verse eid="DEU 4:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 4:30" />When thou art in tribulation, and all these things are come upon thee, <char style="add">even</char> in the latter days, if thou turn to the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and shalt be obedient unto his voice;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">are…: Heb. have found thee</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 4:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 4:31" />(For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">is</char> a merciful God;) he will not forsake thee, neither destroy thee, nor forget the covenant of thy fathers which he sware unto them. <verse eid="DEU 4:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 4:32" />For ask now of the days that are past, which were before thee, since the day that God created man upon the earth, and <char style="add">ask</char> from the one side of heaven unto the other, whether there hath been <char style="add">any such thing</char> as this great thing <char style="add">is</char>, or hath been heard like it? <verse eid="DEU 4:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 4:33" />Did <char style="add">ever</char> people hear the voice of God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as thou hast heard, and live? <verse eid="DEU 4:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 4:34" />Or hath God assayed to go <char style="add">and</char> take him a nation from the midst of <char style="add">another</char> nation, by temptations, by signs, and by wonders, and by war, and by a mighty hand, and by a stretched out arm, and by great terrors, according to all that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God did for you in Egypt before your eyes? <verse eid="DEU 4:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 4:35" />Unto thee it was shewed, that thou mightest know that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> he <char style="add">is</char> God; <char style="add">there is</char> none else beside him. <verse eid="DEU 4:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 4:36" />Out of heaven he made thee to hear his voice, that he might instruct thee: and upon earth he shewed thee his great fire; and thou heardest his words out of the midst of the fire. <verse eid="DEU 4:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 4:37" />And because he loved thy fathers, therefore he chose their seed after them, and brought thee out in his sight with his mighty power out of Egypt; <verse eid="DEU 4:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 4:38" />To drive out nations from before thee greater and mightier than thou <char style="add">art</char>, to bring thee in, to give thee their land <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance, as <char style="add">it is</char> this day. <verse eid="DEU 4:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 4:39" />Know therefore this day, and consider <char style="add">it</char> in thine heart, that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> he <char style="add">is</char> God in heaven above, and upon the earth beneath: <char style="add">there is</char> none else. <verse eid="DEU 4:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 4:40" />Thou shalt keep therefore his statutes, and his commandments, which I command thee this day, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee, and that thou mayest prolong <char style="add">thy</char> days upon the earth, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, for ever.<verse eid="DEU 4:40" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 4:41" />¶ Then Moses severed three cities on this side Jordan toward the sunrising; <verse eid="DEU 4:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 4:42" />That the slayer might flee thither, which should kill his neighbour unawares, and hated him not in times past; and that fleeing unto one of these cities he might live: <verse eid="DEU 4:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 4:43" /><char style="add">Namely</char>, Bezer in the wilderness, in the plain country, of the Reubenites; and Ramoth in Gilead, of the Gadites; and Golan in Bashan, of the Manassites.<verse eid="DEU 4:43" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 4:44" />¶ And this <char style="add">is</char> the law which Moses set before the children of Israel: <verse eid="DEU 4:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 4:45" />These <char style="add">are</char> the testimonies, and the statutes, and the judgments, which Moses spake unto the children of Israel, after they came forth out of Egypt, <verse eid="DEU 4:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 4:46" />On this side Jordan, in the valley over against Beth-peor, in the land of Sihon king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Heshbon, whom Moses and the children of Israel smote, after they were come forth out of Egypt: <verse eid="DEU 4:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 4:47" />And they possessed his land, and the land of Og king of Bashan, two kings of the Amorites, which <char style="add">were</char> on this side Jordan toward the sunrising; <verse eid="DEU 4:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 4:48" />From Aroer, which <char style="add">is</char> by the bank of the river Arnon, even unto mount Sion, which <char style="add">is</char> Hermon, <verse eid="DEU 4:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 4:49" />And all the plain on this side Jordan eastward, even unto the sea of the plain, under the springs of Pisgah.<verse eid="DEU 4:49" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="DEU 5" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 5:1" />And Moses called all Israel, and said unto them, Hear, O Israel, the statutes and judgments which I speak in your ears this day, that ye may learn them, and keep, and do them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">keep…: Heb. keep to do them</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 5:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 5:2" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God made a covenant with us in Horeb. <verse eid="DEU 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 5:3" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> made not this covenant with our fathers, but with us, <char style="add">even</char> us, who <char style="add">are</char> all of us here alive this day. <verse eid="DEU 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 5:4" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> talked with you face to face in the mount out of the midst of the fire, <verse eid="DEU 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 5:5" />(I stood between the <char style="nd">LORD</char> and you at that time, to shew you the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: for ye were afraid by reason of the fire, and went not up into the mount;) saying,<verse eid="DEU 5:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 5:6" />¶ I <char style="add">am</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">bondage: Heb. servants</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 5:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 5:7" />Thou shalt have none other gods before me. <verse eid="DEU 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 5:8" />Thou shalt not make thee <char style="add">any</char> graven image, <char style="add">or</char> any likeness <char style="add">of any thing</char> that <char style="add">is</char> in heaven above, or that <char style="add">is</char> in the earth beneath, or that <char style="add">is</char> in the waters beneath the earth: <verse eid="DEU 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 5:9" />Thou shalt not bow down thyself unto them, nor serve them: for I the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">am</char> a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children unto the third and fourth <char style="add">generation</char> of them that hate me, <verse eid="DEU 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 5:10" />And shewing mercy unto thousands of them that love me and keep my commandments. <verse eid="DEU 5:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 5:11" />Thou shalt not take the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God in vain: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> will not hold <char style="add">him</char> guiltless that taketh his name in vain. <verse eid="DEU 5:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 5:12" />Keep the sabbath day to sanctify it, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath commanded thee. <verse eid="DEU 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 5:13" />Six days thou shalt labour, and do all thy work: <verse eid="DEU 5:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 5:14" />But the seventh day <char style="add">is</char> the sabbath of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: <char style="add">in it</char> thou shalt not do any work, thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, nor thy manservant, nor thy maidservant, nor thine ox, nor thine ass, nor any of thy cattle, nor thy stranger that <char style="add">is</char> within thy gates; that thy manservant and thy maidservant may rest as well as thou. <verse eid="DEU 5:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 5:15" />And remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt, and <char style="add">that</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God brought thee out thence through a mighty hand and by a stretched out arm: therefore the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God commanded thee to keep the sabbath day.<verse eid="DEU 5:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 5:16" />¶ Honour thy father and thy mother, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath commanded thee; that thy days may be prolonged, and that it may go well with thee, in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee. <verse eid="DEU 5:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 5:17" />Thou shalt not kill. <verse eid="DEU 5:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 5:18" />Neither shalt thou commit adultery. <verse eid="DEU 5:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 5:19" />Neither shalt thou steal. <verse eid="DEU 5:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 5:20" />Neither shalt thou bear false witness against thy neighbour. <verse eid="DEU 5:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 5:21" />Neither shalt thou desire thy neighbour’s wife, neither shalt thou covet thy neighbour’s house, his field, or his manservant, or his maidservant, his ox, or his ass, or any <char style="add">thing</char> that <char style="add">is</char> thy neighbour’s.<verse eid="DEU 5:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 5:22" />¶ These words the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto all your assembly in the mount out of the midst of the fire, of the cloud, and of the thick darkness, with a great voice: and he added no more. And he wrote them in two tables of stone, and delivered them unto me.<verse eid="DEU 5:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 5:23" />And it came to pass, when ye heard the voice out of the midst of the darkness, (for the mountain did burn with fire,) that ye came near unto me, <char style="add">even</char> all the heads of your tribes, and your elders; <verse eid="DEU 5:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 5:24" />And ye said, Behold, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God hath shewed us his glory and his greatness, and we have heard his voice out of the midst of the fire: we have seen this day that God doth talk with man, and he liveth. <verse eid="DEU 5:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 5:25" />Now therefore why should we die? for this great fire will consume us: if we hear the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God any more, then we shall die.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">hear: Heb. add to hear</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 5:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 5:26" />For who <char style="add">is there of</char> all flesh, that hath heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as we <char style="add">have</char>, and lived? <verse eid="DEU 5:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 5:27" />Go thou near, and hear all that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God shall say: and speak thou unto us all that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God shall speak unto thee; and we will hear <char style="add">it</char>, and do <char style="add">it</char>. <verse eid="DEU 5:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 5:28" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> heard the voice of your words, when ye spake unto me; and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they have spoken unto thee: they have well said all that they have spoken. <verse eid="DEU 5:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 5:29" />O that there were such an heart in them, that they would fear me, and keep all my commandments always, that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever! <verse eid="DEU 5:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 5:30" />Go say to them, Get you into your tents again. <verse eid="DEU 5:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 5:31" />But as for thee, stand thou here by me, and I will speak unto thee all the commandments, and the statutes, and the judgments, which thou shalt teach them, that they may do <char style="add">them</char> in the land which I give them to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 5:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 5:32" />Ye shall observe to do therefore as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God hath commanded you: ye shall not turn aside to the right hand or to the left. <verse eid="DEU 5:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 5:33" />Ye shall walk in all the ways which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God hath commanded you, that ye may live, and <char style="add">that it may be</char> well with you, and <char style="add">that</char> ye may prolong <char style="add">your</char> days in the land which ye shall possess.<verse eid="DEU 5:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 5" />
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="DEU 6" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 6:1" />Now these <char style="add">are</char> the commandments, the statutes, and the judgments, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God commanded to teach you, that ye might do <char style="add">them</char> in the land whither ye go to possess it:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">go: Heb. pass over</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 6:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 6:2" />That thou mightest fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to keep all his statutes and his commandments, which I command thee, thou, and thy son, and thy son’s son, all the days of thy life; and that thy days may be prolonged.<verse eid="DEU 6:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 6:3" />¶ Hear therefore, O Israel, and observe to do <char style="add">it;</char> that it may be well with thee, and that ye may increase mightily, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of thy fathers hath promised thee, in the land that floweth with milk and honey.<verse eid="DEU 6:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 6:4" />Hear, O Israel: The <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God <char style="add">is</char> one <char style="nd">LORD</char>: <verse eid="DEU 6:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 6:5" />And thou shalt love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might. <verse eid="DEU 6:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 6:6" />And these words, which I command thee this day, shall be in thine heart: <verse eid="DEU 6:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 6:7" />And thou shalt teach them diligently unto thy children, and shalt talk of them when thou sittest in thine house, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">teach: Heb. whet, or, sharpen</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 6:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 6:8" />And thou shalt bind them for a sign upon thine hand, and they shall be as frontlets between thine eyes. <verse eid="DEU 6:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 6:9" />And thou shalt write them upon the posts of thy house, and on thy gates. <verse eid="DEU 6:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 6:10" />And it shall be, when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall have brought thee into the land which he sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give thee great and goodly cities, which thou buildedst not, <verse eid="DEU 6:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 6:11" />And houses full of all good <char style="add">things</char>, which thou filledst not, and wells digged, which thou diggedst not, vineyards and olive trees, which thou plantedst not; when thou shalt have eaten and be full; <verse eid="DEU 6:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 6:12" /><char style="add">Then</char> beware lest thou forget the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, which brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">bondage: Heb. bondmen or, servants</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 6:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 6:13" />Thou shalt fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and serve him, and shalt swear by his name. <verse eid="DEU 6:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 6:14" />Ye shall not go after other gods, of the gods of the people which <char style="add">are</char> round about you; <verse eid="DEU 6:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 6:15" />(For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">is</char> a jealous God among you) lest the anger of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God be kindled against thee, and destroy thee from off the face of the earth.<verse eid="DEU 6:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 6:16" />¶ Ye shall not tempt the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, as ye tempted <char style="add">him</char> in Massah.<verse eid="DEU 6:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 6:17" />Ye shall diligently keep the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, and his testimonies, and his statutes, which he hath commanded thee. <verse eid="DEU 6:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 6:18" />And thou shalt do <char style="add">that which is</char> right and good in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest go in and possess the good land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto thy fathers, <verse eid="DEU 6:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 6:19" />To cast out all thine enemies from before thee, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath spoken. <verse eid="DEU 6:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 6:20" /><char style="add">And</char> when thy son asketh thee in time to come, saying, What <char style="add">mean</char> the testimonies, and the statutes, and the judgments, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God hath commanded you?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: Heb. to morrow</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 6:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 6:21" />Then thou shalt say unto thy son, We were Pharaoh’s bondmen in Egypt; and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> brought us out of Egypt with a mighty hand: <verse eid="DEU 6:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 6:22" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shewed signs and wonders, great and sore, upon Egypt, upon Pharaoh, and upon all his household, before our eyes:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sore: Heb. evil</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 6:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 6:23" />And he brought us out from thence, that he might bring us in, to give us the land which he sware unto our fathers. <verse eid="DEU 6:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 6:24" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> commanded us to do all these statutes, to fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God, for our good always, that he might preserve us alive, as <char style="add">it is</char> at this day. <verse eid="DEU 6:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 6:25" />And it shall be our righteousness, if we observe to do all these commandments before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God, as he hath commanded us.<verse eid="DEU 6:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 6" />
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="DEU 7" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 7:1" />When the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall bring thee into the land whither thou goest to possess it, and hath cast out many nations before thee, the Hittites, and the Girgashites, and the Amorites, and the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, seven nations greater and mightier than thou; <verse eid="DEU 7:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 7:2" />And when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall deliver them before thee; thou shalt smite them, <char style="add">and</char> utterly destroy them; thou shalt make no covenant with them, nor shew mercy unto them: <verse eid="DEU 7:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 7:3" />Neither shalt thou make marriages with them; thy daughter thou shalt not give unto his son, nor his daughter shalt thou take unto thy son. <verse eid="DEU 7:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 7:4" />For they will turn away thy son from following me, that they may serve other gods: so will the anger of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> be kindled against you, and destroy thee suddenly. <verse eid="DEU 7:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 7:5" />But thus shall ye deal with them; ye shall destroy their altars, and break down their images, and cut down their groves, and burn their graven images with fire.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">their images: Heb. their statues, or, pillars</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 7:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 7:6" />For thou <char style="add">art</char> an holy people unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath chosen thee to be a special people unto himself, above all people that <char style="add">are</char> upon the face of the earth. <verse eid="DEU 7:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 7:7" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> did not set his love upon you, nor choose you, because ye were more in number than any people; for ye <char style="add">were</char> the fewest of all people: <verse eid="DEU 7:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 7:8" />But because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> loved you, and because he would keep the oath which he had sworn unto your fathers, hath the <char style="nd">LORD</char> brought you out with a mighty hand, and redeemed you out of the house of bondmen, from the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 7:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 7:9" />Know therefore that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, he <char style="add">is</char> God, the faithful God, which keepeth covenant and mercy with them that love him and keep his commandments to a thousand generations; <verse eid="DEU 7:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 7:10" />And repayeth them that hate him to their face, to destroy them: he will not be slack to him that hateth him, he will repay him to his face. <verse eid="DEU 7:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 7:11" />Thou shalt therefore keep the commandments, and the statutes, and the judgments, which I command thee this day, to do them.<verse eid="DEU 7:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 7:12" />¶ Wherefore it shall come to pass, if ye hearken to these judgments, and keep, and do them, that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall keep unto thee the covenant and the mercy which he sware unto thy fathers:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">if: Heb. because</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 7:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 7:13" />And he will love thee, and bless thee, and multiply thee: he will also bless the fruit of thy womb, and the fruit of thy land, thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep, in the land which he sware unto thy fathers to give thee. <verse eid="DEU 7:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 7:14" />Thou shalt be blessed above all people: there shall not be male or female barren among you, or among your cattle. <verse eid="DEU 7:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 7:15" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> will take away from thee all sickness, and will put none of the evil diseases of Egypt, which thou knowest, upon thee; but will lay them upon all <char style="add">them</char> that hate thee. <verse eid="DEU 7:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 7:16" />And thou shalt consume all the people which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall deliver thee; thine eye shall have no pity upon them: neither shalt thou serve their gods; for that <char style="add">will be</char> a snare unto thee. <verse eid="DEU 7:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 7:17" />If thou shalt say in thine heart, These nations <char style="add">are</char> more than I; how can I dispossess them? <verse eid="DEU 7:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 7:18" />Thou shalt not be afraid of them: <char style="add">but</char> shalt well remember what the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God did unto Pharaoh, and unto all Egypt; <verse eid="DEU 7:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 7:19" />The great temptations which thine eyes saw, and the signs, and the wonders, and the mighty hand, and the stretched out arm, whereby the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God brought thee out: so shall the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God do unto all the people of whom thou art afraid. <verse eid="DEU 7:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 7:20" />Moreover the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will send the hornet among them, until they that are left, and hide themselves from thee, be destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 7:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 7:21" />Thou shalt not be affrighted at them: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">is</char> among you, a mighty God and terrible. <verse eid="DEU 7:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 7:22" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will put out those nations before thee by little and little: thou mayest not consume them at once, lest the beasts of the field increase upon thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">put…: Heb. pluck off</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 7:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 7:23" />But the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall deliver them unto thee, and shall destroy them with a mighty destruction, until they be destroyed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">unto…: Heb. before thy face</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 7:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 7:24" />And he shall deliver their kings into thine hand, and thou shalt destroy their name from under heaven: there shall no man be able to stand before thee, until thou have destroyed them. <verse eid="DEU 7:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 7:25" />The graven images of their gods shall ye burn with fire: thou shalt not desire the silver or gold <char style="add">that is</char> on them, nor take <char style="add">it</char> unto thee, lest thou be snared therein: for it <char style="add">is</char> an abomination to the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God. <verse eid="DEU 7:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 7:26" />Neither shalt thou bring an abomination into thine house, lest thou be a cursed thing like it: <char style="add">but</char> thou shalt utterly detest it, and thou shalt utterly abhor it; for it <char style="add">is</char> a cursed thing.<verse eid="DEU 7:26" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 7" />
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="DEU 8" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 8:1" />All the commandments which I command thee this day shall ye observe to do, that ye may live, and multiply, and go in and possess the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto your fathers. <verse eid="DEU 8:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 8:2" />And thou shalt remember all the way which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God led thee these forty years in the wilderness, to humble thee, <char style="add">and</char> to prove thee, to know what <char style="add">was</char> in thine heart, whether thou wouldest keep his commandments, or no. <verse eid="DEU 8:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 8:3" />And he humbled thee, and suffered thee to hunger, and fed thee with manna, which thou knewest not, neither did thy fathers know; that he might make thee know that man doth not live by bread only, but by every <char style="add">word</char> that proceedeth out of the mouth of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> doth man live. <verse eid="DEU 8:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 8:4" />Thy raiment waxed not old upon thee, neither did thy foot swell, these forty years. <verse eid="DEU 8:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 8:5" />Thou shalt also consider in thine heart, that, as a man chasteneth his son, <char style="add">so</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God chasteneth thee. <verse eid="DEU 8:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 8:6" />Therefore thou shalt keep the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to walk in his ways, and to fear him. <verse eid="DEU 8:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 8:7" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God bringeth thee into a good land, a land of brooks of water, of fountains and depths that spring out of valleys and hills; <verse eid="DEU 8:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 8:8" />A land of wheat, and barley, and vines, and fig trees, and pomegranates; a land of oil olive, and honey;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of oil…: Heb. of olive tree of oil</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 8:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 8:9" />A land wherein thou shalt eat bread without scarceness, thou shalt not lack any <char style="add">thing</char> in it; a land whose stones <char style="add">are</char> iron, and out of whose hills thou mayest dig brass.<verse eid="DEU 8:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 8:10" />When thou hast eaten and art full, then thou shalt bless the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God for the good land which he hath given thee. <verse eid="DEU 8:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 8:11" />Beware that thou forget not the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, in not keeping his commandments, and his judgments, and his statutes, which I command thee this day: <verse eid="DEU 8:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 8:12" />Lest <char style="add">when</char> thou hast eaten and art full, and hast built goodly houses, and dwelt <char style="add">therein;</char> <verse eid="DEU 8:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 8:13" />And <char style="add">when</char> thy herds and thy flocks multiply, and thy silver and thy gold is multiplied, and all that thou hast is multiplied; <verse eid="DEU 8:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 8:14" />Then thine heart be lifted up, and thou forget the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, which brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage; <verse eid="DEU 8:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 8:15" />Who led thee through that great and terrible wilderness, <char style="add">wherein were</char> fiery serpents, and scorpions, and drought, where <char style="add">there was</char> no water; who brought thee forth water out of the rock of flint; <verse eid="DEU 8:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 8:16" />Who fed thee in the wilderness with manna, which thy fathers knew not, that he might humble thee, and that he might prove thee, to do thee good at thy latter end; <verse eid="DEU 8:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 8:17" />And thou say in thine heart, My power and the might of <char style="add">mine</char> hand hath gotten me this wealth. <verse eid="DEU 8:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 8:18" />But thou shalt remember the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: for <char style="add">it is</char> he that giveth thee power to get wealth, that he may establish his covenant which he sware unto thy fathers, as <char style="add">it is</char> this day. <verse eid="DEU 8:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 8:19" />And it shall be, if thou do at all forget the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and walk after other gods, and serve them, and worship them, I testify against you this day that ye shall surely perish. <verse eid="DEU 8:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 8:20" />As the nations which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> destroyeth before your face, so shall ye perish; because ye would not be obedient unto the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God.<verse eid="DEU 8:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 8" />
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="DEU 9" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 9:1" />Hear, O Israel: Thou <char style="add">art</char> to pass over Jordan this day, to go in to possess nations greater and mightier than thyself, cities great and fenced up to heaven, <verse eid="DEU 9:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 9:2" />A people great and tall, the children of the Anakims, whom thou knowest, and <char style="add">of whom</char> thou hast heard <char style="add">say</char>, Who can stand before the children of Anak! <verse eid="DEU 9:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 9:3" />Understand therefore this day, that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">is</char> he which goeth over before thee; <char style="add">as</char> a consuming fire he shall destroy them, and he shall bring them down before thy face: so shalt thou drive them out, and destroy them quickly, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath said unto thee. <verse eid="DEU 9:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 9:4" />Speak not thou in thine heart, after that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath cast them out from before thee, saying, For my righteousness the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath brought me in to possess this land: but for the wickedness of these nations the <char style="nd">LORD</char> doth drive them out from before thee. <verse eid="DEU 9:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 9:5" />Not for thy righteousness, or for the uprightness of thine heart, dost thou go to possess their land: but for the wickedness of these nations the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God doth drive them out from before thee, and that he may perform the word which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto thy fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. <verse eid="DEU 9:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 9:6" />Understand therefore, that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee not this good land to possess it for thy righteousness; for thou <char style="add">art</char> a stiffnecked people.<verse eid="DEU 9:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 9:7" />¶ Remember, <char style="add">and</char> forget not, how thou provokedst the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God to wrath in the wilderness: from the day that thou didst depart out of the land of Egypt, until ye came unto this place, ye have been rebellious against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="DEU 9:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 9:8" />Also in Horeb ye provoked the <char style="nd">LORD</char> to wrath, so that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was angry with you to have destroyed you. <verse eid="DEU 9:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 9:9" />When I was gone up into the mount to receive the tables of stone, <char style="add">even</char> the tables of the covenant which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> made with you, then I abode in the mount forty days and forty nights, I neither did eat bread nor drink water: <verse eid="DEU 9:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 9:10" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> delivered unto me two tables of stone written with the finger of God; and on them <char style="add">was written</char> according to all the words, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake with you in the mount out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly. <verse eid="DEU 9:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 9:11" />And it came to pass at the end of forty days and forty nights, <char style="add">that</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> gave me the two tables of stone, <char style="add">even</char> the tables of the covenant. <verse eid="DEU 9:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 9:12" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Arise, get thee down quickly from hence; for thy people which thou hast brought forth out of Egypt have corrupted <char style="add">themselves;</char> they are quickly turned aside out of the way which I commanded them; they have made them a molten image. <verse eid="DEU 9:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 9:13" />Furthermore the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto me, saying, I have seen this people, and, behold, it <char style="add">is</char> a stiffnecked people: <verse eid="DEU 9:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 9:14" />Let me alone, that I may destroy them, and blot out their name from under heaven: and I will make of thee a nation mightier and greater than they. <verse eid="DEU 9:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 9:15" />So I turned and came down from the mount, and the mount burned with fire: and the two tables of the covenant <char style="add">were</char> in my two hands. <verse eid="DEU 9:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 9:16" />And I looked, and, behold, ye had sinned against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, <char style="add">and</char> had made you a molten calf: ye had turned aside quickly out of the way which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had commanded you. <verse eid="DEU 9:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 9:17" />And I took the two tables, and cast them out of my two hands, and brake them before your eyes. <verse eid="DEU 9:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 9:18" />And I fell down before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, as at the first, forty days and forty nights: I did neither eat bread, nor drink water, because of all your sins which ye sinned, in doing wickedly in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to provoke him to anger. <verse eid="DEU 9:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 9:19" />For I was afraid of the anger and hot displeasure, wherewith the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was wroth against you to destroy you. But the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hearkened unto me at that time also. <verse eid="DEU 9:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 9:20" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was very angry with Aaron to have destroyed him: and I prayed for Aaron also the same time. <verse eid="DEU 9:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 9:21" />And I took your sin, the calf which ye had made, and burnt it with fire, and stamped it, <char style="add">and</char> ground <char style="add">it</char> very small, <char style="add">even</char> until it was as small as dust: and I cast the dust thereof into the brook that descended out of the mount. <verse eid="DEU 9:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 9:22" />And at Taberah, and at Massah, and at Kibroth-hattaavah, ye provoked the <char style="nd">LORD</char> to wrath. <verse eid="DEU 9:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 9:23" />Likewise when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sent you from Kadesh-barnea, saying, Go up and possess the land which I have given you; then ye rebelled against the commandment of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, and ye believed him not, nor hearkened to his voice. <verse eid="DEU 9:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 9:24" />Ye have been rebellious against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> from the day that I knew you. <verse eid="DEU 9:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 9:25" />Thus I fell down before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> forty days and forty nights, as I fell down <char style="add">at the first;</char> because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had said he would destroy you. <verse eid="DEU 9:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 9:26" />I prayed therefore unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and said, O Lord <char style="nd">GOD</char>, destroy not thy people and thine inheritance, which thou hast redeemed through thy greatness, which thou hast brought forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand. <verse eid="DEU 9:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 9:27" />Remember thy servants, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; look not unto the stubbornness of this people, nor to their wickedness, nor to their sin: <verse eid="DEU 9:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 9:28" />Lest the land whence thou broughtest us out say, Because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was not able to bring them into the land which he promised them, and because he hated them, he hath brought them out to slay them in the wilderness. <verse eid="DEU 9:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 9:29" />Yet they <char style="add">are</char> thy people and thine inheritance, which thou broughtest out by thy mighty power and by thy stretched out arm.<verse eid="DEU 9:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 9" />
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="DEU 10" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 10:1" />At that time the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Hew thee two tables of stone like unto the first, and come up unto me into the mount, and make thee an ark of wood. <verse eid="DEU 10:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 10:2" />And I will write on the tables the words that were in the first tables which thou brakest, and thou shalt put them in the ark. <verse eid="DEU 10:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 10:3" />And I made an ark <char style="add">of</char> shittim wood, and hewed two tables of stone like unto the first, and went up into the mount, having the two tables in mine hand. <verse eid="DEU 10:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 10:4" />And he wrote on the tables, according to the first writing, the ten commandments, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto you in the mount out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly: and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> gave them unto me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">commandments: Heb. words</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 10:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 10:5" />And I turned myself and came down from the mount, and put the tables in the ark which I had made; and there they be, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> commanded me.<verse eid="DEU 10:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 10:6" />¶ And the children of Israel took their journey from Beeroth of the children of Jaakan to Mosera: there Aaron died, and there he was buried; and Eleazar his son ministered in the priest’s office in his stead. <verse eid="DEU 10:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 10:7" />From thence they journeyed unto Gudgodah; and from Gudgodah to Jotbath, a land of rivers of waters.<verse eid="DEU 10:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 10:8" />¶ At that time the <char style="nd">LORD</char> separated the tribe of Levi, to bear the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to stand before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> to minister unto him, and to bless in his name, unto this day. <verse eid="DEU 10:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 10:9" />Wherefore Levi hath no part nor inheritance with his brethren; the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">is</char> his inheritance, according as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God promised him. <verse eid="DEU 10:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 10:10" />And I stayed in the mount, according to the first time, forty days and forty nights; and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hearkened unto me at that time also, <char style="add">and</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> would not destroy thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">first…: or, former days</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 10:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 10:11" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, Arise, take <char style="add">thy</char> journey before the people, that they may go in and possess the land, which I sware unto their fathers to give unto them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">take…: Heb. go in journey</char></note><verse eid="DEU 10:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 10:12" />¶ And now, Israel, what doth the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God require of thee, but to fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to serve the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God with all thy heart and with all thy soul, <verse eid="DEU 10:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 10:13" />To keep the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and his statutes, which I command thee this day for thy good? <verse eid="DEU 10:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 10:14" />Behold, the heaven and the heaven of heavens <char style="add">is</char> the <char style="nd">LORD’s</char> thy God, the earth <char style="add">also</char>, with all that therein <char style="add">is</char>. <verse eid="DEU 10:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 10:15" />Only the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had a delight in thy fathers to love them, and he chose their seed after them, <char style="add">even</char> you above all people, as <char style="add">it is</char> this day. <verse eid="DEU 10:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 10:16" />Circumcise therefore the foreskin of your heart, and be no more stiffnecked. <verse eid="DEU 10:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 10:17" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God <char style="add">is</char> God of gods, and Lord of lords, a great God, a mighty, and a terrible, which regardeth not persons, nor taketh reward: <verse eid="DEU 10:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 10:18" />He doth execute the judgment of the fatherless and widow, and loveth the stranger, in giving him food and raiment. <verse eid="DEU 10:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 10:19" />Love ye therefore the stranger: for ye were strangers in the land of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 10:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 10:20" />Thou shalt fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God; him shalt thou serve, and to him shalt thou cleave, and swear by his name. <verse eid="DEU 10:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 10:21" />He <char style="add">is</char> thy praise, and he <char style="add">is</char> thy God, that hath done for thee these great and terrible things, which thine eyes have seen. <verse eid="DEU 10:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 10:22" />Thy fathers went down into Egypt with threescore and ten persons; and now the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath made thee as the stars of heaven for multitude.<verse eid="DEU 10:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 10" />
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="DEU 11" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 11:1" />Therefore thou shalt love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and keep his charge, and his statutes, and his judgments, and his commandments, alway. <verse eid="DEU 11:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 11:2" />And know ye this day: for <char style="add">I speak</char> not with your children which have not known, and which have not seen the chastisement of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, his greatness, his mighty hand, and his stretched out arm, <verse eid="DEU 11:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 11:3" />And his miracles, and his acts, which he did in the midst of Egypt unto Pharaoh the king of Egypt, and unto all his land; <verse eid="DEU 11:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 11:4" />And what he did unto the army of Egypt, unto their horses, and to their chariots; how he made the water of the Red sea to overflow them as they pursued after you, and <char style="add">how</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath destroyed them unto this day; <verse eid="DEU 11:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 11:5" />And what he did unto you in the wilderness, until ye came into this place; <verse eid="DEU 11:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 11:6" />And what he did unto Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben: how the earth opened her mouth, and swallowed them up, and their households, and their tents, and all the substance that <char style="add">was</char> in their possession, in the midst of all Israel:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">substance…: or, living substance which followed them</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was…: Heb. was at their feet</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 11:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 11:7" />But your eyes have seen all the great acts of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> which he did.<verse eid="DEU 11:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 11:8" />Therefore shall ye keep all the commandments which I command you this day, that ye may be strong, and go in and possess the land, whither ye go to possess it; <verse eid="DEU 11:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 11:9" />And that ye may prolong <char style="add">your</char> days in the land, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto your fathers to give unto them and to their seed, a land that floweth with milk and honey.<verse eid="DEU 11:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 11:10" />¶ For the land, whither thou goest in to possess it, <char style="add">is</char> not as the land of Egypt, from whence ye came out, where thou sowedst thy seed, and wateredst <char style="add">it</char> with thy foot, as a garden of herbs: <verse eid="DEU 11:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 11:11" />But the land, whither ye go to possess it, <char style="add">is</char> a land of hills and valleys, <char style="add">and</char> drinketh water of the rain of heaven: <verse eid="DEU 11:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 11:12" />A land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God careth for: the eyes of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">are</char> always upon it, from the beginning of the year even unto the end of the year.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">careth…: Heb. seeketh</char></note><verse eid="DEU 11:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 11:13" />¶ And it shall come to pass, if ye shall hearken diligently unto my commandments which I command you this day, to love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul, <verse eid="DEU 11:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 11:14" />That I will give <char style="add">you</char> the rain of your land in his due season, the first rain and the latter rain, that thou mayest gather in thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil. <verse eid="DEU 11:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 11:15" />And I will send grass in thy fields for thy cattle, that thou mayest eat and be full.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">send: Heb. give</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 11:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 11:16" />Take heed to yourselves, that your heart be not deceived, and ye turn aside, and serve other gods, and worship them; <verse eid="DEU 11:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 11:17" />And <char style="add">then</char> the <char style="nd">LORD’s</char> wrath be kindled against you, and he shut up the heaven, that there be no rain, and that the land yield not her fruit; and <char style="add">lest</char> ye perish quickly from off the good land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> giveth you.<verse eid="DEU 11:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 11:18" />¶ Therefore shall ye lay up these my words in your heart and in your soul, and bind them for a sign upon your hand, that they may be as frontlets between your eyes. <verse eid="DEU 11:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 11:19" />And ye shall teach them your children, speaking of them when thou sittest in thine house, and when thou walkest by the way, when thou liest down, and when thou risest up. <verse eid="DEU 11:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 11:20" />And thou shalt write them upon the door posts of thine house, and upon thy gates: <verse eid="DEU 11:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 11:21" />That your days may be multiplied, and the days of your children, in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto your fathers to give them, as the days of heaven upon the earth.<verse eid="DEU 11:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 11:22" />¶ For if ye shall diligently keep all these commandments which I command you, to do them, to love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, to walk in all his ways, and to cleave unto him; <verse eid="DEU 11:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 11:23" />Then will the <char style="nd">LORD</char> drive out all these nations from before you, and ye shall possess greater nations and mightier than yourselves. <verse eid="DEU 11:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 11:24" />Every place whereon the soles of your feet shall tread shall be yours: from the wilderness and Lebanon, from the river, the river Euphrates, even unto the uttermost sea shall your coast be. <verse eid="DEU 11:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 11:25" />There shall no man be able to stand before you: <char style="add">for</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God shall lay the fear of you and the dread of you upon all the land that ye shall tread upon, as he hath said unto you.<verse eid="DEU 11:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 11:26" />¶ Behold, I set before you this day a blessing and a curse; <verse eid="DEU 11:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 11:27" />A blessing, if ye obey the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, which I command you this day: <verse eid="DEU 11:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 11:28" />And a curse, if ye will not obey the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, but turn aside out of the way which I command you this day, to go after other gods, which ye have not known. <verse eid="DEU 11:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 11:29" />And it shall come to pass, when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath brought thee in unto the land whither thou goest to possess it, that thou shalt put the blessing upon mount Gerizim, and the curse upon mount Ebal. <verse eid="DEU 11:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 11:30" /><char style="add">Are</char> they not on the other side Jordan, by the way where the sun goeth down, in the land of the Canaanites, which dwell in the champaign over against Gilgal, beside the plains of Moreh? <verse eid="DEU 11:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 11:31" />For ye shall pass over Jordan to go in to possess the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God giveth you, and ye shall possess it, and dwell therein. <verse eid="DEU 11:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 11:32" />And ye shall observe to do all the statutes and judgments which I set before you this day.<verse eid="DEU 11:32" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 11" />
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="DEU 12" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 12:1" />These <char style="add">are</char> the statutes and judgments, which ye shall observe to do in the land, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of thy fathers giveth thee to possess it, all the days that ye live upon the earth. <verse eid="DEU 12:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 12:2" />Ye shall utterly destroy all the places, wherein the nations which ye shall possess served their gods, upon the high mountains, and upon the hills, and under every green tree:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">possess: or, inherit</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 12:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 12:3" />And ye shall overthrow their altars, and break their pillars, and burn their groves with fire; and ye shall hew down the graven images of their gods, and destroy the names of them out of that place.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">overthrow: Heb. break down</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 12:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 12:4" />Ye shall not do so unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God.<verse eid="DEU 12:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 12:5" />But unto the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God shall choose out of all your tribes to put his name there, <char style="add">even</char> unto his habitation shall ye seek, and thither thou shalt come: <verse eid="DEU 12:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 12:6" />And thither ye shall bring your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, and your tithes, and heave offerings of your hand, and your vows, and your freewill offerings, and the firstlings of your herds and of your flocks: <verse eid="DEU 12:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 12:7" />And there ye shall eat before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, and ye shall rejoice in all that ye put your hand unto, ye and your households, wherein the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath blessed thee. <verse eid="DEU 12:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 12:8" />Ye shall not do after all <char style="add">the things</char> that we do here this day, every man whatsoever <char style="add">is</char> right in his own eyes. <verse eid="DEU 12:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 12:9" />For ye are not as yet come to the rest and to the inheritance, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God giveth you. <verse eid="DEU 12:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 12:10" />But <char style="add">when</char> ye go over Jordan, and dwell in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God giveth you to inherit, and <char style="add">when</char> he giveth you rest from all your enemies round about, so that ye dwell in safety; <verse eid="DEU 12:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 12:11" />Then there shall be a place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God shall choose to cause his name to dwell there; thither shall ye bring all that I command you; your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, your tithes, and the heave offering of your hand, and all your choice vows which ye vow unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">your choice…: Heb. the choice of your vows</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 12:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 12:12" />And ye shall rejoice before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, ye, and your sons, and your daughters, and your menservants, and your maidservants, and the Levite that <char style="add">is</char> within your gates; forasmuch as he hath no part nor inheritance with you. <verse eid="DEU 12:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 12:13" />Take heed to thyself that thou offer not thy burnt offerings in every place that thou seest: <verse eid="DEU 12:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 12:14" />But in the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall choose in one of thy tribes, there thou shalt offer thy burnt offerings, and there thou shalt do all that I command thee. <verse eid="DEU 12:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 12:15" />Notwithstanding thou mayest kill and eat flesh in all thy gates, whatsoever thy soul lusteth after, according to the blessing of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God which he hath given thee: the unclean and the clean may eat thereof, as of the roebuck, and as of the hart. <verse eid="DEU 12:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 12:16" />Only ye shall not eat the blood; ye shall pour it upon the earth as water.<verse eid="DEU 12:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 12:17" />¶ Thou mayest not eat within thy gates the tithe of thy corn, or of thy wine, or of thy oil, or the firstlings of thy herds or of thy flock, nor any of thy vows which thou vowest, nor thy freewill offerings, or heave offering of thine hand: <verse eid="DEU 12:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 12:18" />But thou must eat them before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God in the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall choose, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite that <char style="add">is</char> within thy gates: and thou shalt rejoice before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God in all that thou puttest thine hands unto. <verse eid="DEU 12:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 12:19" />Take heed to thyself that thou forsake not the Levite as long as thou livest upon the earth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as long…: Heb. all thy days</char></note><verse eid="DEU 12:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 12:20" />¶ When the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall enlarge thy border, as he hath promised thee, and thou shalt say, I will eat flesh, because thy soul longeth to eat flesh; thou mayest eat flesh, whatsoever thy soul lusteth after. <verse eid="DEU 12:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 12:21" />If the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath chosen to put his name there be too far from thee, then thou shalt kill of thy herd and of thy flock, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath given thee, as I have commanded thee, and thou shalt eat in thy gates whatsoever thy soul lusteth after. <verse eid="DEU 12:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 12:22" />Even as the roebuck and the hart is eaten, so thou shalt eat them: the unclean and the clean shall eat <char style="add">of</char> them alike. <verse eid="DEU 12:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 12:23" />Only be sure that thou eat not the blood: for the blood <char style="add">is</char> the life; and thou mayest not eat the life with the flesh.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">be…: Heb. be strong</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 12:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 12:24" />Thou shalt not eat it; thou shalt pour it upon the earth as water. <verse eid="DEU 12:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 12:25" />Thou shalt not eat it; that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee, when thou shalt do <char style="add">that which is</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="DEU 12:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 12:26" />Only thy holy things which thou hast, and thy vows, thou shalt take, and go unto the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall choose: <verse eid="DEU 12:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 12:27" />And thou shalt offer thy burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood, upon the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: and the blood of thy sacrifices shall be poured out upon the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and thou shalt eat the flesh. <verse eid="DEU 12:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 12:28" />Observe and hear all these words which I command thee, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee for ever, when thou doest <char style="add">that which is</char> good and right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God.<verse eid="DEU 12:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 12:29" />¶ When the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall cut off the nations from before thee, whither thou goest to possess them, and thou succeedest them, and dwellest in their land;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">succeedest…: Heb. inheritest, or, possessest them</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 12:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 12:30" />Take heed to thyself that thou be not snared by following them, after that they be destroyed from before thee; and that thou enquire not after their gods, saying, How did these nations serve their gods? even so will I do likewise.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by…: Heb. after them</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 12:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 12:31" />Thou shalt not do so unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: for every abomination to the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, which he hateth, have they done unto their gods; for even their sons and their daughters they have burnt in the fire to their gods.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to the: Heb. of the</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 12:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 12:32" />What thing soever I command you, observe to do it: thou shalt not add thereto, nor diminish from it.<verse eid="DEU 12:32" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 12" />
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="DEU 13" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 13:1" />If there arise among you a prophet, or a dreamer of dreams, and giveth thee a sign or a wonder, <verse eid="DEU 13:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 13:2" />And the sign or the wonder come to pass, whereof he spake unto thee, saying, Let us go after other gods, which thou hast not known, and let us serve them; <verse eid="DEU 13:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 13:3" />Thou shalt not hearken unto the words of that prophet, or that dreamer of dreams: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God proveth you, to know whether ye love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 13:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 13:4" />Ye shall walk after the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, and fear him, and keep his commandments, and obey his voice, and ye shall serve him, and cleave unto him. <verse eid="DEU 13:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 13:5" />And that prophet, or that dreamer of dreams, shall be put to death; because he hath spoken to turn <char style="add">you</char> away from the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed you out of the house of bondage, to thrust thee out of the way which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God commanded thee to walk in. So shalt thou put the evil away from the midst of thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to turn…: Heb. revolt against the <char style="nd">LORD</char></char></note><verse eid="DEU 13:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 13:6" />¶ If thy brother, the son of thy mother, or thy son, or thy daughter, or the wife of thy bosom, or thy friend, which <char style="add">is</char> as thine own soul, entice thee secretly, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which thou hast not known, thou, nor thy fathers; <verse eid="DEU 13:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 13:7" /><char style="add">Namely</char>, of the gods of the people which <char style="add">are</char> round about you, nigh unto thee, or far off from thee, from the <char style="add">one</char> end of the earth even unto the <char style="add">other</char> end of the earth; <verse eid="DEU 13:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 13:8" />Thou shalt not consent unto him, nor hearken unto him; neither shall thine eye pity him, neither shalt thou spare, neither shalt thou conceal him: <verse eid="DEU 13:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 13:9" />But thou shalt surely kill him; thine hand shall be first upon him to put him to death, and afterwards the hand of all the people. <verse eid="DEU 13:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 13:10" />And thou shalt stone him with stones, that he die; because he hath sought to thrust thee away from the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">bondage: Heb. bondmen</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 13:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 13:11" />And all Israel shall hear, and fear, and shall do no more any such wickedness as this is among you.<verse eid="DEU 13:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 13:12" />¶ If thou shalt hear <char style="add">say</char> in one of thy cities, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath given thee to dwell there, saying, <verse eid="DEU 13:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 13:13" /><char style="add">Certain</char> men, the children of Belial, are gone out from among you, and have withdrawn the inhabitants of their city, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which ye have not known;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the children…: or, naughty men</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 13:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 13:14" />Then shalt thou enquire, and make search, and ask diligently; and, behold, <char style="add">if it be</char> truth, <char style="add">and</char> the thing certain, <char style="add">that</char> such abomination is wrought among you; <verse eid="DEU 13:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 13:15" />Thou shalt surely smite the inhabitants of that city with the edge of the sword, destroying it utterly, and all that <char style="add">is</char> therein, and the cattle thereof, with the edge of the sword. <verse eid="DEU 13:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 13:16" />And thou shalt gather all the spoil of it into the midst of the street thereof, and shalt burn with fire the city, and all the spoil thereof every whit, for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: and it shall be an heap for ever; it shall not be built again. <verse eid="DEU 13:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 13:17" />And there shall cleave nought of the cursed thing to thine hand: that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> may turn from the fierceness of his anger, and shew thee mercy, and have compassion upon thee, and multiply thee, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cursed: or, devoted</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 13:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 13:18" />When thou shalt hearken to the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to keep all his commandments which I command thee this day, to do <char style="add">that which is</char> right in the eyes of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God.<verse eid="DEU 13:18" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 13" />
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="DEU 14" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 14:1" />Ye <char style="add">are</char> the children of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God: ye shall not cut yourselves, nor make any baldness between your eyes for the dead. <verse eid="DEU 14:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 14:2" />For thou <char style="add">art</char> an holy people unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath chosen thee to be a peculiar people unto himself, above all the nations that <char style="add">are</char> upon the earth.<verse eid="DEU 14:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 14:3" />¶ Thou shalt not eat any abominable thing. <verse eid="DEU 14:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 14:4" />These <char style="add">are</char> the beasts which ye shall eat: the ox, the sheep, and the goat, <verse eid="DEU 14:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 14:5" />The hart, and the roebuck, and the fallow deer, and the wild goat, and the pygarg, and the wild ox, and the chamois.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">pygarg: or bison: Heb. dishon</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 14:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 14:6" />And every beast that parteth the hoof, and cleaveth the cleft into two claws, <char style="add">and</char> cheweth the cud among the beasts, that ye shall eat. <verse eid="DEU 14:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 14:7" />Nevertheless these ye shall not eat of them that chew the cud, or of them that divide the cloven hoof; <char style="add">as</char> the camel, and the hare, and the coney: for they chew the cud, but divide not the hoof; <char style="add">therefore</char> they <char style="add">are</char> unclean unto you. <verse eid="DEU 14:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 14:8" />And the swine, because it divideth the hoof, yet cheweth not the cud, it <char style="add">is</char> unclean unto you: ye shall not eat of their flesh, nor touch their dead carcase.<verse eid="DEU 14:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 14:9" />¶ These ye shall eat of all that <char style="add">are</char> in the waters: all that have fins and scales shall ye eat: <verse eid="DEU 14:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 14:10" />And whatsoever hath not fins and scales ye may not eat; it <char style="add">is</char> unclean unto you.<verse eid="DEU 14:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 14:11" />¶ <char style="add">Of</char> all clean birds ye shall eat. <verse eid="DEU 14:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 14:12" />But these <char style="add">are they</char> of which ye shall not eat: the eagle, and the ossifrage, and the ospray, <verse eid="DEU 14:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 14:13" />And the glede, and the kite, and the vulture after his kind, <verse eid="DEU 14:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 14:14" />And every raven after his kind, <verse eid="DEU 14:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 14:15" />And the owl, and the night hawk, and the cuckow, and the hawk after his kind, <verse eid="DEU 14:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 14:16" />The little owl, and the great owl, and the swan, <verse eid="DEU 14:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 14:17" />And the pelican, and the gier eagle, and the cormorant, <verse eid="DEU 14:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 14:18" />And the stork, and the heron after her kind, and the lapwing, and the bat. <verse eid="DEU 14:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 14:19" />And every creeping thing that flieth <char style="add">is</char> unclean unto you: they shall not be eaten. <verse eid="DEU 14:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 14:20" /><char style="add">But of</char> all clean fowls ye may eat.<verse eid="DEU 14:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 14:21" />¶ Ye shall not eat <char style="add">of</char> any thing that dieth of itself: thou shalt give it unto the stranger that <char style="add">is</char> in thy gates, that he may eat it; or thou mayest sell it unto an alien: for thou <char style="add">art</char> an holy people unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God. Thou shalt not seethe a kid in his mother’s milk.<verse eid="DEU 14:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 14:22" />Thou shalt truly tithe all the increase of thy seed, that the field bringeth forth year by year. <verse eid="DEU 14:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 14:23" />And thou shalt eat before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, in the place which he shall choose to place his name there, the tithe of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thine oil, and the firstlings of thy herds and of thy flocks; that thou mayest learn to fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God always. <verse eid="DEU 14:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 14:24" />And if the way be too long for thee, so that thou art not able to carry it; <char style="add">or</char> if the place be too far from thee, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall choose to set his name there, when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath blessed thee: <verse eid="DEU 14:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 14:25" />Then shalt thou turn <char style="add">it</char> into money, and bind up the money in thine hand, and shalt go unto the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall choose: <verse eid="DEU 14:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 14:26" />And thou shalt bestow that money for whatsoever thy soul lusteth after, for oxen, or for sheep, or for wine, or for strong drink, or for whatsoever thy soul desireth: and thou shalt eat there before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and thou shalt rejoice, thou, and thine household,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">desireth: Heb. asketh of thee</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 14:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 14:27" />And the Levite that <char style="add">is</char> within thy gates; thou shalt not forsake him; for he hath no part nor inheritance with thee.<verse eid="DEU 14:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 14:28" />¶ At the end of three years thou shalt bring forth all the tithe of thine increase the same year, and shalt lay <char style="add">it</char> up within thy gates: <verse eid="DEU 14:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 14:29" />And the Levite, (because he hath no part nor inheritance with thee,) and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, which <char style="add">are</char> within thy gates, shall come, and shall eat and be satisfied; that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God may bless thee in all the work of thine hand which thou doest.<verse eid="DEU 14:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 14" />
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="DEU 15" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 15:1" />At the end of <char style="add">every</char> seven years thou shalt make a release. <verse eid="DEU 15:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 15:2" />And this <char style="add">is</char> the manner of the release: Every creditor that lendeth <char style="add">ought</char> unto his neighbour shall release <char style="add">it;</char> he shall not exact <char style="add">it</char> of his neighbour, or of his brother; because it is called the <char style="nd">LORD’s</char> release.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">creditor: Heb. master of the lending of his hand</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 15:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 15:3" />Of a foreigner thou mayest exact <char style="add">it again:</char> but <char style="add">that</char> which is thine with thy brother thine hand shall release; <verse eid="DEU 15:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 15:4" />Save when there shall be no poor among you; for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall greatly bless thee in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance to possess it:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Save…: or, To the end that there be no poor among you</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 15:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 15:5" />Only if thou carefully hearken unto the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to observe to do all these commandments which I command thee this day. <verse eid="DEU 15:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 15:6" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God blesseth thee, as he promised thee: and thou shalt lend unto many nations, but thou shalt not borrow; and thou shalt reign over many nations, but they shall not reign over thee.<verse eid="DEU 15:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 15:7" />¶ If there be among you a poor man of one of thy brethren within any of thy gates in thy land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not harden thine heart, nor shut thine hand from thy poor brother: <verse eid="DEU 15:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 15:8" />But thou shalt open thine hand wide unto him, and shalt surely lend him sufficient for his need, <char style="add">in that</char> which he wanteth. <verse eid="DEU 15:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 15:9" />Beware that there be not a thought in thy wicked heart, saying, The seventh year, the year of release, is at hand; and thine eye be evil against thy poor brother, and thou givest him nought; and he cry unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> against thee, and it be sin unto thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">thought: Heb. word</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wicked: Heb. Belial</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 15:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 15:10" />Thou shalt surely give him, and thine heart shall not be grieved when thou givest unto him: because that for this thing the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall bless thee in all thy works, and in all that thou puttest thine hand unto. <verse eid="DEU 15:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 15:11" />For the poor shall never cease out of the land: therefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt open thine hand wide unto thy brother, to thy poor, and to thy needy, in thy land.<verse eid="DEU 15:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 15:12" />¶ <char style="add">And</char> if thy brother, an Hebrew man, or an Hebrew woman, be sold unto thee, and serve thee six years; then in the seventh year thou shalt let him go free from thee. <verse eid="DEU 15:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 15:13" />And when thou sendest him out free from thee, thou shalt not let him go away empty: <verse eid="DEU 15:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 15:14" />Thou shalt furnish him liberally out of thy flock, and out of thy floor, and out of thy winepress: <char style="add">of that</char> wherewith the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath blessed thee thou shalt give unto him. <verse eid="DEU 15:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 15:15" />And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God redeemed thee: therefore I command thee this thing to day. <verse eid="DEU 15:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 15:16" />And it shall be, if he say unto thee, I will not go away from thee; because he loveth thee and thine house, because he is well with thee; <verse eid="DEU 15:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 15:17" />Then thou shalt take an aul, and thrust <char style="add">it</char> through his ear unto the door, and he shall be thy servant for ever. And also unto thy maidservant thou shalt do likewise. <verse eid="DEU 15:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 15:18" />It shall not seem hard unto thee, when thou sendest him away free from thee; for he hath been worth a double hired servant <char style="add">to thee</char>, in serving thee six years: and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall bless thee in all that thou doest.<verse eid="DEU 15:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 15:19" />¶ All the firstling males that come of thy herd and of thy flock thou shalt sanctify unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: thou shalt do no work with the firstling of thy bullock, nor shear the firstling of thy sheep. <verse eid="DEU 15:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 15:20" />Thou shalt eat <char style="add">it</char> before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God year by year in the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall choose, thou and thy household. <verse eid="DEU 15:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 15:21" />And if there be <char style="add">any</char> blemish therein, <char style="add">as if it be</char> lame, or blind, <char style="add">or have</char> any ill blemish, thou shalt not sacrifice it unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God. <verse eid="DEU 15:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 15:22" />Thou shalt eat it within thy gates: the unclean and the clean <char style="add">person shall eat it</char> alike, as the roebuck, and as the hart. <verse eid="DEU 15:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 15:23" />Only thou shalt not eat the blood thereof; thou shalt pour it upon the ground as water.<verse eid="DEU 15:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 15" />
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="DEU 16" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 16:1" />Observe the month of Abib, and keep the passover unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: for in the month of Abib the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God brought thee forth out of Egypt by night. <verse eid="DEU 16:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 16:2" />Thou shalt therefore sacrifice the passover unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, of the flock and the herd, in the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall choose to place his name there. <verse eid="DEU 16:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 16:3" />Thou shalt eat no leavened bread with it; seven days shalt thou eat unleavened bread therewith, <char style="add">even</char> the bread of affliction; for thou camest forth out of the land of Egypt in haste: that thou mayest remember the day when thou camest forth out of the land of Egypt all the days of thy life. <verse eid="DEU 16:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 16:4" />And there shall be no leavened bread seen with thee in all thy coast seven days; neither shall there <char style="add">any thing</char> of the flesh, which thou sacrificedst the first day at even, remain all night until the morning. <verse eid="DEU 16:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 16:5" />Thou mayest not sacrifice the passover within any of thy gates, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sacrifice: or, kill</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 16:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 16:6" />But at the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall choose to place his name in, there thou shalt sacrifice the passover at even, at the going down of the sun, at the season that thou camest forth out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 16:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 16:7" />And thou shalt roast and eat <char style="add">it</char> in the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall choose: and thou shalt turn in the morning, and go unto thy tents. <verse eid="DEU 16:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 16:8" />Six days thou shalt eat unleavened bread: and on the seventh day <char style="add">shall be</char> a solemn assembly to the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: thou shalt do no work <char style="add">therein</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">solemn…: Heb. restraint</char></note><verse eid="DEU 16:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 16:9" />¶ Seven weeks shalt thou number unto thee: begin to number the seven weeks from <char style="add">such time as</char> thou beginnest <char style="add">to put</char> the sickle to the corn. <verse eid="DEU 16:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 16:10" />And thou shalt keep the feast of weeks unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God with a tribute of a freewill offering of thine hand, which thou shalt give <char style="add">unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char> thy God</char>, according as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath blessed thee:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a tribute: or, sufficiency</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 16:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 16:11" />And thou shalt rejoice before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite that <char style="add">is</char> within thy gates, and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that <char style="add">are</char> among you, in the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath chosen to place his name there. <verse eid="DEU 16:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 16:12" />And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt: and thou shalt observe and do these statutes.<verse eid="DEU 16:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 16:13" />¶ Thou shalt observe the feast of tabernacles seven days, after that thou hast gathered in thy corn and thy wine:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">corn…: Heb. floor, and thy winepress</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 16:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 16:14" />And thou shalt rejoice in thy feast, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite, the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that <char style="add">are</char> within thy gates. <verse eid="DEU 16:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 16:15" />Seven days shalt thou keep a solemn feast unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God in the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall choose: because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall bless thee in all thine increase, and in all the works of thine hands, therefore thou shalt surely rejoice.<verse eid="DEU 16:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 16:16" />¶ Three times in a year shall all thy males appear before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God in the place which he shall choose; in the feast of unleavened bread, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of tabernacles: and they shall not appear before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> empty: <verse eid="DEU 16:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 16:17" />Every man <char style="add">shall give</char> as he is able, according to the blessing of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God which he hath given thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as…: Heb. according to the gift of his hand</char></note><verse eid="DEU 16:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 16:18" />¶ Judges and officers shalt thou make thee in all thy gates, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, throughout thy tribes: and they shall judge the people with just judgment. <verse eid="DEU 16:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 16:19" />Thou shalt not wrest judgment; thou shalt not respect persons, neither take a gift: for a gift doth blind the eyes of the wise, and pervert the words of the righteous.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">words: or, matters</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 16:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 16:20" />That which is altogether just shalt thou follow, that thou mayest live, and inherit the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That which…: Heb. Justice, justice</char></note><verse eid="DEU 16:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 16:21" />¶ Thou shalt not plant thee a grove of any trees near unto the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, which thou shalt make thee. <verse eid="DEU 16:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 16:22" />Neither shalt thou set thee up <char style="add">any</char> image; which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hateth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">image: or, statue, or, pillar</char></note><verse eid="DEU 16:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 16" />
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="DEU 17" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 17:1" />Thou shalt not sacrifice unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">any</char> bullock, or sheep, wherein is blemish, <char style="add">or</char> any evilfavouredness: for that <char style="add">is</char> an abomination unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sheep: or, goat</char></note><verse eid="DEU 17:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 17:2" />¶ If there be found among you, within any of thy gates which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, man or woman, that hath wrought wickedness in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, in transgressing his covenant, <verse eid="DEU 17:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 17:3" />And hath gone and served other gods, and worshipped them, either the sun, or moon, or any of the host of heaven, which I have not commanded; <verse eid="DEU 17:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 17:4" />And it be told thee, and thou hast heard <char style="add">of it</char>, and enquired diligently, and, behold, <char style="add">it be</char> true, <char style="add">and</char> the thing certain, <char style="add">that</char> such abomination is wrought in Israel: <verse eid="DEU 17:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 17:5" />Then shalt thou bring forth that man or that woman, which have committed that wicked thing, unto thy gates, <char style="add">even</char> that man or that woman, and shalt stone them with stones, till they die. <verse eid="DEU 17:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 17:6" />At the mouth of two witnesses, or three witnesses, shall he that is worthy of death be put to death; <char style="add">but</char> at the mouth of one witness he shall not be put to death. <verse eid="DEU 17:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 17:7" />The hands of the witnesses shall be first upon him to put him to death, and afterward the hands of all the people. So thou shalt put the evil away from among you.<verse eid="DEU 17:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 17:8" />¶ If there arise a matter too hard for thee in judgment, between blood and blood, between plea and plea, and between stroke and stroke, <char style="add">being</char> matters of controversy within thy gates: then shalt thou arise, and get thee up into the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall choose; <verse eid="DEU 17:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 17:9" />And thou shalt come unto the priests the Levites, and unto the judge that shall be in those days, and enquire; and they shall shew thee the sentence of judgment: <verse eid="DEU 17:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 17:10" />And thou shalt do according to the sentence, which they of that place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall choose shall shew thee; and thou shalt observe to do according to all that they inform thee: <verse eid="DEU 17:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 17:11" />According to the sentence of the law which they shall teach thee, and according to the judgment which they shall tell thee, thou shalt do: thou shalt not decline from the sentence which they shall shew thee, <char style="add">to</char> the right hand, nor <char style="add">to</char> the left. <verse eid="DEU 17:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 17:12" />And the man that will do presumptuously, and will not hearken unto the priest that standeth to minister there before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, or unto the judge, even that man shall die: and thou shalt put away the evil from Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and will…: Heb. not to hearken</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 17:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 17:13" />And all the people shall hear, and fear, and do no more presumptuously.<verse eid="DEU 17:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 17:14" />¶ When thou art come unto the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, and shalt possess it, and shalt dwell therein, and shalt say, I will set a king over me, like as all the nations that <char style="add">are</char> about me; <verse eid="DEU 17:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 17:15" />Thou shalt in any wise set <char style="add">him</char> king over thee, whom the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall choose: <char style="add">one</char> from among thy brethren shalt thou set king over thee: thou mayest not set a stranger over thee, which <char style="add">is</char> not thy brother. <verse eid="DEU 17:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 17:16" />But he shall not multiply horses to himself, nor cause the people to return to Egypt, to the end that he should multiply horses: forasmuch as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath said unto you, Ye shall henceforth return no more that way. <verse eid="DEU 17:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 17:17" />Neither shall he multiply wives to himself, that his heart turn not away: neither shall he greatly multiply to himself silver and gold. <verse eid="DEU 17:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 17:18" />And it shall be, when he sitteth upon the throne of his kingdom, that he shall write him a copy of this law in a book out of <char style="add">that which is</char> before the priests the Levites: <verse eid="DEU 17:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 17:19" />And it shall be with him, and he shall read therein all the days of his life: that he may learn to fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God, to keep all the words of this law and these statutes, to do them: <verse eid="DEU 17:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 17:20" />That his heart be not lifted up above his brethren, and that he turn not aside from the commandment, <char style="add">to</char> the right hand, or <char style="add">to</char> the left: to the end that he may prolong <char style="add">his</char> days in his kingdom, he, and his children, in the midst of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 17:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 17" />
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="DEU 18" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 18:1" />The priests the Levites, <char style="add">and</char> all the tribe of Levi, shall have no part nor inheritance with Israel: they shall eat the offerings of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> made by fire, and his inheritance. <verse eid="DEU 18:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 18:2" />Therefore shall they have no inheritance among their brethren: the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">is</char> their inheritance, as he hath said unto them.<verse eid="DEU 18:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 18:3" />¶ And this shall be the priest’s due from the people, from them that offer a sacrifice, whether <char style="add">it be</char> ox or sheep; and they shall give unto the priest the shoulder, and the two cheeks, and the maw. <verse eid="DEU 18:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 18:4" />The firstfruit <char style="add">also</char> of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thine oil, and the first of the fleece of thy sheep, shalt thou give him. <verse eid="DEU 18:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 18:5" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath chosen him out of all thy tribes, to stand to minister in the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, him and his sons for ever.<verse eid="DEU 18:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 18:6" />¶ And if a Levite come from any of thy gates out of all Israel, where he sojourned, and come with all the desire of his mind unto the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall choose; <verse eid="DEU 18:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 18:7" />Then he shall minister in the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> his God, as all his brethren the Levites <char style="add">do</char>, which stand there before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="DEU 18:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 18:8" />They shall have like portions to eat, beside that which cometh of the sale of his patrimony.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: Heb. his sale by the fathers</char></note><verse eid="DEU 18:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 18:9" />¶ When thou art come into the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not learn to do after the abominations of those nations. <verse eid="DEU 18:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 18:10" />There shall not be found among you <char style="add">any one</char> that maketh his son or his daughter to pass through the fire, <char style="add">or</char> that useth divination, <char style="add">or</char> an observer of times, or an enchanter, or a witch, <verse eid="DEU 18:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 18:11" />Or a charmer, or a consulter with familiar spirits, or a wizard, or a necromancer. <verse eid="DEU 18:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 18:12" />For all that do these things <char style="add">are</char> an abomination unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: and because of these abominations the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God doth drive them out from before thee. <verse eid="DEU 18:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 18:13" />Thou shalt be perfect with the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">perfect: or, upright, or, sincere</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 18:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 18:14" />For these nations, which thou shalt possess, hearkened unto observers of times, and unto diviners: but as for thee, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath not suffered thee so <char style="add">to do</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">possess: or, inherit</char></note><verse eid="DEU 18:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 18:15" />¶ The <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will raise up unto thee a Prophet from the midst of thee, of thy brethren, like unto me; unto him ye shall hearken; <verse eid="DEU 18:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 18:16" />According to all that thou desiredst of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God in Horeb in the day of the assembly, saying, Let me not hear again the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> my God, neither let me see this great fire any more, that I die not. <verse eid="DEU 18:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 18:17" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto me, They have well <char style="add">spoken that</char> which they have spoken. <verse eid="DEU 18:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 18:18" />I will raise them up a Prophet from among their brethren, like unto thee, and will put my words in his mouth; and he shall speak unto them all that I shall command him. <verse eid="DEU 18:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 18:19" />And it shall come to pass, <char style="add">that</char> whosoever will not hearken unto my words which he shall speak in my name, I will require <char style="add">it</char> of him. <verse eid="DEU 18:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 18:20" />But the prophet, which shall presume to speak a word in my name, which I have not commanded him to speak, or that shall speak in the name of other gods, even that prophet shall die. <verse eid="DEU 18:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 18:21" />And if thou say in thine heart, How shall we know the word which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath not spoken? <verse eid="DEU 18:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 18:22" />When a prophet speaketh in the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, if the thing follow not, nor come to pass, that <char style="add">is</char> the thing which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath not spoken, <char style="add">but</char> the prophet hath spoken it presumptuously: thou shalt not be afraid of him.<verse eid="DEU 18:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 18" />
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="DEU 19" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 19:1" />When the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath cut off the nations, whose land the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, and thou succeedest them, and dwellest in their cities, and in their houses;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">succeedest: Heb. inheritest, or, possessest</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 19:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 19:2" />Thou shalt separate three cities for thee in the midst of thy land, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 19:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 19:3" />Thou shalt prepare thee a way, and divide the coasts of thy land, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee to inherit, into three parts, that every slayer may flee thither.<verse eid="DEU 19:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 19:4" />¶ And this <char style="add">is</char> the case of the slayer, which shall flee thither, that he may live: Whoso killeth his neighbour ignorantly, whom he hated not in time past;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: Heb. from yesterday the third day</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 19:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 19:5" />As when a man goeth into the wood with his neighbour to hew wood, and his hand fetcheth a stroke with the axe to cut down the tree, and the head slippeth from the helve, and lighteth upon his neighbour, that he die; he shall flee unto one of those cities, and live:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">head: Heb. iron</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">helve: Heb. wood</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">lighteth…: Heb. findeth</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 19:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 19:6" />Lest the avenger of the blood pursue the slayer, while his heart is hot, and overtake him, because the way is long, and slay him; whereas he <char style="add">was</char> not worthy of death, inasmuch as he hated him not in time past.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">slay…: Heb. smite him in life</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: Heb. from yesterday the third day</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 19:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 19:7" />Wherefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt separate three cities for thee. <verse eid="DEU 19:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 19:8" />And if the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God enlarge thy coast, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, and give thee all the land which he promised to give unto thy fathers; <verse eid="DEU 19:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 19:9" />If thou shalt keep all these commandments to do them, which I command thee this day, to love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and to walk ever in his ways; then shalt thou add three cities more for thee, beside these three: <verse eid="DEU 19:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 19:10" />That innocent blood be not shed in thy land, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance, and <char style="add">so</char> blood be upon thee.<verse eid="DEU 19:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 19:11" />¶ But if any man hate his neighbour, and lie in wait for him, and rise up against him, and smite him mortally that he die, and fleeth into one of these cities:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mortally: Heb. in life</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 19:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 19:12" />Then the elders of his city shall send and fetch him thence, and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, that he may die. <verse eid="DEU 19:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 19:13" />Thine eye shall not pity him, but thou shalt put away <char style="add">the guilt of</char> innocent blood from Israel, that it may go well with thee.<verse eid="DEU 19:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 19:14" />¶ Thou shalt not remove thy neighbour’s landmark, which they of old time have set in thine inheritance, which thou shalt inherit in the land that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee to possess it.<verse eid="DEU 19:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 19:15" />¶ One witness shall not rise up against a man for any iniquity, or for any sin, in any sin that he sinneth: at the mouth of two witnesses, or at the mouth of three witnesses, shall the matter be established.<verse eid="DEU 19:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 19:16" />¶ If a false witness rise up against any man to testify against him <char style="add">that which is</char> wrong;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: or, falling away</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 19:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 19:17" />Then both the men, between whom the controversy <char style="add">is</char>, shall stand before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, before the priests and the judges, which shall be in those days; <verse eid="DEU 19:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 19:18" />And the judges shall make diligent inquisition: and, behold, <char style="add">if</char> the witness <char style="add">be</char> a false witness, <char style="add">and</char> hath testified falsely against his brother; <verse eid="DEU 19:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 19:19" />Then shall ye do unto him, as he had thought to have done unto his brother: so shalt thou put the evil away from among you. <verse eid="DEU 19:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 19:20" />And those which remain shall hear, and fear, and shall henceforth commit no more any such evil among you. <verse eid="DEU 19:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 19:21" />And thine eye shall not pity; <char style="add">but</char> life <char style="add">shall go</char> for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.<verse eid="DEU 19:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 19" />
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="DEU 20" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 20:1" />When thou goest out to battle against thine enemies, and seest horses, and chariots, <char style="add">and</char> a people more than thou, be not afraid of them: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God <char style="add">is</char> with thee, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 20:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 20:2" />And it shall be, when ye are come nigh unto the battle, that the priest shall approach and speak unto the people, <verse eid="DEU 20:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 20:3" />And shall say unto them, Hear, O Israel, ye approach this day unto battle against your enemies: let not your hearts faint, fear not, and do not tremble, neither be ye terrified because of them;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">faint: Heb. be tender</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">tremble: Heb. make haste</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 20:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 20:4" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God <char style="add">is</char> he that goeth with you, to fight for you against your enemies, to save you.<verse eid="DEU 20:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 20:5" />¶ And the officers shall speak unto the people, saying, What man <char style="add">is there</char> that hath built a new house, and hath not dedicated it? let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man dedicate it. <verse eid="DEU 20:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 20:6" />And what man <char style="add">is he</char> that hath planted a vineyard, and hath not <char style="add">yet</char> eaten of it? let him <char style="add">also</char> go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man eat of it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">eaten…: Heb. made it common</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 20:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 20:7" />And what man <char style="add">is there</char> that hath betrothed a wife, and hath not taken her? let him go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man take her. <verse eid="DEU 20:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 20:8" />And the officers shall speak further unto the people, and they shall say, What man <char style="add">is there that is</char> fearful and fainthearted? let him go and return unto his house, lest his brethren’s heart faint as well as his heart.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">faint: Heb. melt</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 20:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 20:9" />And it shall be, when the officers have made an end of speaking unto the people, that they shall make captains of the armies to lead the people.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to lead…: Heb. to be in the head of the people</char></note><verse eid="DEU 20:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 20:10" />¶ When thou comest nigh unto a city to fight against it, then proclaim peace unto it. <verse eid="DEU 20:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 20:11" />And it shall be, if it make thee answer of peace, and open unto thee, then it shall be, <char style="add">that</char> all the people <char style="add">that is</char> found therein shall be tributaries unto thee, and they shall serve thee. <verse eid="DEU 20:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 20:12" />And if it will make no peace with thee, but will make war against thee, then thou shalt besiege it: <verse eid="DEU 20:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 20:13" />And when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath delivered it into thine hands, thou shalt smite every male thereof with the edge of the sword: <verse eid="DEU 20:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 20:14" />But the women, and the little ones, and the cattle, and all that is in the city, <char style="add">even</char> all the spoil thereof, shalt thou take unto thyself; and thou shalt eat the spoil of thine enemies, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath given thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">take: Heb. spoil</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 20:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 20:15" />Thus shalt thou do unto all the cities <char style="add">which are</char> very far off from thee, which <char style="add">are</char> not of the cities of these nations. <verse eid="DEU 20:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 20:16" />But of the cities of these people, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God doth give thee <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance, thou shalt save alive nothing that breatheth: <verse eid="DEU 20:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 20:17" />But thou shalt utterly destroy them; <char style="add">namely</char>, the Hittites, and the Amorites, the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites; as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath commanded thee: <verse eid="DEU 20:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 20:18" />That they teach you not to do after all their abominations, which they have done unto their gods; so should ye sin against the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God.<verse eid="DEU 20:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 20:19" />¶ When thou shalt besiege a city a long time, in making war against it to take it, thou shalt not destroy the trees thereof by forcing an axe against them: for thou mayest eat of them, and thou shalt not cut them down (for the tree of the field <char style="add">is</char> man’s <char style="add">life</char>) to employ <char style="add">them</char> in the siege:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">for the…: or, for, O man, the tree of the field is to be employed in the siege</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to employ…: Heb. to go from before thee</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 20:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 20:20" />Only the trees which thou knowest that they <char style="add">be</char> not trees for meat, thou shalt destroy and cut them down; and thou shalt build bulwarks against the city that maketh war with thee, until it be subdued.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">it…: Heb. it come down</char></note><verse eid="DEU 20:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 20" />
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="DEU 21" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 21:1" />If <char style="add">one</char> be found slain in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee to possess it, lying in the field, <char style="add">and</char> it be not known who hath slain him: <verse eid="DEU 21:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 21:2" />Then thy elders and thy judges shall come forth, and they shall measure unto the cities which <char style="add">are</char> round about him that is slain: <verse eid="DEU 21:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 21:3" />And it shall be, <char style="add">that</char> the city <char style="add">which is</char> next unto the slain man, even the elders of that city shall take an heifer, which hath not been wrought with, <char style="add">and</char> which hath not drawn in the yoke; <verse eid="DEU 21:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 21:4" />And the elders of that city shall bring down the heifer unto a rough valley, which is neither eared nor sown, and shall strike off the heifer’s neck there in the valley: <verse eid="DEU 21:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 21:5" />And the priests the sons of Levi shall come near; for them the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath chosen to minister unto him, and to bless in the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; and by their word shall every controversy and every stroke be <char style="add">tried:</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">word: Heb. mouth</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 21:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 21:6" />And all the elders of that city, <char style="add">that are</char> next unto the slain <char style="add">man</char>, shall wash their hands over the heifer that is beheaded in the valley: <verse eid="DEU 21:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 21:7" />And they shall answer and say, Our hands have not shed this blood, neither have our eyes seen <char style="add">it</char>. <verse eid="DEU 21:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 21:8" />Be merciful, O <char style="nd">LORD</char>, unto thy people Israel, whom thou hast redeemed, and lay not innocent blood unto thy people of Israel’s charge. And the blood shall be forgiven them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">unto thy people of: Heb. in the midst, etc</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 21:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 21:9" />So shalt thou put away the <char style="add">guilt of</char> innocent blood from among you, when thou shalt do <char style="add">that which is</char> right in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<verse eid="DEU 21:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 21:10" />¶ When thou goest forth to war against thine enemies, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath delivered them into thine hands, and thou hast taken them captive, <verse eid="DEU 21:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 21:11" />And seest among the captives a beautiful woman, and hast a desire unto her, that thou wouldest have her to thy wife; <verse eid="DEU 21:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 21:12" />Then thou shalt bring her home to thine house; and she shall shave her head, and pare her nails;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">pare: or, suffer to grow: Heb. make, or, dress</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 21:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 21:13" />And she shall put the raiment of her captivity from off her, and shall remain in thine house, and bewail her father and her mother a full month: and after that thou shalt go in unto her, and be her husband, and she shall be thy wife. <verse eid="DEU 21:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 21:14" />And it shall be, if thou have no delight in her, then thou shalt let her go whither she will; but thou shalt not sell her at all for money, thou shalt not make merchandise of her, because thou hast humbled her.<verse eid="DEU 21:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 21:15" />¶ If a man have two wives, one beloved, and another hated, and they have born him children, <char style="add">both</char> the beloved and the hated; and <char style="add">if</char> the firstborn son be hers that was hated: <verse eid="DEU 21:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 21:16" />Then it shall be, when he maketh his sons to inherit <char style="add">that</char> which he hath, <char style="add">that</char> he may not make the son of the beloved firstborn before the son of the hated, <char style="add">which is indeed</char> the firstborn: <verse eid="DEU 21:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 21:17" />But he shall acknowledge the son of the hated <char style="add">for</char> the firstborn, by giving him a double portion of all that he hath: for he <char style="add">is</char> the beginning of his strength; the right of the firstborn <char style="add">is</char> his.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: Heb. that is found with him</char></note><verse eid="DEU 21:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 21:18" />¶ If a man have a stubborn and rebellious son, which will not obey the voice of his father, or the voice of his mother, and <char style="add">that</char>, when they have chastened him, will not hearken unto them: <verse eid="DEU 21:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 21:19" />Then shall his father and his mother lay hold on him, and bring him out unto the elders of his city, and unto the gate of his place; <verse eid="DEU 21:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 21:20" />And they shall say unto the elders of his city, This our son <char style="add">is</char> stubborn and rebellious, he will not obey our voice; <char style="add">he is</char> a glutton, and a drunkard. <verse eid="DEU 21:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 21:21" />And all the men of his city shall stone him with stones, that he die: so shalt thou put evil away from among you; and all Israel shall hear, and fear.<verse eid="DEU 21:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 21:22" />¶ And if a man have committed a sin worthy of death, and he be to be put to death, and thou hang him on a tree: <verse eid="DEU 21:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 21:23" />His body shall not remain all night upon the tree, but thou shalt in any wise bury him that day; (for he that is hanged <char style="add">is</char> accursed of God;) that thy land be not defiled, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">accursed…: Heb. the curse of God</char></note><verse eid="DEU 21:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 21" />
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="DEU 22" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 22:1" />Thou shalt not see thy brother’s ox or his sheep go astray, and hide thyself from them: thou shalt in any case bring them again unto thy brother. <verse eid="DEU 22:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 22:2" />And if thy brother <char style="add">be</char> not nigh unto thee, or if thou know him not, then thou shalt bring it unto thine own house, and it shall be with thee until thy brother seek after it, and thou shalt restore it to him again. <verse eid="DEU 22:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 22:3" />In like manner shalt thou do with his ass; and so shalt thou do with his raiment; and with all lost thing of thy brother’s, which he hath lost, and thou hast found, shalt thou do likewise: thou mayest not hide thyself.<verse eid="DEU 22:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 22:4" />¶ Thou shalt not see thy brother’s ass or his ox fall down by the way, and hide thyself from them: thou shalt surely help him to lift <char style="add">them</char> up again.<verse eid="DEU 22:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 22:5" />¶ The woman shall not wear that which pertaineth unto a man, neither shall a man put on a woman’s garment: for all that do so <char style="add">are</char> abomination unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God.<verse eid="DEU 22:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 22:6" />¶ If a bird’s nest chance to be before thee in the way in any tree, or on the ground, <char style="add">whether they be</char> young ones, or eggs, and the dam sitting upon the young, or upon the eggs, thou shalt not take the dam with the young: <verse eid="DEU 22:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 22:7" /><char style="add">But</char> thou shalt in any wise let the dam go, and take the young to thee; that it may be well with thee, and <char style="add">that</char> thou mayest prolong <char style="add">thy</char> days.<verse eid="DEU 22:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 22:8" />¶ When thou buildest a new house, then thou shalt make a battlement for thy roof, that thou bring not blood upon thine house, if any man fall from thence.<verse eid="DEU 22:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 22:9" />¶ Thou shalt not sow thy vineyard with divers seeds: lest the fruit of thy seed which thou hast sown, and the fruit of thy vineyard, be defiled.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fruit of thy seed: Heb. fulness of the seed</char></note><verse eid="DEU 22:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 22:10" />¶ Thou shalt not plow with an ox and an ass together.<verse eid="DEU 22:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 22:11" />¶ Thou shalt not wear a garment of divers sorts, <char style="add">as</char> of woollen and linen together.<verse eid="DEU 22:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 22:12" />¶ Thou shalt make thee fringes upon the four quarters of thy vesture, wherewith thou coverest <char style="add">thyself</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">quarters: Heb. wings</char></note><verse eid="DEU 22:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 22:13" />¶ If any man take a wife, and go in unto her, and hate her, <verse eid="DEU 22:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 22:14" />And give occasions of speech against her, and bring up an evil name upon her, and say, I took this woman, and when I came to her, I found her not a maid: <verse eid="DEU 22:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 22:15" />Then shall the father of the damsel, and her mother, take and bring forth <char style="add">the tokens of</char> the damsel’s virginity unto the elders of the city in the gate: <verse eid="DEU 22:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 22:16" />And the damsel’s father shall say unto the elders, I gave my daughter unto this man to wife, and he hateth her; <verse eid="DEU 22:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 22:17" />And, lo, he hath given occasions of speech <char style="add">against her</char>, saying, I found not thy daughter a maid; and yet these <char style="add">are the tokens of</char> my daughter’s virginity. And they shall spread the cloth before the elders of the city. <verse eid="DEU 22:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 22:18" />And the elders of that city shall take that man and chastise him; <verse eid="DEU 22:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 22:19" />And they shall amerce him in an hundred <char style="add">shekels</char> of silver, and give <char style="add">them</char> unto the father of the damsel, because he hath brought up an evil name upon a virgin of Israel: and she shall be his wife; he may not put her away all his days. <verse eid="DEU 22:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 22:20" />But if this thing be true, <char style="add">and the tokens of</char> virginity be not found for the damsel: <verse eid="DEU 22:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 22:21" />Then they shall bring out the damsel to the door of her father’s house, and the men of her city shall stone her with stones that she die: because she hath wrought folly in Israel, to play the whore in her father’s house: so shalt thou put evil away from among you.<verse eid="DEU 22:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 22:22" />¶ If a man be found lying with a woman married to an husband, then they shall both of them die, <char style="add">both</char> the man that lay with the woman, and the woman: so shalt thou put away evil from Israel.<verse eid="DEU 22:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 22:23" />¶ If a damsel <char style="add">that is</char> a virgin be betrothed unto an husband, and a man find her in the city, and lie with her; <verse eid="DEU 22:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 22:24" />Then ye shall bring them both out unto the gate of that city, and ye shall stone them with stones that they die; the damsel, because she cried not, <char style="add">being</char> in the city; and the man, because he hath humbled his neighbour’s wife: so thou shalt put away evil from among you.<verse eid="DEU 22:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 22:25" />¶ But if a man find a betrothed damsel in the field, and the man force her, and lie with her: then the man only that lay with her shall die:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">force: or, take strong hold of</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 22:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 22:26" />But unto the damsel thou shalt do nothing; <char style="add">there is</char> in the damsel no sin <char style="add">worthy</char> of death: for as when a man riseth against his neighbour, and slayeth him, even so <char style="add">is</char> this matter: <verse eid="DEU 22:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 22:27" />For he found her in the field, <char style="add">and</char> the betrothed damsel cried, and <char style="add">there was</char> none to save her.<verse eid="DEU 22:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 22:28" />¶ If a man find a damsel <char style="add">that is</char> a virgin, which is not betrothed, and lay hold on her, and lie with her, and they be found; <verse eid="DEU 22:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 22:29" />Then the man that lay with her shall give unto the damsel’s father fifty <char style="add">shekels</char> of silver, and she shall be his wife; because he hath humbled her, he may not put her away all his days.<verse eid="DEU 22:29" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 22:30" />¶ A man shall not take his father’s wife, nor discover his father’s skirt.<verse eid="DEU 22:30" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 22" />
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="DEU 23" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 23:1" />He that is wounded in the stones, or hath his privy member cut off, shall not enter into the congregation of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="DEU 23:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 23:2" />A bastard shall not enter into the congregation of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; even to his tenth generation shall he not enter into the congregation of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="DEU 23:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 23:3" />An Ammonite or Moabite shall not enter into the congregation of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; even to their tenth generation shall they not enter into the congregation of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> for ever: <verse eid="DEU 23:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 23:4" />Because they met you not with bread and with water in the way, when ye came forth out of Egypt; and because they hired against thee Balaam the son of Beor of Pethor of Mesopotamia, to curse thee. <verse eid="DEU 23:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 23:5" />Nevertheless the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God would not hearken unto Balaam; but the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God turned the curse into a blessing unto thee, because the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God loved thee. <verse eid="DEU 23:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 23:6" />Thou shalt not seek their peace nor their prosperity all thy days for ever.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">prosperity: Heb. good</char></note><verse eid="DEU 23:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 23:7" />¶ Thou shalt not abhor an Edomite; for he <char style="add">is</char> thy brother: thou shalt not abhor an Egyptian; because thou wast a stranger in his land. <verse eid="DEU 23:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 23:8" />The children that are begotten of them shall enter into the congregation of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> in their third generation.<verse eid="DEU 23:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 23:9" />¶ When the host goeth forth against thine enemies, then keep thee from every wicked thing.<verse eid="DEU 23:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 23:10" />¶ If there be among you any man, that is not clean by reason of uncleanness that chanceth him by night, then shall he go abroad out of the camp, he shall not come within the camp: <verse eid="DEU 23:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 23:11" />But it shall be, when evening cometh on, he shall wash <char style="add">himself</char> with water: and when the sun is down, he shall come into the camp <char style="add">again</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cometh…: Heb. turneth toward</char></note><verse eid="DEU 23:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 23:12" />¶ Thou shalt have a place also without the camp, whither thou shalt go forth abroad: <verse eid="DEU 23:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 23:13" />And thou shalt have a paddle upon thy weapon; and it shall be, when thou wilt ease thyself abroad, thou shalt dig therewith, and shalt turn back and cover that which cometh from thee:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wilt…: Heb. sittest down</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 23:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 23:14" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God walketh in the midst of thy camp, to deliver thee, and to give up thine enemies before thee; therefore shall thy camp be holy: that he see no unclean thing in thee, and turn away from thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">unclean…: Heb. nakedness of any thing</char></note><verse eid="DEU 23:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 23:15" />¶ Thou shalt not deliver unto his master the servant which is escaped from his master unto thee: <verse eid="DEU 23:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 23:16" />He shall dwell with thee, <char style="add">even</char> among you, in that place which he shall choose in one of thy gates, where it liketh him best: thou shalt not oppress him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">liketh…: Heb. is good for him</char></note><verse eid="DEU 23:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 23:17" />¶ There shall be no whore of the daughters of Israel, nor a sodomite of the sons of Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">whore: or, sodomitess</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 23:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 23:18" />Thou shalt not bring the hire of a whore, or the price of a dog, into the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God for any vow: for even both these <char style="add">are</char> abomination unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God.<verse eid="DEU 23:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 23:19" />¶ Thou shalt not lend upon usury to thy brother; usury of money, usury of victuals, usury of any thing that is lent upon usury: <verse eid="DEU 23:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 23:20" />Unto a stranger thou mayest lend upon usury; but unto thy brother thou shalt not lend upon usury: that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God may bless thee in all that thou settest thine hand to in the land whither thou goest to possess it.<verse eid="DEU 23:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 23:21" />¶ When thou shalt vow a vow unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, thou shalt not slack to pay it: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will surely require it of thee; and it would be sin in thee. <verse eid="DEU 23:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 23:22" />But if thou shalt forbear to vow, it shall be no sin in thee. <verse eid="DEU 23:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 23:23" />That which is gone out of thy lips thou shalt keep and perform; <char style="add">even</char> a freewill offering, according as thou hast vowed unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, which thou hast promised with thy mouth.<verse eid="DEU 23:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 23:24" />¶ When thou comest into thy neighbour’s vineyard, then thou mayest eat grapes thy fill at thine own pleasure; but thou shalt not put <char style="add">any</char> in thy vessel. <verse eid="DEU 23:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 23:25" />When thou comest into the standing corn of thy neighbour, then thou mayest pluck the ears with thine hand; but thou shalt not move a sickle unto thy neighbour’s standing corn.<verse eid="DEU 23:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 23" />
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="DEU 24" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 24:1" />When a man hath taken a wife, and married her, and it come to pass that she find no favour in his eyes, because he hath found some uncleanness in her: then let him write her a bill of divorcement, and give <char style="add">it</char> in her hand, and send her out of his house.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">some…: Heb. matter of nakedness</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">divorcement: Heb. cutting off</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 24:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 24:2" />And when she is departed out of his house, she may go and be another man’s <char style="add">wife</char>. <verse eid="DEU 24:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 24:3" />And <char style="add">if</char> the latter husband hate her, and write her a bill of divorcement, and giveth <char style="add">it</char> in her hand, and sendeth her out of his house; or if the latter husband die, which took her <char style="add">to be</char> his wife; <verse eid="DEU 24:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 24:4" />Her former husband, which sent her away, may not take her again to be his wife, after that she is defiled; for that <char style="add">is</char> abomination before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: and thou shalt not cause the land to sin, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance.<verse eid="DEU 24:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 24:5" />¶ When a man hath taken a new wife, he shall not go out to war, neither shall he be charged with any business: <char style="add">but</char> he shall be free at home one year, and shall cheer up his wife which he hath taken.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">neither…: Heb. not any thing shall pass upon him</char></note><verse eid="DEU 24:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 24:6" />¶ No man shall take the nether or the upper millstone to pledge: for he taketh <char style="add">a man’s</char> life to pledge.<verse eid="DEU 24:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 24:7" />¶ If a man be found stealing any of his brethren of the children of Israel, and maketh merchandise of him, or selleth him; then that thief shall die; and thou shalt put evil away from among you.<verse eid="DEU 24:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 24:8" />¶ Take heed in the plague of leprosy, that thou observe diligently, and do according to all that the priests the Levites shall teach you: as I commanded them, <char style="add">so</char> ye shall observe to do. <verse eid="DEU 24:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 24:9" />Remember what the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God did unto Miriam by the way, after that ye were come forth out of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 24:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 24:10" />¶ When thou dost lend thy brother any thing, thou shalt not go into his house to fetch his pledge.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">lend…: Heb. lend the loan of any thing to, etc</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 24:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 24:11" />Thou shalt stand abroad, and the man to whom thou dost lend shall bring out the pledge abroad unto thee. <verse eid="DEU 24:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 24:12" />And if the man <char style="add">be</char> poor, thou shalt not sleep with his pledge: <verse eid="DEU 24:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 24:13" />In any case thou shalt deliver him the pledge again when the sun goeth down, that he may sleep in his own raiment, and bless thee: and it shall be righteousness unto thee before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God.<verse eid="DEU 24:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 24:14" />¶ Thou shalt not oppress an hired servant <char style="add">that is</char> poor and needy, <char style="add">whether he be</char> of thy brethren, or of thy strangers that <char style="add">are</char> in thy land within thy gates: <verse eid="DEU 24:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 24:15" />At his day thou shalt give <char style="add">him</char> his hire, neither shall the sun go down upon it; for he <char style="add">is</char> poor, and setteth his heart upon it: lest he cry against thee unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and it be sin unto thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">setteth…: Heb. lifteth his soul unto it</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 24:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 24:16" />The fathers shall not be put to death for the children, neither shall the children be put to death for the fathers: every man shall be put to death for his own sin.<verse eid="DEU 24:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 24:17" />¶ Thou shalt not pervert the judgment of the stranger, <char style="add">nor</char> of the fatherless; nor take a widow’s raiment to pledge: <verse eid="DEU 24:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 24:18" />But thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God redeemed thee thence: therefore I command thee to do this thing.<verse eid="DEU 24:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 24:19" />¶ When thou cuttest down thine harvest in thy field, and hast forgot a sheaf in the field, thou shalt not go again to fetch it: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow: that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God may bless thee in all the work of thine hands. <verse eid="DEU 24:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 24:20" />When thou beatest thine olive tree, thou shalt not go over the boughs again: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">go…: Heb. bough it after thee</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 24:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 24:21" />When thou gatherest the grapes of thy vineyard, thou shalt not glean <char style="add">it</char> afterward: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">afterward: Heb. after thee</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 24:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 24:22" />And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt: therefore I command thee to do this thing.<verse eid="DEU 24:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 24" />
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="DEU 25" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 25:1" />If there be a controversy between men, and they come unto judgment, that <char style="add">the judges</char> may judge them; then they shall justify the righteous, and condemn the wicked. <verse eid="DEU 25:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 25:2" />And it shall be, if the wicked man <char style="add">be</char> worthy to be beaten, that the judge shall cause him to lie down, and to be beaten before his face, according to his fault, by a certain number. <verse eid="DEU 25:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 25:3" />Forty stripes he may give him, <char style="add">and</char> not exceed: lest, <char style="add">if</char> he should exceed, and beat him above these with many stripes, then thy brother should seem vile unto thee.<verse eid="DEU 25:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 25:4" />¶ Thou shalt not muzzle the ox when he treadeth out <char style="add">the corn</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">treadeth…: Heb. thresheth</char></note><verse eid="DEU 25:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 25:5" />¶ If brethren dwell together, and one of them die, and have no child, the wife of the dead shall not marry without unto a stranger: her husband’s brother shall go in unto her, and take her to him to wife, and perform the duty of an husband’s brother unto her.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">her husband’s…: or, her next kinsman</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 25:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 25:6" />And it shall be, <char style="add">that</char> the firstborn which she beareth shall succeed in the name of his brother <char style="add">which is</char> dead, that his name be not put out of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 25:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 25:7" />And if the man like not to take his brother’s wife, then let his brother’s wife go up to the gate unto the elders, and say, My husband’s brother refuseth to raise up unto his brother a name in Israel, he will not perform the duty of my husband’s brother.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">brother’s: or, next kinsman’s</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 25:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 25:8" />Then the elders of his city shall call him, and speak unto him: and <char style="add">if</char> he stand <char style="add">to it</char>, and say, I like not to take her; <verse eid="DEU 25:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 25:9" />Then shall his brother’s wife come unto him in the presence of the elders, and loose his shoe from off his foot, and spit in his face, and shall answer and say, So shall it be done unto that man that will not build up his brother’s house. <verse eid="DEU 25:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 25:10" />And his name shall be called in Israel, The house of him that hath his shoe loosed.<verse eid="DEU 25:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 25:11" />¶ When men strive together one with another, and the wife of the one draweth near for to deliver her husband out of the hand of him that smiteth him, and putteth forth her hand, and taketh him by the secrets: <verse eid="DEU 25:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 25:12" />Then thou shalt cut off her hand, thine eye shall not pity <char style="add">her</char>.<verse eid="DEU 25:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 25:13" />¶ Thou shalt not have in thy bag divers weights, a great and a small.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">divers…: Heb. a stone and a stone</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 25:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 25:14" />Thou shalt not have in thine house divers measures, a great and a small.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">divers…: Heb. an ephah and an ephah</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 25:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 25:15" /><char style="add">But</char> thou shalt have a perfect and just weight, a perfect and just measure shalt thou have: that thy days may be lengthened in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee. <verse eid="DEU 25:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 25:16" />For all that do such things, <char style="add">and</char> all that do unrighteously, <char style="add">are</char> an abomination unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God.<verse eid="DEU 25:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 25:17" />¶ Remember what Amalek did unto thee by the way, when ye were come forth out of Egypt; <verse eid="DEU 25:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 25:18" />How he met thee by the way, and smote the hindmost of thee, <char style="add">even</char> all <char style="add">that were</char> feeble behind thee, when thou <char style="add">wast</char> faint and weary; and he feared not God. <verse eid="DEU 25:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 25:19" />Therefore it shall be, when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath given thee rest from all thine enemies round about, in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance to possess it, <char style="add">that</char> thou shalt blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under heaven; thou shalt not forget <char style="add">it</char>.<verse eid="DEU 25:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 25" />
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="DEU 26" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 26:1" />And it shall be, when thou <char style="add">art</char> come in unto the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee <char style="add">for</char> an inheritance, and possessest it, and dwellest therein; <verse eid="DEU 26:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 26:2" />That thou shalt take of the first of all the fruit of the earth, which thou shalt bring of thy land that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, and shalt put <char style="add">it</char> in a basket, and shalt go unto the place which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall choose to place his name there. <verse eid="DEU 26:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 26:3" />And thou shalt go unto the priest that shall be in those days, and say unto him, I profess this day unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, that I am come unto the country which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto our fathers for to give us. <verse eid="DEU 26:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 26:4" />And the priest shall take the basket out of thine hand, and set it down before the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God. <verse eid="DEU 26:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 26:5" />And thou shalt speak and say before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, A Syrian ready to perish <char style="add">was</char> my father, and he went down into Egypt, and sojourned there with a few, and became there a nation, great, mighty, and populous: <verse eid="DEU 26:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 26:6" />And the Egyptians evil entreated us, and afflicted us, and laid upon us hard bondage: <verse eid="DEU 26:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 26:7" />And when we cried unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of our fathers, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> heard our voice, and looked on our affliction, and our labour, and our oppression: <verse eid="DEU 26:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 26:8" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> brought us forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with great terribleness, and with signs, and with wonders: <verse eid="DEU 26:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 26:9" />And he hath brought us into this place, and hath given us this land, <char style="add">even</char> a land that floweth with milk and honey. <verse eid="DEU 26:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 26:10" />And now, behold, I have brought the firstfruits of the land, which thou, O <char style="nd">LORD</char>, hast given me. And thou shalt set it before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and worship before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: <verse eid="DEU 26:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 26:11" />And thou shalt rejoice in every good <char style="add">thing</char> which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath given unto thee, and unto thine house, thou, and the Levite, and the stranger that <char style="add">is</char> among you.<verse eid="DEU 26:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 26:12" />¶ When thou hast made an end of tithing all the tithes of thine increase the third year, <char style="add">which is</char> the year of tithing, and hast given <char style="add">it</char> unto the Levite, the stranger, the fatherless, and the widow, that they may eat within thy gates, and be filled; <verse eid="DEU 26:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 26:13" />Then thou shalt say before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, I have brought away the hallowed things out of <char style="add">mine</char> house, and also have given them unto the Levite, and unto the stranger, to the fatherless, and to the widow, according to all thy commandments which thou hast commanded me: I have not transgressed thy commandments, neither have I forgotten <char style="add">them:</char> <verse eid="DEU 26:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 26:14" />I have not eaten thereof in my mourning, neither have I taken away <char style="add">ought</char> thereof for <char style="add">any</char> unclean <char style="add">use</char>, nor given <char style="add">ought</char> thereof for the dead: <char style="add">but</char> I have hearkened to the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> my God, <char style="add">and</char> have done according to all that thou hast commanded me. <verse eid="DEU 26:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 26:15" />Look down from thy holy habitation, from heaven, and bless thy people Israel, and the land which thou hast given us, as thou swarest unto our fathers, a land that floweth with milk and honey.<verse eid="DEU 26:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 26:16" />¶ This day the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath commanded thee to do these statutes and judgments: thou shalt therefore keep and do them with all thine heart, and with all thy soul. <verse eid="DEU 26:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 26:17" />Thou hast avouched the <char style="nd">LORD</char> this day to be thy God, and to walk in his ways, and to keep his statutes, and his commandments, and his judgments, and to hearken unto his voice: <verse eid="DEU 26:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 26:18" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath avouched thee this day to be his peculiar people, as he hath promised thee, and that <char style="add">thou</char> shouldest keep all his commandments; <verse eid="DEU 26:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 26:19" />And to make thee high above all nations which he hath made, in praise, and in name, and in honour; and that thou mayest be an holy people unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, as he hath spoken.<verse eid="DEU 26:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 26" />
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="DEU 27" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 27:1" />And Moses with the elders of Israel commanded the people, saying, Keep all the commandments which I command you this day. <verse eid="DEU 27:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 27:2" />And it shall be on the day when ye shall pass over Jordan unto the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, that thou shalt set thee up great stones, and plaister them with plaister: <verse eid="DEU 27:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 27:3" />And thou shalt write upon them all the words of this law, when thou art passed over, that thou mayest go in unto the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee, a land that floweth with milk and honey; as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of thy fathers hath promised thee. <verse eid="DEU 27:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 27:4" />Therefore it shall be when ye be gone over Jordan, <char style="add">that</char> ye shall set up these stones, which I command you this day, in mount Ebal, and thou shalt plaister them with plaister. <verse eid="DEU 27:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 27:5" />And there shalt thou build an altar unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, an altar of stones: thou shalt not lift up <char style="add">any</char> iron <char style="add">tool</char> upon them. <verse eid="DEU 27:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 27:6" />Thou shalt build the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God of whole stones: and thou shalt offer burnt offerings thereon unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God: <verse eid="DEU 27:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 27:7" />And thou shalt offer peace offerings, and shalt eat there, and rejoice before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God. <verse eid="DEU 27:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 27:8" />And thou shalt write upon the stones all the words of this law very plainly.<verse eid="DEU 27:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 27:9" />¶ And Moses and the priests the Levites spake unto all Israel, saying, Take heed, and hearken, O Israel; this day thou art become the people of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God. <verse eid="DEU 27:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 27:10" />Thou shalt therefore obey the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and do his commandments and his statutes, which I command thee this day.<verse eid="DEU 27:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 27:11" />¶ And Moses charged the people the same day, saying, <verse eid="DEU 27:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 27:12" />These shall stand upon mount Gerizim to bless the people, when ye are come over Jordan; Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Joseph, and Benjamin: <verse eid="DEU 27:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 27:13" />And these shall stand upon mount Ebal to curse; Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to curse: Heb. for a cursing</char></note><verse eid="DEU 27:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 27:14" />¶ And the Levites shall speak, and say unto all the men of Israel with a loud voice, <verse eid="DEU 27:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 27:15" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> the man that maketh <char style="add">any</char> graven or molten image, an abomination unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, the work of the hands of the craftsman, and putteth <char style="add">it</char> in <char style="add">a</char> secret <char style="add">place</char>. And all the people shall answer and say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 27:16" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that setteth light by his father or his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 27:17" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that removeth his neighbour’s landmark. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 27:18" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that maketh the blind to wander out of the way. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 27:19" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that perverteth the judgment of the stranger, fatherless, and widow. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 27:20" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that lieth with his father’s wife; because he uncovereth his father’s skirt. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 27:21" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that lieth with any manner of beast. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 27:22" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that lieth with his sister, the daughter of his father, or the daughter of his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 27:23" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that lieth with his mother in law. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 27:24" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that smiteth his neighbour secretly. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 27:25" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that taketh reward to slay an innocent person. And all the people shall say, Amen. <verse eid="DEU 27:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 27:26" />Cursed <char style="add">be</char> he that confirmeth not <char style="add">all</char> the words of this law to do them. And all the people shall say, Amen.<verse eid="DEU 27:26" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 27" />
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="DEU 28" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 28:1" />And it shall come to pass, if thou shalt hearken diligently unto the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to observe <char style="add">and</char> to do all his commandments which I command thee this day, that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will set thee on high above all nations of the earth: <verse eid="DEU 28:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 28:2" />And all these blessings shall come on thee, and overtake thee, if thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God. <verse eid="DEU 28:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 28:3" />Blessed <char style="add">shalt</char> thou <char style="add">be</char> in the city, and blessed <char style="add">shalt</char> thou <char style="add">be</char> in the field. <verse eid="DEU 28:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 28:4" />Blessed <char style="add">shall be</char> the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit of thy cattle, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep. <verse eid="DEU 28:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 28:5" />Blessed <char style="add">shall be</char> thy basket and thy store.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">store: or, dough, or, kneadingtroughs</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 28:6" />Blessed <char style="add">shalt</char> thou <char style="add">be</char> when thou comest in, and blessed <char style="add">shalt</char> thou <char style="add">be</char> when thou goest out. <verse eid="DEU 28:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 28:7" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall cause thine enemies that rise up against thee to be smitten before thy face: they shall come out against thee one way, and flee before thee seven ways. <verse eid="DEU 28:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 28:8" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall command the blessing upon thee in thy storehouses, and in all that thou settest thine hand unto; and he shall bless thee in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God giveth thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">storehouses: or, barns</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 28:9" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall establish thee an holy people unto himself, as he hath sworn unto thee, if thou shalt keep the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and walk in his ways. <verse eid="DEU 28:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 28:10" />And all people of the earth shall see that thou art called by the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; and they shall be afraid of thee. <verse eid="DEU 28:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 28:11" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall make thee plenteous in goods, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy ground, in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto thy fathers to give thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in goods: or, for good</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">body: Heb. belly</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 28:12" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall open unto thee his good treasure, the heaven to give the rain unto thy land in his season, and to bless all the work of thine hand: and thou shalt lend unto many nations, and thou shalt not borrow. <verse eid="DEU 28:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 28:13" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall make thee the head, and not the tail; and thou shalt be above only, and thou shalt not be beneath; if that thou hearken unto the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, which I command thee this day, to observe and to do <char style="add">them:</char> <verse eid="DEU 28:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 28:14" />And thou shalt not go aside from any of the words which I command thee this day, <char style="add">to</char> the right hand, or <char style="add">to</char> the left, to go after other gods to serve them.<verse eid="DEU 28:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 28:15" />¶ But it shall come to pass, if thou wilt not hearken unto the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to observe to do all his commandments and his statutes which I command thee this day; that all these curses shall come upon thee, and overtake thee: <verse eid="DEU 28:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 28:16" />Cursed <char style="add">shalt</char> thou <char style="add">be</char> in the city, and cursed <char style="add">shalt</char> thou <char style="add">be</char> in the field. <verse eid="DEU 28:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 28:17" />Cursed <char style="add">shall be</char> thy basket and thy store. <verse eid="DEU 28:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 28:18" />Cursed <char style="add">shall be</char> the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy land, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep. <verse eid="DEU 28:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 28:19" />Cursed <char style="add">shalt</char> thou <char style="add">be</char> when thou comest in, and cursed <char style="add">shalt</char> thou <char style="add">be</char> when thou goest out. <verse eid="DEU 28:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 28:20" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall send upon thee cursing, vexation, and rebuke, in all that thou settest thine hand unto for to do, until thou be destroyed, and until thou perish quickly; because of the wickedness of thy doings, whereby thou hast forsaken me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">for…: Heb. which thou wouldest do</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 28:21" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall make the pestilence cleave unto thee, until he have consumed thee from off the land, whither thou goest to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 28:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 28:22" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall smite thee with a consumption, and with a fever, and with an inflammation, and with an extreme burning, and with the sword, and with blasting, and with mildew; and they shall pursue thee until thou perish.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sword: or, drought</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 28:23" />And thy heaven that <char style="add">is</char> over thy head shall be brass, and the earth that is under thee <char style="add">shall be</char> iron. <verse eid="DEU 28:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 28:24" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall make the rain of thy land powder and dust: from heaven shall it come down upon thee, until thou be destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 28:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 28:25" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall cause thee to be smitten before thine enemies: thou shalt go out one way against them, and flee seven ways before them: and shalt be removed into all the kingdoms of the earth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">removed: Heb. for a removing</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 28:26" />And thy carcase shall be meat unto all fowls of the air, and unto the beasts of the earth, and no man shall fray <char style="add">them</char> away. <verse eid="DEU 28:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 28:27" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> will smite thee with the botch of Egypt, and with the emerods, and with the scab, and with the itch, whereof thou canst not be healed. <verse eid="DEU 28:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 28:28" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall smite thee with madness, and blindness, and astonishment of heart: <verse eid="DEU 28:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 28:29" />And thou shalt grope at noonday, as the blind gropeth in darkness, and thou shalt not prosper in thy ways: and thou shalt be only oppressed and spoiled evermore, and no man shall save <char style="add">thee</char>. <verse eid="DEU 28:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 28:30" />Thou shalt betroth a wife, and another man shall lie with her: thou shalt build an house, and thou shalt not dwell therein: thou shalt plant a vineyard, and shalt not gather the grapes thereof.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gather…: Heb. profane, or, use it as common meat</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 28:31" />Thine ox <char style="add">shall be</char> slain before thine eyes, and thou shalt not eat thereof: thine ass <char style="add">shall be</char> violently taken away from before thy face, and shall not be restored to thee: thy sheep <char style="add">shall be</char> given unto thine enemies, and thou shalt have none to rescue <char style="add">them</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">shall not…: Heb. shall not return to thee</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 28:32" />Thy sons and thy daughters <char style="add">shall be</char> given unto another people, and thine eyes shall look, and fail <char style="add">with longing</char> for them all the day long: and <char style="add">there shall be</char> no might in thine hand. <verse eid="DEU 28:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 28:33" />The fruit of thy land, and all thy labours, shall a nation which thou knowest not eat up; and thou shalt be only oppressed and crushed alway: <verse eid="DEU 28:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 28:34" />So that thou shalt be mad for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt see. <verse eid="DEU 28:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 28:35" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall smite thee in the knees, and in the legs, with a sore botch that cannot be healed, from the sole of thy foot unto the top of thy head. <verse eid="DEU 28:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 28:36" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall bring thee, and thy king which thou shalt set over thee, unto a nation which neither thou nor thy fathers have known; and there shalt thou serve other gods, wood and stone. <verse eid="DEU 28:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 28:37" />And thou shalt become an astonishment, a proverb, and a byword, among all nations whither the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall lead thee. <verse eid="DEU 28:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 28:38" />Thou shalt carry much seed out into the field, and shalt gather <char style="add">but</char> little in; for the locust shall consume it. <verse eid="DEU 28:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 28:39" />Thou shalt plant vineyards, and dress <char style="add">them</char>, but shalt neither drink <char style="add">of</char> the wine, nor gather <char style="add">the grapes;</char> for the worms shall eat them. <verse eid="DEU 28:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 28:40" />Thou shalt have olive trees throughout all thy coasts, but thou shalt not anoint <char style="add">thyself</char> with the oil; for thine olive shall cast <char style="add">his fruit</char>. <verse eid="DEU 28:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 28:41" />Thou shalt beget sons and daughters, but thou shalt not enjoy them; for they shall go into captivity.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.41 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">thou shalt not…: Heb. they shall not be thine</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 28:42" />All thy trees and fruit of thy land shall the locust consume.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.42 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">consume: or, possess</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 28:43" />The stranger that <char style="add">is</char> within thee shall get up above thee very high; and thou shalt come down very low. <verse eid="DEU 28:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 28:44" />He shall lend to thee, and thou shalt not lend to him: he shall be the head, and thou shalt be the tail.<verse eid="DEU 28:44" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 28:45" />Moreover all these curses shall come upon thee, and shall pursue thee, and overtake thee, till thou be destroyed; because thou hearkenedst not unto the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which he commanded thee: <verse eid="DEU 28:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 28:46" />And they shall be upon thee for a sign and for a wonder, and upon thy seed for ever. <verse eid="DEU 28:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 28:47" />Because thou servedst not the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God with joyfulness, and with gladness of heart, for the abundance of all <char style="add">things;</char> <verse eid="DEU 28:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 28:48" />Therefore shalt thou serve thine enemies which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall send against thee, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in want of all <char style="add">things:</char> and he shall put a yoke of iron upon thy neck, until he have destroyed thee. <verse eid="DEU 28:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 28:49" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall bring a nation against thee from far, from the end of the earth, <char style="add">as swift</char> as the eagle flieth; a nation whose tongue thou shalt not understand;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.49 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">understand: Heb. hear</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="DEU 28:50" />A nation of fierce countenance, which shall not regard the person of the old, nor shew favour to the young:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.50 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of fierce…: Heb. strong of face</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="DEU 28:51" />And he shall eat the fruit of thy cattle, and the fruit of thy land, until thou be destroyed: which <char style="add">also</char> shall not leave thee <char style="add">either</char> corn, wine, or oil, <char style="add">or</char> the increase of thy kine, or flocks of thy sheep, until he have destroyed thee. <verse eid="DEU 28:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="DEU 28:52" />And he shall besiege thee in all thy gates, until thy high and fenced walls come down, wherein thou trustedst, throughout all thy land: and he shall besiege thee in all thy gates throughout all thy land, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath given thee. <verse eid="DEU 28:52" /><verse number="53" style="v" sid="DEU 28:53" />And thou shalt eat the fruit of thine own body, the flesh of thy sons and of thy daughters, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath given thee, in the siege, and in the straitness, wherewith thine enemies shall distress thee:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.53 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">body: Heb. belly</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:53" /><verse number="54" style="v" sid="DEU 28:54" /><char style="add">So that</char> the man <char style="add">that is</char> tender among you, and very delicate, his eye shall be evil toward his brother, and toward the wife of his bosom, and toward the remnant of his children which he shall leave: <verse eid="DEU 28:54" /><verse number="55" style="v" sid="DEU 28:55" />So that he will not give to any of them of the flesh of his children whom he shall eat: because he hath nothing left him in the siege, and in the straitness, wherewith thine enemies shall distress thee in all thy gates. <verse eid="DEU 28:55" /><verse number="56" style="v" sid="DEU 28:56" />The tender and delicate woman among you, which would not adventure to set the sole of her foot upon the ground for delicateness and tenderness, her eye shall be evil toward the husband of her bosom, and toward her son, and toward her daughter, <verse eid="DEU 28:56" /><verse number="57" style="v" sid="DEU 28:57" />And toward her young one that cometh out from between her feet, and toward her children which she shall bear: for she shall eat them for want of all <char style="add">things</char> secretly in the siege and straitness, wherewith thine enemy shall distress thee in thy gates.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.57 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">young one: Heb. afterbirth</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:57" /><verse number="58" style="v" sid="DEU 28:58" />If thou wilt not observe to do all the words of this law that are written in this book, that thou mayest fear this glorious and fearful name, THE <char style="nd">LORD</char> THY GOD; <verse eid="DEU 28:58" /><verse number="59" style="v" sid="DEU 28:59" />Then the <char style="nd">LORD</char> will make thy plagues wonderful, and the plagues of thy seed, <char style="add">even</char> great plagues, and of long continuance, and sore sicknesses, and of long continuance. <verse eid="DEU 28:59" /><verse number="60" style="v" sid="DEU 28:60" />Moreover he will bring upon thee all the diseases of Egypt, which thou wast afraid of; and they shall cleave unto thee. <verse eid="DEU 28:60" /><verse number="61" style="v" sid="DEU 28:61" />Also every sickness, and every plague, which <char style="add">is</char> not written in the book of this law, them will the <char style="nd">LORD</char> bring upon thee, until thou be destroyed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.61 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">bring: Heb. cause to ascend</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 28:61" /><verse number="62" style="v" sid="DEU 28:62" />And ye shall be left few in number, whereas ye were as the stars of heaven for multitude; because thou wouldest not obey the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God. <verse eid="DEU 28:62" /><verse number="63" style="v" sid="DEU 28:63" />And it shall come to pass, <char style="add">that</char> as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> rejoiced over you to do you good, and to multiply you; so the <char style="nd">LORD</char> will rejoice over you to destroy you, and to bring you to nought; and ye shall be plucked from off the land whither thou goest to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 28:63" /><verse number="64" style="v" sid="DEU 28:64" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall scatter thee among all people, from the one end of the earth even unto the other; and there thou shalt serve other gods, which neither thou nor thy fathers have known, <char style="add">even</char> wood and stone. <verse eid="DEU 28:64" /><verse number="65" style="v" sid="DEU 28:65" />And among these nations shalt thou find no ease, neither shall the sole of thy foot have rest: but the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall give thee there a trembling heart, and failing of eyes, and sorrow of mind: <verse eid="DEU 28:65" /><verse number="66" style="v" sid="DEU 28:66" />And thy life shall hang in doubt before thee; and thou shalt fear day and night, and shalt have none assurance of thy life: <verse eid="DEU 28:66" /><verse number="67" style="v" sid="DEU 28:67" />In the morning thou shalt say, Would God it were even! and at even thou shalt say, Would God it were morning! for the fear of thine heart wherewith thou shalt fear, and for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt see. <verse eid="DEU 28:67" /><verse number="68" style="v" sid="DEU 28:68" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall bring thee into Egypt again with ships, by the way whereof I spake unto thee, Thou shalt see it no more again: and there ye shall be sold unto your enemies for bondmen and bondwomen, and no man shall buy <char style="add">you</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:68" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 28" />
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="DEU 29" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 29:1" />These <char style="add">are</char> the words of the covenant, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> commanded Moses to make with the children of Israel in the land of Moab, beside the covenant which he made with them in Horeb.<verse eid="DEU 29:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 29:2" />¶ And Moses called unto all Israel, and said unto them, Ye have seen all that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> did before your eyes in the land of Egypt unto Pharaoh, and unto all his servants, and unto all his land; <verse eid="DEU 29:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 29:3" />The great temptations which thine eyes have seen, the signs, and those great miracles: <verse eid="DEU 29:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 29:4" />Yet the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath not given you an heart to perceive, and eyes to see, and ears to hear, unto this day. <verse eid="DEU 29:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 29:5" />And I have led you forty years in the wilderness: your clothes are not waxen old upon you, and thy shoe is not waxen old upon thy foot. <verse eid="DEU 29:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 29:6" />Ye have not eaten bread, neither have ye drunk wine or strong drink: that ye might know that I <char style="add">am</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 29:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 29:7" />And when ye came unto this place, Sihon the king of Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, came out against us unto battle, and we smote them: <verse eid="DEU 29:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 29:8" />And we took their land, and gave it for an inheritance unto the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to the half tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="DEU 29:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 29:9" />Keep therefore the words of this covenant, and do them, that ye may prosper in all that ye do.<verse eid="DEU 29:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 29:10" />¶ Ye stand this day all of you before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God; your captains of your tribes, your elders, and your officers, <char style="add">with</char> all the men of Israel, <verse eid="DEU 29:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 29:11" />Your little ones, your wives, and thy stranger that <char style="add">is</char> in thy camp, from the hewer of thy wood unto the drawer of thy water: <verse eid="DEU 29:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 29:12" />That thou shouldest enter into covenant with the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and into his oath, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God maketh with thee this day:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">enter: Heb. pass</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 29:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 29:13" />That he may establish thee to day for a people unto himself, and <char style="add">that</char> he may be unto thee a God, as he hath said unto thee, and as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. <verse eid="DEU 29:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 29:14" />Neither with you only do I make this covenant and this oath; <verse eid="DEU 29:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 29:15" />But with <char style="add">him</char> that standeth here with us this day before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God, and also with <char style="add">him</char> that <char style="add">is</char> not here with us this day: <verse eid="DEU 29:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 29:16" />(For ye know how we have dwelt in the land of Egypt; and how we came through the nations which ye passed by; <verse eid="DEU 29:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 29:17" />And ye have seen their abominations, and their idols, wood and stone, silver and gold, which <char style="add">were</char> among them:)<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">idols: Heb. dungy gods</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 29:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 29:18" />Lest there should be among you man, or woman, or family, or tribe, whose heart turneth away this day from the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God, to go <char style="add">and</char> serve the gods of these nations; lest there should be among you a root that beareth gall and wormwood;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gall: or, a poisonous herb: Heb. rosh</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 29:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 29:19" />And it come to pass, when he heareth the words of this curse, that he bless himself in his heart, saying, I shall have peace, though I walk in the imagination of mine heart, to add drunkenness to thirst:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">imagination: or, stubbornness</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">drunkenness…: Heb. the drunken to the thirsty</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 29:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 29:20" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> will not spare him, but then the anger of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> and his jealousy shall smoke against that man, and all the curses that are written in this book shall lie upon him, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall blot out his name from under heaven. <verse eid="DEU 29:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 29:21" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall separate him unto evil out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the covenant that are written in this book of the law:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">are: Heb. is</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 29:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 29:22" />So that the generation to come of your children that shall rise up after you, and the stranger that shall come from a far land, shall say, when they see the plagues of that land, and the sicknesses which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath laid upon it;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">which…: Heb. wherewith the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath made it sick</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 29:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 29:23" /><char style="add">And that</char> the whole land thereof <char style="add">is</char> brimstone, and salt, <char style="add">and</char> burning, <char style="add">that</char> it is not sown, nor beareth, nor any grass groweth therein, like the overthrow of Sodom, and Gomorrah, Admah, and Zeboim, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> overthrew in his anger, and in his wrath: <verse eid="DEU 29:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 29:24" />Even all nations shall say, Wherefore hath the <char style="nd">LORD</char> done thus unto this land? what <char style="add">meaneth</char> the heat of this great anger? <verse eid="DEU 29:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 29:25" />Then men shall say, Because they have forsaken the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them forth out of the land of Egypt: <verse eid="DEU 29:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 29:26" />For they went and served other gods, and worshipped them, gods whom they knew not, and <char style="add">whom</char> he had not given unto them:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">whom he…: or, who had not given to them any portion</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">given: Heb. divided</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 29:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 29:27" />And the anger of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> was kindled against this land, to bring upon it all the curses that are written in this book: <verse eid="DEU 29:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 29:28" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> rooted them out of their land in anger, and in wrath, and in great indignation, and cast them into another land, as <char style="add">it is</char> this day. <verse eid="DEU 29:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 29:29" />The secret <char style="add">things belong</char> unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God: but those <char style="add">things which are</char> revealed <char style="add">belong</char> unto us and to our children for ever, that <char style="add">we</char> may do all the words of this law.<verse eid="DEU 29:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 29" />
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="DEU 30" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 30:1" />And it shall come to pass, when all these things are come upon thee, the blessing and the curse, which I have set before thee, and thou shalt call <char style="add">them</char> to mind among all the nations, whither the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath driven thee, <verse eid="DEU 30:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 30:2" />And shalt return unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, and shalt obey his voice according to all that I command thee this day, thou and thy children, with all thine heart, and with all thy soul; <verse eid="DEU 30:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 30:3" />That then the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will turn thy captivity, and have compassion upon thee, and will return and gather thee from all the nations, whither the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God hath scattered thee. <verse eid="DEU 30:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 30:4" />If <char style="add">any</char> of thine be driven out unto the outmost <char style="add">parts</char> of heaven, from thence will the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God gather thee, and from thence will he fetch thee: <verse eid="DEU 30:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 30:5" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will bring thee into the land which thy fathers possessed, and thou shalt possess it; and he will do thee good, and multiply thee above thy fathers. <verse eid="DEU 30:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 30:6" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will circumcise thine heart, and the heart of thy seed, to love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul, that thou mayest live. <verse eid="DEU 30:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 30:7" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will put all these curses upon thine enemies, and on them that hate thee, which persecuted thee. <verse eid="DEU 30:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 30:8" />And thou shalt return and obey the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and do all his commandments which I command thee this day. <verse eid="DEU 30:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 30:9" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God will make thee plenteous in every work of thine hand, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy land, for good: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> will again rejoice over thee for good, as he rejoiced over thy fathers: <verse eid="DEU 30:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 30:10" />If thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which are written in this book of the law, <char style="add">and</char> if thou turn unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul.<verse eid="DEU 30:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 30:11" />¶ For this commandment which I command thee this day, it <char style="add">is</char> not hidden from thee, neither <char style="add">is</char> it far off. <verse eid="DEU 30:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 30:12" />It <char style="add">is</char> not in heaven, that thou shouldest say, Who shall go up for us to heaven, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it, and do it? <verse eid="DEU 30:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 30:13" />Neither <char style="add">is</char> it beyond the sea, that thou shouldest say, Who shall go over the sea for us, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it, and do it? <verse eid="DEU 30:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 30:14" />But the word <char style="add">is</char> very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayest do it.<verse eid="DEU 30:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 30:15" />¶ See, I have set before thee this day life and good, and death and evil; <verse eid="DEU 30:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 30:16" />In that I command thee this day to love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his commandments and his statutes and his judgments, that thou mayest live and multiply: and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God shall bless thee in the land whither thou goest to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 30:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 30:17" />But if thine heart turn away, so that thou wilt not hear, but shalt be drawn away, and worship other gods, and serve them; <verse eid="DEU 30:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 30:18" />I denounce unto you this day, that ye shall surely perish, <char style="add">and that</char> ye shall not prolong <char style="add">your</char> days upon the land, whither thou passest over Jordan to go to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 30:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 30:19" />I call heaven and earth to record this day against you, <char style="add">that</char> I have set before you life and death, blessing and cursing: therefore choose life, that both thou and thy seed may live: <verse eid="DEU 30:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 30:20" />That thou mayest love the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, <char style="add">and</char> that thou mayest obey his voice, and that thou mayest cleave unto him: for he <char style="add">is</char> thy life, and the length of thy days: that thou mayest dwell in the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give them.<verse eid="DEU 30:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 30" />
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="DEU 31" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 31:1" />And Moses went and spake these words unto all Israel. <verse eid="DEU 31:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 31:2" />And he said unto them, I <char style="add">am</char> an hundred and twenty years old this day; I can no more go out and come in: also the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath said unto me, Thou shalt not go over this Jordan. <verse eid="DEU 31:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 31:3" />The <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, he will go over before thee, <char style="add">and</char> he will destroy these nations from before thee, and thou shalt possess them: <char style="add">and</char> Joshua, he shall go over before thee, as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath said. <verse eid="DEU 31:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 31:4" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall do unto them as he did to Sihon and to Og, kings of the Amorites, and unto the land of them, whom he destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 31:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 31:5" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall give them up before your face, that ye may do unto them according unto all the commandments which I have commanded you. <verse eid="DEU 31:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 31:6" />Be strong and of a good courage, fear not, nor be afraid of them: for the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God, he <char style="add">it is</char> that doth go with thee; he will not fail thee, nor forsake thee.<verse eid="DEU 31:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 31:7" />¶ And Moses called unto Joshua, and said unto him in the sight of all Israel, Be strong and of a good courage: for thou must go with this people unto the land which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath sworn unto their fathers to give them; and thou shalt cause them to inherit it. <verse eid="DEU 31:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 31:8" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, he <char style="add">it is</char> that doth go before thee; he will be with thee, he will not fail thee, neither forsake thee: fear not, neither be dismayed.<verse eid="DEU 31:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 31:9" />¶ And Moses wrote this law, and delivered it unto the priests the sons of Levi, which bare the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and unto all the elders of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 31:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 31:10" />And Moses commanded them, saying, At the end of <char style="add">every</char> seven years, in the solemnity of the year of release, in the feast of tabernacles, <verse eid="DEU 31:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 31:11" />When all Israel is come to appear before the <char style="nd">LORD</char> thy God in the place which he shall choose, thou shalt read this law before all Israel in their hearing. <verse eid="DEU 31:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 31:12" />Gather the people together, men, and women, and children, and thy stranger that <char style="add">is</char> within thy gates, that they may hear, and that they may learn, and fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, and observe to do all the words of this law: <verse eid="DEU 31:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 31:13" />And <char style="add">that</char> their children, which have not known <char style="add">any thing</char>, may hear, and learn to fear the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, as long as ye live in the land whither ye go over Jordan to possess it.<verse eid="DEU 31:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 31:14" />¶ And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto Moses, Behold, thy days approach that thou must die: call Joshua, and present yourselves in the tabernacle of the congregation, that I may give him a charge. And Moses and Joshua went, and presented themselves in the tabernacle of the congregation. <verse eid="DEU 31:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 31:15" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> appeared in the tabernacle in a pillar of a cloud: and the pillar of the cloud stood over the door of the tabernacle.<verse eid="DEU 31:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 31:16" />¶ And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto Moses, Behold, thou shalt sleep with thy fathers; and this people will rise up, and go a whoring after the gods of the strangers of the land, whither they go <char style="add">to be</char> among them, and will forsake me, and break my covenant which I have made with them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sleep: Heb. lie down</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 31:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 31:17" />Then my anger shall be kindled against them in that day, and I will forsake them, and I will hide my face from them, and they shall be devoured, and many evils and troubles shall befall them; so that they will say in that day, Are not these evils come upon us, because our God <char style="add">is</char> not among us?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">befall: Heb. find</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 31:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 31:18" />And I will surely hide my face in that day for all the evils which they shall have wrought, in that they are turned unto other gods. <verse eid="DEU 31:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 31:19" />Now therefore write ye this song for you, and teach it the children of Israel: put it in their mouths, that this song may be a witness for me against the children of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 31:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 31:20" />For when I shall have brought them into the land which I sware unto their fathers, that floweth with milk and honey; and they shall have eaten and filled themselves, and waxen fat; then will they turn unto other gods, and serve them, and provoke me, and break my covenant. <verse eid="DEU 31:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 31:21" />And it shall come to pass, when many evils and troubles are befallen them, that this song shall testify against them as a witness; for it shall not be forgotten out of the mouths of their seed: for I know their imagination which they go about, even now, before I have brought them into the land which I sware.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">against: Heb. before</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">go…: Heb. do</char></note><verse eid="DEU 31:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 31:22" />¶ Moses therefore wrote this song the same day, and taught it the children of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 31:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 31:23" />And he gave Joshua the son of Nun a charge, and said, Be strong and of a good courage: for thou shalt bring the children of Israel into the land which I sware unto them: and I will be with thee.<verse eid="DEU 31:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 31:24" />¶ And it came to pass, when Moses had made an end of writing the words of this law in a book, until they were finished, <verse eid="DEU 31:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 31:25" />That Moses commanded the Levites, which bare the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, saying, <verse eid="DEU 31:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 31:26" />Take this book of the law, and put it in the side of the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God, that it may be there for a witness against thee. <verse eid="DEU 31:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 31:27" />For I know thy rebellion, and thy stiff neck: behold, while I am yet alive with you this day, ye have been rebellious against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>; and how much more after my death?<verse eid="DEU 31:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 31:28" />¶ Gather unto me all the elders of your tribes, and your officers, that I may speak these words in their ears, and call heaven and earth to record against them. <verse eid="DEU 31:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 31:29" />For I know that after my death ye will utterly corrupt <char style="add">yourselves</char>, and turn aside from the way which I have commanded you; and evil will befall you in the latter days; because ye will do evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, to provoke him to anger through the work of your hands. <verse eid="DEU 31:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 31:30" />And Moses spake in the ears of all the congregation of Israel the words of this song, until they were ended.<verse eid="DEU 31:30" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 31" />
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="DEU 32" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 32:1" />Give ear, O ye heavens, and I will speak; and hear, O earth, the words of my mouth. <verse eid="DEU 32:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 32:2" />My doctrine shall drop as the rain, my speech shall distil as the dew, as the small rain upon the tender herb, and as the showers upon the grass: <verse eid="DEU 32:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 32:3" />Because I will publish the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: ascribe ye greatness unto our God. <verse eid="DEU 32:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 32:4" /><char style="add">He is</char> the Rock, his work <char style="add">is</char> perfect: for all his ways <char style="add">are</char> judgment: a God of truth and without iniquity, just and right <char style="add">is</char> he. <verse eid="DEU 32:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 32:5" />They have corrupted themselves, their spot <char style="add">is</char> not <char style="add">the spot</char> of his children: <char style="add">they are</char> a perverse and crooked generation.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">They have…: Heb. He hath corrupted to himself</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">their…: or, that they are not his children, that is their blot</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 32:6" />Do ye thus requite the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, O foolish people and unwise? <char style="add">is</char> not he thy father <char style="add">that</char> hath bought thee? hath he not made thee, and established thee?<verse eid="DEU 32:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 32:7" />¶ Remember the days of old, consider the years of many generations: ask thy father, and he will shew thee; thy elders, and they will tell thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">many…: Heb. generation and generation</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 32:8" />When the most High divided to the nations their inheritance, when he separated the sons of Adam, he set the bounds of the people according to the number of the children of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 32:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 32:9" />For the <char style="nd">LORD’s</char> portion <char style="add">is</char> his people; Jacob <char style="add">is</char> the lot of his inheritance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">lot: Heb. cord</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 32:10" />He found him in a desert land, and in the waste howling wilderness; he led him about, he instructed him, he kept him as the apple of his eye.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">led: or, compassed</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 32:11" />As an eagle stirreth up her nest, fluttereth over her young, spreadeth abroad her wings, taketh them, beareth them on her wings: <verse eid="DEU 32:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 32:12" /><char style="add">So</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> alone did lead him, and <char style="add">there was</char> no strange god with him. <verse eid="DEU 32:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 32:13" />He made him ride on the high places of the earth, that he might eat the increase of the fields; and he made him to suck honey out of the rock, and oil out of the flinty rock; <verse eid="DEU 32:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 32:14" />Butter of kine, and milk of sheep, with fat of lambs, and rams of the breed of Bashan, and goats, with the fat of kidneys of wheat; and thou didst drink the pure blood of the grape.<verse eid="DEU 32:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 32:15" />¶ But Jeshurun waxed fat, and kicked: thou art waxen fat, thou art grown thick, thou art covered <char style="add">with fatness;</char> then he forsook God <char style="add">which</char> made him, and lightly esteemed the Rock of his salvation. <verse eid="DEU 32:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 32:16" />They provoked him to jealousy with strange <char style="add">gods</char>, with abominations provoked they him to anger. <verse eid="DEU 32:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 32:17" />They sacrificed unto devils, not to God; to gods whom they knew not, to new <char style="add">gods that</char> came newly up, whom your fathers feared not.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">not to…: or, which were not God</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 32:18" />Of the Rock <char style="add">that</char> begat thee thou art unmindful, and hast forgotten God that formed thee.<verse eid="DEU 32:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 32:19" />And when the <char style="nd">LORD</char> saw <char style="add">it</char>, he abhorred <char style="add">them</char>, because of the provoking of his sons, and of his daughters.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">abhorred: or, despised</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 32:20" />And he said, I will hide my face from them, I will see what their end <char style="add">shall be:</char> for they <char style="add">are</char> a very froward generation, children in whom <char style="add">is</char> no faith. <verse eid="DEU 32:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 32:21" />They have moved me to jealousy with <char style="add">that which is</char> not God; they have provoked me to anger with their vanities: and I will move them to jealousy with <char style="add">those which are</char> not a people; I will provoke them to anger with a foolish nation. <verse eid="DEU 32:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 32:22" />For a fire is kindled in mine anger, and shall burn unto the lowest hell, and shall consume the earth with her increase, and set on fire the foundations of the mountains.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">shall burn: or, hath burned</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">shall consume: or, hath consumed</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 32:23" />I will heap mischiefs upon them; I will spend mine arrows upon them. <verse eid="DEU 32:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 32:24" /><char style="add">They shall be</char> burnt with hunger, and devoured with burning heat, and with bitter destruction: I will also send the teeth of beasts upon them, with the poison of serpents of the dust.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">heat: Heb. coals</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 32:25" />The sword without, and terror within, shall destroy both the young man and the virgin, the suckling <char style="add">also</char> with the man of gray hairs.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">within: Heb. from the chambers</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">destroy: Heb. bereave</char></note><verse eid="DEU 32:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 32:26" />I said, I would scatter them into corners, I would make the remembrance of them to cease from among men: <verse eid="DEU 32:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 32:27" />Were it not that I feared the wrath of the enemy, lest their adversaries should behave themselves strangely, <char style="add">and</char> lest they should say, Our hand <char style="add">is</char> high, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath not done all this.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Our…: or, Our high hand, and not the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath done</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 32:28" />For they <char style="add">are</char> a nation void of counsel, neither <char style="add">is there any</char> understanding in them. <verse eid="DEU 32:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 32:29" />O that they were wise, <char style="add">that</char> they understood this, <char style="add">that</char> they would consider their latter end! <verse eid="DEU 32:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 32:30" />How should one chase a thousand, and two put ten thousand to flight, except their Rock had sold them, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had shut them up? <verse eid="DEU 32:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 32:31" />For their rock <char style="add">is</char> not as our Rock, even our enemies themselves <char style="add">being</char> judges. <verse eid="DEU 32:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 32:32" />For their vine <char style="add">is</char> of the vine of Sodom, and of the fields of Gomorrah: their grapes <char style="add">are</char> grapes of gall, their clusters <char style="add">are</char> bitter:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of the vine: or, worse than the vine</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 32:33" />Their wine <char style="add">is</char> the poison of dragons, and the cruel venom of asps. <verse eid="DEU 32:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 32:34" /><char style="add">Is</char> not this laid up in store with me, <char style="add">and</char> sealed up among my treasures? <verse eid="DEU 32:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 32:35" />To me <char style="add">belongeth</char> vengeance, and recompence; their foot shall slide in <char style="add">due</char> time: for the day of their calamity <char style="add">is</char> at hand, and the things that shall come upon them make haste. <verse eid="DEU 32:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 32:36" />For the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall judge his people, and repent himself for his servants, when he seeth that <char style="add">their</char> power is gone, and <char style="add">there is</char> none shut up, or left.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">power: Heb. hand</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 32:37" />And he shall say, Where <char style="add">are</char> their gods, <char style="add">their</char> rock in whom they trusted, <verse eid="DEU 32:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 32:38" />Which did eat the fat of their sacrifices, <char style="add">and</char> drank the wine of their drink offerings? let them rise up and help you, <char style="add">and</char> be your protection.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">your…: Heb. an hiding for you</char></note><verse eid="DEU 32:38" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 32:39" />See now that I, <char style="add">even</char> I, <char style="add">am</char> he, and <char style="add">there is</char> no god with me: I kill, and I make alive; I wound, and I heal: neither <char style="add">is there any</char> that can deliver out of my hand. <verse eid="DEU 32:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 32:40" />For I lift up my hand to heaven, and say, I live for ever. <verse eid="DEU 32:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 32:41" />If I whet my glittering sword, and mine hand take hold on judgment; I will render vengeance to mine enemies, and will reward them that hate me. <verse eid="DEU 32:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 32:42" />I will make mine arrows drunk with blood, and my sword shall devour flesh; <char style="add">and that</char> with the blood of the slain and of the captives, from the beginning of revenges upon the enemy. <verse eid="DEU 32:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 32:43" />Rejoice, O ye nations, <char style="add">with</char> his people: for he will avenge the blood of his servants, and will render vengeance to his adversaries, and will be merciful unto his land, <char style="add">and</char> to his people.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.43 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Rejoice…: or, Praise his people, ye nations: or, Sing ye</char></note><verse eid="DEU 32:43" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 32:44" />¶ And Moses came and spake all the words of this song in the ears of the people, he, and Hoshea the son of Nun.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.44 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hoshea: or, Joshua</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 32:45" />And Moses made an end of speaking all these words to all Israel: <verse eid="DEU 32:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 32:46" />And he said unto them, Set your hearts unto all the words which I testify among you this day, which ye shall command your children to observe to do, all the words of this law. <verse eid="DEU 32:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 32:47" />For it <char style="add">is</char> not a vain thing for you; because it <char style="add">is</char> your life: and through this thing ye shall prolong <char style="add">your</char> days in the land, whither ye go over Jordan to possess it. <verse eid="DEU 32:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 32:48" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> spake unto Moses that selfsame day, saying, <verse eid="DEU 32:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 32:49" />Get thee up into this mountain Abarim, <char style="add">unto</char> mount Nebo, which <char style="add">is</char> in the land of Moab, that <char style="add">is</char> over against Jericho; and behold the land of Canaan, which I give unto the children of Israel for a possession: <verse eid="DEU 32:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="DEU 32:50" />And die in the mount whither thou goest up, and be gathered unto thy people; as Aaron thy brother died in mount Hor, and was gathered unto his people: <verse eid="DEU 32:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="DEU 32:51" />Because ye trespassed against me among the children of Israel at the waters of Meribah-Kadesh, in the wilderness of Zin; because ye sanctified me not in the midst of the children of Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.51 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Meribah-Kadesh: or, strife at Kadesh</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 32:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="DEU 32:52" />Yet thou shalt see the land before <char style="add">thee;</char> but thou shalt not go thither unto the land which I give the children of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 32:52" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 32" />
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="DEU 33" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 33:1" />And this <char style="add">is</char> the blessing, wherewith Moses the man of God blessed the children of Israel before his death. <verse eid="DEU 33:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 33:2" />And he said, The <char style="nd">LORD</char> came from Sinai, and rose up from Seir unto them; he shined forth from mount Paran, and he came with ten thousands of saints: from his right hand <char style="add">went</char> a fiery law for them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a fiery…: Heb. a fire of law</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 33:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 33:3" />Yea, he loved the people; all his saints <char style="add">are</char> in thy hand: and they sat down at thy feet; <char style="add">every one</char> shall receive of thy words. <verse eid="DEU 33:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 33:4" />Moses commanded us a law, <char style="add">even</char> the inheritance of the congregation of Jacob. <verse eid="DEU 33:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 33:5" />And he was king in Jeshurun, when the heads of the people <char style="add">and</char> the tribes of Israel were gathered together.<verse eid="DEU 33:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 33:6" />¶ Let Reuben live, and not die; and let <char style="add">not</char> his men be few.<verse eid="DEU 33:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 33:7" />¶ And this <char style="add">is the blessing</char> of Judah: and he said, Hear, <char style="nd">LORD</char>, the voice of Judah, and bring him unto his people: let his hands be sufficient for him; and be thou an help <char style="add">to him</char> from his enemies.<verse eid="DEU 33:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 33:8" />¶ And of Levi he said, <char style="add">Let</char> thy Thummim and thy Urim <char style="add">be</char> with thy holy one, whom thou didst prove at Massah, <char style="add">and with</char> whom thou didst strive at the waters of Meribah; <verse eid="DEU 33:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 33:9" />Who said unto his father and to his mother, I have not seen him; neither did he acknowledge his brethren, nor knew his own children: for they have observed thy word, and kept thy covenant. <verse eid="DEU 33:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 33:10" />They shall teach Jacob thy judgments, and Israel thy law: they shall put incense before thee, and whole burnt sacrifice upon thine altar.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">They shall teach: or, Let them teach</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">they shall put: or, let them put</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">before…: Heb. at thy nose</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 33:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 33:11" />Bless, <char style="nd">LORD</char>, his substance, and accept the work of his hands: smite through the loins of them that rise against him, and of them that hate him, that they rise not again.<verse eid="DEU 33:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 33:12" />¶ <char style="add">And</char> of Benjamin he said, The beloved of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shall dwell in safety by him; <char style="add">and the <char style="nd">Lord</char></char> shall cover him all the day long, and he shall dwell between his shoulders.<verse eid="DEU 33:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 33:13" />¶ And of Joseph he said, Blessed of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> <char style="add">be</char> his land, for the precious things of heaven, for the dew, and for the deep that coucheth beneath, <verse eid="DEU 33:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 33:14" />And for the precious fruits <char style="add">brought forth</char> by the sun, and for the precious things put forth by the moon,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">put: Heb. thrust</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">moon: Heb. moons</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 33:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 33:15" />And for the chief things of the ancient mountains, and for the precious things of the lasting hills, <verse eid="DEU 33:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 33:16" />And for the precious things of the earth and fulness thereof, and <char style="add">for</char> the good will of him that dwelt in the bush: let <char style="add">the blessing</char> come upon the head of Joseph, and upon the top of the head of him <char style="add">that was</char> separated from his brethren. <verse eid="DEU 33:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 33:17" />His glory <char style="add">is like</char> the firstling of his bullock, and his horns <char style="add">are like</char> the horns of unicorns: with them he shall push the people together to the ends of the earth: and they <char style="add">are</char> the ten thousands of Ephraim, and they <char style="add">are</char> the thousands of Manasseh.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">unicorns: Heb. an unicorn</char></note><verse eid="DEU 33:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 33:18" />¶ And of Zebulun he said, Rejoice, Zebulun, in thy going out; and, Issachar, in thy tents. <verse eid="DEU 33:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 33:19" />They shall call the people unto the mountain; there they shall offer sacrifices of righteousness: for they shall suck <char style="add">of</char> the abundance of the seas, and <char style="add">of</char> treasures hid in the sand.<verse eid="DEU 33:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 33:20" />¶ And of Gad he said, Blessed <char style="add">be</char> he that enlargeth Gad: he dwelleth as a lion, and teareth the arm with the crown of the head. <verse eid="DEU 33:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 33:21" />And he provided the first part for himself, because there, <char style="add">in</char> a portion of the lawgiver, <char style="add">was he</char> seated; and he came with the heads of the people, he executed the justice of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and his judgments with Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">seated: Heb. cieled</char></note><verse eid="DEU 33:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 33:22" />¶ And of Dan he said, Dan <char style="add">is</char> a lion’s whelp: he shall leap from Bashan.<verse eid="DEU 33:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 33:23" />¶ And of Naphtali he said, O Naphtali, satisfied with favour, and full with the blessing of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: possess thou the west and the south.<verse eid="DEU 33:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 33:24" />¶ And of Asher he said, <char style="add">Let</char> Asher <char style="add">be</char> blessed with children; let him be acceptable to his brethren, and let him dip his foot in oil. <verse eid="DEU 33:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 33:25" />Thy shoes <char style="add">shall be</char> iron and brass; and as thy days, <char style="add">so shall</char> thy strength <char style="add">be</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Thy shoes: or, Under thy shoes</char></note><verse eid="DEU 33:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 33:26" />¶ <char style="add">There is</char> none like unto the God of Jeshurun, <char style="add">who</char> rideth upon the heaven in thy help, and in his excellency on the sky. <verse eid="DEU 33:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 33:27" />The eternal God <char style="add">is thy</char> refuge, and underneath <char style="add">are</char> the everlasting arms: and he shall thrust out the enemy from before thee; and shall say, Destroy <char style="add">them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 33:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 33:28" />Israel then shall dwell in safety alone: the fountain of Jacob <char style="add">shall be</char> upon a land of corn and wine; also his heavens shall drop down dew. <verse eid="DEU 33:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 33:29" />Happy <char style="add">art</char> thou, O Israel: who <char style="add">is</char> like unto thee, O people saved by the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, the shield of thy help, and who <char style="add">is</char> the sword of thy excellency! and thine enemies shall be found liars unto thee; and thou shalt tread upon their high places.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">found…: or, subdued</char></note><verse eid="DEU 33:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 33" />
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="DEU 34" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 34:1" />And Moses went up from the plains of Moab unto the mountain of Nebo, to the top of Pisgah, that <char style="add">is</char> over against Jericho. And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> shewed him all the land of Gilead, unto Dan,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Pisgah: or, the hill</char></note> <verse eid="DEU 34:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 34:2" />And all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim, and Manasseh, and all the land of Judah, unto the utmost sea, <verse eid="DEU 34:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 34:3" />And the south, and the plain of the valley of Jericho, the city of palm trees, unto Zoar. <verse eid="DEU 34:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 34:4" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto him, This <char style="add">is</char> the land which I sware unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, saying, I will give it unto thy seed: I have caused thee to see <char style="add">it</char> with thine eyes, but thou shalt not go over thither.<verse eid="DEU 34:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 34:5" />¶ So Moses the servant of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> died there in the land of Moab, according to the word of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="DEU 34:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 34:6" />And he buried him in a valley in the land of Moab, over against Beth-peor: but no man knoweth of his sepulchre unto this day.<verse eid="DEU 34:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 34:7" />¶ And Moses <char style="add">was</char> an hundred and twenty years old when he died: his eye was not dim, nor his natural force abated.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">natural…: Heb. moisture</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">abated: Heb. fled</char></note><verse eid="DEU 34:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 34:8" />¶ And the children of Israel wept for Moses in the plains of Moab thirty days: so the days of weeping <char style="add">and</char> mourning for Moses were ended.<verse eid="DEU 34:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 34:9" />¶ And Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom; for Moses had laid his hands upon him: and the children of Israel hearkened unto him, and did as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> commanded Moses.<verse eid="DEU 34:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 34:10" />¶ And there arose not a prophet since in Israel like unto Moses, whom the <char style="nd">LORD</char> knew face to face, <verse eid="DEU 34:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 34:11" />In all the signs and the wonders, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> sent him to do in the land of Egypt to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land, <verse eid="DEU 34:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 34:12" />And in all that mighty hand, and in all the great terror which Moses shewed in the sight of all Israel.<verse eid="DEU 34:12" /></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 34" />
</usx>