<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JOB" style="id">Job</book>
  <para style="h">Job</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Book of Job</para>
  <para style="toc2">Job</para>
  <para style="toc3">Job</para>
  <para style="mt1">The Book of Job</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JOB 1" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 1:1" />There was a man in the land of Uz, whose name <char style="add">was</char> Job; and that man was perfect and upright, and one that feared God, and eschewed evil. <verse eid="JOB 1:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 1:2" />And there were born unto him seven sons and three daughters. <verse eid="JOB 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 1:3" />His substance also was seven thousand sheep, and three thousand camels, and five hundred yoke of oxen, and five hundred she asses, and a very great household; so that this man was the greatest of all the men of the east.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">substance: or, cattle</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">household: or, husbandry</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">men: Heb. sons</char></note><verse eid="JOB 1:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 1:4" />And his sons went and feasted <char style="add">in their</char> houses, every one his day; and sent and called for their three sisters to eat and to drink with them. <verse eid="JOB 1:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 1:5" />And it was so, when the days of <char style="add">their</char> feasting were gone about, that Job sent and sanctified them, and rose up early in the morning, and offered burnt offerings <char style="add">according</char> to the number of them all: for Job said, It may be that my sons have sinned, and cursed God in their hearts. Thus did Job continually.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">continually: Heb. all the days</char></note><verse eid="JOB 1:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 1:6" />¶ Now there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and Satan came also among them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Satan: Heb. the adversary</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">among: Heb. in the midst of</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 1:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 1:7" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto Satan, Whence comest thou? Then Satan answered the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and said, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it. <verse eid="JOB 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 1:8" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job, that <char style="add">there is</char> none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">considered: Heb. set thy heart on</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 1:9" />Then Satan answered the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and said, Doth Job fear God for nought? <verse eid="JOB 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 1:10" />Hast not thou made an hedge about him, and about his house, and about all that he hath on every side? thou hast blessed the work of his hands, and his substance is increased in the land.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">substance: or, cattle</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 1:11" />But put forth thine hand now, and touch all that he hath, and he will curse thee to thy face.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and he…: Heb. if he curse thee not to thy face</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 1:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 1:12" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto Satan, Behold, all that he hath <char style="add">is</char> in thy power; only upon himself put not forth thine hand. So Satan went forth from the presence of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">power: Heb. hand</char></note><verse eid="JOB 1:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 1:13" />¶ And there was a day when his sons and his daughters <char style="add">were</char> eating and drinking wine in their eldest brother’s house: <verse eid="JOB 1:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 1:14" />And there came a messenger unto Job, and said, The oxen were plowing, and the asses feeding beside them: <verse eid="JOB 1:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 1:15" />And the Sabeans fell <char style="add">upon them</char>, and took them away; yea, they have slain the servants with the edge of the sword; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee. <verse eid="JOB 1:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 1:16" />While he <char style="add">was</char> yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The fire of God is fallen from heaven, and hath burned up the sheep, and the servants, and consumed them; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The fire…: or, A great fire</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 1:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 1:17" />While he <char style="add">was</char> yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The Chaldeans made out three bands, and fell upon the camels, and have carried them away, yea, and slain the servants with the edge of the sword; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fell: Heb. rushed</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 1:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 1:18" />While he <char style="add">was</char> yet speaking, there came also another, and said, Thy sons and thy daughters <char style="add">were</char> eating and drinking wine in their eldest brother’s house: <verse eid="JOB 1:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 1:19" />And, behold, there came a great wind from the wilderness, and smote the four corners of the house, and it fell upon the young men, and they are dead; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from…: Heb. from aside, etc</char></note><verse eid="JOB 1:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 1:20" />Then Job arose, and rent his mantle, and shaved his head, and fell down upon the ground, and worshipped,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mantle: or, robe</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 1:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 1:21" />And said, Naked came I out of my mother’s womb, and naked shall I return thither: the <char style="nd">LORD</char> gave, and the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath taken away; blessed be the name of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="JOB 1:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 1:22" />In all this Job sinned not, nor charged God foolishly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">charged…: or, attributed folly to God</char></note><verse eid="JOB 1:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JOB 2" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 2:1" />Again there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and Satan came also among them to present himself before the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. <verse eid="JOB 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 2:2" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto Satan, From whence comest thou? And Satan answered the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and said, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it. <verse eid="JOB 2:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 2:3" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job, that <char style="add">there is</char> none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil? and still he holdeth fast his integrity, although thou movedst me against him, to destroy him without cause.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to destroy…: Heb. to swallow him up</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 2:4" />And Satan answered the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and said, Skin for skin, yea, all that a man hath will he give for his life. <verse eid="JOB 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 2:5" />But put forth thine hand now, and touch his bone and his flesh, and he will curse thee to thy face. <verse eid="JOB 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 2:6" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said unto Satan, Behold, he <char style="add">is</char> in thine hand; but save his life.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">but: or, only</char></note><verse eid="JOB 2:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 2:7" />¶ So went Satan forth from the presence of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and smote Job with sore boils from the sole of his foot unto his crown. <verse eid="JOB 2:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 2:8" />And he took him a potsherd to scrape himself withal; and he sat down among the ashes.<verse eid="JOB 2:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 2:9" />¶ Then said his wife unto him, Dost thou still retain thine integrity? curse God, and die. <verse eid="JOB 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 2:10" />But he said unto her, Thou speakest as one of the foolish women speaketh. What? shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not receive evil? In all this did not Job sin with his lips.<verse eid="JOB 2:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 2:11" />¶ Now when Job’s three friends heard of all this evil that was come upon him, they came every one from his own place; Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite: for they had made an appointment together to come to mourn with him and to comfort him. <verse eid="JOB 2:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 2:12" />And when they lifted up their eyes afar off, and knew him not, they lifted up their voice, and wept; and they rent every one his mantle, and sprinkled dust upon their heads toward heaven. <verse eid="JOB 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 2:13" />So they sat down with him upon the ground seven days and seven nights, and none spake a word unto him: for they saw that <char style="add">his</char> grief was very great.<verse eid="JOB 2:13" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JOB 3" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 3:1" />After this opened Job his mouth, and cursed his day. <verse eid="JOB 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 3:2" />And Job spake, and said,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">spake: Heb. answered</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 3:3" />Let the day perish wherein I was born, and the night <char style="add">in which</char> it was said, There is a man child conceived. <verse eid="JOB 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 3:4" />Let that day be darkness; let not God regard it from above, neither let the light shine upon it. <verse eid="JOB 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 3:5" />Let darkness and the shadow of death stain it; let a cloud dwell upon it; let the blackness of the day terrify it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">stain: or, challenge</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">let the…: or, let them terrify it, as those who have a bitter day</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 3:6" />As <char style="add">for</char> that night, let darkness seize upon it; let it not be joined unto the days of the year, let it not come into the number of the months.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">let it not be…: or, let it not rejoice among the days</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 3:7" />Lo, let that night be solitary, let no joyful voice come therein. <verse eid="JOB 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 3:8" />Let them curse it that curse the day, who are ready to raise up their mourning.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">their…: or, leviathan</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 3:9" />Let the stars of the twilight thereof be dark; let it look for light, but <char style="add">have</char> none; neither let it see the dawning of the day:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the dawning…: Heb. the eyelids of the morning</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 3:10" />Because it shut not up the doors of my <char style="add">mother’s</char> womb, nor hid sorrow from mine eyes.<verse eid="JOB 3:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 3:11" />Why died I not from the womb? <char style="add">why</char> did I <char style="add">not</char> give up the ghost when I came out of the belly? <verse eid="JOB 3:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 3:12" />Why did the knees prevent me? or why the breasts that I should suck? <verse eid="JOB 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 3:13" />For now should I have lain still and been quiet, I should have slept: then had I been at rest, <verse eid="JOB 3:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 3:14" />With kings and counsellors of the earth, which built desolate places for themselves; <verse eid="JOB 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 3:15" />Or with princes that had gold, who filled their houses with silver: <verse eid="JOB 3:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 3:16" />Or as an hidden untimely birth I had not been; as infants <char style="add">which</char> never saw light. <verse eid="JOB 3:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 3:17" />There the wicked cease <char style="add">from</char> troubling; and there the weary be at rest.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">weary: Heb. wearied in strength</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 3:18" /><char style="add">There</char> the prisoners rest together; they hear not the voice of the oppressor. <verse eid="JOB 3:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 3:19" />The small and great are there; and the servant <char style="add">is</char> free from his master.<verse eid="JOB 3:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 3:20" />Wherefore is light given to him that is in misery, and life unto the bitter <char style="add">in</char> soul; <verse eid="JOB 3:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 3:21" />Which long for death, but it <char style="add">cometh</char> not; and dig for it more than for hid treasures;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">long: Heb. wait</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 3:22" />Which rejoice exceedingly, <char style="add">and</char> are glad, when they can find the grave? <verse eid="JOB 3:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 3:23" /><char style="add">Why is light given</char> to a man whose way is hid, and whom God hath hedged in? <verse eid="JOB 3:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 3:24" />For my sighing cometh before I eat, and my roarings are poured out like the waters.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I eat: Heb. my meat</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 3:25" />For the thing which I greatly feared is come upon me, and that which I was afraid of is come unto me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the thing…: Heb. I feared a fear, and it came upon me</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 3:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 3:26" />I was not in safety, neither had I rest, neither was I quiet; yet trouble came.<verse eid="JOB 3:26" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JOB 4" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 4:1" />Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 4:2" /><char style="add">If</char> we assay to commune with thee, wilt thou be grieved? but who can withhold himself from speaking?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to…: Heb. a word</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">withhold…: Heb. refrain from words?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 4:3" />Behold, thou hast instructed many, and thou hast strengthened the weak hands. <verse eid="JOB 4:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 4:4" />Thy words have upholden him that was falling, and thou hast strengthened the feeble knees. <verse eid="JOB 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 4:5" />But now it is come upon thee, and thou faintest; it toucheth thee, and thou art troubled. <verse eid="JOB 4:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 4:6" /><char style="add">Is</char> not <char style="add">this</char> thy fear, thy confidence, thy hope, and the uprightness of thy ways?<verse eid="JOB 4:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 4:7" />Remember, I pray thee, who <char style="add">ever</char> perished, being innocent? or where were the righteous cut off? <verse eid="JOB 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 4:8" />Even as I have seen, they that plow iniquity, and sow wickedness, reap the same. <verse eid="JOB 4:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 4:9" />By the blast of God they perish, and by the breath of his nostrils are they consumed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by the breath…: that is, by his anger</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 4:10" />The roaring of the lion, and the voice of the fierce lion, and the teeth of the young lions, are broken. <verse eid="JOB 4:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 4:11" />The old lion perisheth for lack of prey, and the stout lion’s whelps are scattered abroad.<verse eid="JOB 4:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 4:12" />Now a thing was secretly brought to me, and mine ear received a little thereof.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">secretly: Heb. by stealth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 4:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 4:13" />In thoughts from the visions of the night, when deep sleep falleth on men, <verse eid="JOB 4:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 4:14" />Fear came upon me, and trembling, which made all my bones to shake.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">came…: Heb. met</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">all: Heb. the multitude of</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 4:15" />Then a spirit passed before my face; the hair of my flesh stood up: <verse eid="JOB 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 4:16" />It stood still, but I could not discern the form thereof: an image <char style="add">was</char> before mine eyes, <char style="add">there was</char> silence, and I heard a voice, <char style="add">saying</char>,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">there…: or, I heard a still voice</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 4:17" />Shall mortal man be more just than God? shall a man be more pure than his maker? <verse eid="JOB 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 4:18" />Behold, he put no trust in his servants; and his angels he charged with folly:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and his…: or, nor in his angels, in whom he put light</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 4:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 4:19" />How much less <char style="add">in</char> them that dwell in houses of clay, whose foundation <char style="add">is</char> in the dust, <char style="add">which</char> are crushed before the moth? <verse eid="JOB 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 4:20" />They are destroyed from morning to evening: they perish for ever without any regarding <char style="add">it</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">destroyed: Heb. beaten in pieces</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 4:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 4:21" />Doth not their excellency <char style="add">which is</char> in them go away? they die, even without wisdom.<verse eid="JOB 4:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JOB 5" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 5:1" />Call now, if there be any that will answer thee; and to which of the saints wilt thou turn?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">turn: or, look?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 5:2" />For wrath killeth the foolish man, and envy slayeth the silly one.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">envy: or, indignation</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 5:3" />I have seen the foolish taking root: but suddenly I cursed his habitation. <verse eid="JOB 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 5:4" />His children are far from safety, and they are crushed in the gate, neither <char style="add">is there</char> any to deliver <char style="add">them</char>. <verse eid="JOB 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 5:5" />Whose harvest the hungry eateth up, and taketh it even out of the thorns, and the robber swalloweth up their substance.<verse eid="JOB 5:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 5:6" />Although affliction cometh not forth of the dust, neither doth trouble spring out of the ground;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">affliction: or, iniquity</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 5:7" />Yet man is born unto trouble, as the sparks fly upward.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">trouble: or, labour</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sparks…: Heb. the sons of the burning coal lift up to fly</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 5:8" />I would seek unto God, and unto God would I commit my cause: <verse eid="JOB 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 5:9" />Which doeth great things and unsearchable; marvellous things without number:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">unsearchable: Heb. there is no search</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">without…: Heb. till there be no number</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 5:10" />Who giveth rain upon the earth, and sendeth waters upon the fields:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fields: Heb. outplaces</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 5:11" />To set up on high those that be low; that those which mourn may be exalted to safety. <verse eid="JOB 5:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 5:12" />He disappointeth the devices of the crafty, so that their hands cannot perform <char style="add">their</char> enterprise.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">their enterprise: or, any thing</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 5:13" />He taketh the wise in their own craftiness: and the counsel of the froward is carried headlong. <verse eid="JOB 5:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 5:14" />They meet with darkness in the daytime, and grope in the noonday as in the night.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">meet…: or, run into</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 5:15" />But he saveth the poor from the sword, from their mouth, and from the hand of the mighty. <verse eid="JOB 5:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 5:16" />So the poor hath hope, and iniquity stoppeth her mouth.<verse eid="JOB 5:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 5:17" />Behold, happy <char style="add">is</char> the man whom God correcteth: therefore despise not thou the chastening of the Almighty: <verse eid="JOB 5:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 5:18" />For he maketh sore, and bindeth up: he woundeth, and his hands make whole. <verse eid="JOB 5:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 5:19" />He shall deliver thee in six troubles: yea, in seven there shall no evil touch thee. <verse eid="JOB 5:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 5:20" />In famine he shall redeem thee from death: and in war from the power of the sword.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">power: Heb. hands</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 5:21" />Thou shalt be hid from the scourge of the tongue: neither shalt thou be afraid of destruction when it cometh.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from…: or, when the tongue scourgeth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 5:22" />At destruction and famine thou shalt laugh: neither shalt thou be afraid of the beasts of the earth. <verse eid="JOB 5:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 5:23" />For thou shalt be in league with the stones of the field: and the beasts of the field shall be at peace with thee. <verse eid="JOB 5:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 5:24" />And thou shalt know that thy tabernacle <char style="add">shall be</char> in peace; and thou shalt visit thy habitation, and shalt not sin.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">thy tabernacle…: or, peace is thy tabernacle</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sin: or, err</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 5:25" />Thou shalt know also that thy seed <char style="add">shall be</char> great, and thine offspring as the grass of the earth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">great: or, much</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 5:26" />Thou shalt come to <char style="add">thy</char> grave in a full age, like as a shock of corn cometh in in his season.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cometh in: Heb. ascendeth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 5:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 5:27" />Lo this, we have searched it, so it <char style="add">is;</char> hear it, and know thou <char style="add">it</char> for thy good.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">for…: Heb. for thyself</char></note><verse eid="JOB 5:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 5" />
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JOB 6" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 6:1" />But Job answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 6:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 6:2" />Oh that my grief were throughly weighed, and my calamity laid in the balances together!<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">laid: Heb. lifted up</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 6:3" />For now it would be heavier than the sand of the sea: therefore my words are swallowed up.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my words…: that is, I want words to express my grief</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 6:4" />For the arrows of the Almighty <char style="add">are</char> within me, the poison whereof drinketh up my spirit: the terrors of God do set themselves in array against me. <verse eid="JOB 6:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 6:5" />Doth the wild ass bray when he hath grass? or loweth the ox over his fodder?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">when he…: Heb. at grass?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 6:6" />Can that which is unsavoury be eaten without salt? or is there <char style="add">any</char> taste in the white of an egg? <verse eid="JOB 6:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 6:7" />The things <char style="add">that</char> my soul refused to touch <char style="add">are</char> as my sorrowful meat.<verse eid="JOB 6:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 6:8" />Oh that I might have my request; and that God would grant <char style="add">me</char> the thing that I long for!<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the thing…: Heb. my expectation</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 6:9" />Even that it would please God to destroy me; that he would let loose his hand, and cut me off! <verse eid="JOB 6:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 6:10" />Then should I yet have comfort; yea, I would harden myself in sorrow: let him not spare; for I have not concealed the words of the Holy One. <verse eid="JOB 6:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 6:11" />What <char style="add">is</char> my strength, that I should hope? and what <char style="add">is</char> mine end, that I should prolong my life? <verse eid="JOB 6:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 6:12" /><char style="add">Is</char> my strength the strength of stones? or <char style="add">is</char> my flesh of brass?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of brass: Heb. brasen?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 6:13" /><char style="add">Is</char> not my help in me? and is wisdom driven quite from me?<verse eid="JOB 6:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 6:14" />To him that is afflicted pity <char style="add">should be shewed</char> from his friend; but he forsaketh the fear of the Almighty.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is afflicted: Heb. melteth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 6:15" />My brethren have dealt deceitfully as a brook, <char style="add">and</char> as the stream of brooks they pass away; <verse eid="JOB 6:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 6:16" />Which are blackish by reason of the ice, <char style="add">and</char> wherein the snow is hid: <verse eid="JOB 6:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 6:17" />What time they wax warm, they vanish: when it is hot, they are consumed out of their place.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">vanish: Heb. are cut off</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">when…: Heb. in the heat thereof</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">consumed: Heb. extinguished</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 6:18" />The paths of their way are turned aside; they go to nothing, and perish. <verse eid="JOB 6:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 6:19" />The troops of Tema looked, the companies of Sheba waited for them. <verse eid="JOB 6:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 6:20" />They were confounded because they had hoped; they came thither, and were ashamed. <verse eid="JOB 6:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 6:21" />For now ye are nothing; ye see <char style="add">my</char> casting down, and are afraid.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">ye are…: or, ye are like to them: Heb. to it</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">nothing: Heb. not</char></note><verse eid="JOB 6:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 6:22" />Did I say, Bring unto me? or, Give a reward for me of your substance? <verse eid="JOB 6:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 6:23" />Or, Deliver me from the enemy’s hand? or, Redeem me from the hand of the mighty? <verse eid="JOB 6:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 6:24" />Teach me, and I will hold my tongue: and cause me to understand wherein I have erred. <verse eid="JOB 6:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 6:25" />How forcible are right words! but what doth your arguing reprove? <verse eid="JOB 6:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 6:26" />Do ye imagine to reprove words, and the speeches of one that is desperate, <char style="add">which are</char> as wind? <verse eid="JOB 6:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 6:27" />Yea, ye overwhelm the fatherless, and ye dig <char style="add">a pit</char> for your friend.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">ye overwhelm: Heb. ye cause to fall upon</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 6:28" />Now therefore be content, look upon me; for <char style="add">it is</char> evident unto you if I lie.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">evident…: Heb. before your face</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 6:29" />Return, I pray you, let it not be iniquity; yea, return again, my righteousness <char style="add">is</char> in it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in it: that is, in this matter</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 6:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 6:30" />Is there iniquity in my tongue? cannot my taste discern perverse things?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my taste: Heb. my palate</char></note><verse eid="JOB 6:30" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 6" />
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JOB 7" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 7:1" />
    <char style="add">Is there</char> not an appointed time to man upon earth? <char style="add">are not</char> his days also like the days of an hireling?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">an appointed…: or, a warfare</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 7:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 7:2" />As a servant earnestly desireth the shadow, and as an hireling looketh for <char style="add">the reward of</char> his work:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">earnestly…: Heb. gapeth after</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 7:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 7:3" />So am I made to possess months of vanity, and wearisome nights are appointed to me. <verse eid="JOB 7:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 7:4" />When I lie down, I say, When shall I arise, and the night be gone? and I am full of tossings to and fro unto the dawning of the day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the night…: Heb. the evening be measured?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 7:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 7:5" />My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of dust; my skin is broken, and become loathsome. <verse eid="JOB 7:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 7:6" />My days are swifter than a weaver’s shuttle, and are spent without hope.<verse eid="JOB 7:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 7:7" />O remember that my life <char style="add">is</char> wind: mine eye shall no more see good.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">shall…: Heb. shall not return</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">see: to see, that is, to enjoy</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 7:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 7:8" />The eye of him that hath seen me shall see me no <char style="add">more:</char> thine eyes <char style="add">are</char> upon me, and I <char style="add">am</char> not.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I am…: that is, I can live no longer</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 7:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 7:9" /><char style="add">As</char> the cloud is consumed and vanisheth away: so he that goeth down to the grave shall come up no <char style="add">more</char>. <verse eid="JOB 7:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 7:10" />He shall return no more to his house, neither shall his place know him any more. <verse eid="JOB 7:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 7:11" />Therefore I will not refrain my mouth; I will speak in the anguish of my spirit; I will complain in the bitterness of my soul. <verse eid="JOB 7:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 7:12" /><char style="add">Am</char> I a sea, or a whale, that thou settest a watch over me? <verse eid="JOB 7:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 7:13" />When I say, My bed shall comfort me, my couch shall ease my complaint; <verse eid="JOB 7:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 7:14" />Then thou scarest me with dreams, and terrifiest me through visions: <verse eid="JOB 7:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 7:15" />So that my soul chooseth strangling, <char style="add">and</char> death rather than my life.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">life: Heb. bones</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 7:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 7:16" />I loathe <char style="add">it;</char> I would not live alway: let me alone; for my days <char style="add">are</char> vanity.<verse eid="JOB 7:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 7:17" />What <char style="add">is</char> man, that thou shouldest magnify him? and that thou shouldest set thine heart upon him? <verse eid="JOB 7:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 7:18" />And <char style="add">that</char> thou shouldest visit him every morning, <char style="add">and</char> try him every moment? <verse eid="JOB 7:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 7:19" />How long wilt thou not depart from me, nor let me alone till I swallow down my spittle? <verse eid="JOB 7:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 7:20" />I have sinned; what shall I do unto thee, O thou preserver of men? why hast thou set me as a mark against thee, so that I am a burden to myself? <verse eid="JOB 7:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 7:21" />And why dost thou not pardon my transgression, and take away mine iniquity? for now shall I sleep in the dust; and thou shalt seek me in the morning, but I <char style="add">shall</char> not <char style="add">be</char>.<verse eid="JOB 7:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 7" />
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JOB 8" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 8:1" />Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said, <verse eid="JOB 8:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 8:2" />How long wilt thou speak these <char style="add">things</char>? and <char style="add">how long shall</char> the words of thy mouth <char style="add">be like</char> a strong wind? <verse eid="JOB 8:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 8:3" />Doth God pervert judgment? or doth the Almighty pervert justice? <verse eid="JOB 8:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 8:4" />If thy children have sinned against him, and he have cast them away for their transgression;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">for…: Heb. in the hand of their transgression</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 8:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 8:5" />If thou wouldest seek unto God betimes, and make thy supplication to the Almighty; <verse eid="JOB 8:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 8:6" />If thou <char style="add">wert</char> pure and upright; surely now he would awake for thee, and make the habitation of thy righteousness prosperous. <verse eid="JOB 8:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 8:7" />Though thy beginning was small, yet thy latter end should greatly increase.<verse eid="JOB 8:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 8:8" />For enquire, I pray thee, of the former age, and prepare thyself to the search of their fathers: <verse eid="JOB 8:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 8:9" />(For we <char style="add">are but of</char> yesterday, and know nothing, because our days upon earth <char style="add">are</char> a shadow:)<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">nothing: Heb. not</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 8:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 8:10" />Shall not they teach thee, <char style="add">and</char> tell thee, and utter words out of their heart? <verse eid="JOB 8:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 8:11" />Can the rush grow up without mire? can the flag grow without water? <verse eid="JOB 8:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 8:12" />Whilst it <char style="add">is</char> yet in his greenness, <char style="add">and</char> not cut down, it withereth before any <char style="add">other</char> herb. <verse eid="JOB 8:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 8:13" />So <char style="add">are</char> the paths of all that forget God; and the hypocrite’s hope shall perish: <verse eid="JOB 8:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 8:14" />Whose hope shall be cut off, and whose trust <char style="add">shall be</char> a spider’s web.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">web: Heb. house</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 8:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 8:15" />He shall lean upon his house, but it shall not stand: he shall hold it fast, but it shall not endure. <verse eid="JOB 8:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 8:16" />He <char style="add">is</char> green before the sun, and his branch shooteth forth in his garden. <verse eid="JOB 8:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 8:17" />His roots are wrapped about the heap, <char style="add">and</char> seeth the place of stones. <verse eid="JOB 8:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 8:18" />If he destroy him from his place, then <char style="add">it</char> shall deny him, <char style="add">saying</char>, I have not seen thee. <verse eid="JOB 8:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 8:19" />Behold, this <char style="add">is</char> the joy of his way, and out of the earth shall others grow.<verse eid="JOB 8:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 8:20" />Behold, God will not cast away a perfect <char style="add">man</char>, neither will he help the evil doers:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">help…: Heb. take the ungodly by the hand</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">come: Heb. shall not be</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 8:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 8:21" />Till he fill thy mouth with laughing, and thy lips with rejoicing.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">rejoicing: Heb. shouting for joy</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 8:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 8:22" />They that hate thee shall be clothed with shame; and the dwelling place of the wicked shall come to nought.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">shall come…: Heb. shall not be</char></note><verse eid="JOB 8:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 8" />
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JOB 9" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 9:1" />Then Job answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 9:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 9:2" />I know <char style="add">it is</char> so of a truth: but how should man be just with God?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">with God: or, before God?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 9:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 9:3" />If he will contend with him, he cannot answer him one of a thousand. <verse eid="JOB 9:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 9:4" /><char style="add">He is</char> wise in heart, and mighty in strength: who hath hardened <char style="add">himself</char> against him, and hath prospered? <verse eid="JOB 9:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 9:5" />Which removeth the mountains, and they know not: which overturneth them in his anger. <verse eid="JOB 9:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 9:6" />Which shaketh the earth out of her place, and the pillars thereof tremble. <verse eid="JOB 9:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 9:7" />Which commandeth the sun, and it riseth not; and sealeth up the stars. <verse eid="JOB 9:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 9:8" />Which alone spreadeth out the heavens, and treadeth upon the waves of the sea.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">waves: Heb. heights</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 9:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 9:9" />Which maketh Arcturus, Orion, and Pleiades, and the chambers of the south.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Arcturus…: Heb. Ash, Cesil, and Cimah</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 9:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 9:10" />Which doeth great things past finding out; yea, and wonders without number. <verse eid="JOB 9:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 9:11" />Lo, he goeth by me, and I see <char style="add">him</char> not: he passeth on also, but I perceive him not. <verse eid="JOB 9:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 9:12" />Behold, he taketh away, who can hinder him? who will say unto him, What doest thou?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">hinder…: Heb. turn him away?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 9:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 9:13" /><char style="add">If</char> God will not withdraw his anger, the proud helpers do stoop under him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">proud…: Heb. helpers of pride, or, strength</char></note><verse eid="JOB 9:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 9:14" />How much less shall I answer him, <char style="add">and</char> choose out my words <char style="add">to reason</char> with him? <verse eid="JOB 9:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 9:15" />Whom, though I were righteous, <char style="add">yet</char> would I not answer, <char style="add">but</char> I would make supplication to my judge. <verse eid="JOB 9:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 9:16" />If I had called, and he had answered me; <char style="add">yet</char> would I not believe that he had hearkened unto my voice. <verse eid="JOB 9:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 9:17" />For he breaketh me with a tempest, and multiplieth my wounds without cause. <verse eid="JOB 9:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 9:18" />He will not suffer me to take my breath, but filleth me with bitterness. <verse eid="JOB 9:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 9:19" />If <char style="add">I speak</char> of strength, lo, <char style="add">he is</char> strong: and if of judgment, who shall set me a time <char style="add">to plead</char>? <verse eid="JOB 9:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 9:20" />If I justify myself, mine own mouth shall condemn me: <char style="add">if I say</char>, I <char style="add">am</char> perfect, it shall also prove me perverse. <verse eid="JOB 9:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 9:21" /><char style="add">Though</char> I <char style="add">were</char> perfect, <char style="add">yet</char> would I not know my soul: I would despise my life.<verse eid="JOB 9:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 9:22" />This <char style="add">is</char> one <char style="add">thing</char>, therefore I said <char style="add">it</char>, He destroyeth the perfect and the wicked. <verse eid="JOB 9:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 9:23" />If the scourge slay suddenly, he will laugh at the trial of the innocent. <verse eid="JOB 9:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 9:24" />The earth is given into the hand of the wicked: he covereth the faces of the judges thereof; if not, where, <char style="add">and</char> who <char style="add">is</char> he?<verse eid="JOB 9:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 9:25" />Now my days are swifter than a post: they flee away, they see no good. <verse eid="JOB 9:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 9:26" />They are passed away as the swift ships: as the eagle <char style="add">that</char> hasteth to the prey.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">swift…: or, ships of Ebeh: Heb. ships of desire</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 9:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 9:27" />If I say, I will forget my complaint, I will leave off my heaviness, and comfort <char style="add">myself:</char> <verse eid="JOB 9:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 9:28" />I am afraid of all my sorrows, I know that thou wilt not hold me innocent. <verse eid="JOB 9:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 9:29" /><char style="add">If</char> I be wicked, why then labour I in vain? <verse eid="JOB 9:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 9:30" />If I wash myself with snow water, and make my hands never so clean; <verse eid="JOB 9:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 9:31" />Yet shalt thou plunge me in the ditch, and mine own clothes shall abhor me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">abhor…: or, make me to be abhorred</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 9:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 9:32" />For <char style="add">he is</char> not a man, as I <char style="add">am, that</char> I should answer him, <char style="add">and</char> we should come together in judgment. <verse eid="JOB 9:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 9:33" />Neither is there any daysman betwixt us, <char style="add">that</char> might lay his hand upon us both.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">any…: Heb. one that should argue</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">daysman: or, umpire</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 9:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOB 9:34" />Let him take his rod away from me, and let not his fear terrify me: <verse eid="JOB 9:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOB 9:35" /><char style="add">Then</char> would I speak, and not fear him; but <char style="add">it is</char> not so with me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">it is…: Heb. I am not so with myself</char></note><verse eid="JOB 9:35" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 9" />
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JOB 10" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 10:1" />My soul is weary of my life; I will leave my complaint upon myself; I will speak in the bitterness of my soul.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">weary…: or, cut off while I live</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 10:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 10:2" />I will say unto God, Do not condemn me; shew me wherefore thou contendest with me. <verse eid="JOB 10:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 10:3" /><char style="add">Is it</char> good unto thee that thou shouldest oppress, that thou shouldest despise the work of thine hands, and shine upon the counsel of the wicked?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">work: Heb. labour</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 10:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 10:4" />Hast thou eyes of flesh? or seest thou as man seeth? <verse eid="JOB 10:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 10:5" /><char style="add">Are</char> thy days as the days of man? <char style="add">are</char> thy years as man’s days, <verse eid="JOB 10:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 10:6" />That thou enquirest after mine iniquity, and searchest after my sin? <verse eid="JOB 10:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 10:7" />Thou knowest that I am not wicked; and <char style="add">there is</char> none that can deliver out of thine hand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Thou…: Heb. It is upon thy knowledge</char></note><verse eid="JOB 10:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 10:8" />Thine hands have made me and fashioned me together round about; yet thou dost destroy me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">have…: Heb. took pains about me</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 10:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 10:9" />Remember, I beseech thee, that thou hast made me as the clay; and wilt thou bring me into dust again? <verse eid="JOB 10:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 10:10" />Hast thou not poured me out as milk, and curdled me like cheese? <verse eid="JOB 10:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 10:11" />Thou hast clothed me with skin and flesh, and hast fenced me with bones and sinews.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fenced: Heb. hedged</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 10:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 10:12" />Thou hast granted me life and favour, and thy visitation hath preserved my spirit. <verse eid="JOB 10:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 10:13" />And these <char style="add">things</char> hast thou hid in thine heart: I know that this <char style="add">is</char> with thee.<verse eid="JOB 10:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 10:14" />If I sin, then thou markest me, and thou wilt not acquit me from mine iniquity. <verse eid="JOB 10:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 10:15" />If I be wicked, woe unto me; and <char style="add">if</char> I be righteous, <char style="add">yet</char> will I not lift up my head. <char style="add">I am</char> full of confusion; therefore see thou mine affliction; <verse eid="JOB 10:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 10:16" />For it increaseth. Thou huntest me as a fierce lion: and again thou shewest thyself marvellous upon me. <verse eid="JOB 10:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 10:17" />Thou renewest thy witnesses against me, and increasest thine indignation upon me; changes and war <char style="add">are</char> against me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">witnesses: that is, plagues</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 10:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 10:18" />Wherefore then hast thou brought me forth out of the womb? Oh that I had given up the ghost, and no eye had seen me! <verse eid="JOB 10:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 10:19" />I should have been as though I had not been; I should have been carried from the womb to the grave. <verse eid="JOB 10:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 10:20" /><char style="add">Are</char> not my days few? cease <char style="add">then, and</char> let me alone, that I may take comfort a little, <verse eid="JOB 10:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 10:21" />Before I go <char style="add">whence</char> I shall not return, <char style="add">even</char> to the land of darkness and the shadow of death; <verse eid="JOB 10:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 10:22" />A land of darkness, as darkness <char style="add">itself; and</char> of the shadow of death, without any order, and <char style="add">where</char> the light <char style="add">is</char> as darkness.<verse eid="JOB 10:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 10" />
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JOB 11" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 11:1" />Then answered Zophar the Naamathite, and said, <verse eid="JOB 11:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 11:2" />Should not the multitude of words be answered? and should a man full of talk be justified?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">full…: Heb. of lips</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 11:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 11:3" />Should thy lies make men hold their peace? and when thou mockest, shall no man make thee ashamed?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">lies: or, devices</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 11:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 11:4" />For thou hast said, My doctrine <char style="add">is</char> pure, and I am clean in thine eyes. <verse eid="JOB 11:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 11:5" />But oh that God would speak, and open his lips against thee; <verse eid="JOB 11:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 11:6" />And that he would shew thee the secrets of wisdom, that <char style="add">they are</char> double to that which is! Know therefore that God exacteth of thee <char style="add">less</char> than thine iniquity <char style="add">deserveth</char>.<verse eid="JOB 11:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 11:7" />Canst thou by searching find out God? canst thou find out the Almighty unto perfection? <verse eid="JOB 11:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 11:8" /><char style="add">It is</char> as high as heaven; what canst thou do? deeper than hell; what canst thou know?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as high…: Heb. the heights of heaven</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 11:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 11:9" />The measure thereof <char style="add">is</char> longer than the earth, and broader than the sea. <verse eid="JOB 11:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 11:10" />If he cut off, and shut up, or gather together, then who can hinder him?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cut…: or, make a change</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">hinder…: Heb. turn him away?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 11:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 11:11" />For he knoweth vain men: he seeth wickedness also; will he not then consider <char style="add">it</char>? <verse eid="JOB 11:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 11:12" />For vain man would be wise, though man be born <char style="add">like</char> a wild ass’s colt.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">vain: Heb. empty</char></note><verse eid="JOB 11:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 11:13" />If thou prepare thine heart, and stretch out thine hands toward him; <verse eid="JOB 11:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 11:14" />If iniquity <char style="add">be</char> in thine hand, put it far away, and let not wickedness dwell in thy tabernacles. <verse eid="JOB 11:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 11:15" />For then shalt thou lift up thy face without spot; yea, thou shalt be stedfast, and shalt not fear: <verse eid="JOB 11:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 11:16" />Because thou shalt forget <char style="add">thy</char> misery, <char style="add">and</char> remember <char style="add">it</char> as waters <char style="add">that</char> pass away: <verse eid="JOB 11:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 11:17" />And <char style="add">thine</char> age shall be clearer than the noonday; thou shalt shine forth, thou shalt be as the morning.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">be clearer…: Heb. arise above</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 11:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 11:18" />And thou shalt be secure, because there is hope; yea, thou shalt dig <char style="add">about thee, and</char> thou shalt take thy rest in safety. <verse eid="JOB 11:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 11:19" />Also thou shalt lie down, and none shall make <char style="add">thee</char> afraid; yea, many shall make suit unto thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">make suit…: Heb. intreat thy face</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 11:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 11:20" />But the eyes of the wicked shall fail, and they shall not escape, and their hope <char style="add">shall be as</char> the giving up of the ghost.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">they shall…: Heb. flight shall perish from them</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the giving…: or, a puff of breath</char></note><verse eid="JOB 11:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 11" />
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JOB 12" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 12:1" />And Job answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 12:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 12:2" />No doubt but ye <char style="add">are</char> the people, and wisdom shall die with you. <verse eid="JOB 12:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 12:3" />But I have understanding as well as you; I <char style="add">am</char> not inferior to you: yea, who knoweth not such things as these?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">understanding: Heb. an heart</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I am…: Heb. I fall not lower than you</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">who…: Heb. with whom are not such as these?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 12:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 12:4" />I am <char style="add">as</char> one mocked of his neighbour, who calleth upon God, and he answereth him: the just upright <char style="add">man is</char> laughed to scorn. <verse eid="JOB 12:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 12:5" />He that is ready to slip with <char style="add">his</char> feet <char style="add">is as</char> a lamp despised in the thought of him that is at ease.<verse eid="JOB 12:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 12:6" />The tabernacles of robbers prosper, and they that provoke God are secure; into whose hand God bringeth <char style="add">abundantly</char>. <verse eid="JOB 12:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 12:7" />But ask now the beasts, and they shall teach thee; and the fowls of the air, and they shall tell thee: <verse eid="JOB 12:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 12:8" />Or speak to the earth, and it shall teach thee: and the fishes of the sea shall declare unto thee. <verse eid="JOB 12:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 12:9" />Who knoweth not in all these that the hand of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> hath wrought this? <verse eid="JOB 12:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 12:10" />In whose hand <char style="add">is</char> the soul of every living thing, and the breath of all mankind.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">soul: or, life</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">all…: Heb. all flesh of man</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 12:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 12:11" />Doth not the ear try words? and the mouth taste his meat?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mouth: Heb. palate</char></note><verse eid="JOB 12:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 12:12" />With the ancient <char style="add">is</char> wisdom; and in length of days understanding. <verse eid="JOB 12:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 12:13" />With him <char style="add">is</char> wisdom and strength, he hath counsel and understanding.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">With…: that is, With God</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 12:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 12:14" />Behold, he breaketh down, and it cannot be built again: he shutteth up a man, and there can be no opening.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">up: Heb. upon</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 12:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 12:15" />Behold, he withholdeth the waters, and they dry up: also he sendeth them out, and they overturn the earth. <verse eid="JOB 12:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 12:16" />With him <char style="add">is</char> strength and wisdom: the deceived and the deceiver <char style="add">are</char> his. <verse eid="JOB 12:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 12:17" />He leadeth counsellors away spoiled, and maketh the judges fools. <verse eid="JOB 12:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 12:18" />He looseth the bond of kings, and girdeth their loins with a girdle. <verse eid="JOB 12:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 12:19" />He leadeth princes away spoiled, and overthroweth the mighty. <verse eid="JOB 12:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 12:20" />He removeth away the speech of the trusty, and taketh away the understanding of the aged.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">speech…: Heb. lip of the faithful</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 12:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 12:21" />He poureth contempt upon princes, and weakeneth the strength of the mighty.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">weakeneth…: or, looseth the girdle of the strong</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 12:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 12:22" />He discovereth deep things out of darkness, and bringeth out to light the shadow of death. <verse eid="JOB 12:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 12:23" />He increaseth the nations, and destroyeth them: he enlargeth the nations, and straiteneth them <char style="add">again</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">straiteneth: Heb. leadeth in</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 12:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 12:24" />He taketh away the heart of the chief of the people of the earth, and causeth them to wander in a wilderness <char style="add">where there is</char> no way. <verse eid="JOB 12:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 12:25" />They grope in the dark without light, and he maketh them to stagger like <char style="add">a</char> drunken <char style="add">man</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">stagger: Heb. wander</char></note><verse eid="JOB 12:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 12" />
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JOB 13" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 13:1" />Lo, mine eye hath seen all <char style="add">this</char>, mine ear hath heard and understood it. <verse eid="JOB 13:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 13:2" />What ye know, <char style="add">the same</char> do I know also: I <char style="add">am</char> not inferior unto you. <verse eid="JOB 13:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 13:3" />Surely I would speak to the Almighty, and I desire to reason with God. <verse eid="JOB 13:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 13:4" />But ye <char style="add">are</char> forgers of lies, ye <char style="add">are</char> all physicians of no value. <verse eid="JOB 13:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 13:5" />O that ye would altogether hold your peace! and it should be your wisdom. <verse eid="JOB 13:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 13:6" />Hear now my reasoning, and hearken to the pleadings of my lips. <verse eid="JOB 13:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 13:7" />Will ye speak wickedly for God? and talk deceitfully for him? <verse eid="JOB 13:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 13:8" />Will ye accept his person? will ye contend for God? <verse eid="JOB 13:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 13:9" />Is it good that he should search you out? or as one man mocketh another, do ye <char style="add">so</char> mock him? <verse eid="JOB 13:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 13:10" />He will surely reprove you, if ye do secretly accept persons. <verse eid="JOB 13:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 13:11" />Shall not his excellency make you afraid? and his dread fall upon you? <verse eid="JOB 13:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 13:12" />Your remembrances <char style="add">are</char> like unto ashes, your bodies to bodies of clay.<verse eid="JOB 13:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 13:13" />Hold your peace, let me alone, that I may speak, and let come on me what <char style="add">will</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hold…: Heb. Be silent from me</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 13:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 13:14" />Wherefore do I take my flesh in my teeth, and put my life in mine hand? <verse eid="JOB 13:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 13:15" />Though he slay me, yet will I trust in him: but I will maintain mine own ways before him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">maintain: Heb. prove, or, argue</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 13:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 13:16" />He also <char style="add">shall be</char> my salvation: for an hypocrite shall not come before him. <verse eid="JOB 13:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 13:17" />Hear diligently my speech, and my declaration with your ears. <verse eid="JOB 13:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 13:18" />Behold now, I have ordered <char style="add">my</char> cause; I know that I shall be justified. <verse eid="JOB 13:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 13:19" />Who <char style="add">is</char> he <char style="add">that</char> will plead with me? for now, if I hold my tongue, I shall give up the ghost. <verse eid="JOB 13:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 13:20" />Only do not two <char style="add">things</char> unto me: then will I not hide myself from thee. <verse eid="JOB 13:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 13:21" />Withdraw thine hand far from me: and let not thy dread make me afraid. <verse eid="JOB 13:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 13:22" />Then call thou, and I will answer: or let me speak, and answer thou me.<verse eid="JOB 13:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 13:23" />How many <char style="add">are</char> mine iniquities and sins? make me to know my transgression and my sin. <verse eid="JOB 13:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 13:24" />Wherefore hidest thou thy face, and holdest me for thine enemy? <verse eid="JOB 13:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 13:25" />Wilt thou break a leaf driven to and fro? and wilt thou pursue the dry stubble? <verse eid="JOB 13:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 13:26" />For thou writest bitter things against me, and makest me to possess the iniquities of my youth. <verse eid="JOB 13:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 13:27" />Thou puttest my feet also in the stocks, and lookest narrowly unto all my paths; thou settest a print upon the heels of my feet.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">lookest…: Heb. observest</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">heels: Heb. roots</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 13:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 13:28" />And he, as a rotten thing, consumeth, as a garment that is moth eaten.<verse eid="JOB 13:28" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 13" />
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JOB 14" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 14:1" />Man <char style="add">that is</char> born of a woman <char style="add">is</char> of few days, and full of trouble.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">few…: Heb. short of days</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 14:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 14:2" />He cometh forth like a flower, and is cut down: he fleeth also as a shadow, and continueth not. <verse eid="JOB 14:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 14:3" />And dost thou open thine eyes upon such an one, and bringest me into judgment with thee? <verse eid="JOB 14:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 14:4" />Who can bring a clean <char style="add">thing</char> out of an unclean? not one.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">can…: Heb. will give</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 14:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 14:5" />Seeing his days <char style="add">are</char> determined, the number of his months <char style="add">are</char> with thee, thou hast appointed his bounds that he cannot pass; <verse eid="JOB 14:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 14:6" />Turn from him, that he may rest, till he shall accomplish, as an hireling, his day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">rest: Heb. cease</char></note><verse eid="JOB 14:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 14:7" />For there is hope of a tree, if it be cut down, that it will sprout again, and that the tender branch thereof will not cease. <verse eid="JOB 14:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 14:8" />Though the root thereof wax old in the earth, and the stock thereof die in the ground; <verse eid="JOB 14:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 14:9" /><char style="add">Yet</char> through the scent of water it will bud, and bring forth boughs like a plant. <verse eid="JOB 14:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 14:10" />But man dieth, and wasteth away: yea, man giveth up the ghost, and where <char style="add">is</char> he?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wasteth…: Heb. is weakened, or, cut off</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 14:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 14:11" /><char style="add">As</char> the waters fail from the sea, and the flood decayeth and drieth up: <verse eid="JOB 14:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 14:12" />So man lieth down, and riseth not: till the heavens <char style="add">be</char> no more, they shall not awake, nor be raised out of their sleep. <verse eid="JOB 14:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 14:13" />O that thou wouldest hide me in the grave, that thou wouldest keep me secret, until thy wrath be past, that thou wouldest appoint me a set time, and remember me! <verse eid="JOB 14:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 14:14" />If a man die, shall he live <char style="add">again</char>? all the days of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come. <verse eid="JOB 14:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 14:15" />Thou shalt call, and I will answer thee: thou wilt have a desire to the work of thine hands.<verse eid="JOB 14:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 14:16" />For now thou numberest my steps: dost thou not watch over my sin? <verse eid="JOB 14:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 14:17" />My transgression <char style="add">is</char> sealed up in a bag, and thou sewest up mine iniquity. <verse eid="JOB 14:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 14:18" />And surely the mountain falling cometh to nought, and the rock is removed out of his place.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cometh…: Heb. fadeth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 14:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 14:19" />The waters wear the stones: thou washest away the things which grow <char style="add">out</char> of the dust of the earth; and thou destroyest the hope of man.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">washest…: Heb. overflowest</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 14:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 14:20" />Thou prevailest for ever against him, and he passeth: thou changest his countenance, and sendest him away. <verse eid="JOB 14:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 14:21" />His sons come to honour, and he knoweth <char style="add">it</char> not; and they are brought low, but he perceiveth <char style="add">it</char> not of them. <verse eid="JOB 14:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 14:22" />But his flesh upon him shall have pain, and his soul within him shall mourn.<verse eid="JOB 14:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 14" />
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JOB 15" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 15:1" />Then answered Eliphaz the Temanite, and said, <verse eid="JOB 15:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 15:2" />Should a wise man utter vain knowledge, and fill his belly with the east wind?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">vain…: Heb. knowledge of wind</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 15:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 15:3" />Should he reason with unprofitable talk? or with speeches wherewith he can do no good? <verse eid="JOB 15:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 15:4" />Yea, thou castest off fear, and restrainest prayer before God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">castest…: Heb. makest void</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">prayer: or, speech</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 15:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 15:5" />For thy mouth uttereth thine iniquity, and thou choosest the tongue of the crafty.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">uttereth: Heb. teacheth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 15:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 15:6" />Thine own mouth condemneth thee, and not I: yea, thine own lips testify against thee. <verse eid="JOB 15:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 15:7" /><char style="add">Art</char> thou the first man <char style="add">that</char> was born? or wast thou made before the hills? <verse eid="JOB 15:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 15:8" />Hast thou heard the secret of God? and dost thou restrain wisdom to thyself? <verse eid="JOB 15:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 15:9" />What knowest thou, that we know not? <char style="add">what</char> understandest thou, which <char style="add">is</char> not in us? <verse eid="JOB 15:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 15:10" />With us <char style="add">are</char> both the grayheaded and very aged men, much elder than thy father. <verse eid="JOB 15:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 15:11" /><char style="add">Are</char> the consolations of God small with thee? is there any secret thing with thee? <verse eid="JOB 15:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 15:12" />Why doth thine heart carry thee away? and what do thy eyes wink at, <verse eid="JOB 15:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 15:13" />That thou turnest thy spirit against God, and lettest <char style="add">such</char> words go out of thy mouth? <verse eid="JOB 15:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 15:14" />What <char style="add">is</char> man, that he should be clean? and <char style="add">he which is</char> born of a woman, that he should be righteous? <verse eid="JOB 15:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 15:15" />Behold, he putteth no trust in his saints; yea, the heavens are not clean in his sight. <verse eid="JOB 15:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 15:16" />How much more abominable and filthy <char style="add">is</char> man, which drinketh iniquity like water?<verse eid="JOB 15:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 15:17" />I will shew thee, hear me; and that <char style="add">which</char> I have seen I will declare; <verse eid="JOB 15:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 15:18" />Which wise men have told from their fathers, and have not hid <char style="add">it:</char> <verse eid="JOB 15:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 15:19" />Unto whom alone the earth was given, and no stranger passed among them. <verse eid="JOB 15:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 15:20" />The wicked man travaileth with pain all <char style="add">his</char> days, and the number of years is hidden to the oppressor. <verse eid="JOB 15:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 15:21" />A dreadful sound <char style="add">is</char> in his ears: in prosperity the destroyer shall come upon him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A dreadful…: Heb. A sound of fears</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 15:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 15:22" />He believeth not that he shall return out of darkness, and he is waited for of the sword. <verse eid="JOB 15:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 15:23" />He wandereth abroad for bread, <char style="add">saying</char>, Where <char style="add">is it</char>? he knoweth that the day of darkness is ready at his hand. <verse eid="JOB 15:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 15:24" />Trouble and anguish shall make him afraid; they shall prevail against him, as a king ready to the battle. <verse eid="JOB 15:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 15:25" />For he stretcheth out his hand against God, and strengtheneth himself against the Almighty. <verse eid="JOB 15:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 15:26" />He runneth upon him, <char style="add">even</char> on <char style="add">his</char> neck, upon the thick bosses of his bucklers: <verse eid="JOB 15:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 15:27" />Because he covereth his face with his fatness, and maketh collops of fat on <char style="add">his</char> flanks. <verse eid="JOB 15:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 15:28" />And he dwelleth in desolate cities, <char style="add">and</char> in houses which no man inhabiteth, which are ready to become heaps. <verse eid="JOB 15:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 15:29" />He shall not be rich, neither shall his substance continue, neither shall he prolong the perfection thereof upon the earth. <verse eid="JOB 15:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 15:30" />He shall not depart out of darkness; the flame shall dry up his branches, and by the breath of his mouth shall he go away. <verse eid="JOB 15:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 15:31" />Let not him that is deceived trust in vanity: for vanity shall be his recompence. <verse eid="JOB 15:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 15:32" />It shall be accomplished before his time, and his branch shall not be green.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">accomplished: or, cut off</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 15:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 15:33" />He shall shake off his unripe grape as the vine, and shall cast off his flower as the olive. <verse eid="JOB 15:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOB 15:34" />For the congregation of hypocrites <char style="add">shall be</char> desolate, and fire shall consume the tabernacles of bribery. <verse eid="JOB 15:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOB 15:35" />They conceive mischief, and bring forth vanity, and their belly prepareth deceit.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15.35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">vanity: or, iniquity</char></note><verse eid="JOB 15:35" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 15" />
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JOB 16" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 16:1" />Then Job answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 16:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 16:2" />I have heard many such things: miserable comforters <char style="add">are</char> ye all.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">miserable: or, troublesome</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 16:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 16:3" />Shall vain words have an end? or what emboldeneth thee that thou answerest?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">vain…: Heb. words of wind</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 16:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 16:4" />I also could speak as ye <char style="add">do:</char> if your soul were in my soul’s stead, I could heap up words against you, and shake mine head at you. <verse eid="JOB 16:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 16:5" /><char style="add">But</char> I would strengthen you with my mouth, and the moving of my lips should asswage <char style="add">your grief</char>.<verse eid="JOB 16:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 16:6" />Though I speak, my grief is not asswaged: and <char style="add">though</char> I forbear, what am I eased?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">what…: Heb. what goeth from me?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 16:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 16:7" />But now he hath made me weary: thou hast made desolate all my company. <verse eid="JOB 16:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 16:8" />And thou hast filled me with wrinkles, <char style="add">which</char> is a witness <char style="add">against me:</char> and my leanness rising up in me beareth witness to my face. <verse eid="JOB 16:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 16:9" />He teareth <char style="add">me</char> in his wrath, who hateth me: he gnasheth upon me with his teeth; mine enemy sharpeneth his eyes upon me. <verse eid="JOB 16:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 16:10" />They have gaped upon me with their mouth; they have smitten me upon the cheek reproachfully; they have gathered themselves together against me. <verse eid="JOB 16:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 16:11" />God hath delivered me to the ungodly, and turned me over into the hands of the wicked.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">hath…: Heb. hath shut me up</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 16:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 16:12" />I was at ease, but he hath broken me asunder: he hath also taken <char style="add">me</char> by my neck, and shaken me to pieces, and set me up for his mark. <verse eid="JOB 16:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 16:13" />His archers compass me round about, he cleaveth my reins asunder, and doth not spare; he poureth out my gall upon the ground. <verse eid="JOB 16:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 16:14" />He breaketh me with breach upon breach, he runneth upon me like a giant. <verse eid="JOB 16:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 16:15" />I have sewed sackcloth upon my skin, and defiled my horn in the dust. <verse eid="JOB 16:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 16:16" />My face is foul with weeping, and on my eyelids <char style="add">is</char> the shadow of death;<verse eid="JOB 16:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 16:17" />Not for <char style="add">any</char> injustice in mine hands: also my prayer <char style="add">is</char> pure. <verse eid="JOB 16:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 16:18" />O earth, cover not thou my blood, and let my cry have no place. <verse eid="JOB 16:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 16:19" />Also now, behold, my witness <char style="add">is</char> in heaven, and my record <char style="add">is</char> on high.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">on high: Heb. in the high places</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 16:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 16:20" />My friends scorn me: <char style="add">but</char> mine eye poureth out <char style="add">tears</char> unto God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">scorn me: Heb. are my scorners</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 16:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 16:21" />O that one might plead for a man with God, as a man <char style="add">pleadeth</char> for his neighbour!<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">neighbour: or, friend</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 16:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 16:22" />When a few years are come, then I shall go the way <char style="add">whence</char> I shall not return.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a few…: Heb. years of number</char></note><verse eid="JOB 16:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 16" />
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JOB 17" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 17:1" />My breath is corrupt, my days are extinct, the graves <char style="add">are ready</char> for me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">breath…: or, spirit is spent</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 17:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 17:2" /><char style="add">Are there</char> not mockers with me? and doth not mine eye continue in their provocation?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">continue: Heb. lodge</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 17:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 17:3" />Lay down now, put me in a surety with thee; who <char style="add">is</char> he <char style="add">that</char> will strike hands with me? <verse eid="JOB 17:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 17:4" />For thou hast hid their heart from understanding: therefore shalt thou not exalt <char style="add">them</char>. <verse eid="JOB 17:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 17:5" />He that speaketh flattery to <char style="add">his</char> friends, even the eyes of his children shall fail. <verse eid="JOB 17:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 17:6" />He hath made me also a byword of the people; and aforetime I was as a tabret.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">aforetime: or, before them</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 17:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 17:7" />Mine eye also is dim by reason of sorrow, and all my members <char style="add">are</char> as a shadow.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my members: or, my thoughts</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 17:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 17:8" />Upright <char style="add">men</char> shall be astonied at this, and the innocent shall stir up himself against the hypocrite. <verse eid="JOB 17:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 17:9" />The righteous also shall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands shall be stronger and stronger.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">be…: Heb. add strength</char></note><verse eid="JOB 17:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 17:10" />But as for you all, do ye return, and come now: for I cannot find <char style="add">one</char> wise <char style="add">man</char> among you. <verse eid="JOB 17:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 17:11" />My days are past, my purposes are broken off, <char style="add">even</char> the thoughts of my heart.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the thoughts: Heb. the possessions</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 17:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 17:12" />They change the night into day: the light <char style="add">is</char> short because of darkness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">short: Heb. near</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 17:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 17:13" />If I wait, the grave <char style="add">is</char> mine house: I have made my bed in the darkness. <verse eid="JOB 17:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 17:14" />I have said to corruption, Thou <char style="add">art</char> my father: to the worm, <char style="add">Thou art</char> my mother, and my sister.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">said: Heb. cried, or, called</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 17:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 17:15" />And where <char style="add">is</char> now my hope? as for my hope, who shall see it? <verse eid="JOB 17:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 17:16" />They shall go down to the bars of the pit, when <char style="add">our</char> rest together <char style="add">is</char> in the dust.<verse eid="JOB 17:16" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 17" />
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JOB 18" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 18:1" />Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said, <verse eid="JOB 18:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 18:2" />How long <char style="add">will it be ere</char> ye make an end of words? mark, and afterwards we will speak. <verse eid="JOB 18:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 18:3" />Wherefore are we counted as beasts, <char style="add">and</char> reputed vile in your sight? <verse eid="JOB 18:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 18:4" />He teareth himself in his anger: shall the earth be forsaken for thee? and shall the rock be removed out of his place?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">himself: Heb. his soul</char></note><verse eid="JOB 18:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 18:5" />Yea, the light of the wicked shall be put out, and the spark of his fire shall not shine. <verse eid="JOB 18:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 18:6" />The light shall be dark in his tabernacle, and his candle shall be put out with him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">candle: or, lamp</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 18:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 18:7" />The steps of his strength shall be straitened, and his own counsel shall cast him down. <verse eid="JOB 18:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 18:8" />For he is cast into a net by his own feet, and he walketh upon a snare. <verse eid="JOB 18:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 18:9" />The gin shall take <char style="add">him</char> by the heel, <char style="add">and</char> the robber shall prevail against him. <verse eid="JOB 18:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 18:10" />The snare <char style="add">is</char> laid for him in the ground, and a trap for him in the way.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">laid: Heb. hidden</char></note><verse eid="JOB 18:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 18:11" />Terrors shall make him afraid on every side, and shall drive him to his feet.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">drive: Heb. scatter</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 18:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 18:12" />His strength shall be hungerbitten, and destruction <char style="add">shall be</char> ready at his side. <verse eid="JOB 18:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 18:13" />It shall devour the strength of his skin: <char style="add">even</char> the firstborn of death shall devour his strength.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">strength: Heb. bars</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 18:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 18:14" />His confidence shall be rooted out of his tabernacle, and it shall bring him to the king of terrors. <verse eid="JOB 18:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 18:15" />It shall dwell in his tabernacle, because <char style="add">it is</char> none of his: brimstone shall be scattered upon his habitation. <verse eid="JOB 18:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 18:16" />His roots shall be dried up beneath, and above shall his branch be cut off. <verse eid="JOB 18:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 18:17" />His remembrance shall perish from the earth, and he shall have no name in the street. <verse eid="JOB 18:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 18:18" />He shall be driven from light into darkness, and chased out of the world.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">He…: Heb. They shall drive him</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 18:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 18:19" />He shall neither have son nor nephew among his people, nor any remaining in his dwellings. <verse eid="JOB 18:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 18:20" />They that come after <char style="add">him</char> shall be astonied at his day, as they that went before were affrighted.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">went…: or, lived with him</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">were…: Heb. laid hold on horror</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 18:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 18:21" />Surely such <char style="add">are</char> the dwellings of the wicked, and this <char style="add">is</char> the place <char style="add">of him that</char> knoweth not God.<verse eid="JOB 18:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 18" />
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JOB 19" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 19:1" />Then Job answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 19:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 19:2" />How long will ye vex my soul, and break me in pieces with words? <verse eid="JOB 19:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 19:3" />These ten times have ye reproached me: ye are not ashamed <char style="add">that</char> ye make yourselves strange to me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">make…: or, harden yourselves against me</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 19:4" />And be it indeed <char style="add">that</char> I have erred, mine error remaineth with myself. <verse eid="JOB 19:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 19:5" />If indeed ye will magnify <char style="add">yourselves</char> against me, and plead against me my reproach: <verse eid="JOB 19:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 19:6" />Know now that God hath overthrown me, and hath compassed me with his net. <verse eid="JOB 19:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 19:7" />Behold, I cry out of wrong, but I am not heard: I cry aloud, but <char style="add">there is</char> no judgment.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wrong: or, violence</char></note><verse eid="JOB 19:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 19:8" />He hath fenced up my way that I cannot pass, and he hath set darkness in my paths. <verse eid="JOB 19:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 19:9" />He hath stripped me of my glory, and taken the crown <char style="add">from</char> my head. <verse eid="JOB 19:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 19:10" />He hath destroyed me on every side, and I am gone: and mine hope hath he removed like a tree. <verse eid="JOB 19:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 19:11" />He hath also kindled his wrath against me, and he counteth me unto him as <char style="add">one of</char> his enemies. <verse eid="JOB 19:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 19:12" />His troops come together, and raise up their way against me, and encamp round about my tabernacle. <verse eid="JOB 19:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 19:13" />He hath put my brethren far from me, and mine acquaintance are verily estranged from me. <verse eid="JOB 19:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 19:14" />My kinsfolk have failed, and my familiar friends have forgotten me. <verse eid="JOB 19:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 19:15" />They that dwell in mine house, and my maids, count me for a stranger: I am an alien in their sight. <verse eid="JOB 19:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 19:16" />I called my servant, and he gave <char style="add">me</char> no answer; I intreated him with my mouth. <verse eid="JOB 19:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 19:17" />My breath is strange to my wife, though I intreated for the children’s <char style="add">sake</char> of mine own body.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mine…: Heb. my belly</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 19:18" />Yea, young children despised me; I arose, and they spake against me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">young…: or, the wicked</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 19:19" />All my inward friends abhorred me: and they whom I loved are turned against me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my…: Heb. the men of my secret</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 19:20" />My bone cleaveth to my skin and to my flesh, and I am escaped with the skin of my teeth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and to: or, as to</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 19:21" />Have pity upon me, have pity upon me, O ye my friends; for the hand of God hath touched me. <verse eid="JOB 19:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 19:22" />Why do ye persecute me as God, and are not satisfied with my flesh?<verse eid="JOB 19:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 19:23" />Oh that my words were now written! oh that they were printed in a book!<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Oh…: Heb. Who will give, etc</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 19:24" />That they were graven with an iron pen and lead in the rock for ever! <verse eid="JOB 19:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 19:25" />For I know <char style="add">that</char> my redeemer liveth, and <char style="add">that</char> he shall stand at the latter <char style="add">day</char> upon the earth: <verse eid="JOB 19:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 19:26" />And <char style="add">though</char> after my skin <char style="add">worms</char> destroy this <char style="add">body</char>, yet in my flesh shall I see God:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">And…: or, After I shall awake, though this body be destroyed, yet out of my flesh</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 19:27" />Whom I shall see for myself, and mine eyes shall behold, and not another; <char style="add">though</char> my reins be consumed within me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">another: Heb. a stranger</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">though…: or, my reins within me are consumed with earnest desire (for that day)</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">within…: Heb. in my bosom</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 19:28" />But ye should say, Why persecute we him, seeing the root of the matter is found in me?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">seeing…: or, and what root of matter is found in me?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 19:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 19:29" />Be ye afraid of the sword: for wrath <char style="add">bringeth</char> the punishments of the sword, that ye may know <char style="add">there is</char> a judgment.<verse eid="JOB 19:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 19" />
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JOB 20" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 20:1" />Then answered Zophar the Naamathite, and said, <verse eid="JOB 20:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 20:2" />Therefore do my thoughts cause me to answer, and for <char style="add">this</char> I make haste.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I make…: Heb. my haste is in me</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 20:3" />I have heard the check of my reproach, and the spirit of my understanding causeth me to answer. <verse eid="JOB 20:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 20:4" />Knowest thou <char style="add">not</char> this of old, since man was placed upon earth, <verse eid="JOB 20:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 20:5" />That the triumphing of the wicked <char style="add">is</char> short, and the joy of the hypocrite <char style="add">but</char> for a moment?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">short: Heb. from near</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 20:6" />Though his excellency mount up to the heavens, and his head reach unto the clouds;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">clouds: Heb. cloud</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 20:7" /><char style="add">Yet</char> he shall perish for ever like his own dung: they which have seen him shall say, Where <char style="add">is</char> he? <verse eid="JOB 20:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 20:8" />He shall fly away as a dream, and shall not be found: yea, he shall be chased away as a vision of the night. <verse eid="JOB 20:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 20:9" />The eye also <char style="add">which</char> saw him shall <char style="add">see him</char> no more; neither shall his place any more behold him.<verse eid="JOB 20:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 20:10" />His children shall seek to please the poor, and his hands shall restore their goods.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">His children…: or, The poor shall oppress his children</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 20:11" />His bones are full <char style="add">of the sin</char> of his youth, which shall lie down with him in the dust. <verse eid="JOB 20:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 20:12" />Though wickedness be sweet in his mouth, <char style="add">though</char> he hide it under his tongue; <verse eid="JOB 20:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 20:13" /><char style="add">Though</char> he spare it, and forsake it not; but keep it still within his mouth:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">within…: Heb. in the midst of his palate</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 20:14" /><char style="add">Yet</char> his meat in his bowels is turned, <char style="add">it is</char> the gall of asps within him. <verse eid="JOB 20:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 20:15" />He hath swallowed down riches, and he shall vomit them up again: God shall cast them out of his belly. <verse eid="JOB 20:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 20:16" />He shall suck the poison of asps: the viper’s tongue shall slay him. <verse eid="JOB 20:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 20:17" />He shall not see the rivers, the floods, the brooks of honey and butter.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the floods…: or, streaming brooks</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 20:18" />That which he laboured for shall he restore, and shall not swallow <char style="add">it</char> down: according to <char style="add">his</char> substance <char style="add">shall</char> the restitution <char style="add">be</char>, and he shall not rejoice <char style="add">therein</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">his…: Heb. the substance of his exchange</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 20:19" />Because he hath oppressed <char style="add">and</char> hath forsaken the poor; <char style="add">because</char> he hath violently taken away an house which he builded not;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">oppressed: Heb. crushed</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 20:20" />Surely he shall not feel quietness in his belly, he shall not save of that which he desired.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">feel: Heb. know</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 20:21" />There shall none of his meat be left; therefore shall no man look for his goods.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">none…: or, be none left for his meat</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 20:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 20:22" />In the fulness of his sufficiency he shall be in straits: every hand of the wicked shall come upon him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wicked: or, troublesome</char></note><verse eid="JOB 20:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 20:23" />
    <char style="add">When</char> he is about to fill his belly, <char style="add">God</char> shall cast the fury of his wrath upon him, and shall rain <char style="add">it</char> upon him while he is eating. <verse eid="JOB 20:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 20:24" />He shall flee from the iron weapon, <char style="add">and</char> the bow of steel shall strike him through. <verse eid="JOB 20:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 20:25" />It is drawn, and cometh out of the body; yea, the glittering sword cometh out of his gall: terrors <char style="add">are</char> upon him. <verse eid="JOB 20:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 20:26" />All darkness <char style="add">shall be</char> hid in his secret places: a fire not blown shall consume him; it shall go ill with him that is left in his tabernacle. <verse eid="JOB 20:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 20:27" />The heaven shall reveal his iniquity; and the earth shall rise up against him. <verse eid="JOB 20:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 20:28" />The increase of his house shall depart, <char style="add">and his goods</char> shall flow away in the day of his wrath. <verse eid="JOB 20:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 20:29" />This <char style="add">is</char> the portion of a wicked man from God, and the heritage appointed unto him by God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">appointed…: Heb. of his decree from God</char></note><verse eid="JOB 20:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 20" />
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JOB 21" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 21:1" />But Job answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 21:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 21:2" />Hear diligently my speech, and let this be your consolations. <verse eid="JOB 21:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 21:3" />Suffer me that I may speak; and after that I have spoken, mock on. <verse eid="JOB 21:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 21:4" />As for me, <char style="add">is</char> my complaint to man? and if <char style="add">it were so</char>, why should not my spirit be troubled?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">troubled: Heb. shortened?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 21:5" />Mark me, and be astonished, and lay <char style="add">your</char> hand upon <char style="add">your</char> mouth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Mark…: Heb. Look unto me</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 21:6" />Even when I remember I am afraid, and trembling taketh hold on my flesh.<verse eid="JOB 21:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 21:7" />Wherefore do the wicked live, become old, yea, are mighty in power? <verse eid="JOB 21:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 21:8" />Their seed is established in their sight with them, and their offspring before their eyes. <verse eid="JOB 21:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 21:9" />Their houses <char style="add">are</char> safe from fear, neither <char style="add">is</char> the rod of God upon them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">safe…: Heb. peace from</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 21:10" />Their bull gendereth, and faileth not; their cow calveth, and casteth not her calf. <verse eid="JOB 21:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 21:11" />They send forth their little ones like a flock, and their children dance. <verse eid="JOB 21:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 21:12" />They take the timbrel and harp, and rejoice at the sound of the organ. <verse eid="JOB 21:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 21:13" />They spend their days in wealth, and in a moment go down to the grave.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in wealth: or, in mirth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 21:14" />Therefore they say unto God, Depart from us; for we desire not the knowledge of thy ways. <verse eid="JOB 21:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 21:15" />What <char style="add">is</char> the Almighty, that we should serve him? and what profit should we have, if we pray unto him? <verse eid="JOB 21:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 21:16" />Lo, their good <char style="add">is</char> not in their hand: the counsel of the wicked is far from me.<verse eid="JOB 21:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 21:17" />How oft is the candle of the wicked put out! and <char style="add">how oft</char> cometh their destruction upon them! <char style="add">God</char> distributeth sorrows in his anger.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">candle: or, lamp</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 21:18" />They are as stubble before the wind, and as chaff that the storm carrieth away.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">carrieth: Heb. stealeth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 21:19" />God layeth up his iniquity for his children: he rewardeth him, and he shall know <char style="add">it</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">his iniquity: that is, the punishment of his iniquity</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 21:20" />His eyes shall see his destruction, and he shall drink of the wrath of the Almighty. <verse eid="JOB 21:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 21:21" />For what pleasure <char style="add">hath</char> he in his house after him, when the number of his months is cut off in the midst? <verse eid="JOB 21:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 21:22" />Shall <char style="add">any</char> teach God knowledge? seeing he judgeth those that are high. <verse eid="JOB 21:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 21:23" />One dieth in his full strength, being wholly at ease and quiet.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">his…: Heb. his very, or, the strength of, his perfection</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 21:24" />His breasts are full of milk, and his bones are moistened with marrow.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">breasts: or, milk pails</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 21:25" />And another dieth in the bitterness of his soul, and never eateth with pleasure. <verse eid="JOB 21:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 21:26" />They shall lie down alike in the dust, and the worms shall cover them.<verse eid="JOB 21:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 21:27" />Behold, I know your thoughts, and the devices <char style="add">which</char> ye wrongfully imagine against me. <verse eid="JOB 21:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 21:28" />For ye say, Where <char style="add">is</char> the house of the prince? and where <char style="add">are</char> the dwelling places of the wicked?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the dwelling…: Heb. the tent of the tabernacles</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 21:29" />Have ye not asked them that go by the way? and do ye not know their tokens, <verse eid="JOB 21:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 21:30" />That the wicked is reserved to the day of destruction? they shall be brought forth to the day of wrath.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wrath: Heb. wraths</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 21:31" />Who shall declare his way to his face? and who shall repay him <char style="add">what</char> he hath done? <verse eid="JOB 21:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 21:32" />Yet shall he be brought to the grave, and shall remain in the tomb.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">grave: Heb. graves</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">remain…: Heb. watch in the heap</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 21:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 21:33" />The clods of the valley shall be sweet unto him, and every man shall draw after him, as <char style="add">there are</char> innumerable before him. <verse eid="JOB 21:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOB 21:34" />How then comfort ye me in vain, seeing in your answers there remaineth falsehood?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21.34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">falsehood: Heb. transgression?</char></note><verse eid="JOB 21:34" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 21" />
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="JOB 22" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 22:1" />Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 22:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 22:2" />Can a man be profitable unto God, as he that is wise may be profitable unto himself?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as he…: or, if he may be profitable, doth his good success depend thereon?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 22:3" /><char style="add">Is it</char> any pleasure to the Almighty, that thou art righteous? or <char style="add">is it</char> gain <char style="add">to him</char>, that thou makest thy ways perfect? <verse eid="JOB 22:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 22:4" />Will he reprove thee for fear of thee? will he enter with thee into judgment?<verse eid="JOB 22:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 22:5" />
    <char style="add">Is</char> not thy wickedness great? and thine iniquities infinite? <verse eid="JOB 22:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 22:6" />For thou hast taken a pledge from thy brother for nought, and stripped the naked of their clothing.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the naked…: Heb. the clothes of the naked</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 22:7" />Thou hast not given water to the weary to drink, and thou hast withholden bread from the hungry. <verse eid="JOB 22:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 22:8" />But <char style="add">as for</char> the mighty man, he had the earth; and the honourable man dwelt in it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mighty…: Heb. man of arm</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">honourable…: Heb. eminent, or, accepted for countenance</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 22:9" />Thou hast sent widows away empty, and the arms of the fatherless have been broken. <verse eid="JOB 22:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 22:10" />Therefore snares <char style="add">are</char> round about thee, and sudden fear troubleth thee; <verse eid="JOB 22:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 22:11" />Or darkness, <char style="add">that</char> thou canst not see; and abundance of waters cover thee. <verse eid="JOB 22:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 22:12" /><char style="add">Is</char> not God in the height of heaven? and behold the height of the stars, how high they are!<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">height of the stars: Heb. head of the stars</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 22:13" />And thou sayest, How doth God know? can he judge through the dark cloud?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">How: or, What</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 22:14" />Thick clouds <char style="add">are</char> a covering to him, that he seeth not; and he walketh in the circuit of heaven.<verse eid="JOB 22:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 22:15" />Hast thou marked the old way which wicked men have trodden? <verse eid="JOB 22:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 22:16" />Which were cut down out of time, whose foundation was overflown with a flood:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">whose…: Heb. a flood was poured upon their foundation</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 22:17" />Which said unto God, Depart from us: and what can the Almighty do for them?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">for: or, to</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 22:18" />Yet he filled their houses with good <char style="add">things:</char> but the counsel of the wicked is far from me. <verse eid="JOB 22:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 22:19" />The righteous see <char style="add">it</char>, and are glad: and the innocent laugh them to scorn. <verse eid="JOB 22:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 22:20" />Whereas our substance is not cut down, but the remnant of them the fire consumeth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">substance: or, estate</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the remnant…: or, their excellency</char></note><verse eid="JOB 22:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 22:21" />Acquaint now thyself with him, and be at peace: thereby good shall come unto thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">him: that is, God</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 22:22" />Receive, I pray thee, the law from his mouth, and lay up his words in thine heart. <verse eid="JOB 22:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 22:23" />If thou return to the Almighty, thou shalt be built up, thou shalt put away iniquity far from thy tabernacles. <verse eid="JOB 22:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 22:24" />Then shalt thou lay up gold as dust, and the <char style="add">gold</char> of Ophir as the stones of the brooks.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as dust: or, on the dust</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 22:25" />Yea, the Almighty shall be thy defence, and thou shalt have plenty of silver.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">defence: or, gold</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">plenty…: Heb. silver of strength</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 22:26" />For then shalt thou have thy delight in the Almighty, and shalt lift up thy face unto God. <verse eid="JOB 22:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 22:27" />Thou shalt make thy prayer unto him, and he shall hear thee, and thou shalt pay thy vows. <verse eid="JOB 22:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 22:28" />Thou shalt also decree a thing, and it shall be established unto thee: and the light shall shine upon thy ways. <verse eid="JOB 22:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 22:29" />When <char style="add">men</char> are cast down, then thou shalt say, <char style="add">There is</char> lifting up; and he shall save the humble person.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the humble…: Heb. him that hath low eyes</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 22:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 22:30" />He shall deliver the island of the innocent: and it is delivered by the pureness of thine hands.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">He shall…: or, The innocent shall deliver the island</char></note><verse eid="JOB 22:30" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 22" />
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="JOB 23" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 23:1" />Then Job answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 23:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 23:2" />Even to day <char style="add">is</char> my complaint bitter: my stroke is heavier than my groaning.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">stroke: Heb. hand</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 23:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 23:3" />Oh that I knew where I might find him! <char style="add">that</char> I might come <char style="add">even</char> to his seat! <verse eid="JOB 23:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 23:4" />I would order <char style="add">my</char> cause before him, and fill my mouth with arguments. <verse eid="JOB 23:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 23:5" />I would know the words <char style="add">which</char> he would answer me, and understand what he would say unto me. <verse eid="JOB 23:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 23:6" />Will he plead against me with <char style="add">his</char> great power? No; but he would put <char style="add">strength</char> in me. <verse eid="JOB 23:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 23:7" />There the righteous might dispute with him; so should I be delivered for ever from my judge.<verse eid="JOB 23:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 23:8" />Behold, I go forward, but he <char style="add">is</char> not <char style="add">there;</char> and backward, but I cannot perceive him: <verse eid="JOB 23:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 23:9" />On the left hand, where he doth work, but I cannot behold <char style="add">him:</char> he hideth himself on the right hand, that I cannot see <char style="add">him:</char> <verse eid="JOB 23:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 23:10" />But he knoweth the way that I take: <char style="add">when</char> he hath tried me, I shall come forth as gold.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: Heb. that is with me</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 23:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 23:11" />My foot hath held his steps, his way have I kept, and not declined. <verse eid="JOB 23:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 23:12" />Neither have I gone back from the commandment of his lips; I have esteemed the words of his mouth more than my necessary <char style="add">food</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">esteemed: Heb. hid, or, laid up</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my…: or, my appointed portion</char></note><verse eid="JOB 23:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 23:13" />But he <char style="add">is</char> in one <char style="add">mind</char>, and who can turn him? and <char style="add">what</char> his soul desireth, even <char style="add">that</char> he doeth. <verse eid="JOB 23:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 23:14" />For he performeth <char style="add">the thing that is</char> appointed for me: and many such <char style="add">things are</char> with him. <verse eid="JOB 23:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 23:15" />Therefore am I troubled at his presence: when I consider, I am afraid of him. <verse eid="JOB 23:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 23:16" />For God maketh my heart soft, and the Almighty troubleth me: <verse eid="JOB 23:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 23:17" />Because I was not cut off before the darkness, <char style="add">neither</char> hath he covered the darkness from my face.<verse eid="JOB 23:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 23" />
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="JOB 24" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 24:1" />Why, seeing times are not hidden from the Almighty, do they that know him not see his days? <verse eid="JOB 24:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 24:2" /><char style="add">Some</char> remove the landmarks; they violently take away flocks, and feed <char style="add">thereof</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">feed…: or, feed them</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 24:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 24:3" />They drive away the ass of the fatherless, they take the widow’s ox for a pledge. <verse eid="JOB 24:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 24:4" />They turn the needy out of the way: the poor of the earth hide themselves together. <verse eid="JOB 24:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 24:5" />Behold, <char style="add">as</char> wild asses in the desert, go they forth to their work; rising betimes for a prey: the wilderness <char style="add">yieldeth</char> food for them <char style="add">and</char> for <char style="add">their</char> children. <verse eid="JOB 24:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 24:6" />They reap <char style="add">every one</char> his corn in the field: and they gather the vintage of the wicked.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">corn: Heb. mingled corn, or, dredge</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">they gather…: Heb. the wicked gather the vintage</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 24:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 24:7" />They cause the naked to lodge without clothing, that <char style="add">they have</char> no covering in the cold. <verse eid="JOB 24:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 24:8" />They are wet with the showers of the mountains, and embrace the rock for want of a shelter. <verse eid="JOB 24:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 24:9" />They pluck the fatherless from the breast, and take a pledge of the poor. <verse eid="JOB 24:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 24:10" />They cause <char style="add">him</char> to go naked without clothing, and they take away the sheaf <char style="add">from</char> the hungry; <verse eid="JOB 24:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 24:11" /><char style="add">Which</char> make oil within their walls, <char style="add">and</char> tread <char style="add">their</char> winepresses, and suffer thirst. <verse eid="JOB 24:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 24:12" />Men groan from out of the city, and the soul of the wounded crieth out: yet God layeth not folly <char style="add">to them</char>.<verse eid="JOB 24:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 24:13" />They are of those that rebel against the light; they know not the ways thereof, nor abide in the paths thereof. <verse eid="JOB 24:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 24:14" />The murderer rising with the light killeth the poor and needy, and in the night is as a thief. <verse eid="JOB 24:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 24:15" />The eye also of the adulterer waiteth for the twilight, saying, No eye shall see me: and disguiseth <char style="add">his</char> face.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">disguiseth…: Heb. setteth his face in secret</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 24:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 24:16" />In the dark they dig through houses, <char style="add">which</char> they had marked for themselves in the daytime: they know not the light. <verse eid="JOB 24:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 24:17" />For the morning <char style="add">is</char> to them even as the shadow of death: if <char style="add">one</char> know <char style="add">them, they are in</char> the terrors of the shadow of death.<verse eid="JOB 24:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 24:18" />He <char style="add">is</char> swift as the waters; their portion is cursed in the earth: he beholdeth not the way of the vineyards. <verse eid="JOB 24:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 24:19" />Drought and heat consume the snow waters: <char style="add">so doth</char> the grave <char style="add">those which</char> have sinned.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">consume: Heb. violently take</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 24:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 24:20" />The womb shall forget him; the worm shall feed sweetly on him; he shall be no more remembered; and wickedness shall be broken as a tree. <verse eid="JOB 24:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 24:21" />He evil entreateth the barren <char style="add">that</char> beareth not: and doeth not good to the widow. <verse eid="JOB 24:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 24:22" />He draweth also the mighty with his power: he riseth up, and no <char style="add">man</char> is sure of life.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">no…: or, he trusteth not his own life</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 24:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 24:23" /><char style="add">Though</char> it be given him <char style="add">to be</char> in safety, whereon he resteth; yet his eyes <char style="add">are</char> upon their ways. <verse eid="JOB 24:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 24:24" />They are exalted for a little while, but are gone and brought low; they are taken out of the way as all <char style="add">other</char>, and cut off as the tops of the ears of corn.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">are gone: Heb. are not</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">taken…: Heb. closed up</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 24:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 24:25" />And if <char style="add">it be</char> not <char style="add">so</char> now, who will make me a liar, and make my speech nothing worth?<verse eid="JOB 24:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 24" />
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="JOB 25" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 25:1" />Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said, <verse eid="JOB 25:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 25:2" />Dominion and fear <char style="add">are</char> with him, he maketh peace in his high places. <verse eid="JOB 25:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 25:3" />Is there any number of his armies? and upon whom doth not his light arise? <verse eid="JOB 25:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 25:4" />How then can man be justified with God? or how can he be clean <char style="add">that is</char> born of a woman? <verse eid="JOB 25:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 25:5" />Behold even to the moon, and it shineth not; yea, the stars are not pure in his sight. <verse eid="JOB 25:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 25:6" />How much less man, <char style="add">that is</char> a worm? and the son of man, <char style="add">which is</char> a worm?<verse eid="JOB 25:6" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 25" />
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="JOB 26" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 26:1" />But Job answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 26:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 26:2" />How hast thou helped <char style="add">him that is</char> without power? <char style="add">how</char> savest thou the arm <char style="add">that hath</char> no strength? <verse eid="JOB 26:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 26:3" />How hast thou counselled <char style="add">him that hath</char> no wisdom? and <char style="add">how</char> hast thou plentifully declared the thing as it is? <verse eid="JOB 26:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 26:4" />To whom hast thou uttered words? and whose spirit came from thee?<verse eid="JOB 26:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 26:5" />Dead <char style="add">things</char> are formed from under the waters, and the inhabitants thereof.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and the…: or, with the inhabitants</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 26:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 26:6" />Hell <char style="add">is</char> naked before him, and destruction hath no covering. <verse eid="JOB 26:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 26:7" />He stretcheth out the north over the empty place, <char style="add">and</char> hangeth the earth upon nothing. <verse eid="JOB 26:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 26:8" />He bindeth up the waters in his thick clouds; and the cloud is not rent under them. <verse eid="JOB 26:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 26:9" />He holdeth back the face of his throne, <char style="add">and</char> spreadeth his cloud upon it. <verse eid="JOB 26:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 26:10" />He hath compassed the waters with bounds, until the day and night come to an end.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">until…: Heb. until the end of light with darkness</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 26:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 26:11" />The pillars of heaven tremble and are astonished at his reproof. <verse eid="JOB 26:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 26:12" />He divideth the sea with his power, and by his understanding he smiteth through the proud.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the proud: Heb. pride</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 26:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 26:13" />By his spirit he hath garnished the heavens; his hand hath formed the crooked serpent. <verse eid="JOB 26:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 26:14" />Lo, these <char style="add">are</char> parts of his ways: but how little a portion is heard of him? but the thunder of his power who can understand?<verse eid="JOB 26:14" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 26" />
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="JOB 27" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 27:1" />Moreover Job continued his parable, and said,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">continued: Heb. added to take up</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 27:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 27:2" /><char style="add">As</char> God liveth, <char style="add">who</char> hath taken away my judgment; and the Almighty, <char style="add">who</char> hath vexed my soul;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">vexed…: Heb. made my soul bitter</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 27:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 27:3" />All the while my breath <char style="add">is</char> in me, and the spirit of God <char style="add">is</char> in my nostrils;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the spirit…: that is, the breath which God gave him</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 27:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 27:4" />My lips shall not speak wickedness, nor my tongue utter deceit. <verse eid="JOB 27:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 27:5" />God forbid that I should justify you: till I die I will not remove mine integrity from me. <verse eid="JOB 27:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 27:6" />My righteousness I hold fast, and will not let it go: my heart shall not reproach <char style="add">me</char> so long as I live.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">so long…: Heb. from my days</char></note><verse eid="JOB 27:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 27:7" />Let mine enemy be as the wicked, and he that riseth up against me as the unrighteous. <verse eid="JOB 27:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 27:8" />For what <char style="add">is</char> the hope of the hypocrite, though he hath gained, when God taketh away his soul? <verse eid="JOB 27:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 27:9" />Will God hear his cry when trouble cometh upon him? <verse eid="JOB 27:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 27:10" />Will he delight himself in the Almighty? will he always call upon God?<verse eid="JOB 27:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 27:11" />I will teach you by the hand of God: <char style="add">that</char> which <char style="add">is</char> with the Almighty will I not conceal.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by…: or, being in the hand, etc</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 27:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 27:12" />Behold, all ye yourselves have seen <char style="add">it;</char> why then are ye thus altogether vain? <verse eid="JOB 27:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 27:13" />This <char style="add">is</char> the portion of a wicked man with God, and the heritage of oppressors, <char style="add">which</char> they shall receive of the Almighty. <verse eid="JOB 27:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 27:14" />If his children be multiplied, <char style="add">it is</char> for the sword: and his offspring shall not be satisfied with bread. <verse eid="JOB 27:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 27:15" />Those that remain of him shall be buried in death: and his widows shall not weep. <verse eid="JOB 27:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 27:16" />Though he heap up silver as the dust, and prepare raiment as the clay; <verse eid="JOB 27:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 27:17" />He may prepare <char style="add">it</char>, but the just shall put <char style="add">it</char> on, and the innocent shall divide the silver. <verse eid="JOB 27:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 27:18" />He buildeth his house as a moth, and as a booth <char style="add">that</char> the keeper maketh. <verse eid="JOB 27:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 27:19" />The rich man shall lie down, but he shall not be gathered: he openeth his eyes, and he <char style="add">is</char> not. <verse eid="JOB 27:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 27:20" />Terrors take hold on him as waters, a tempest stealeth him away in the night. <verse eid="JOB 27:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 27:21" />The east wind carrieth him away, and he departeth: and as a storm hurleth him out of his place. <verse eid="JOB 27:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 27:22" />For <char style="add">God</char> shall cast upon him, and not spare: he would fain flee out of his hand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he…: Heb. in fleeing he would flee</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 27:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 27:23" /><char style="add">Men</char> shall clap their hands at him, and shall hiss him out of his place.<verse eid="JOB 27:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 27" />
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="JOB 28" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 28:1" />Surely there is a vein for the silver, and a place for gold <char style="add">where</char> they fine <char style="add">it</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">vein: or, mine</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 28:2" />Iron is taken out of the earth, and brass <char style="add">is</char> molten <char style="add">out of</char> the stone.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">earth: or, dust</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 28:3" />He setteth an end to darkness, and searcheth out all perfection: the stones of darkness, and the shadow of death. <verse eid="JOB 28:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 28:4" />The flood breaketh out from the inhabitant; <char style="add">even the waters</char> forgotten of the foot: they are dried up, they are gone away from men. <verse eid="JOB 28:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 28:5" /><char style="add">As for</char> the earth, out of it cometh bread: and under it is turned up as it were fire. <verse eid="JOB 28:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 28:6" />The stones of it <char style="add">are</char> the place of sapphires: and it hath dust of gold.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">dust…: or, gold ore</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 28:7" /><char style="add">There is</char> a path which no fowl knoweth, and which the vulture’s eye hath not seen: <verse eid="JOB 28:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 28:8" />The lion’s whelps have not trodden it, nor the fierce lion passed by it. <verse eid="JOB 28:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 28:9" />He putteth forth his hand upon the rock; he overturneth the mountains by the roots.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">rock: or, flint</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 28:10" />He cutteth out rivers among the rocks; and his eye seeth every precious thing. <verse eid="JOB 28:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 28:11" />He bindeth the floods from overflowing; and <char style="add">the thing that is</char> hid bringeth he forth to light.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">overflowing: Heb. weeping</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 28:12" />But where shall wisdom be found? and where <char style="add">is</char> the place of understanding? <verse eid="JOB 28:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 28:13" />Man knoweth not the price thereof; neither is it found in the land of the living.<verse eid="JOB 28:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 28:14" />The depth saith, It <char style="add">is</char> not in me: and the sea saith, <char style="add">It is</char> not with me. <verse eid="JOB 28:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 28:15" />It cannot be gotten for gold, neither shall silver be weighed <char style="add">for</char> the price thereof.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">It…: Heb. Fine gold shall not be given for it</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 28:16" />It cannot be valued with the gold of Ophir, with the precious onyx, or the sapphire. <verse eid="JOB 28:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 28:17" />The gold and the crystal cannot equal it: and the exchange of it <char style="add">shall not be for</char> jewels of fine gold.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">jewels…: or, vessels of</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 28:18" />No mention shall be made of coral, or of pearls: for the price of wisdom <char style="add">is</char> above rubies.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">coral: or, Ramoth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 28:19" />The topaz of Ethiopia shall not equal it, neither shall it be valued with pure gold.<verse eid="JOB 28:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 28:20" />Whence then cometh wisdom? and where <char style="add">is</char> the place of understanding? <verse eid="JOB 28:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 28:21" />Seeing it is hid from the eyes of all living, and kept close from the fowls of the air.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">air: or, heaven</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 28:22" />Destruction and death say, We have heard the fame thereof with our ears. <verse eid="JOB 28:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 28:23" />God understandeth the way thereof, and he knoweth the place thereof. <verse eid="JOB 28:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 28:24" />For he looketh to the ends of the earth, <char style="add">and</char> seeth under the whole heaven; <verse eid="JOB 28:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 28:25" />To make the weight for the winds; and he weigheth the waters by measure. <verse eid="JOB 28:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 28:26" />When he made a decree for the rain, and a way for the lightning of the thunder: <verse eid="JOB 28:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 28:27" />Then did he see it, and declare it; he prepared it, yea, and searched it out.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">declare…: or, number it</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 28:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 28:28" />And unto man he said, Behold, the fear of the Lord, that <char style="add">is</char> wisdom; and to depart from evil <char style="add">is</char> understanding.<verse eid="JOB 28:28" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 28" />
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="JOB 29" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 29:1" />Moreover Job continued his parable, and said,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">continued: Heb. added to take up</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 29:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 29:2" />Oh that I were as <char style="add">in</char> months past, as <char style="add">in</char> the days <char style="add">when</char> God preserved me; <verse eid="JOB 29:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 29:3" />When his candle shined upon my head, <char style="add">and when</char> by his light I walked <char style="add">through</char> darkness;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">candle: or, lamp</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 29:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 29:4" />As I was in the days of my youth, when the secret of God <char style="add">was</char> upon my tabernacle; <verse eid="JOB 29:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 29:5" />When the Almighty <char style="add">was</char> yet with me, <char style="add">when</char> my children <char style="add">were</char> about me; <verse eid="JOB 29:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 29:6" />When I washed my steps with butter, and the rock poured me out rivers of oil;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">me: Heb. with me</char></note><verse eid="JOB 29:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 29:7" />When I went out to the gate through the city, <char style="add">when</char> I prepared my seat in the street! <verse eid="JOB 29:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 29:8" />The young men saw me, and hid themselves: and the aged arose, <char style="add">and</char> stood up. <verse eid="JOB 29:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 29:9" />The princes refrained talking, and laid <char style="add">their</char> hand on their mouth. <verse eid="JOB 29:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 29:10" />The nobles held their peace, and their tongue cleaved to the roof of their mouth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The nobles…: Heb. The voice of the nobles was hid</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 29:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 29:11" />When the ear heard <char style="add">me</char>, then it blessed me; and when the eye saw <char style="add">me</char>, it gave witness to me: <verse eid="JOB 29:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 29:12" />Because I delivered the poor that cried, and the fatherless, and <char style="add">him that had</char> none to help him. <verse eid="JOB 29:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 29:13" />The blessing of him that was ready to perish came upon me: and I caused the widow’s heart to sing for joy. <verse eid="JOB 29:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 29:14" />I put on righteousness, and it clothed me: my judgment <char style="add">was</char> as a robe and a diadem. <verse eid="JOB 29:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 29:15" />I was eyes to the blind, and feet <char style="add">was</char> I to the lame. <verse eid="JOB 29:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 29:16" />I <char style="add">was</char> a father to the poor: and the cause <char style="add">which</char> I knew not I searched out. <verse eid="JOB 29:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 29:17" />And I brake the jaws of the wicked, and plucked the spoil out of his teeth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the jaws: Heb. the jawteeth, or, the grinders</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">plucked: Heb. cast</char></note><verse eid="JOB 29:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 29:18" />Then I said, I shall die in my nest, and I shall multiply <char style="add">my</char> days as the sand. <verse eid="JOB 29:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 29:19" />My root <char style="add">was</char> spread out by the waters, and the dew lay all night upon my branch.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">spread…: Heb. opened</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 29:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 29:20" />My glory <char style="add">was</char> fresh in me, and my bow was renewed in my hand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fresh: Heb. new</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">29.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">renewed: Heb. changed</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 29:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 29:21" />Unto me <char style="add">men</char> gave ear, and waited, and kept silence at my counsel. <verse eid="JOB 29:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 29:22" />After my words they spake not again; and my speech dropped upon them. <verse eid="JOB 29:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 29:23" />And they waited for me as for the rain; and they opened their mouth wide <char style="add">as</char> for the latter rain. <verse eid="JOB 29:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 29:24" /><char style="add">If</char> I laughed on them, they believed <char style="add">it</char> not; and the light of my countenance they cast not down. <verse eid="JOB 29:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 29:25" />I chose out their way, and sat chief, and dwelt as a king in the army, as one <char style="add">that</char> comforteth the mourners.<verse eid="JOB 29:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 29" />
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="JOB 30" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 30:1" />But now <char style="add">they that are</char> younger than I have me in derision, whose fathers I would have disdained to have set with the dogs of my flock.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">younger…: Heb. of fewer days than I</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 30:2" />Yea, whereto <char style="add">might</char> the strength of their hands <char style="add">profit</char> me, in whom old age was perished? <verse eid="JOB 30:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 30:3" />For want and famine <char style="add">they were</char> solitary; fleeing into the wilderness in former time desolate and waste.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">solitary: or, dark as the night</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: Heb. yesternight</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 30:4" />Who cut up mallows by the bushes, and juniper roots <char style="add">for</char> their meat. <verse eid="JOB 30:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 30:5" />They were driven forth from among <char style="add">men</char>, (they cried after them as <char style="add">after</char> a thief;) <verse eid="JOB 30:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 30:6" />To dwell in the clifts of the valleys, <char style="add">in</char> caves of the earth, and <char style="add">in</char> the rocks.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">caves: Heb. holes</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 30:7" />Among the bushes they brayed; under the nettles they were gathered together. <verse eid="JOB 30:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 30:8" /><char style="add">They were</char> children of fools, yea, children of base men: they were viler than the earth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">base…: Heb. men of no name</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 30:9" />And now am I their song, yea, I am their byword. <verse eid="JOB 30:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 30:10" />They abhor me, they flee far from me, and spare not to spit in my face.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and…: Heb. and withhold not spittle from</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 30:11" />Because he hath loosed my cord, and afflicted me, they have also let loose the bridle before me. <verse eid="JOB 30:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 30:12" />Upon <char style="add">my</char> right <char style="add">hand</char> rise the youth; they push away my feet, and they raise up against me the ways of their destruction. <verse eid="JOB 30:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 30:13" />They mar my path, they set forward my calamity, they have no helper. <verse eid="JOB 30:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 30:14" />They came <char style="add">upon me</char> as a wide breaking in <char style="add">of waters:</char> in the desolation they rolled themselves <char style="add">upon me</char>.<verse eid="JOB 30:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 30:15" />Terrors are turned upon me: they pursue my soul as the wind: and my welfare passeth away as a cloud.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my soul: Heb. my principal one</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 30:16" />And now my soul is poured out upon me; the days of affliction have taken hold upon me. <verse eid="JOB 30:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 30:17" />My bones are pierced in me in the night season: and my sinews take no rest. <verse eid="JOB 30:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 30:18" />By the great force <char style="add">of my disease</char> is my garment changed: it bindeth me about as the collar of my coat. <verse eid="JOB 30:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 30:19" />He hath cast me into the mire, and I am become like dust and ashes. <verse eid="JOB 30:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 30:20" />I cry unto thee, and thou dost not hear me: I stand up, and thou regardest me <char style="add">not</char>. <verse eid="JOB 30:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 30:21" />Thou art become cruel to me: with thy strong hand thou opposest thyself against me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">become…: Heb. turned to be cruel</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">thy…: Heb. the strength of thy hand</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 30:22" />Thou liftest me up to the wind; thou causest me to ride <char style="add">upon it</char>, and dissolvest my substance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">substance: or, wisdom</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 30:23" />For I know <char style="add">that</char> thou wilt bring me <char style="add">to</char> death, and <char style="add">to</char> the house appointed for all living. <verse eid="JOB 30:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 30:24" />Howbeit he will not stretch out <char style="add">his</char> hand to the grave, though they cry in his destruction.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">grave: Heb. heap</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 30:25" />Did not I weep for him that was in trouble? was <char style="add">not</char> my soul grieved for the poor?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in trouble: Heb. hard of day?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 30:26" />When I looked for good, then evil came <char style="add">unto me:</char> and when I waited for light, there came darkness. <verse eid="JOB 30:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 30:27" />My bowels boiled, and rested not: the days of affliction prevented me. <verse eid="JOB 30:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 30:28" />I went mourning without the sun: I stood up, <char style="add">and</char> I cried in the congregation. <verse eid="JOB 30:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 30:29" />I am a brother to dragons, and a companion to owls.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">30.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">owls: or, ostriches</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 30:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 30:30" />My skin is black upon me, and my bones are burned with heat. <verse eid="JOB 30:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 30:31" />My harp also is <char style="add">turned</char> to mourning, and my organ into the voice of them that weep.<verse eid="JOB 30:31" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 30" />
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="JOB 31" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 31:1" />I made a covenant with mine eyes; why then should I think upon a maid? <verse eid="JOB 31:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 31:2" />For what portion of God <char style="add">is there</char> from above? and <char style="add">what</char> inheritance of the Almighty from on high? <verse eid="JOB 31:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 31:3" /><char style="add">Is</char> not destruction to the wicked? and a strange <char style="add">punishment</char> to the workers of iniquity? <verse eid="JOB 31:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 31:4" />Doth not he see my ways, and count all my steps? <verse eid="JOB 31:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 31:5" />If I have walked with vanity, or if my foot hath hasted to deceit; <verse eid="JOB 31:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 31:6" />Let me be weighed in an even balance, that God may know mine integrity.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Let…: Heb. Let him weigh me in balances of justice</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 31:7" />If my step hath turned out of the way, and mine heart walked after mine eyes, and if any blot hath cleaved to mine hands; <verse eid="JOB 31:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 31:8" /><char style="add">Then</char> let me sow, and let another eat; yea, let my offspring be rooted out.<verse eid="JOB 31:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 31:9" />If mine heart have been deceived by a woman, or <char style="add">if</char> I have laid wait at my neighbour’s door; <verse eid="JOB 31:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 31:10" /><char style="add">Then</char> let my wife grind unto another, and let others bow down upon her. <verse eid="JOB 31:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 31:11" />For this <char style="add">is</char> an heinous crime; yea, it <char style="add">is</char> an iniquity <char style="add">to be punished by</char> the judges. <verse eid="JOB 31:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 31:12" />For it <char style="add">is</char> a fire <char style="add">that</char> consumeth to destruction, and would root out all mine increase. <verse eid="JOB 31:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 31:13" />If I did despise the cause of my manservant or of my maidservant, when they contended with me; <verse eid="JOB 31:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 31:14" />What then shall I do when God riseth up? and when he visiteth, what shall I answer him? <verse eid="JOB 31:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 31:15" />Did not he that made me in the womb make him? and did not one fashion us in the womb?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">did not one…: or, did he not fashion us in one womb?</char></note><verse eid="JOB 31:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 31:16" />If I have withheld the poor from <char style="add">their</char> desire, or have caused the eyes of the widow to fail; <verse eid="JOB 31:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 31:17" />Or have eaten my morsel myself alone, and the fatherless hath not eaten thereof; <verse eid="JOB 31:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 31:18" />(For from my youth he was brought up with me, as <char style="add">with</char> a father, and I have guided her from my mother’s womb;)<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">her: that is, the widow</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 31:19" />If I have seen any perish for want of clothing, or any poor without covering; <verse eid="JOB 31:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 31:20" />If his loins have not blessed me, and <char style="add">if</char> he were <char style="add">not</char> warmed with the fleece of my sheep; <verse eid="JOB 31:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 31:21" />If I have lifted up my hand against the fatherless, when I saw my help in the gate: <verse eid="JOB 31:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 31:22" /><char style="add">Then</char> let mine arm fall from my shoulder blade, and mine arm be broken from the bone.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">bone: or, chanelbone</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 31:23" />For destruction <char style="add">from</char> God <char style="add">was</char> a terror to me, and by reason of his highness I could not endure.<verse eid="JOB 31:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 31:24" />If I have made gold my hope, or have said to the fine gold, <char style="add">Thou art</char> my confidence; <verse eid="JOB 31:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 31:25" />If I rejoiced because my wealth <char style="add">was</char> great, and because mine hand had gotten much;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gotten…: Heb. found much</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 31:26" />If I beheld the sun when it shined, or the moon walking <char style="add">in</char> brightness;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sun: Heb. light</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: Heb. bright</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 31:27" />And my heart hath been secretly enticed, or my mouth hath kissed my hand:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my mouth…: Heb. my hand hath kissed my mouth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 31:28" />This also <char style="add">were</char> an iniquity <char style="add">to be punished by</char> the judge: for I should have denied the God <char style="add">that is</char> above. <verse eid="JOB 31:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 31:29" />If I rejoiced at the destruction of him that hated me, or lifted up myself when evil found him: <verse eid="JOB 31:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 31:30" />Neither have I suffered my mouth to sin by wishing a curse to his soul.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mouth: Heb. palate</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 31:31" />If the men of my tabernacle said not, Oh that we had of his flesh! we cannot be satisfied. <verse eid="JOB 31:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 31:32" />The stranger did not lodge in the street: <char style="add">but</char> I opened my doors to the traveller.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">traveller: or, way</char></note><verse eid="JOB 31:32" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 31:33" />If I covered my transgressions as Adam, by hiding mine iniquity in my bosom:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as Adam: or, after the manner of men</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOB 31:34" />Did I fear a great multitude, or did the contempt of families terrify me, that I kept silence, <char style="add">and</char> went not out of the door? <verse eid="JOB 31:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOB 31:35" />Oh that one would hear me! behold, my desire <char style="add">is, that</char> the Almighty would answer me, and <char style="add">that</char> mine adversary had written a book.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my…: or, my sign is that the Almighty will</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOB 31:36" />Surely I would take it upon my shoulder, <char style="add">and</char> bind it <char style="add">as</char> a crown to me. <verse eid="JOB 31:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOB 31:37" />I would declare unto him the number of my steps; as a prince would I go near unto him. <verse eid="JOB 31:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOB 31:38" />If my land cry against me, or that the furrows likewise thereof complain;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">complain: Heb. weep</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOB 31:39" />If I have eaten the fruits thereof without money, or have caused the owners thereof to lose their life:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.39 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fruits: Heb. strength</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.39 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the owners…: Heb. the soul of the owners thereof to expire, or, breathe out</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 31:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOB 31:40" />Let thistles grow instead of wheat, and cockle instead of barley. The words of Job are ended.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31.40 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cockle: or, noisome weeds</char></note><verse eid="JOB 31:40" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 31" />
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="JOB 32" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 32:1" />So these three men ceased to answer Job, because he <char style="add">was</char> righteous in his own eyes.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to…: Heb. from answering</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 32:2" />Then was kindled the wrath of Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite, of the kindred of Ram: against Job was his wrath kindled, because he justified himself rather than God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">himself: Heb. his soul</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 32:3" />Also against his three friends was his wrath kindled, because they had found no answer, and <char style="add">yet</char> had condemned Job. <verse eid="JOB 32:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 32:4" />Now Elihu had waited till Job had spoken, because they <char style="add">were</char> elder than he.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">waited…: Heb. expected Job in words</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">elder: Heb. elder for days</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 32:5" />When Elihu saw that <char style="add">there was</char> no answer in the mouth of <char style="add">these</char> three men, then his wrath was kindled.<verse eid="JOB 32:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 32:6" />And Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite answered and said, I <char style="add">am</char> young, and ye <char style="add">are</char> very old; wherefore I was afraid, and durst not shew you mine opinion.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">young: Heb. few of days</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">durst…: Heb. feared</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 32:7" />I said, Days should speak, and multitude of years should teach wisdom. <verse eid="JOB 32:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 32:8" />But <char style="add">there is</char> a spirit in man: and the inspiration of the Almighty giveth them understanding. <verse eid="JOB 32:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 32:9" />Great men are not <char style="add">always</char> wise: neither do the aged understand judgment. <verse eid="JOB 32:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 32:10" />Therefore I said, Hearken to me; I also will shew mine opinion. <verse eid="JOB 32:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 32:11" />Behold, I waited for your words; I gave ear to your reasons, whilst ye searched out what to say.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">reasons: Heb. understandings</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">what…: Heb. words</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 32:12" />Yea, I attended unto you, and, behold, <char style="add">there was</char> none of you that convinced Job, <char style="add">or</char> that answered his words: <verse eid="JOB 32:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 32:13" />Lest ye should say, We have found out wisdom: God thrusteth him down, not man. <verse eid="JOB 32:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 32:14" />Now he hath not directed <char style="add">his</char> words against me: neither will I answer him with your speeches.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">directed: or, ordered</char></note><verse eid="JOB 32:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 32:15" />They were amazed, they answered no more: they left off speaking.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">left…: Heb. removed speeches from themselves</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 32:16" />When I had waited, (for they spake not, but stood still, <char style="add">and</char> answered no more;) <verse eid="JOB 32:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 32:17" /><char style="add">I said</char>, I will answer also my part, I also will shew mine opinion. <verse eid="JOB 32:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 32:18" />For I am full of matter, the spirit within me constraineth me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">matter: Heb. words</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">spirit…: Heb. spirit of my belly</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 32:19" />Behold, my belly <char style="add">is</char> as wine <char style="add">which</char> hath no vent; it is ready to burst like new bottles.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">hath…: Heb. is not opened</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 32:20" />I will speak, that I may be refreshed: I will open my lips and answer.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">be…: Heb. breathe</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 32:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 32:21" />Let me not, I pray you, accept any man’s person, neither let me give flattering titles unto man. <verse eid="JOB 32:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 32:22" />For I know not to give flattering titles; <char style="add">in so doing</char> my maker would soon take me away.<verse eid="JOB 32:22" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 32" />
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="JOB 33" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 33:1" />Wherefore, Job, I pray thee, hear my speeches, and hearken to all my words. <verse eid="JOB 33:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 33:2" />Behold, now I have opened my mouth, my tongue hath spoken in my mouth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in my mouth: Heb. in my palate</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 33:3" />My words <char style="add">shall be of</char> the uprightness of my heart: and my lips shall utter knowledge clearly. <verse eid="JOB 33:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 33:4" />The Spirit of God hath made me, and the breath of the Almighty hath given me life. <verse eid="JOB 33:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 33:5" />If thou canst answer me, set <char style="add">thy words</char> in order before me, stand up. <verse eid="JOB 33:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 33:6" />Behold, I <char style="add">am</char> according to thy wish in God’s stead: I also am formed out of the clay.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wish: Heb. mouth</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">formed: Heb. cut</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 33:7" />Behold, my terror shall not make thee afraid, neither shall my hand be heavy upon thee.<verse eid="JOB 33:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 33:8" />Surely thou hast spoken in mine hearing, and I have heard the voice of <char style="add">thy</char> words, <char style="add">saying</char>,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">hearing: Heb. ears</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 33:9" />I am clean without transgression, I <char style="add">am</char> innocent; neither <char style="add">is there</char> iniquity in me. <verse eid="JOB 33:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 33:10" />Behold, he findeth occasions against me, he counteth me for his enemy, <verse eid="JOB 33:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 33:11" />He putteth my feet in the stocks, he marketh all my paths. <verse eid="JOB 33:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 33:12" />Behold, <char style="add">in</char> this thou art not just: I will answer thee, that God is greater than man. <verse eid="JOB 33:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 33:13" />Why dost thou strive against him? for he giveth not account of any of his matters.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he giveth…: Heb. he answereth not</char></note><verse eid="JOB 33:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 33:14" />For God speaketh once, yea twice, <char style="add">yet man</char> perceiveth it not. <verse eid="JOB 33:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 33:15" />In a dream, in a vision of the night, when deep sleep falleth upon men, in slumberings upon the bed; <verse eid="JOB 33:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 33:16" />Then he openeth the ears of men, and sealeth their instruction,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he…: Heb. he revealeth, or, uncovereth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 33:17" />That he may withdraw man <char style="add">from his</char> purpose, and hide pride from man.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">purpose: Heb. work</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 33:18" />He keepeth back his soul from the pit, and his life from perishing by the sword.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from perishing: Heb. from passing</char></note><verse eid="JOB 33:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 33:19" />He is chastened also with pain upon his bed, and the multitude of his bones with strong <char style="add">pain:</char> <verse eid="JOB 33:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 33:20" />So that his life abhorreth bread, and his soul dainty meat.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">dainty…: Heb. meat of desire</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 33:21" />His flesh is consumed away, that it cannot be seen; and his bones <char style="add">that</char> were not seen stick out. <verse eid="JOB 33:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 33:22" />Yea, his soul draweth near unto the grave, and his life to the destroyers. <verse eid="JOB 33:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 33:23" />If there be a messenger with him, an interpreter, one among a thousand, to shew unto man his uprightness: <verse eid="JOB 33:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 33:24" />Then he is gracious unto him, and saith, Deliver him from going down to the pit: I have found a ransom.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a ransom: or, an atonement</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 33:25" />His flesh shall be fresher than a child’s: he shall return to the days of his youth:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a child’s: Heb. childhood</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 33:26" />He shall pray unto God, and he will be favourable unto him: and he shall see his face with joy: for he will render unto man his righteousness. <verse eid="JOB 33:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 33:27" />He looketh upon men, and <char style="add">if any</char> say, I have sinned, and perverted <char style="add">that which was</char> right, and it profited me not;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">He…: or, He shall look upon men, and say</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 33:28" />He will deliver his soul from going into the pit, and his life shall see the light.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">He…: or, He hath delivered my soul, etc, and my life</char></note><verse eid="JOB 33:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 33:29" />Lo, all these <char style="add">things</char> worketh God oftentimes with man,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">oftentimes: Heb. twice and thrice</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 33:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 33:30" />To bring back his soul from the pit, to be enlightened with the light of the living. <verse eid="JOB 33:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 33:31" />Mark well, O Job, hearken unto me: hold thy peace, and I will speak. <verse eid="JOB 33:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 33:32" />If thou hast any thing to say, answer me: speak, for I desire to justify thee. <verse eid="JOB 33:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 33:33" />If not, hearken unto me: hold thy peace, and I shall teach thee wisdom.<verse eid="JOB 33:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 33" />
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="JOB 34" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 34:1" />Furthermore Elihu answered and said, <verse eid="JOB 34:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 34:2" />Hear my words, O ye wise <char style="add">men;</char> and give ear unto me, ye that have knowledge. <verse eid="JOB 34:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 34:3" />For the ear trieth words, as the mouth tasteth meat.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">mouth: Heb. palate</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 34:4" />Let us choose to us judgment: let us know among ourselves what <char style="add">is</char> good. <verse eid="JOB 34:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 34:5" />For Job hath said, I am righteous: and God hath taken away my judgment. <verse eid="JOB 34:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 34:6" />Should I lie against my right? my wound <char style="add">is</char> incurable without transgression.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">my wound: Heb. mine arrow</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 34:7" />What man <char style="add">is</char> like Job, <char style="add">who</char> drinketh up scorning like water? <verse eid="JOB 34:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 34:8" />Which goeth in company with the workers of iniquity, and walketh with wicked men. <verse eid="JOB 34:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 34:9" />For he hath said, It profiteth a man nothing that he should delight himself with God.<verse eid="JOB 34:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 34:10" />Therefore hearken unto me, ye men of understanding: far be it from God, <char style="add">that he should do</char> wickedness; and <char style="add">from</char> the Almighty, <char style="add">that he should commit</char> iniquity.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">men…: Heb. men of heart</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 34:11" />For the work of a man shall he render unto him, and cause every man to find according to <char style="add">his</char> ways. <verse eid="JOB 34:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 34:12" />Yea, surely God will not do wickedly, neither will the Almighty pervert judgment. <verse eid="JOB 34:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 34:13" />Who hath given him a charge over the earth? or who hath disposed the whole world?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the whole: Heb. all of it?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 34:14" />If he set his heart upon man, <char style="add">if</char> he gather unto himself his spirit and his breath;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">man: Heb. him</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 34:15" />All flesh shall perish together, and man shall turn again unto dust.<verse eid="JOB 34:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 34:16" />If now <char style="add">thou hast</char> understanding, hear this: hearken to the voice of my words. <verse eid="JOB 34:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 34:17" />Shall even he that hateth right govern? and wilt thou condemn him that is most just?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">govern: Heb. bind?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 34:18" /><char style="add">Is it fit</char> to say to a king, <char style="add">Thou art</char> wicked? <char style="add">and</char> to princes, <char style="add">Ye are</char> ungodly? <verse eid="JOB 34:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 34:19" /><char style="add">How much less to him</char> that accepteth not the persons of princes, nor regardeth the rich more than the poor? for they all <char style="add">are</char> the work of his hands. <verse eid="JOB 34:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 34:20" />In a moment shall they die, and the people shall be troubled at midnight, and pass away: and the mighty shall be taken away without hand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the mighty…: Heb. they shall take away the mighty</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 34:21" />For his eyes <char style="add">are</char> upon the ways of man, and he seeth all his goings. <verse eid="JOB 34:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 34:22" /><char style="add">There is</char> no darkness, nor shadow of death, where the workers of iniquity may hide themselves. <verse eid="JOB 34:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 34:23" />For he will not lay upon man more <char style="add">than right;</char> that he should enter into judgment with God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">enter: Heb. go</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 34:24" />He shall break in pieces mighty men without number, and set others in their stead.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">number: Heb. searching out</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 34:25" />Therefore he knoweth their works, and he overturneth <char style="add">them</char> in the night, so that they are destroyed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">destroyed: Heb. crushed</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 34:26" />He striketh them as wicked men in the open sight of others;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">open…: Heb. place of beholders</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 34:27" />Because they turned back from him, and would not consider any of his ways:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">him: Heb. after him</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 34:28" />So that they cause the cry of the poor to come unto him, and he heareth the cry of the afflicted. <verse eid="JOB 34:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 34:29" />When he giveth quietness, who then can make trouble? and when he hideth <char style="add">his</char> face, who then can behold him? whether <char style="add">it be done</char> against a nation, or against a man only: <verse eid="JOB 34:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 34:30" />That the hypocrite reign not, lest the people be ensnared.<verse eid="JOB 34:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 34:31" />Surely it is meet to be said unto God, I have borne <char style="add">chastisement</char>, I will not offend <char style="add">any more:</char> <verse eid="JOB 34:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 34:32" /><char style="add">That which</char> I see not teach thou me: if I have done iniquity, I will do no more. <verse eid="JOB 34:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 34:33" /><char style="add">Should it be</char> according to thy mind? he will recompense it, whether thou refuse, or whether thou choose; and not I: therefore speak what thou knowest.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">according…: Heb. from with thee?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOB 34:34" />Let men of understanding tell me, and let a wise man hearken unto me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of…: Heb. of heart</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOB 34:35" />Job hath spoken without knowledge, and his words <char style="add">were</char> without wisdom. <verse eid="JOB 34:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOB 34:36" />My desire <char style="add">is that</char> Job may be tried unto the end because of <char style="add">his</char> answers for wicked men.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34.36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">My…: or, My father, let Job be tried</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 34:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOB 34:37" />For he addeth rebellion unto his sin, he clappeth <char style="add">his hands</char> among us, and multiplieth his words against God.<verse eid="JOB 34:37" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 34" />
  <chapter number="35" style="c" sid="JOB 35" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 35:1" />Elihu spake moreover, and said, <verse eid="JOB 35:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 35:2" />Thinkest thou this to be right, <char style="add">that</char> thou saidst, My righteousness <char style="add">is</char> more than God’s? <verse eid="JOB 35:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 35:3" />For thou saidst, What advantage will it be unto thee? <char style="add">and</char>, What profit shall I have, <char style="add">if I be cleansed</char> from my sin?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">if…: or, by it more than by my sin</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 35:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 35:4" />I will answer thee, and thy companions with thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">answer…: Heb. return to thee words</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 35:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 35:5" />Look unto the heavens, and see; and behold the clouds <char style="add">which</char> are higher than thou. <verse eid="JOB 35:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 35:6" />If thou sinnest, what doest thou against him? or <char style="add">if</char> thy transgressions be multiplied, what doest thou unto him? <verse eid="JOB 35:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 35:7" />If thou be righteous, what givest thou him? or what receiveth he of thine hand? <verse eid="JOB 35:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 35:8" />Thy wickedness <char style="add">may hurt</char> a man as thou <char style="add">art;</char> and thy righteousness <char style="add">may profit</char> the son of man.<verse eid="JOB 35:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 35:9" />By reason of the multitude of oppressions they make <char style="add">the oppressed</char> to cry: they cry out by reason of the arm of the mighty. <verse eid="JOB 35:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 35:10" />But none saith, Where <char style="add">is</char> God my maker, who giveth songs in the night; <verse eid="JOB 35:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 35:11" />Who teacheth us more than the beasts of the earth, and maketh us wiser than the fowls of heaven? <verse eid="JOB 35:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 35:12" />There they cry, but none giveth answer, because of the pride of evil men. <verse eid="JOB 35:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 35:13" />Surely God will not hear vanity, neither will the Almighty regard it.<verse eid="JOB 35:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 35:14" />Although thou sayest thou shalt not see him, <char style="add">yet</char> judgment <char style="add">is</char> before him; therefore trust thou in him. <verse eid="JOB 35:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 35:15" />But now, because <char style="add">it is</char> not <char style="add">so</char>, he hath visited in his anger; yet he knoweth <char style="add">it</char> not in great extremity:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he hath: that is, God hath</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he knoweth: that is, Job knoweth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 35:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 35:16" />Therefore doth Job open his mouth in vain; he multiplieth words without knowledge.<verse eid="JOB 35:16" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 35" />
  <chapter number="36" style="c" sid="JOB 36" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 36:1" />Elihu also proceeded, and said, <verse eid="JOB 36:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 36:2" />Suffer me a little, and I will shew thee that <char style="add">I have</char> yet to speak on God’s behalf.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I have…: Heb. there are yet words for God</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 36:3" />I will fetch my knowledge from afar, and will ascribe righteousness to my Maker. <verse eid="JOB 36:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 36:4" />For truly my words <char style="add">shall</char> not <char style="add">be</char> false: he that is perfect in knowledge <char style="add">is</char> with thee.<verse eid="JOB 36:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 36:5" />Behold, God <char style="add">is</char> mighty, and despiseth not <char style="add">any: he is</char> mighty in strength <char style="add">and</char> wisdom.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wisdom: Heb. heart</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 36:6" />He preserveth not the life of the wicked: but giveth right to the poor.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">poor: or, afflicted</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 36:7" />He withdraweth not his eyes from the righteous: but with kings <char style="add">are they</char> on the throne; yea, he doth establish them for ever, and they are exalted. <verse eid="JOB 36:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 36:8" />And if <char style="add">they be</char> bound in fetters, <char style="add">and</char> be holden in cords of affliction; <verse eid="JOB 36:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 36:9" />Then he sheweth them their work, and their transgressions that they have exceeded. <verse eid="JOB 36:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 36:10" />He openeth also their ear to discipline, and commandeth that they return from iniquity. <verse eid="JOB 36:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 36:11" />If they obey and serve <char style="add">him</char>, they shall spend their days in prosperity, and their years in pleasures. <verse eid="JOB 36:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 36:12" />But if they obey not, they shall perish by the sword, and they shall die without knowledge.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">perish: Heb. pass away</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 36:13" />But the hypocrites in heart heap up wrath: they cry not when he bindeth them. <verse eid="JOB 36:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 36:14" />They die in youth, and their life <char style="add">is</char> among the unclean.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">They…: Heb. Their soul dieth</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">unclean: or, sodomites</char></note><verse eid="JOB 36:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 36:15" />He delivereth the poor in his affliction, and openeth their ears in oppression.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">poor: or, afflicted</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 36:16" />Even so would he have removed thee out of the strait <char style="add">into</char> a broad place, where <char style="add">there is</char> no straitness; and that which should be set on thy table <char style="add">should be</char> full of fatness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: Heb. the rest of thy table</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 36:17" />But thou hast fulfilled the judgment of the wicked: judgment and justice take hold <char style="add">on thee</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">take…: or, should uphold thee</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 36:18" />Because <char style="add">there is</char> wrath, <char style="add">beware</char> lest he take thee away with <char style="add">his</char> stroke: then a great ransom cannot deliver thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">deliver…: Heb. turn thee aside</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 36:19" />Will he esteem thy riches? <char style="add">no</char>, not gold, nor all the forces of strength. <verse eid="JOB 36:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 36:20" />Desire not the night, when people are cut off in their place. <verse eid="JOB 36:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 36:21" />Take heed, regard not iniquity: for this hast thou chosen rather than affliction. <verse eid="JOB 36:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 36:22" />Behold, God exalteth by his power: who teacheth like him? <verse eid="JOB 36:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 36:23" />Who hath enjoined him his way? or who can say, Thou hast wrought iniquity?<verse eid="JOB 36:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 36:24" />Remember that thou magnify his work, which men behold. <verse eid="JOB 36:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 36:25" />Every man may see it; man may behold <char style="add">it</char> afar off. <verse eid="JOB 36:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 36:26" />Behold, God <char style="add">is</char> great, and we know <char style="add">him</char> not, neither can the number of his years be searched out. <verse eid="JOB 36:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 36:27" />For he maketh small the drops of water: they pour down rain according to the vapour thereof: <verse eid="JOB 36:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 36:28" />Which the clouds do drop <char style="add">and</char> distil upon man abundantly. <verse eid="JOB 36:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 36:29" />Also can <char style="add">any</char> understand the spreadings of the clouds, <char style="add">or</char> the noise of his tabernacle? <verse eid="JOB 36:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 36:30" />Behold, he spreadeth his light upon it, and covereth the bottom of the sea.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">bottom: Heb. roots</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 36:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 36:31" />For by them judgeth he the people; he giveth meat in abundance. <verse eid="JOB 36:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 36:32" />With clouds he covereth the light; and commandeth it <char style="add">not to shine</char> by <char style="add">the cloud</char> that cometh betwixt. <verse eid="JOB 36:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 36:33" />The noise thereof sheweth concerning it, the cattle also concerning the vapour.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">36.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the vapour: Heb. that which goeth up</char></note><verse eid="JOB 36:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 36" />
  <chapter number="37" style="c" sid="JOB 37" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 37:1" />At this also my heart trembleth, and is moved out of his place. <verse eid="JOB 37:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 37:2" />Hear attentively the noise of his voice, and the sound <char style="add">that</char> goeth out of his mouth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hear…: Heb. Hear in hearing</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 37:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 37:3" />He directeth it under the whole heaven, and his lightning unto the ends of the earth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">lightning: Heb. light</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">ends: Heb. wings</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 37:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 37:4" />After it a voice roareth: he thundereth with the voice of his excellency; and he will not stay them when his voice is heard. <verse eid="JOB 37:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 37:5" />God thundereth marvellously with his voice; great things doeth he, which we cannot comprehend.<verse eid="JOB 37:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 37:6" />For he saith to the snow, Be thou <char style="add">on</char> the earth; likewise to the small rain, and to the great rain of his strength.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">likewise…: Heb. and to the shower of rain, and to the showers of rain of his strength</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 37:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 37:7" />He sealeth up the hand of every man; that all men may know his work. <verse eid="JOB 37:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 37:8" />Then the beasts go into dens, and remain in their places. <verse eid="JOB 37:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 37:9" />Out of the south cometh the whirlwind: and cold out of the north.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">south: Heb. chamber</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">north: Heb. scattering winds</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 37:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 37:10" />By the breath of God frost is given: and the breadth of the waters is straitened. <verse eid="JOB 37:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 37:11" />Also by watering he wearieth the thick cloud: he scattereth his bright cloud:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">his…: Heb. the cloud of his light</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 37:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 37:12" />And it is turned round about by his counsels: that they may do whatsoever he commandeth them upon the face of the world in the earth. <verse eid="JOB 37:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 37:13" />He causeth it to come, whether for correction, or for his land, or for mercy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">correction: Heb. a rod</char></note><verse eid="JOB 37:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 37:14" />Hearken unto this, O Job: stand still, and consider the wondrous works of God. <verse eid="JOB 37:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 37:15" />Dost thou know when God disposed them, and caused the light of his cloud to shine? <verse eid="JOB 37:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 37:16" />Dost thou know the balancings of the clouds, the wondrous works of him which is perfect in knowledge? <verse eid="JOB 37:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 37:17" />How thy garments <char style="add">are</char> warm, when he quieteth the earth by the south <char style="add">wind</char>? <verse eid="JOB 37:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 37:18" />Hast thou with him spread out the sky, <char style="add">which is</char> strong, <char style="add">and</char> as a molten looking glass? <verse eid="JOB 37:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 37:19" />Teach us what we shall say unto him; <char style="add">for</char> we cannot order <char style="add">our speech</char> by reason of darkness. <verse eid="JOB 37:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 37:20" />Shall it be told him that I speak? if a man speak, surely he shall be swallowed up.<verse eid="JOB 37:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 37:21" />And now <char style="add">men</char> see not the bright light which <char style="add">is</char> in the clouds: but the wind passeth, and cleanseth them. <verse eid="JOB 37:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 37:22" />Fair weather cometh out of the north: with God <char style="add">is</char> terrible majesty.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">37.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Fair…: Heb. Gold</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 37:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 37:23" /><char style="add">Touching</char> the Almighty, we cannot find him out: <char style="add">he is</char> excellent in power, and in judgment, and in plenty of justice: he will not afflict. <verse eid="JOB 37:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 37:24" />Men do therefore fear him: he respecteth not any <char style="add">that are</char> wise of heart.<verse eid="JOB 37:24" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 37" />
  <chapter number="38" style="c" sid="JOB 38" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 38:1" />Then the <char style="nd">LORD</char> answered Job out of the whirlwind, and said, <verse eid="JOB 38:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 38:2" />Who <char style="add">is</char> this that darkeneth counsel by words without knowledge? <verse eid="JOB 38:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 38:3" />Gird up now thy loins like a man; for I will demand of thee, and answer thou me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">answer…: Heb. make me know</char></note><verse eid="JOB 38:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 38:4" />Where wast thou when I laid the foundations of the earth? declare, if thou hast understanding.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">hast…: Heb. knowest understanding</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 38:5" />Who hath laid the measures thereof, if thou knowest? or who hath stretched the line upon it? <verse eid="JOB 38:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 38:6" />Whereupon are the foundations thereof fastened? or who laid the corner stone thereof;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">foundations: Heb. sockets</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fastened: Heb. made to sink?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 38:7" />When the morning stars sang together, and all the sons of God shouted for joy? <verse eid="JOB 38:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 38:8" />Or <char style="add">who</char> shut up the sea with doors, when it brake forth, <char style="add">as if</char> it had issued out of the womb? <verse eid="JOB 38:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 38:9" />When I made the cloud the garment thereof, and thick darkness a swaddlingband for it, <verse eid="JOB 38:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 38:10" />And brake up for it my decreed <char style="add">place</char>, and set bars and doors,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">brake…: or, established my decree upon it</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 38:11" />And said, Hitherto shalt thou come, but no further: and here shall thy proud waves be stayed?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">thy…: Heb. the pride of thy waves</char></note><verse eid="JOB 38:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 38:12" />Hast thou commanded the morning since thy days; <char style="add">and</char> caused the dayspring to know his place; <verse eid="JOB 38:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 38:13" />That it might take hold of the ends of the earth, that the wicked might be shaken out of it?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">ends: Heb. wings</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 38:14" />It is turned as clay <char style="add">to</char> the seal; and they stand as a garment. <verse eid="JOB 38:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 38:15" />And from the wicked their light is withholden, and the high arm shall be broken. <verse eid="JOB 38:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 38:16" />Hast thou entered into the springs of the sea? or hast thou walked in the search of the depth? <verse eid="JOB 38:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 38:17" />Have the gates of death been opened unto thee? or hast thou seen the doors of the shadow of death? <verse eid="JOB 38:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 38:18" />Hast thou perceived the breadth of the earth? declare if thou knowest it all. <verse eid="JOB 38:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 38:19" />Where <char style="add">is</char> the way <char style="add">where</char> light dwelleth? and <char style="add">as for</char> darkness, where <char style="add">is</char> the place thereof, <verse eid="JOB 38:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 38:20" />That thou shouldest take it to the bound thereof, and that thou shouldest know the paths <char style="add">to</char> the house thereof?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to the bound: or, at, etc</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 38:21" />Knowest thou <char style="add">it</char>, because thou wast then born? or <char style="add">because</char> the number of thy days <char style="add">is</char> great? <verse eid="JOB 38:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 38:22" />Hast thou entered into the treasures of the snow? or hast thou seen the treasures of the hail, <verse eid="JOB 38:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 38:23" />Which I have reserved against the time of trouble, against the day of battle and war? <verse eid="JOB 38:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 38:24" />By what way is the light parted, <char style="add">which</char> scattereth the east wind upon the earth?<verse eid="JOB 38:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 38:25" />Who hath divided a watercourse for the overflowing of waters, or a way for the lightning of thunder; <verse eid="JOB 38:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 38:26" />To cause it to rain on the earth, <char style="add">where</char> no man <char style="add">is; on</char> the wilderness, wherein <char style="add">there is</char> no man; <verse eid="JOB 38:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 38:27" />To satisfy the desolate and waste <char style="add">ground;</char> and to cause the bud of the tender herb to spring forth? <verse eid="JOB 38:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 38:28" />Hath the rain a father? or who hath begotten the drops of dew? <verse eid="JOB 38:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 38:29" />Out of whose womb came the ice? and the hoary frost of heaven, who hath gendered it? <verse eid="JOB 38:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 38:30" />The waters are hid as <char style="add">with</char> a stone, and the face of the deep is frozen.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is…: Heb. is taken</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 38:31" />Canst thou bind the sweet influences of Pleiades, or loose the bands of Orion?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Pleiades: or, the seven stars: Heb. Cimah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Orion: Heb. Cesil?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 38:32" />Canst thou bring forth Mazzaroth in his season? or canst thou guide Arcturus with his sons?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Mazzaroth: or, the twelve signs</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">guide: Heb. guide them</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 38:33" />Knowest thou the ordinances of heaven? canst thou set the dominion thereof in the earth? <verse eid="JOB 38:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOB 38:34" />Canst thou lift up thy voice to the clouds, that abundance of waters may cover thee? <verse eid="JOB 38:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOB 38:35" />Canst thou send lightnings, that they may go, and say unto thee, Here we <char style="add">are</char>?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Here…: Heb. Behold us?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOB 38:36" />Who hath put wisdom in the inward parts? or who hath given understanding to the heart? <verse eid="JOB 38:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOB 38:37" />Who can number the clouds in wisdom? or who can stay the bottles of heaven,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.37 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">stay: Heb. cause to lie down</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOB 38:38" />When the dust groweth into hardness, and the clods cleave fast together?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">groweth…: or, is turned into mire: Heb. is poured</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOB 38:39" />Wilt thou hunt the prey for the lion? or fill the appetite of the young lions,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">38.39 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the appetite: Heb. the life</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 38:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOB 38:40" />When they couch in <char style="add">their</char> dens, <char style="add">and</char> abide in the covert to lie in wait? <verse eid="JOB 38:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOB 38:41" />Who provideth for the raven his food? when his young ones cry unto God, they wander for lack of meat.<verse eid="JOB 38:41" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 38" />
  <chapter number="39" style="c" sid="JOB 39" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 39:1" />Knowest thou the time when the wild goats of the rock bring forth? <char style="add">or</char> canst thou mark when the hinds do calve? <verse eid="JOB 39:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 39:2" />Canst thou number the months <char style="add">that</char> they fulfil? or knowest thou the time when they bring forth? <verse eid="JOB 39:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 39:3" />They bow themselves, they bring forth their young ones, they cast out their sorrows. <verse eid="JOB 39:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 39:4" />Their young ones are in good liking, they grow up with corn; they go forth, and return not unto them. <verse eid="JOB 39:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 39:5" />Who hath sent out the wild ass free? or who hath loosed the bands of the wild ass? <verse eid="JOB 39:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 39:6" />Whose house I have made the wilderness, and the barren land his dwellings.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">39.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">barren…: Heb. salt places</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 39:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 39:7" />He scorneth the multitude of the city, neither regardeth he the crying of the driver.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">39.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of the driver: Heb. of the exactor</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 39:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 39:8" />The range of the mountains <char style="add">is</char> his pasture, and he searcheth after every green thing. <verse eid="JOB 39:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 39:9" />Will the unicorn be willing to serve thee, or abide by thy crib? <verse eid="JOB 39:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 39:10" />Canst thou bind the unicorn with his band in the furrow? or will he harrow the valleys after thee? <verse eid="JOB 39:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 39:11" />Wilt thou trust him, because his strength <char style="add">is</char> great? or wilt thou leave thy labour to him? <verse eid="JOB 39:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 39:12" />Wilt thou believe him, that he will bring home thy seed, and gather <char style="add">it into</char> thy barn?<verse eid="JOB 39:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 39:13" />
    <char style="add">Gavest thou</char> the goodly wings unto the peacocks? or wings and feathers unto the ostrich?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">39.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wings and…: or, the feathers of the stork and ostrich</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 39:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 39:14" />Which leaveth her eggs in the earth, and warmeth them in dust, <verse eid="JOB 39:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 39:15" />And forgetteth that the foot may crush them, or that the wild beast may break them. <verse eid="JOB 39:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 39:16" />She is hardened against her young ones, as though <char style="add">they were</char> not hers: her labour is in vain without fear; <verse eid="JOB 39:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 39:17" />Because God hath deprived her of wisdom, neither hath he imparted to her understanding. <verse eid="JOB 39:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 39:18" />What time she lifteth up herself on high, she scorneth the horse and his rider.<verse eid="JOB 39:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 39:19" />Hast thou given the horse strength? hast thou clothed his neck with thunder? <verse eid="JOB 39:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 39:20" />Canst thou make him afraid as a grasshopper? the glory of his nostrils <char style="add">is</char> terrible.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">39.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">terrible: Heb. terror</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 39:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 39:21" />He paweth in the valley, and rejoiceth in <char style="add">his</char> strength: he goeth on to meet the armed men.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">39.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">He paweth: or, His feet dig</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">39.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the armed…: Heb. the armour</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 39:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 39:22" />He mocketh at fear, and is not affrighted; neither turneth he back from the sword. <verse eid="JOB 39:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 39:23" />The quiver rattleth against him, the glittering spear and the shield. <verse eid="JOB 39:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 39:24" />He swalloweth the ground with fierceness and rage: neither believeth he that <char style="add">it is</char> the sound of the trumpet. <verse eid="JOB 39:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 39:25" />He saith among the trumpets, Ha, ha; and he smelleth the battle afar off, the thunder of the captains, and the shouting.<verse eid="JOB 39:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 39:26" />Doth the hawk fly by thy wisdom, <char style="add">and</char> stretch her wings toward the south? <verse eid="JOB 39:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 39:27" />Doth the eagle mount up at thy command, and make her nest on high?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">39.27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">at…: Heb. by thy mouth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 39:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 39:28" />She dwelleth and abideth on the rock, upon the crag of the rock, and the strong place. <verse eid="JOB 39:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 39:29" />From thence she seeketh the prey, <char style="add">and</char> her eyes behold afar off. <verse eid="JOB 39:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 39:30" />Her young ones also suck up blood: and where the slain <char style="add">are</char>, there <char style="add">is</char> she.<verse eid="JOB 39:30" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 39" />
  <chapter number="40" style="c" sid="JOB 40" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 40:1" />Moreover the <char style="nd">LORD</char> answered Job, and said, <verse eid="JOB 40:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 40:2" />Shall he that contendeth with the Almighty instruct <char style="add">him</char>? he that reproveth God, let him answer it.<verse eid="JOB 40:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 40:3" />¶ Then Job answered the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and said, <verse eid="JOB 40:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 40:4" />Behold, I am vile; what shall I answer thee? I will lay mine hand upon my mouth. <verse eid="JOB 40:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 40:5" />Once have I spoken; but I will not answer: yea, twice; but I will proceed no further.<verse eid="JOB 40:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 40:6" />¶ Then answered the <char style="nd">LORD</char> unto Job out of the whirlwind, and said, <verse eid="JOB 40:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 40:7" />Gird up thy loins now like a man: I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me. <verse eid="JOB 40:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 40:8" />Wilt thou also disannul my judgment? wilt thou condemn me, that thou mayest be righteous? <verse eid="JOB 40:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 40:9" />Hast thou an arm like God? or canst thou thunder with a voice like him? <verse eid="JOB 40:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 40:10" />Deck thyself now <char style="add">with</char> majesty and excellency; and array thyself with glory and beauty. <verse eid="JOB 40:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 40:11" />Cast abroad the rage of thy wrath: and behold every one <char style="add">that is</char> proud, and abase him. <verse eid="JOB 40:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 40:12" />Look on every one <char style="add">that is</char> proud, <char style="add">and</char> bring him low; and tread down the wicked in their place. <verse eid="JOB 40:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 40:13" />Hide them in the dust together; <char style="add">and</char> bind their faces in secret. <verse eid="JOB 40:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 40:14" />Then will I also confess unto thee that thine own right hand can save thee.<verse eid="JOB 40:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 40:15" />¶ Behold now behemoth, which I made with thee; he eateth grass as an ox.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">40.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">behemoth: probably an extinct animal of some kind</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 40:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 40:16" />Lo now, his strength <char style="add">is</char> in his loins, and his force <char style="add">is</char> in the navel of his belly. <verse eid="JOB 40:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 40:17" />He moveth his tail like a cedar: the sinews of his stones are wrapped together.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">40.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">He…: or, He setteth up</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 40:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 40:18" />His bones <char style="add">are as</char> strong pieces of brass; his bones <char style="add">are</char> like bars of iron. <verse eid="JOB 40:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 40:19" />He <char style="add">is</char> the chief of the ways of God: he that made him can make his sword to approach <char style="add">unto him</char>. <verse eid="JOB 40:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 40:20" />Surely the mountains bring him forth food, where all the beasts of the field play. <verse eid="JOB 40:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 40:21" />He lieth under the shady trees, in the covert of the reed, and fens. <verse eid="JOB 40:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 40:22" />The shady trees cover him <char style="add">with</char> their shadow; the willows of the brook compass him about. <verse eid="JOB 40:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 40:23" />Behold, he drinketh up a river, <char style="add">and</char> hasteth not: he trusteth that he can draw up Jordan into his mouth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">40.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">he drinketh up: Heb. he oppresseth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 40:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 40:24" />He taketh it with his eyes: <char style="add">his</char> nose pierceth through snares.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">40.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">He…: or, Will any take him in his sight, or, bore his nose with a gin?</char></note><verse eid="JOB 40:24" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 40" />
  <chapter number="41" style="c" sid="JOB 41" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 41:1" />Canst thou draw out leviathan with an hook? or his tongue with a cord <char style="add">which</char> thou lettest down?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">leviathan: probably an extinct animal of some kind</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">which…: Heb. which thou drownest?</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 41:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 41:2" />Canst thou put an hook into his nose? or bore his jaw through with a thorn? <verse eid="JOB 41:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 41:3" />Will he make many supplications unto thee? will he speak soft <char style="add">words</char> unto thee? <verse eid="JOB 41:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 41:4" />Will he make a covenant with thee? wilt thou take him for a servant for ever? <verse eid="JOB 41:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 41:5" />Wilt thou play with him as <char style="add">with</char> a bird? or wilt thou bind him for thy maidens? <verse eid="JOB 41:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 41:6" />Shall the companions make a banquet of him? shall they part him among the merchants? <verse eid="JOB 41:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 41:7" />Canst thou fill his skin with barbed irons? or his head with fish spears? <verse eid="JOB 41:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 41:8" />Lay thine hand upon him, remember the battle, do no more. <verse eid="JOB 41:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 41:9" />Behold, the hope of him is in vain: shall not <char style="add">one</char> be cast down even at the sight of him? <verse eid="JOB 41:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 41:10" />None <char style="add">is so</char> fierce that dare stir him up: who then is able to stand before me?<verse eid="JOB 41:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 41:11" />Who hath prevented me, that I should repay <char style="add">him? whatsoever is</char> under the whole heaven is mine. <verse eid="JOB 41:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 41:12" />I will not conceal his parts, nor his power, nor his comely proportion. <verse eid="JOB 41:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 41:13" />Who can discover the face of his garment? <char style="add">or</char> who can come <char style="add">to him</char> with his double bridle?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">with: or, within</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 41:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 41:14" />Who can open the doors of his face? his teeth <char style="add">are</char> terrible round about. <verse eid="JOB 41:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 41:15" /><char style="add">His</char> scales <char style="add">are his</char> pride, shut up together <char style="add">as with</char> a close seal.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">scales: Heb. strong pieces of shields</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 41:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 41:16" />One is so near to another, that no air can come between them. <verse eid="JOB 41:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 41:17" />They are joined one to another, they stick together, that they cannot be sundered. <verse eid="JOB 41:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOB 41:18" />By his neesings a light doth shine, and his eyes <char style="add">are</char> like the eyelids of the morning. <verse eid="JOB 41:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOB 41:19" />Out of his mouth go burning lamps, <char style="add">and</char> sparks of fire leap out. <verse eid="JOB 41:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOB 41:20" />Out of his nostrils goeth smoke, as <char style="add">out</char> of a seething pot or caldron. <verse eid="JOB 41:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOB 41:21" />His breath kindleth coals, and a flame goeth out of his mouth. <verse eid="JOB 41:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOB 41:22" />In his neck remaineth strength, and sorrow is turned into joy before him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is turned into joy: Heb. rejoiceth</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 41:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOB 41:23" />The flakes of his flesh are joined together: they are firm in themselves; they cannot be moved.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">flakes: Heb. fallings</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 41:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOB 41:24" />His heart is as firm as a stone; yea, as hard as a piece of the nether <char style="add">millstone</char>. <verse eid="JOB 41:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOB 41:25" />When he raiseth up himself, the mighty are afraid: by reason of breakings they purify themselves. <verse eid="JOB 41:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOB 41:26" />The sword of him that layeth at him cannot hold: the spear, the dart, nor the habergeon.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">habergeon: or, breastplate</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 41:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOB 41:27" />He esteemeth iron as straw, <char style="add">and</char> brass as rotten wood. <verse eid="JOB 41:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOB 41:28" />The arrow cannot make him flee: slingstones are turned with him into stubble. <verse eid="JOB 41:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOB 41:29" />Darts are counted as stubble: he laugheth at the shaking of a spear. <verse eid="JOB 41:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOB 41:30" />Sharp stones <char style="add">are</char> under him: he spreadeth sharp pointed things upon the mire.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Sharp stones: Heb. Sharp pieces of potsherd</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 41:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOB 41:31" />He maketh the deep to boil like a pot: he maketh the sea like a pot of ointment. <verse eid="JOB 41:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOB 41:32" />He maketh a path to shine after him; <char style="add">one</char> would think the deep <char style="add">to be</char> hoary. <verse eid="JOB 41:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOB 41:33" />Upon earth there is not his like, who is made without fear.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">41.33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is made without fear: or, behave themselves without fear</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 41:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOB 41:34" />He beholdeth all high <char style="add">things:</char> he <char style="add">is</char> a king over all the children of pride.<verse eid="JOB 41:34" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 41" />
  <chapter number="42" style="c" sid="JOB 42" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOB 42:1" />Then Job answered the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, and said, <verse eid="JOB 42:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOB 42:2" />I know that thou canst do every <char style="add">thing</char>, and <char style="add">that</char> no thought can be withholden from thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">42.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">no thought can be…: or, no thought of thine can be hindered</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 42:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOB 42:3" />Who <char style="add">is</char> he that hideth counsel without knowledge? therefore have I uttered that I understood not; things too wonderful for me, which I knew not. <verse eid="JOB 42:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOB 42:4" />Hear, I beseech thee, and I will speak: I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me. <verse eid="JOB 42:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOB 42:5" />I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear: but now mine eye seeth thee. <verse eid="JOB 42:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOB 42:6" />Wherefore I abhor <char style="add">myself</char>, and repent in dust and ashes.<verse eid="JOB 42:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOB 42:7" />¶ And it was <char style="add">so</char>, that after the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had spoken these words unto Job, the <char style="nd">LORD</char> said to Eliphaz the Temanite, My wrath is kindled against thee, and against thy two friends: for ye have not spoken of me <char style="add">the thing that is</char> right, as my servant Job <char style="add">hath</char>. <verse eid="JOB 42:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOB 42:8" />Therefore take unto you now seven bullocks and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and offer up for yourselves a burnt offering; and my servant Job shall pray for you: for him will I accept: lest I deal with you <char style="add">after your</char> folly, in that ye have not spoken of me <char style="add">the thing which is</char> right, like my servant Job.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">42.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">him: Heb. his face, or, person</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 42:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOB 42:9" />So Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite <char style="add">and</char> Zophar the Naamathite went, and did according as the <char style="nd">LORD</char> commanded them: the <char style="nd">LORD</char> also accepted Job.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">42.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Job: Heb. the face of Job</char></note><verse eid="JOB 42:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOB 42:10" />And the <char style="nd">LORD</char> turned the captivity of Job, when he prayed for his friends: also the <char style="nd">LORD</char> gave Job twice as much as he had before.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">42.10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">gave…: Heb. added all that had been to Job unto the double</char></note> <verse eid="JOB 42:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOB 42:11" />Then came there unto him all his brethren, and all his sisters, and all they that had been of his acquaintance before, and did eat bread with him in his house: and they bemoaned him, and comforted him over all the evil that the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had brought upon him: every man also gave him a piece of money, and every one an earring of gold. <verse eid="JOB 42:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOB 42:12" />So the <char style="nd">LORD</char> blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning: for he had fourteen thousand sheep, and six thousand camels, and a thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand she asses. <verse eid="JOB 42:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOB 42:13" />He had also seven sons and three daughters. <verse eid="JOB 42:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOB 42:14" />And he called the name of the first, Jemima; and the name of the second, Kezia; and the name of the third, Keren-happuch. <verse eid="JOB 42:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOB 42:15" />And in all the land were no women found <char style="add">so</char> fair as the daughters of Job: and their father gave them inheritance among their brethren. <verse eid="JOB 42:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOB 42:16" />After this lived Job an hundred and forty years, and saw his sons, and his sons’ sons, <char style="add">even</char> four generations. <verse eid="JOB 42:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOB 42:17" />So Job died, <char style="add">being</char> old and full of days.<verse eid="JOB 42:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JOB 42" />
</usx>