<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="MRK" style="id">The Gospel According to Mark</book>
  <para style="h">Mark</para>
  <para style="toc1">THE GOSPEL ACCORDING TO ST. MARK</para>
  <para style="toc2">Mark</para>
  <para style="toc3">Mrk</para>
  <para style="mt1">THE GOSPEL ACCORDING TO ST. MARK</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="MRK 1" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 1:1" />The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of God; <verse eid="MRK 1:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 1:2" />As it is written in the prophets, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face, which shall prepare thy way before thee. <verse eid="MRK 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 1:3" />The voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths straight. <verse eid="MRK 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 1:4" />John did baptize in the wilderness, and preach the baptism of repentance for the remission of sins. <verse eid="MRK 1:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 1:5" />And there went out unto him all the land of Judæa, and they of Jerusalem, and were all baptized of him in the river of Jordan, confessing their sins. <verse eid="MRK 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 1:6" />And John was clothed with camel’s hair, and with a girdle of a skin about his loins; and he did eat locusts and wild honey; <verse eid="MRK 1:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 1:7" />And preached, saying, There cometh one mightier than I after me, the latchet of whose shoes I am not worthy to stoop down and unloose. <verse eid="MRK 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 1:8" />I indeed have baptized you with water: but he shall baptize you with the Holy Ghost. <verse eid="MRK 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 1:9" />And it came to pass in those days, that Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and was baptized of John in Jordan. <verse eid="MRK 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 1:10" />And straightway coming up out of the water, he saw the heavens opened, and the Spirit like a dove descending upon him: <verse eid="MRK 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 1:11" />And there came a voice from heaven, <char style="add">saying</char>, Thou art my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased. <verse eid="MRK 1:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 1:12" />And immediately the Spirit driveth him into the wilderness. <verse eid="MRK 1:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 1:13" />And he was there in the wilderness forty days, tempted of Satan; and was with the wild beasts; and the angels ministered unto him. <verse eid="MRK 1:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 1:14" />Now after that John was put in prison, Jesus came into Galilee, preaching the gospel of the kingdom of God, <verse eid="MRK 1:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 1:15" />And saying, <char style="wj">The time is fulfilled, and the kingdom of God is at hand: repent ye, and believe the gospel.</char> <verse eid="MRK 1:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 1:16" />Now as he walked by the sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and Andrew his brother casting a net into the sea: for they were fishers. <verse eid="MRK 1:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 1:17" />And Jesus said unto them, <char style="wj">Come ye after me, and I will make you to become fishers of men.</char> <verse eid="MRK 1:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 1:18" />And straightway they forsook their nets, and followed him. <verse eid="MRK 1:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 1:19" />And when he had gone a little further thence, he saw James the <char style="add">son</char> of Zebedee, and John his brother, who also were in the ship mending their nets. <verse eid="MRK 1:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 1:20" />And straightway he called them: and they left their father Zebedee in the ship with the hired servants, and went after him. <verse eid="MRK 1:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 1:21" />And they went into Capernaum; and straightway on the sabbath day he entered into the synagogue, and taught. <verse eid="MRK 1:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 1:22" />And they were astonished at his doctrine: for he taught them as one that had authority, and not as the scribes. <verse eid="MRK 1:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 1:23" />And there was in their synagogue a man with an unclean spirit; and he cried out, <verse eid="MRK 1:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 1:24" />Saying, Let <char style="add">us</char> alone; what have we to do with thee, thou Jesus of Nazareth? art thou come to destroy us? I know thee who thou art, the Holy One of God. <verse eid="MRK 1:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 1:25" />And Jesus rebuked him, saying, <char style="wj">Hold thy peace, and come out of him.</char> <verse eid="MRK 1:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 1:26" />And when the unclean spirit had torn him, and cried with a loud voice, he came out of him. <verse eid="MRK 1:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 1:27" />And they were all amazed, insomuch that they questioned among themselves, saying, What thing is this? what new doctrine <char style="add">is</char> this? for with authority commandeth he even the unclean spirits, and they do obey him. <verse eid="MRK 1:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 1:28" />And immediately his fame spread abroad throughout all the region round about Galilee. <verse eid="MRK 1:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 1:29" />And forthwith, when they were come out of the synagogue, they entered into the house of Simon and Andrew, with James and John. <verse eid="MRK 1:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 1:30" />But Simon’s wife’s mother lay sick of a fever, and anon they tell him of her. <verse eid="MRK 1:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 1:31" />And he came and took her by the hand, and lifted her up; and immediately the fever left her, and she ministered unto them. <verse eid="MRK 1:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 1:32" />And at even, when the sun did set, they brought unto him all that were diseased, and them that were possessed with devils. <verse eid="MRK 1:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 1:33" />And all the city was gathered together at the door. <verse eid="MRK 1:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 1:34" />And he healed many that were sick of divers diseases, and cast out many devils; and suffered not the devils to speak, because they knew him. <verse eid="MRK 1:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 1:35" />And in the morning, rising up a great while before day, he went out, and departed into a solitary place, and there prayed. <verse eid="MRK 1:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 1:36" />And Simon and they that were with him followed after him. <verse eid="MRK 1:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 1:37" />And when they had found him, they said unto him, All <char style="add">men</char> seek for thee. <verse eid="MRK 1:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 1:38" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Let us go into the next towns, that I may preach there also: for therefore came I forth.</char> <verse eid="MRK 1:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 1:39" />And he preached in their synagogues throughout all Galilee, and cast out devils. <verse eid="MRK 1:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 1:40" />And there came a leper to him, beseeching him, and kneeling down to him, and saying unto him, If thou wilt, thou canst make me clean. <verse eid="MRK 1:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 1:41" />And Jesus, moved with compassion, put forth <char style="add">his</char> hand, and touched him, and saith unto him, <char style="wj">I will; be thou clean.</char> <verse eid="MRK 1:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 1:42" />And as soon as he had spoken, immediately the leprosy departed from him, and he was cleansed. <verse eid="MRK 1:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 1:43" />And he straitly charged him, and forthwith sent him away; <verse eid="MRK 1:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 1:44" />And saith unto him, <char style="wj">See thou say nothing to any man: but go thy way, shew thyself to the priest, and offer for thy cleansing those things which Moses commanded, for a testimony unto them.</char> <verse eid="MRK 1:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 1:45" />But he went out, and began to publish <char style="add">it</char> much, and to blaze abroad the matter, insomuch that Jesus could no more openly enter into the city, but was without in desert places: and they came to him from every quarter.<verse eid="MRK 1:45" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="MRK 2" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 2:1" />And again he entered into Capernaum after <char style="add">some</char> days; and it was noised that he was in the house. <verse eid="MRK 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 2:2" />And straightway many were gathered together, insomuch that there was no room to receive <char style="add">them</char>, no, not so much as about the door: and he preached the word unto them. <verse eid="MRK 2:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 2:3" />And they come unto him, bringing one sick of the palsy, which was borne of four. <verse eid="MRK 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 2:4" />And when they could not come nigh unto him for the press, they uncovered the roof where he was: and when they had broken <char style="add">it</char> up, they let down the bed wherein the sick of the palsy lay. <verse eid="MRK 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 2:5" />When Jesus saw their faith, he said unto the sick of the palsy, <char style="wj">Son, thy sins be forgiven thee.</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 2:6" />But there were certain of the scribes sitting there, and reasoning in their hearts, <verse eid="MRK 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 2:7" />Why doth this <char style="add">man</char> thus speak blasphemies? who can forgive sins but God only? <verse eid="MRK 2:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 2:8" />And immediately when Jesus perceived in his spirit that they so reasoned within themselves, he said unto them, <char style="wj">Why reason ye these things in your hearts?</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 2:9" /><char style="wj">Whether is it easier to say to the sick of the palsy, <char style="add">Thy</char> sins be forgiven thee; or to say, Arise, and take up thy bed, and walk?</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 2:10" /><char style="wj">But that ye may know that the Son of man hath power on earth to forgive sins,</char> (he saith to the sick of the palsy,) <verse eid="MRK 2:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 2:11" /><char style="wj">I say unto thee, Arise, and take up thy bed, and go thy way into thine house.</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 2:12" />And immediately he arose, took up the bed, and went forth before them all; insomuch that they were all amazed, and glorified God, saying, We never saw it on this fashion. <verse eid="MRK 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 2:13" />And he went forth again by the sea side; and all the multitude resorted unto him, and he taught them. <verse eid="MRK 2:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 2:14" />And as he passed by, he saw Levi the <char style="add">son</char> of Alphæus sitting at the receipt of custom, and said unto him, <char style="wj">Follow me.</char> And he arose and followed him. <verse eid="MRK 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 2:15" />And it came to pass, that, as Jesus sat at meat in his house, many publicans and sinners sat also together with Jesus and his disciples: for there were many, and they followed him. <verse eid="MRK 2:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 2:16" />And when the scribes and Pharisees saw him eat with publicans and sinners, they said unto his disciples, How is it that he eateth and drinketh with publicans and sinners? <verse eid="MRK 2:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 2:17" />When Jesus heard <char style="add">it</char>, he saith unto them, <char style="wj">They that are whole have no need of the physician, but they that are sick: I came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance.</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 2:18" />And the disciples of John and of the Pharisees used to fast: and they come and say unto him, Why do the disciples of John and of the Pharisees fast, but thy disciples fast not? <verse eid="MRK 2:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 2:19" />And Jesus said unto them, <char style="wj">Can the children of the bridechamber fast, while the bridegroom is with them? as long as they have the bridegroom with them, they cannot fast.</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 2:20" /><char style="wj">But the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken away from them, and then shall they fast in those days.</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 2:21" /><char style="wj">No man also seweth a piece of new cloth on an old garment: else the new piece that filled it up taketh away from the old, and the rent is made worse.</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 2:22" /><char style="wj">And no man putteth new wine into old bottles: else the new wine doth burst the bottles, and the wine is spilled, and the bottles will be marred: but new wine must be put into new bottles.</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 2:23" />And it came to pass, that he went through the corn fields on the sabbath day; and his disciples began, as they went, to pluck the ears of corn. <verse eid="MRK 2:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 2:24" />And the Pharisees said unto him, Behold, why do they on the sabbath day that which is not lawful? <verse eid="MRK 2:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 2:25" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Have ye never read what David did, when he had need, and was an hungred, he, and they that were with him?</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 2:26" /><char style="wj">How he went into the house of God in the days of Abiathar the high priest, and did eat the shewbread, which is not lawful to eat but for the priests, and gave also to them which were with him?</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 2:27" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">The sabbath was made for man, and not man for the sabbath:</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 2:28" /><char style="wj">Therefore the Son of man is Lord also of the sabbath.</char><verse eid="MRK 2:28" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="MRK 3" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 3:1" />And he entered again into the synagogue; and there was a man there which had a withered hand. <verse eid="MRK 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 3:2" />And they watched him, whether he would heal him on the sabbath day; that they might accuse him. <verse eid="MRK 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 3:3" />And he saith unto the man which had the withered hand, <char style="wj">Stand forth.</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 3:4" />And he saith unto them, <char style="wj">Is it lawful to do good on the sabbath days, or to do evil? to save life, or to kill?</char> But they held their peace. <verse eid="MRK 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 3:5" />And when he had looked round about on them with anger, being grieved for the hardness of their hearts, he saith unto the man, <char style="wj">Stretch forth thine hand.</char> And he stretched <char style="add">it</char> out: and his hand was restored whole as the other. <verse eid="MRK 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 3:6" />And the Pharisees went forth, and straightway took counsel with the Herodians against him, how they might destroy him. <verse eid="MRK 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 3:7" />But Jesus withdrew himself with his disciples to the sea: and a great multitude from Galilee followed him, and from Judæa, <verse eid="MRK 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 3:8" />And from Jerusalem, and from Idumaea, and <char style="add">from</char> beyond Jordan; and they about Tyre and Sidon, a great multitude, when they had heard what great things he did, came unto him. <verse eid="MRK 3:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 3:9" />And he spake to his disciples, that a small ship should wait on him because of the multitude, lest they should throng him. <verse eid="MRK 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 3:10" />For he had healed many; insomuch that they pressed upon him for to touch him, as many as had plagues. <verse eid="MRK 3:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 3:11" />And unclean spirits, when they saw him, fell down before him, and cried, saying, Thou art the Son of God. <verse eid="MRK 3:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 3:12" />And he straitly charged them that they should not make him known. <verse eid="MRK 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 3:13" />And he goeth up into a mountain, and calleth <char style="add">unto him</char> whom he would: and they came unto him. <verse eid="MRK 3:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 3:14" />And he ordained twelve, that they should be with him, and that he might send them forth to preach, <verse eid="MRK 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 3:15" />And to have power to heal sicknesses, and to cast out devils: <verse eid="MRK 3:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 3:16" />And Simon he surnamed Peter; <verse eid="MRK 3:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 3:17" />And James the <char style="add">son</char> of Zebedee, and John the brother of James; and he surnamed them Boanerges, which is, The sons of thunder: <verse eid="MRK 3:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 3:18" />And Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James the <char style="add">son</char> of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus, and Simon the Canaanite, <verse eid="MRK 3:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 3:19" />And Judas Iscariot, which also betrayed him: and they went into an house. <verse eid="MRK 3:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 3:20" />And the multitude cometh together again, so that they could not so much as eat bread. <verse eid="MRK 3:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 3:21" />And when his friends heard <char style="add">of it</char>, they went out to lay hold on him: for they said, He is beside himself.<verse eid="MRK 3:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 3:22" />¶ And the scribes which came down from Jerusalem said, He hath Beelzebub, and by the prince of the devils casteth he out devils. <verse eid="MRK 3:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 3:23" />And he called them <char style="add">unto him</char>, and said unto them in parables, <char style="wj">How can Satan cast out Satan?</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 3:24" /><char style="wj">And if a kingdom be divided against itself, that kingdom cannot stand.</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 3:25" /><char style="wj">And if a house be divided against itself, that house cannot stand.</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 3:26" /><char style="wj">And if Satan rise up against himself, and be divided, he cannot stand, but hath an end.</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 3:27" /><char style="wj">No man can enter into a strong man’s house, and spoil his goods, except he will first bind the strong man; and then he will spoil his house.</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 3:28" /><char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, All sins shall be forgiven unto the sons of men, and blasphemies wherewith soever they shall blaspheme:</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 3:29" /><char style="wj">But he that shall blaspheme against the Holy Ghost hath never forgiveness, but is in danger of eternal damnation:</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 3:30" />Because they said, He hath an unclean spirit.<verse eid="MRK 3:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 3:31" />¶ There came then his brethren and his mother, and, standing without, sent unto him, calling him. <verse eid="MRK 3:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 3:32" />And the multitude sat about him, and they said unto him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren without seek for thee. <verse eid="MRK 3:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 3:33" />And he answered them, saying, <char style="wj">Who is my mother, or my brethren?</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 3:34" />And he looked round about on them which sat about him, and said, <char style="wj">Behold my mother and my brethren!</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 3:35" /><char style="wj">For whosoever shall do the will of God, the same is my brother, and my sister, and mother.</char><verse eid="MRK 3:35" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="MRK 4" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 4:1" />And he began again to teach by the sea side: and there was gathered unto him a great multitude, so that he entered into a ship, and sat in the sea; and the whole multitude was by the sea on the land. <verse eid="MRK 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 4:2" />And he taught them many things by parables, and said unto them in his doctrine, <verse eid="MRK 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 4:3" /><char style="wj">Hearken; Behold, there went out a sower to sow:</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 4:4" /><char style="wj">And it came to pass, as he sowed, some fell by the way side, and the fowls of the air came and devoured it up.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 4:5" /><char style="wj">And some fell on stony ground, where it had not much earth; and immediately it sprang up, because it had no depth of earth:</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 4:6" /><char style="wj">But when the sun was up, it was scorched; and because it had no root, it withered away.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 4:7" /><char style="wj">And some fell among thorns, and the thorns grew up, and choked it, and it yielded no fruit.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 4:8" /><char style="wj">And other fell on good ground, and did yield fruit that sprang up and increased; and brought forth, some thirty, and some sixty, and some an hundred.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 4:9" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 4:10" />And when he was alone, they that were about him with the twelve asked of him the parable. <verse eid="MRK 4:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 4:11" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Unto you it is given to know the mystery of the kingdom of God: but unto them that are without, all <char style="add">these</char> things are done in parables:</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 4:12" /><char style="wj">That seeing they may see, and not perceive; and hearing they may hear, and not understand; lest at any time they should be converted, and <char style="add">their</char> sins should be forgiven them.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 4:13" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Know ye not this parable? and how then will ye know all parables?</char><verse eid="MRK 4:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 4:14" />
    <char style="wj">¶ The sower soweth the word.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 4:15" /><char style="wj">And these are they by the way side, where the word is sown; but when they have heard, Satan cometh immediately, and taketh away the word that was sown in their hearts.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 4:16" /><char style="wj">And these are they likewise which are sown on stony ground; who, when they have heard the word, immediately receive it with gladness;</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 4:17" /><char style="wj">And have no root in themselves, and so endure but for a time: afterward, when affliction or persecution ariseth for the word’s sake, immediately they are offended.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 4:18" /><char style="wj">And these are they which are sown among thorns; such as hear the word,</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 4:19" /><char style="wj">And the cares of this world, and the deceitfulness of riches, and the lusts of other things entering in, choke the word, and it becometh unfruitful.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 4:20" /><char style="wj">And these are they which are sown on good ground; such as hear the word, and receive <char style="add">it</char>, and bring forth fruit, some thirtyfold, some sixty, and some an hundred.</char><verse eid="MRK 4:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 4:21" />¶ And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Is a candle brought to be put under a bushel, or under a bed? and not to be set on a candlestick?</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 4:22" /><char style="wj">For there is nothing hid, which shall not be manifested; neither was any thing kept secret, but that it should come abroad.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 4:23" /><char style="wj">If any man have ears to hear, let him hear.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 4:24" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Take heed what ye hear: with what measure ye mete, it shall be measured to you: and unto you that hear shall more be given.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 4:25" /><char style="wj">For he that hath, to him shall be given: and he that hath not, from him shall be taken even that which he hath.</char><verse eid="MRK 4:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 4:26" />¶ And he said, <char style="wj">So is the kingdom of God, as if a man should cast seed into the ground;</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 4:27" /><char style="wj">And should sleep, and rise night and day, and the seed should spring and grow up, he knoweth not how.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 4:28" /><char style="wj">For the earth bringeth forth fruit of herself; first the blade, then the ear, after that the full corn in the ear.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 4:29" /><char style="wj">But when the fruit is brought forth, immediately he putteth in the sickle, because the harvest is come.</char><verse eid="MRK 4:29" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 4:30" />¶ And he said, <char style="wj">Whereunto shall we liken the kingdom of God? or with what comparison shall we compare it?</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 4:31" /><char style="wj"><char style="add">It is</char> like a grain of mustard seed, which, when it is sown in the earth, is less than all the seeds that be in the earth:</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 4:32" /><char style="wj">But when it is sown, it groweth up, and becometh greater than all herbs, and shooteth out great branches; so that the fowls of the air may lodge under the shadow of it.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 4:33" />And with many such parables spake he the word unto them, as they were able to hear <char style="add">it</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 4:34" />But without a parable spake he not unto them: and when they were alone, he expounded all things to his disciples. <verse eid="MRK 4:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 4:35" />And the same day, when the even was come, he saith unto them, <char style="wj">Let us pass over unto the other side.</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 4:36" />And when they had sent away the multitude, they took him even as he was in the ship. And there were also with him other little ships. <verse eid="MRK 4:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 4:37" />And there arose a great storm of wind, and the waves beat into the ship, so that it was now full. <verse eid="MRK 4:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 4:38" />And he was in the hinder part of the ship, asleep on a pillow: and they awake him, and say unto him, Master, carest thou not that we perish? <verse eid="MRK 4:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 4:39" />And he arose, and rebuked the wind, and said unto the sea, <char style="wj">Peace, be still.</char> And the wind ceased, and there was a great calm. <verse eid="MRK 4:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 4:40" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Why are ye so fearful? how is it that ye have no faith?</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 4:41" />And they feared exceedingly, and said one to another, What manner of man is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?<verse eid="MRK 4:41" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="MRK 5" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 5:1" />And they came over unto the other side of the sea, into the country of the Gadarenes. <verse eid="MRK 5:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 5:2" />And when he was come out of the ship, immediately there met him out of the tombs a man with an unclean spirit, <verse eid="MRK 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 5:3" />Who had <char style="add">his</char> dwelling among the tombs; and no man could bind him, no, not with chains: <verse eid="MRK 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 5:4" />Because that he had been often bound with fetters and chains, and the chains had been plucked asunder by him, and the fetters broken in pieces: neither could any <char style="add">man</char> tame him. <verse eid="MRK 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 5:5" />And always, night and day, he was in the mountains, and in the tombs, crying, and cutting himself with stones. <verse eid="MRK 5:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 5:6" />But when he saw Jesus afar off, he ran and worshipped him, <verse eid="MRK 5:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 5:7" />And cried with a loud voice, and said, What have I to do with thee, Jesus, <char style="add">thou</char> Son of the most high God? I adjure thee by God, that thou torment me not. <verse eid="MRK 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 5:8" />For he said unto him, <char style="wj">Come out of the man, <char style="add">thou</char> unclean spirit.</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 5:9" />And he asked him, <char style="wj">What <char style="add">is</char> thy name?</char> And he answered, saying, My name <char style="add">is</char> Legion: for we are many. <verse eid="MRK 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 5:10" />And he besought him much that he would not send them away out of the country. <verse eid="MRK 5:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 5:11" />Now there was there nigh unto the mountains a great herd of swine feeding. <verse eid="MRK 5:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 5:12" />And all the devils besought him, saying, Send us into the swine, that we may enter into them. <verse eid="MRK 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 5:13" />And forthwith Jesus gave them leave. And the unclean spirits went out, and entered into the swine: and the herd ran violently down a steep place into the sea, (they were about two thousand;) and were choked in the sea. <verse eid="MRK 5:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 5:14" />And they that fed the swine fled, and told <char style="add">it</char> in the city, and in the country. And they went out to see what it was that was done. <verse eid="MRK 5:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 5:15" />And they come to Jesus, and see him that was possessed with the devil, and had the legion, sitting, and clothed, and in his right mind: and they were afraid. <verse eid="MRK 5:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 5:16" />And they that saw <char style="add">it</char> told them how it befell to him that was possessed with the devil, and <char style="add">also</char> concerning the swine. <verse eid="MRK 5:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 5:17" />And they began to pray him to depart out of their coasts. <verse eid="MRK 5:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 5:18" />And when he was come into the ship, he that had been possessed with the devil prayed him that he might be with him. <verse eid="MRK 5:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 5:19" />Howbeit Jesus suffered him not, but saith unto him, <char style="wj">Go home to thy friends, and tell them how great things the Lord hath done for thee, and hath had compassion on thee.</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 5:20" />And he departed, and began to publish in Decapolis how great things Jesus had done for him: and all <char style="add">men</char> did marvel. <verse eid="MRK 5:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 5:21" />And when Jesus was passed over again by ship unto the other side, much people gathered unto him: and he was nigh unto the sea. <verse eid="MRK 5:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 5:22" />And, behold, there cometh one of the rulers of the synagogue, Jairus by name; and when he saw him, he fell at his feet, <verse eid="MRK 5:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 5:23" />And besought him greatly, saying, My little daughter lieth at the point of death: <char style="add">I pray thee</char>, come and lay thy hands on her, that she may be healed; and she shall live. <verse eid="MRK 5:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 5:24" />And <char style="add">Jesus</char> went with him; and much people followed him, and thronged him. <verse eid="MRK 5:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 5:25" />And a certain woman, which had an issue of blood twelve years, <verse eid="MRK 5:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 5:26" />And had suffered many things of many physicians, and had spent all that she had, and was nothing bettered, but rather grew worse, <verse eid="MRK 5:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 5:27" />When she had heard of Jesus, came in the press behind, and touched his garment. <verse eid="MRK 5:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 5:28" />For she said, If I may touch but his clothes, I shall be whole. <verse eid="MRK 5:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 5:29" />And straightway the fountain of her blood was dried up; and she felt in her body that she was healed of that plague. <verse eid="MRK 5:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 5:30" />And Jesus, immediately knowing in himself that virtue had gone out of him, turned him about in the press, and said, <char style="wj">Who touched my clothes?</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 5:31" />And his disciples said unto him, Thou seest the multitude thronging thee, and sayest thou, Who touched me? <verse eid="MRK 5:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 5:32" />And he looked round about to see her that had done this thing. <verse eid="MRK 5:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 5:33" />But the woman fearing and trembling, knowing what was done in her, came and fell down before him, and told him all the truth. <verse eid="MRK 5:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 5:34" />And he said unto her, <char style="wj">Daughter, thy faith hath made thee whole; go in peace, and be whole of thy plague.</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 5:35" />While he yet spake, there came from the ruler of the synagogue’s <char style="add">house certain</char> which said, Thy daughter is dead: why troublest thou the Master any further? <verse eid="MRK 5:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 5:36" />As soon as Jesus heard the word that was spoken, he saith unto the ruler of the synagogue, <char style="wj">Be not afraid, only believe.</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 5:37" />And he suffered no man to follow him, save Peter, and James, and John the brother of James. <verse eid="MRK 5:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 5:38" />And he cometh to the house of the ruler of the synagogue, and seeth the tumult, and them that wept and wailed greatly. <verse eid="MRK 5:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 5:39" />And when he was come in, he saith unto them, <char style="wj">Why make ye this ado, and weep? the damsel is not dead, but sleepeth.</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 5:40" />And they laughed him to scorn. But when he had put them all out, he taketh the father and the mother of the damsel, and them that were with him, and entereth in where the damsel was lying. <verse eid="MRK 5:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 5:41" />And he took the damsel by the hand, and said unto her, <char style="wj">Talitha cumi;</char> which is, being interpreted, Damsel, I say unto thee, arise. <verse eid="MRK 5:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 5:42" />And straightway the damsel arose, and walked; for she was <char style="add">of the age</char> of twelve years. And they were astonished with a great astonishment. <verse eid="MRK 5:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 5:43" />And he charged them straitly that no man should know it; and commanded that something should be given her to eat.<verse eid="MRK 5:43" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 5" />
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="MRK 6" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 6:1" />And he went out from thence, and came into his own country; and his disciples follow him. <verse eid="MRK 6:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 6:2" />And when the sabbath day was come, he began to teach in the synagogue: and many hearing <char style="add">him</char> were astonished, saying, From whence hath this <char style="add">man</char> these things? and what wisdom <char style="add">is</char> this which is given unto him, that even such mighty works are wrought by his hands? <verse eid="MRK 6:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 6:3" />Is not this the carpenter, the son of Mary, the brother of James, and Joses, and of Juda, and Simon? and are not his sisters here with us? And they were offended at him. <verse eid="MRK 6:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 6:4" />But Jesus said unto them, <char style="wj">A prophet is not without honour, but in his own country, and among his own kin, and in his own house.</char> <verse eid="MRK 6:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 6:5" />And he could there do no mighty work, save that he laid his hands upon a few sick folk, and healed <char style="add">them</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 6:6" />And he marvelled because of their unbelief. And he went round about the villages, teaching.<verse eid="MRK 6:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 6:7" />¶ And he called <char style="add">unto him</char> the twelve, and began to send them forth by two and two; and gave them power over unclean spirits; <verse eid="MRK 6:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 6:8" />And commanded them that they should take nothing for <char style="add">their</char> journey, save a staff only; no scrip, no bread, no money in <char style="add">their</char> purse: <verse eid="MRK 6:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 6:9" />But <char style="add">be</char> shod with sandals; and not put on two coats. <verse eid="MRK 6:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 6:10" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">In what place soever ye enter into an house, there abide till ye depart from that place.</char> <verse eid="MRK 6:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 6:11" /><char style="wj">And whosoever shall not receive you, nor hear you, when ye depart thence, shake off the dust under your feet for a testimony against them. Verily I say unto you, It shall be more tolerable for Sodom and Gomorrha in the day of judgment, than for that city.</char> <verse eid="MRK 6:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 6:12" />And they went out, and preached that men should repent. <verse eid="MRK 6:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 6:13" />And they cast out many devils, and anointed with oil many that were sick, and healed <char style="add">them</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 6:14" />And king Herod heard <char style="add">of him</char>; (for his name was spread abroad:) and he said, That John the Baptist was risen from the dead, and therefore mighty works do shew forth themselves in him. <verse eid="MRK 6:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 6:15" />Others said, That it is Elias. And others said, That it is a prophet, or as one of the prophets. <verse eid="MRK 6:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 6:16" />But when Herod heard <char style="add">thereof</char>, he said, It is John, whom I beheaded: he is risen from the dead. <verse eid="MRK 6:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 6:17" />For Herod himself had sent forth and laid hold upon John, and bound him in prison for Herodias’ sake, his brother Philip’s wife: for he had married her. <verse eid="MRK 6:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 6:18" />For John had said unto Herod, It is not lawful for thee to have thy brother’s wife. <verse eid="MRK 6:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 6:19" />Therefore Herodias had a quarrel against him, and would have killed him; but she could not: <verse eid="MRK 6:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 6:20" />For Herod feared John, knowing that he was a just man and an holy, and observed him; and when he heard him, he did many things, and heard him gladly. <verse eid="MRK 6:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 6:21" />And when a convenient day was come, that Herod on his birthday made a supper to his lords, high captains, and chief <char style="add">estates</char> of Galilee; <verse eid="MRK 6:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 6:22" />And when the daughter of the said Herodias came in, and danced, and pleased Herod and them that sat with him, the king said unto the damsel, Ask of me whatsoever thou wilt, and I will give <char style="add">it</char> thee. <verse eid="MRK 6:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 6:23" />And he sware unto her, Whatsoever thou shalt ask of me, I will give <char style="add">it</char> thee, unto the half of my kingdom. <verse eid="MRK 6:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 6:24" />And she went forth, and said unto her mother, What shall I ask? And she said, The head of John the Baptist. <verse eid="MRK 6:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 6:25" />And she came in straightway with haste unto the king, and asked, saying, I will that thou give me by and by in a charger the head of John the Baptist. <verse eid="MRK 6:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 6:26" />And the king was exceeding sorry; <char style="add">yet</char> for his oath’s sake, and for their sakes which sat with him, he would not reject her. <verse eid="MRK 6:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 6:27" />And immediately the king sent an executioner, and commanded his head to be brought: and he went and beheaded him in the prison, <verse eid="MRK 6:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 6:28" />And brought his head in a charger, and gave it to the damsel: and the damsel gave it to her mother. <verse eid="MRK 6:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 6:29" />And when his disciples heard <char style="add">of it</char>, they came and took up his corpse, and laid it in a tomb. <verse eid="MRK 6:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 6:30" />And the apostles gathered themselves together unto Jesus, and told him all things, both what they had done, and what they had taught. <verse eid="MRK 6:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 6:31" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Come ye yourselves apart into a desert place, and rest a while:</char> for there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure so much as to eat. <verse eid="MRK 6:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 6:32" />And they departed into a desert place by ship privately. <verse eid="MRK 6:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 6:33" />And the people saw them departing, and many knew him, and ran afoot thither out of all cities, and outwent them, and came together unto him. <verse eid="MRK 6:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 6:34" />And Jesus, when he came out, saw much people, and was moved with compassion toward them, because they were as sheep not having a shepherd: and he began to teach them many things. <verse eid="MRK 6:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 6:35" />And when the day was now far spent, his disciples came unto him, and said, This is a desert place, and now the time <char style="add">is</char> far passed: <verse eid="MRK 6:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 6:36" />Send them away, that they may go into the country round about, and into the villages, and buy themselves bread: for they have nothing to eat. <verse eid="MRK 6:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 6:37" />He answered and said unto them, <char style="wj">Give ye them to eat.</char> And they say unto him, Shall we go and buy two hundred pennyworth of bread, and give them to eat? <verse eid="MRK 6:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 6:38" />He saith unto them, <char style="wj">How many loaves have ye? go and see.</char> And when they knew, they say, Five, and two fishes. <verse eid="MRK 6:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 6:39" />And he commanded them to make all sit down by companies upon the green grass. <verse eid="MRK 6:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 6:40" />And they sat down in ranks, by hundreds, and by fifties. <verse eid="MRK 6:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 6:41" />And when he had taken the five loaves and the two fishes, he looked up to heaven, and blessed, and brake the loaves, and gave <char style="add">them</char> to his disciples to set before them; and the two fishes divided he among them all. <verse eid="MRK 6:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 6:42" />And they did all eat, and were filled. <verse eid="MRK 6:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 6:43" />And they took up twelve baskets full of the fragments, and of the fishes. <verse eid="MRK 6:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 6:44" />And they that did eat of the loaves were about five thousand men. <verse eid="MRK 6:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 6:45" />And straightway he constrained his disciples to get into the ship, and to go to the other side before unto Bethsaida, while he sent away the people. <verse eid="MRK 6:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 6:46" />And when he had sent them away, he departed into a mountain to pray. <verse eid="MRK 6:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 6:47" />And when even was come, the ship was in the midst of the sea, and he alone on the land. <verse eid="MRK 6:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 6:48" />And he saw them toiling in rowing; for the wind was contrary unto them: and about the fourth watch of the night he cometh unto them, walking upon the sea, and would have passed by them. <verse eid="MRK 6:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 6:49" />But when they saw him walking upon the sea, they supposed it had been a spirit, and cried out: <verse eid="MRK 6:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 6:50" />For they all saw him, and were troubled. And immediately he talked with them, and saith unto them, <char style="wj">Be of good cheer: it is I; be not afraid.</char> <verse eid="MRK 6:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 6:51" />And he went up unto them into the ship; and the wind ceased: and they were sore amazed in themselves beyond measure, and wondered. <verse eid="MRK 6:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 6:52" />For they considered not <char style="add">the miracle</char> of the loaves: for their heart was hardened. <verse eid="MRK 6:52" /><verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 6:53" />And when they had passed over, they came into the land of Gennesaret, and drew to the shore. <verse eid="MRK 6:53" /><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 6:54" />And when they were come out of the ship, straightway they knew him, <verse eid="MRK 6:54" /><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 6:55" />And ran through that whole region round about, and began to carry about in beds those that were sick, where they heard he was. <verse eid="MRK 6:55" /><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 6:56" />And whithersoever he entered, into villages, or cities, or country, they laid the sick in the streets, and besought him that they might touch if it were but the border of his garment: and as many as touched him were made whole.<verse eid="MRK 6:56" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 6" />
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="MRK 7" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 7:1" />Then came together unto him the Pharisees, and certain of the scribes, which came from Jerusalem. <verse eid="MRK 7:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 7:2" />And when they saw some of his disciples eat bread with defiled, that is to say, with unwashen, hands, they found fault. <verse eid="MRK 7:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 7:3" />For the Pharisees, and all the Jews, except they wash <char style="add">their</char> hands oft, eat not, holding the tradition of the elders. <verse eid="MRK 7:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 7:4" />And <char style="add">when they come</char> from the market, except they wash, they eat not. And many other things there be, which they have received to hold, <char style="add">as</char> the washing of cups, and pots, brasen vessels, and of tables. <verse eid="MRK 7:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 7:5" />Then the Pharisees and scribes asked him, Why walk not thy disciples according to the tradition of the elders, but eat bread with unwashen hands? <verse eid="MRK 7:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 7:6" />He answered and said unto them, <char style="wj">Well hath Esaias prophesied of you hypocrites, as it is written, This people honoureth me with <char style="add">their</char> lips, but their heart is far from me.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 7:7" /><char style="wj">Howbeit in vain do they worship me, teaching <char style="add">for</char> doctrines the commandments of men.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 7:8" /><char style="wj">For laying aside the commandment of God, ye hold the tradition of men, <char style="add">as</char> the washing of pots and cups: and many other such like things ye do.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 7:9" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Full well ye reject the commandment of God, that ye may keep your own tradition.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 7:10" /><char style="wj">For Moses said, Honour thy father and thy mother; and, Whoso curseth father or mother, let him die the death:</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 7:11" /><char style="wj">But ye say, If a man shall say to his father or mother, <char style="add">It is</char> Corban, that is to say, a gift, by whatsoever thou mightest be profited by me; <char style="add">he shall be free</char>.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 7:12" /><char style="wj">And ye suffer him no more to do ought for his father or his mother;</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 7:13" /><char style="wj">Making the word of God of none effect through your tradition, which ye have delivered: and many such like things do ye.</char><verse eid="MRK 7:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 7:14" />¶ And when he had called all the people <char style="add">unto him</char>, he said unto them, <char style="wj">Hearken unto me every one <char style="add">of you</char>, and understand:</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 7:15" /><char style="wj">There is nothing from without a man, that entering into him can defile him: but the things which come out of him, those are they that defile the man.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 7:16" /><char style="wj">If any man have ears to hear, let him hear.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 7:17" />And when he was entered into the house from the people, his disciples asked him concerning the parable. <verse eid="MRK 7:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 7:18" />And he saith unto them, <char style="wj">Are ye so without understanding also? Do ye not perceive, that whatsoever thing from without entereth into the man, <char style="add">it</char> cannot defile him;</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 7:19" /><char style="wj">Because it entereth not into his heart, but into the belly, and goeth out into the draught, purging all meats?</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 7:20" />And he said, <char style="wj">That which cometh out of the man, that defileth the man.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 7:21" /><char style="wj">For from within, out of the heart of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murders,</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 7:22" /><char style="wj">Thefts, covetousness, wickedness, deceit, lasciviousness, an evil eye, blasphemy, pride, foolishness:</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 7:23" /><char style="wj">All these evil things come from within, and defile the man.</char><verse eid="MRK 7:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 7:24" />¶ And from thence he arose, and went into the borders of Tyre and Sidon, and entered into an house, and would have no man know <char style="add">it</char>: but he could not be hid. <verse eid="MRK 7:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 7:25" />For a <char style="add">certain</char> woman, whose young daughter had an unclean spirit, heard of him, and came and fell at his feet: <verse eid="MRK 7:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 7:26" />The woman was a Greek, a Syrophenician by nation; and she besought him that he would cast forth the devil out of her daughter. <verse eid="MRK 7:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 7:27" />But Jesus said unto her, <char style="wj">Let the children first be filled: for it is not meet to take the children’s bread, and to cast <char style="add">it</char> unto the dogs.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 7:28" />And she answered and said unto him, Yes, Lord: yet the dogs under the table eat of the children’s crumbs. <verse eid="MRK 7:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 7:29" />And he said unto her, <char style="wj">For this saying go thy way; the devil is gone out of thy daughter.</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 7:30" />And when she was come to her house, she found the devil gone out, and her daughter laid upon the bed.<verse eid="MRK 7:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 7:31" />¶ And again, departing from the coasts of Tyre and Sidon, he came unto the sea of Galilee, through the midst of the coasts of Decapolis. <verse eid="MRK 7:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 7:32" />And they bring unto him one that was deaf, and had an impediment in his speech; and they beseech him to put his hand upon him. <verse eid="MRK 7:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 7:33" />And he took him aside from the multitude, and put his fingers into his ears, and he spit, and touched his tongue; <verse eid="MRK 7:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 7:34" />And looking up to heaven, he sighed, and saith unto him, <char style="wj">Ephphatha,</char> that is, Be opened. <verse eid="MRK 7:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 7:35" />And straightway his ears were opened, and the string of his tongue was loosed, and he spake plain. <verse eid="MRK 7:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 7:36" />And he charged them that they should tell no man: but the more he charged them, so much the more a great deal they published <char style="add">it</char>; <verse eid="MRK 7:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 7:37" />And were beyond measure astonished, saying, He hath done all things well: he maketh both the deaf to hear, and the dumb to speak.<verse eid="MRK 7:37" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 7" />
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="MRK 8" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 8:1" />In those days the multitude being very great, and having nothing to eat, Jesus called his disciples <char style="add">unto him</char>, and saith unto them, <verse eid="MRK 8:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 8:2" /><char style="wj">I have compassion on the multitude, because they have now been with me three days, and have nothing to eat:</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 8:3" /><char style="wj">And if I send them away fasting to their own houses, they will faint by the way: for divers of them came from far.</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 8:4" />And his disciples answered him, From whence can a man satisfy these <char style="add">men</char> with bread here in the wilderness? <verse eid="MRK 8:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 8:5" />And he asked them, <char style="wj">How many loaves have ye?</char> And they said, Seven. <verse eid="MRK 8:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 8:6" />And he commanded the people to sit down on the ground: and he took the seven loaves, and gave thanks, and brake, and gave to his disciples to set before <char style="add">them</char>; and they did set <char style="add">them</char> before the people. <verse eid="MRK 8:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 8:7" />And they had a few small fishes: and he blessed, and commanded to set them also before <char style="add">them</char>. <verse eid="MRK 8:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 8:8" />So they did eat, and were filled: and they took up of the broken <char style="add">meat</char> that was left seven baskets. <verse eid="MRK 8:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 8:9" />And they that had eaten were about four thousand: and he sent them away.<verse eid="MRK 8:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 8:10" />¶ And straightway he entered into a ship with his disciples, and came into the parts of Dalmanutha. <verse eid="MRK 8:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 8:11" />And the Pharisees came forth, and began to question with him, seeking of him a sign from heaven, tempting him. <verse eid="MRK 8:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 8:12" />And he sighed deeply in his spirit, and saith, <char style="wj">Why doth this generation seek after a sign? verily I say unto you, There shall no sign be given unto this generation.</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 8:13" />And he left them, and entering into the ship again departed to the other side.<verse eid="MRK 8:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 8:14" />¶ Now <char style="add">the disciples</char> had forgotten to take bread, neither had they in the ship with them more than one loaf. <verse eid="MRK 8:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 8:15" />And he charged them, saying, <char style="wj">Take heed, beware of the leaven of the Pharisees, and <char style="add">of</char> the leaven of Herod.</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 8:16" />And they reasoned among themselves, saying, <char style="add">It is</char> because we have no bread. <verse eid="MRK 8:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 8:17" />And when Jesus knew <char style="add">it</char>, he saith unto them, <char style="wj">Why reason ye, because ye have no bread? perceive ye not yet, neither understand? have ye your heart yet hardened?</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 8:18" /><char style="wj">Having eyes, see ye not? and having ears, hear ye not? and do ye not remember?</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 8:19" /><char style="wj">When I brake the five loaves among five thousand, how many baskets full of fragments took ye up?</char> They say unto him, Twelve. <verse eid="MRK 8:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 8:20" /><char style="wj">And when the seven among four thousand, how many baskets full of fragments took ye up?</char> And they said, Seven. <verse eid="MRK 8:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 8:21" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">How is it that ye do not understand?</char><verse eid="MRK 8:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 8:22" />¶ And he cometh to Bethsaida; and they bring a blind man unto him, and besought him to touch him. <verse eid="MRK 8:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 8:23" />And he took the blind man by the hand, and led him out of the town; and when he had spit on his eyes, and put his hands upon him, he asked him if he saw ought. <verse eid="MRK 8:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 8:24" />And he looked up, and said, I see men as trees, walking. <verse eid="MRK 8:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 8:25" />After that he put <char style="add">his</char> hands again upon his eyes, and made him look up: and he was restored, and saw every man clearly. <verse eid="MRK 8:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 8:26" />And he sent him away to his house, saying, <char style="wj">Neither go into the town, nor tell <char style="add">it</char> to any in the town.</char><verse eid="MRK 8:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 8:27" />¶ And Jesus went out, and his disciples, into the towns of Cæsarea Philippi: and by the way he asked his disciples, saying unto them, <char style="wj">Whom do men say that I am?</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 8:28" />And they answered, John the Baptist: but some <char style="add">say</char>, Elias; and others, One of the prophets. <verse eid="MRK 8:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 8:29" />And he saith unto them, <char style="wj">But whom say ye that I am?</char> And Peter answereth and saith unto him, Thou art the Christ. <verse eid="MRK 8:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 8:30" />And he charged them that they should tell no man of him. <verse eid="MRK 8:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 8:31" />And he began to teach them, that the Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected of the elders, and <char style="add">of</char> the chief priests, and scribes, and be killed, and after three days rise again. <verse eid="MRK 8:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 8:32" />And he spake that saying openly. And Peter took him, and began to rebuke him. <verse eid="MRK 8:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 8:33" />But when he had turned about and looked on his disciples, he rebuked Peter, saying, <char style="wj">Get thee behind me, Satan: for thou savourest not the things that be of God, but the things that be of men.</char><verse eid="MRK 8:33" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 8:34" />¶ And when he had called the people <char style="add">unto him</char> with his disciples also, he said unto them, <char style="wj">Whosoever will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 8:35" /><char style="wj">For whosoever will save his life shall lose it; but whosoever shall lose his life for my sake and the gospel’s, the same shall save it.</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 8:36" /><char style="wj">For what shall it profit a man, if he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul?</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 8:37" /><char style="wj">Or what shall a man give in exchange for his soul?</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 8:38" /><char style="wj">Whosoever therefore shall be ashamed of me and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation; of him also shall the Son of man be ashamed, when he cometh in the glory of his Father with the holy angels.</char><verse eid="MRK 8:38" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 8" />
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="MRK 9" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 9:1" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, That there be some of them that stand here, which shall not taste of death, till they have seen the kingdom of God come with power.</char><verse eid="MRK 9:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 9:2" />¶ And after six days Jesus taketh <char style="add">with him</char> Peter, and James, and John, and leadeth them up into an high mountain apart by themselves: and he was transfigured before them. <verse eid="MRK 9:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 9:3" />And his raiment became shining, exceeding white as snow; so as no fuller on earth can white them. <verse eid="MRK 9:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 9:4" />And there appeared unto them Elias with Moses: and they were talking with Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 9:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 9:5" />And Peter answered and said to Jesus, Master, it is good for us to be here: and let us make three tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias. <verse eid="MRK 9:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 9:6" />For he wist not what to say; for they were sore afraid. <verse eid="MRK 9:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 9:7" />And there was a cloud that overshadowed them: and a voice came out of the cloud, saying, This is my beloved Son: hear him. <verse eid="MRK 9:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 9:8" />And suddenly, when they had looked round about, they saw no man any more, save Jesus only with themselves. <verse eid="MRK 9:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 9:9" />And as they came down from the mountain, he charged them that they should tell no man what things they had seen, till the Son of man were risen from the dead. <verse eid="MRK 9:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 9:10" />And they kept that saying with themselves, questioning one with another what the rising from the dead should mean.<verse eid="MRK 9:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 9:11" />¶ And they asked him, saying, Why say the scribes that Elias must first come? <verse eid="MRK 9:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 9:12" />And he answered and told them, <char style="wj">Elias verily cometh first, and restoreth all things; and how it is written of the Son of man, that he must suffer many things, and be set at nought.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 9:13" /><char style="wj">But I say unto you, That Elias is indeed come, and they have done unto him whatsoever they listed, as it is written of him.</char><verse eid="MRK 9:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 9:14" />¶ And when he came to <char style="add">his</char> disciples, he saw a great multitude about them, and the scribes questioning with them. <verse eid="MRK 9:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 9:15" />And straightway all the people, when they beheld him, were greatly amazed, and running to <char style="add">him</char> saluted him. <verse eid="MRK 9:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 9:16" />And he asked the scribes, <char style="wj">What question ye with them?</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 9:17" />And one of the multitude answered and said, Master, I have brought unto thee my son, which hath a dumb spirit; <verse eid="MRK 9:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 9:18" />And wheresoever he taketh him, he teareth him: and he foameth, and gnasheth with his teeth, and pineth away: and I spake to thy disciples that they should cast him out; and they could not. <verse eid="MRK 9:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 9:19" />He answereth him, and saith, <char style="wj">O faithless generation, how long shall I be with you? how long shall I suffer you? bring him unto me.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 9:20" />And they brought him unto him: and when he saw him, straightway the spirit tare him; and he fell on the ground, and wallowed foaming. <verse eid="MRK 9:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 9:21" />And he asked his father, <char style="wj">How long is it ago since this came unto him?</char> And he said, Of a child. <verse eid="MRK 9:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 9:22" />And ofttimes it hath cast him into the fire, and into the waters, to destroy him: but if thou canst do any thing, have compassion on us, and help us. <verse eid="MRK 9:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 9:23" />Jesus said unto him, <char style="wj">If thou canst believe, all things <char style="add">are</char> possible to him that believeth.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 9:24" />And straightway the father of the child cried out, and said with tears, Lord, I believe; help thou mine unbelief. <verse eid="MRK 9:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 9:25" />When Jesus saw that the people came running together, he rebuked the foul spirit, saying unto him, <char style="wj"><char style="add">Thou</char> dumb and deaf spirit, I charge thee, come out of him, and enter no more into him.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 9:26" />And <char style="add">the spirit</char> cried, and rent him sore, and came out of him: and he was as one dead; insomuch that many said, He is dead. <verse eid="MRK 9:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 9:27" />But Jesus took him by the hand, and lifted him up; and he arose. <verse eid="MRK 9:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 9:28" />And when he was come into the house, his disciples asked him privately, Why could not we cast him out? <verse eid="MRK 9:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 9:29" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">This kind can come forth by nothing, but by prayer and fasting.</char><verse eid="MRK 9:29" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 9:30" />¶ And they departed thence, and passed through Galilee; and he would not that any man should know <char style="add">it</char>. <verse eid="MRK 9:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 9:31" />For he taught his disciples, and said unto them, <char style="wj">The Son of man is delivered into the hands of men, and they shall kill him; and after that he is killed, he shall rise the third day.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 9:32" />But they understood not that saying, and were afraid to ask him.<verse eid="MRK 9:32" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 9:33" />¶ And he came to Capernaum: and being in the house he asked them, <char style="wj">What was it that ye disputed among yourselves by the way?</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 9:34" />But they held their peace: for by the way they had disputed among themselves, who <char style="add">should be</char> the greatest. <verse eid="MRK 9:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 9:35" />And he sat down, and called the twelve, and saith unto them, <char style="wj">If any man desire to be first, <char style="add">the same</char> shall be last of all, and servant of all.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 9:36" />And he took a child, and set him in the midst of them: and when he had taken him in his arms, he said unto them, <verse eid="MRK 9:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 9:37" /><char style="wj">Whosoever shall receive one of such children in my name, receiveth me: and whosoever shall receive me, receiveth not me, but him that sent me.</char><verse eid="MRK 9:37" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 9:38" />¶ And John answered him, saying, Master, we saw one casting out devils in thy name, and he followeth not us: and we forbad him, because he followeth not us. <verse eid="MRK 9:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 9:39" />But Jesus said, <char style="wj">Forbid him not: for there is no man which shall do a miracle in my name, that can lightly speak evil of me.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 9:40" /><char style="wj">For he that is not against us is on our part.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 9:41" /><char style="wj">For whosoever shall give you a cup of water to drink in my name, because ye belong to Christ, verily I say unto you, he shall not lose his reward.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 9:42" /><char style="wj">And whosoever shall offend one of <char style="add">these</char> little ones that believe in me, it is better for him that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and he were cast into the sea.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 9:43" /><char style="wj">And if thy hand offend thee, cut it off: it is better for thee to enter into life maimed, than having two hands to go into hell, into the fire that never shall be quenched:</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 9:44" /><char style="wj">Where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 9:45" /><char style="wj">And if thy foot offend thee, cut it off: it is better for thee to enter halt into life, than having two feet to be cast into hell, into the fire that never shall be quenched:</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 9:46" /><char style="wj">Where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 9:47" /><char style="wj">And if thine eye offend thee, pluck it out: it is better for thee to enter into the kingdom of God with one eye, than having two eyes to be cast into hell fire:</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 9:48" /><char style="wj">Where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 9:49" /><char style="wj">For every one shall be salted with fire, and every sacrifice shall be salted with salt.</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 9:50" /><char style="wj">Salt <char style="add">is</char> good: but if the salt have lost his saltness, wherewith will ye season it? Have salt in yourselves, and have peace one with another.</char><verse eid="MRK 9:50" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 9" />
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="MRK 10" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 10:1" />And he arose from thence, and cometh into the coasts of Judæa by the farther side of Jordan: and the people resort unto him again; and, as he was wont, he taught them again.<verse eid="MRK 10:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 10:2" />¶ And the Pharisees came to him, and asked him, Is it lawful for a man to put away <char style="add">his</char> wife? tempting him. <verse eid="MRK 10:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 10:3" />And he answered and said unto them, <char style="wj">What did Moses command you?</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 10:4" />And they said, Moses suffered to write a bill of divorcement, and to put her away. <verse eid="MRK 10:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 10:5" />And Jesus answered and said unto them, <char style="wj">For the hardness of your heart he wrote you this precept.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 10:6" /><char style="wj">But from the beginning of the creation God made them male and female.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 10:7" /><char style="wj">For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and cleave to his wife;</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 10:8" /><char style="wj">And they twain shall be one flesh: so then they are no more twain, but one flesh.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 10:9" /><char style="wj">What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 10:10" />And in the house his disciples asked him again of the same <char style="add">matter</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 10:11" />And he saith unto them, <char style="wj">Whosoever shall put away his wife, and marry another, committeth adultery against her.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 10:12" /><char style="wj">And if a woman shall put away her husband, and be married to another, she committeth adultery.</char><verse eid="MRK 10:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 10:13" />¶ And they brought young children to him, that he should touch them: and <char style="add">his</char> disciples rebuked those that brought <char style="add">them</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 10:14" />But when Jesus saw <char style="add">it</char>, he was much displeased, and said unto them, <char style="wj">Suffer the little children to come unto me, and forbid them not: for of such is the kingdom of God.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 10:15" /><char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, Whosoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child, he shall not enter therein.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 10:16" />And he took them up in his arms, put <char style="add">his</char> hands upon them, and blessed them.<verse eid="MRK 10:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 10:17" />¶ And when he was gone forth into the way, there came one running, and kneeled to him, and asked him, Good Master, what shall I do that I may inherit eternal life? <verse eid="MRK 10:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 10:18" />And Jesus said unto him, <char style="wj">Why callest thou me good? <char style="add">there is</char> none good but one, <char style="add">that is</char>, God.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 10:19" /><char style="wj">Thou knowest the commandments, Do not commit adultery, Do not kill, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Defraud not, Honour thy father and mother.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 10:20" />And he answered and said unto him, Master, all these have I observed from my youth. <verse eid="MRK 10:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 10:21" />Then Jesus beholding him loved him, and said unto him, <char style="wj">One thing thou lackest: go thy way, sell whatsoever thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come, take up the cross, and follow me.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 10:22" />And he was sad at that saying, and went away grieved: for he had great possessions.<verse eid="MRK 10:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 10:23" />¶ And Jesus looked round about, and saith unto his disciples, <char style="wj">How hardly shall they that have riches enter into the kingdom of God!</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 10:24" />And the disciples were astonished at his words. But Jesus answereth again, and saith unto them, <char style="wj">Children, how hard is it for them that trust in riches to enter into the kingdom of God!</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 10:25" /><char style="wj">It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 10:26" />And they were astonished out of measure, saying among themselves, Who then can be saved? <verse eid="MRK 10:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 10:27" />And Jesus looking upon them saith, <char style="wj">With men <char style="add">it is</char> impossible, but not with God: for with God all things are possible.</char><verse eid="MRK 10:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 10:28" />¶ Then Peter began to say unto him, Lo, we have left all, and have followed thee. <verse eid="MRK 10:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 10:29" />And Jesus answered and said, <char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, There is no man that hath left house, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my sake, and the gospel’s,</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 10:30" /><char style="wj">But he shall receive an hundredfold now in this time, houses, and brethren, and sisters, and mothers, and children, and lands, with persecutions; and in the world to come eternal life.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 10:31" /><char style="wj">But many <char style="add">that are</char> first shall be last; and the last first.</char><verse eid="MRK 10:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 10:32" />¶ And they were in the way going up to Jerusalem; and Jesus went before them: and they were amazed; and as they followed, they were afraid. And he took again the twelve, and began to tell them what things should happen unto him, <verse eid="MRK 10:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 10:33" /><char style="add">Saying</char>, <char style="wj">Behold, we go up to Jerusalem; and the Son of man shall be delivered unto the chief priests, and unto the scribes; and they shall condemn him to death, and shall deliver him to the Gentiles:</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 10:34" /><char style="wj">And they shall mock him, and shall scourge him, and shall spit upon him, and shall kill him: and the third day he shall rise again.</char><verse eid="MRK 10:34" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 10:35" />¶ And James and John, the sons of Zebedee, come unto him, saying, Master, we would that thou shouldest do for us whatsoever we shall desire. <verse eid="MRK 10:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 10:36" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">What would ye that I should do for you?</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 10:37" />They said unto him, Grant unto us that we may sit, one on thy right hand, and the other on thy left hand, in thy glory. <verse eid="MRK 10:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 10:38" />But Jesus said unto them, <char style="wj">Ye know not what ye ask: can ye drink of the cup that I drink of? and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with?</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 10:39" />And they said unto him, We can. And Jesus said unto them, <char style="wj">Ye shall indeed drink of the cup that I drink of; and with the baptism that I am baptized withal shall ye be baptized:</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 10:40" /><char style="wj">But to sit on my right hand and on my left hand is not mine to give; but <char style="add">it shall be given to them</char> for whom it is prepared.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 10:41" />And when the ten heard <char style="add">it</char>, they began to be much displeased with James and John. <verse eid="MRK 10:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 10:42" />But Jesus called them <char style="add">to him</char>, and saith unto them, <char style="wj">Ye know that they which are accounted to rule over the Gentiles exercise lordship over them; and their great ones exercise authority upon them.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 10:43" /><char style="wj">But so shall it not be among you: but whosoever will be great among you, shall be your minister:</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 10:44" /><char style="wj">And whosoever of you will be the chiefest, shall be servant of all.</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 10:45" /><char style="wj">For even the Son of man came not to be ministered unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransom for many.</char><verse eid="MRK 10:45" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 10:46" />¶ And they came to Jericho: and as he went out of Jericho with his disciples and a great number of people, blind Bartimæus, the son of Timæus, sat by the highway side begging. <verse eid="MRK 10:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 10:47" />And when he heard that it was Jesus of Nazareth, he began to cry out, and say, Jesus, <char style="add">thou</char> Son of David, have mercy on me. <verse eid="MRK 10:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 10:48" />And many charged him that he should hold his peace: but he cried the more a great deal, <char style="add">Thou</char> Son of David, have mercy on me. <verse eid="MRK 10:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 10:49" />And Jesus stood still, and commanded him to be called. And they call the blind man, saying unto him, Be of good comfort, rise; he calleth thee. <verse eid="MRK 10:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 10:50" />And he, casting away his garment, rose, and came to Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 10:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 10:51" />And Jesus answered and said unto him, <char style="wj">What wilt thou that I should do unto thee?</char> The blind man said unto him, Lord, that I might receive my sight. <verse eid="MRK 10:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 10:52" />And Jesus said unto him, <char style="wj">Go thy way; thy faith hath made thee whole.</char> And immediately he received his sight, and followed Jesus in the way.<verse eid="MRK 10:52" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 10" />
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="MRK 11" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 11:1" />And when they came nigh to Jerusalem, unto Bethphage and Bethany, at the mount of Olives, he sendeth forth two of his disciples, <verse eid="MRK 11:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 11:2" />And saith unto them, <char style="wj">Go your way into the village over against you: and as soon as ye be entered into it, ye shall find a colt tied, whereon never man sat; loose him, and bring <char style="add">him</char>.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 11:3" /><char style="wj">And if any man say unto you, Why do ye this? say ye that the Lord hath need of him; and straightway he will send him hither.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 11:4" />And they went their way, and found the colt tied by the door without in a place where two ways met; and they loose him. <verse eid="MRK 11:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 11:5" />And certain of them that stood there said unto them, What do ye, loosing the colt? <verse eid="MRK 11:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 11:6" />And they said unto them even as Jesus had commanded: and they let them go. <verse eid="MRK 11:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 11:7" />And they brought the colt to Jesus, and cast their garments on him; and he sat upon him. <verse eid="MRK 11:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 11:8" />And many spread their garments in the way: and others cut down branches off the trees, and strawed <char style="add">them</char> in the way. <verse eid="MRK 11:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 11:9" />And they that went before, and they that followed, cried, saying, Hosanna; Blessed <char style="add">is</char> he that cometh in the name of the Lord: <verse eid="MRK 11:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 11:10" />Blessed <char style="add">be</char> the kingdom of our father David, that cometh in the name of the Lord: Hosanna in the highest. <verse eid="MRK 11:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 11:11" />And Jesus entered into Jerusalem, and into the temple: and when he had looked round about upon all things, and now the eventide was come, he went out unto Bethany with the twelve.<verse eid="MRK 11:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 11:12" />¶ And on the morrow, when they were come from Bethany, he was hungry: <verse eid="MRK 11:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 11:13" />And seeing a fig tree afar off having leaves, he came, if haply he might find any thing thereon: and when he came to it, he found nothing but leaves; for the time of figs was not <char style="add">yet</char>. <verse eid="MRK 11:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 11:14" />And Jesus answered and said unto it, <char style="wj">No man eat fruit of thee hereafter for ever.</char> And his disciples heard <char style="add">it.</char><verse eid="MRK 11:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 11:15" />¶ And they come to Jerusalem: and Jesus went into the temple, and began to cast out them that sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the moneychangers, and the seats of them that sold doves; <verse eid="MRK 11:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 11:16" />And would not suffer that any man should carry <char style="add">any</char> vessel through the temple. <verse eid="MRK 11:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 11:17" />And he taught, saying unto them, <char style="wj">Is it not written, My house shall be called of all nations the house of prayer? but ye have made it a den of thieves.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 11:18" />And the scribes and chief priests heard <char style="add">it</char>, and sought how they might destroy him: for they feared him, because all the people was astonished at his doctrine. <verse eid="MRK 11:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 11:19" />And when even was come, he went out of the city.<verse eid="MRK 11:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 11:20" />¶ And in the morning, as they passed by, they saw the fig tree dried up from the roots. <verse eid="MRK 11:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 11:21" />And Peter calling to remembrance saith unto him, Master, behold, the fig tree which thou cursedst is withered away. <verse eid="MRK 11:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 11:22" />And Jesus answering saith unto them, <char style="wj">Have faith in God.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 11:23" /><char style="wj">For verily I say unto you, That whosoever shall say unto this mountain, Be thou removed, and be thou cast into the sea; and shall not doubt in his heart, but shall believe that those things which he saith shall come to pass; he shall have whatsoever he saith.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 11:24" /><char style="wj">Therefore I say unto you, What things soever ye desire, when ye pray, believe that ye receive <char style="add">them</char>, and ye shall have <char style="add">them</char>.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 11:25" /><char style="wj">And when ye stand praying, forgive, if ye have ought against any: that your Father also which is in heaven may forgive you your trespasses.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 11:26" /><char style="wj">But if ye do not forgive, neither will your Father which is in heaven forgive your trespasses.</char><verse eid="MRK 11:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 11:27" />¶ And they come again to Jerusalem: and as he was walking in the temple, there come to him the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders, <verse eid="MRK 11:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 11:28" />And say unto him, By what authority doest thou these things? and who gave thee this authority to do these things? <verse eid="MRK 11:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 11:29" />And Jesus answered and said unto them, <char style="wj">I will also ask of you one question, and answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 11:30" /><char style="wj">The baptism of John, was <char style="add">it</char> from heaven, or of men? answer me.</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 11:31" />And they reasoned with themselves, saying, If we shall say, From heaven; he will say, Why then did ye not believe him? <verse eid="MRK 11:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 11:32" />But if we shall say, Of men; they feared the people: for all <char style="add">men</char> counted John, that he was a prophet indeed. <verse eid="MRK 11:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 11:33" />And they answered and said unto Jesus, We cannot tell. And Jesus answering saith unto them, <char style="wj">Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.</char><verse eid="MRK 11:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 11" />
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="MRK 12" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 12:1" />And he began to speak unto them by parables. <char style="wj">A <char style="add">certain</char> man planted a vineyard, and set an hedge about <char style="add">it</char>, and digged <char style="add">a place for</char> the winefat, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into a far country.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 12:2" /><char style="wj">And at the season he sent to the husbandmen a servant, that he might receive from the husbandmen of the fruit of the vineyard.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 12:3" /><char style="wj">And they caught <char style="add">him</char>, and beat him, and sent <char style="add">him</char> away empty.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 12:4" /><char style="wj">And again he sent unto them another servant; and at him they cast stones, and wounded <char style="add">him</char> in the head, and sent <char style="add">him</char> away shamefully handled.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 12:5" /><char style="wj">And again he sent another; and him they killed, and many others; beating some, and killing some.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 12:6" /><char style="wj">Having yet therefore one son, his wellbeloved, he sent him also last unto them, saying, They will reverence my son.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 12:7" /><char style="wj">But those husbandmen said among themselves, This is the heir; come, let us kill him, and the inheritance shall be ours.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 12:8" /><char style="wj">And they took him, and killed <char style="add">him</char>, and cast <char style="add">him</char> out of the vineyard.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 12:9" /><char style="wj">What shall therefore the lord of the vineyard do? he will come and destroy the husbandmen, and will give the vineyard unto others.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 12:10" /><char style="wj">And have ye not read this scripture; The stone which the builders rejected is become the head of the corner:</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 12:11" /><char style="wj">This was the Lord’s doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes?</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 12:12" />And they sought to lay hold on him, but feared the people: for they knew that he had spoken the parable against them: and they left him, and went their way.<verse eid="MRK 12:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 12:13" />¶ And they send unto him certain of the Pharisees and of the Herodians, to catch him in <char style="add">his</char> words. <verse eid="MRK 12:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 12:14" />And when they were come, they say unto him, Master, we know that thou art true, and carest for no man: for thou regardest not the person of men, but teachest the way of God in truth: Is it lawful to give tribute to Cæsar, or not? <verse eid="MRK 12:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 12:15" />Shall we give, or shall we not give? But he, knowing their hypocrisy, said unto them, <char style="wj">Why tempt ye me? bring me a penny, that I may see <char style="add">it</char>.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 12:16" />And they brought <char style="add">it</char>. And he saith unto them, <char style="wj">Whose <char style="add">is</char> this image and superscription?</char> And they said unto him, Cæsar’s. <verse eid="MRK 12:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 12:17" />And Jesus answering said unto them, <char style="wj">Render to Cæsar the things that are Cæsar’s, and to God the things that are God’s.</char> And they marvelled at him.<verse eid="MRK 12:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 12:18" />¶ Then come unto him the Sadducees, which say there is no resurrection; and they asked him, saying, <verse eid="MRK 12:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 12:19" />Master, Moses wrote unto us, If a man’s brother die, and leave <char style="add">his</char> wife <char style="add">behind him</char>, and leave no children, that his brother should take his wife, and raise up seed unto his brother. <verse eid="MRK 12:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 12:20" />Now there were seven brethren: and the first took a wife, and dying left no seed. <verse eid="MRK 12:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 12:21" />And the second took her, and died, neither left he any seed: and the third likewise. <verse eid="MRK 12:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 12:22" />And the seven had her, and left no seed: last of all the woman died also. <verse eid="MRK 12:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 12:23" />In the resurrection therefore, when they shall rise, whose wife shall she be of them? for the seven had her to wife. <verse eid="MRK 12:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 12:24" />And Jesus answering said unto them, <char style="wj">Do ye not therefore err, because ye know not the scriptures, neither the power of God?</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 12:25" /><char style="wj">For when they shall rise from the dead, they neither marry, nor are given in marriage; but are as the angels which are in heaven.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 12:26" /><char style="wj">And as touching the dead, that they rise: have ye not read in the book of Moses, how in the bush God spake unto him, saying, I <char style="add">am</char> the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob?</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 12:27" /><char style="wj">He is not the God of the dead, but the God of the living: ye therefore do greatly err.</char><verse eid="MRK 12:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 12:28" />¶ And one of the scribes came, and having heard them reasoning together, and perceiving that he had answered them well, asked him, Which is the first commandment of all? <verse eid="MRK 12:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 12:29" />And Jesus answered him, <char style="wj">The first of all the commandments <char style="add">is</char>, Hear, O Israel; The Lord our God is one Lord:</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 12:30" /><char style="wj">And thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind, and with all thy strength: this <char style="add">is</char> the first commandment.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 12:31" /><char style="wj">And the second <char style="add">is</char> like, <char style="add">namely</char> this, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. There is none other commandment greater than these.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 12:32" />And the scribe said unto him, Well, Master, thou hast said the truth: for there is one God; and there is none other but he: <verse eid="MRK 12:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 12:33" />And to love him with all the heart, and with all the understanding, and with all the soul, and with all the strength, and to love <char style="add">his</char> neighbour as himself, is more than all whole burnt offerings and sacrifices. <verse eid="MRK 12:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 12:34" />And when Jesus saw that he answered discreetly, he said unto him, <char style="wj">Thou art not far from the kingdom of God.</char> And no man after that durst ask him <char style="add">any question.</char><verse eid="MRK 12:34" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 12:35" />¶ And Jesus answered and said, while he taught in the temple, <char style="wj">How say the scribes that Christ is the Son of David?</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 12:36" /><char style="wj">For David himself said by the Holy Ghost, The <char style="nd">LORD</char> said to my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand, till I make thine enemies thy footstool.</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 12:37" /><char style="wj">David therefore himself calleth him Lord; and whence is he <char style="add">then</char> his son? And the common people heard him gladly.</char><verse eid="MRK 12:37" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 12:38" />¶ And he said unto them in his doctrine, <char style="wj">Beware of the scribes, which love to go in long clothing, and <char style="add">love</char> salutations in the marketplaces,</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 12:39" /><char style="wj">And the chief seats in the synagogues, and the uppermost rooms at feasts:</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 12:40" /><char style="wj">Which devour widows’ houses, and for a pretence make long prayers: these shall receive greater damnation.</char><verse eid="MRK 12:40" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 12:41" />¶ And Jesus sat over against the treasury, and beheld how the people cast money into the treasury: and many that were rich cast in much. <verse eid="MRK 12:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 12:42" />And there came a certain poor widow, and she threw in two mites, which make a farthing. <verse eid="MRK 12:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 12:43" />And he called <char style="add">unto him</char> his disciples, and saith unto them, <char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, That this poor widow hath cast more in, than all they which have cast into the treasury:</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 12:44" /><char style="wj">For all <char style="add">they</char> did cast in of their abundance; but she of her want did cast in all that she had, <char style="add">even</char> all her living.</char><verse eid="MRK 12:44" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 12" />
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="MRK 13" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 13:1" />And as he went out of the temple, one of his disciples saith unto him, Master, see what manner of stones and what buildings <char style="add">are here</char>! <verse eid="MRK 13:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 13:2" />And Jesus answering said unto him, <char style="wj">Seest thou these great buildings? there shall not be left one stone upon another, that shall not be thrown down.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 13:3" />And as he sat upon the mount of Olives over against the temple, Peter and James and John and Andrew asked him privately, <verse eid="MRK 13:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 13:4" />Tell us, when shall these things be? and what <char style="add">shall be</char> the sign when all these things shall be fulfilled? <verse eid="MRK 13:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 13:5" />And Jesus answering them began to say, <char style="wj">Take heed lest any <char style="add">man</char> deceive you:</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 13:6" /><char style="wj">For many shall come in my name, saying, I am <char style="add">Christ</char>; and shall deceive many.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 13:7" /><char style="wj">And when ye shall hear of wars and rumours of wars, be ye not troubled: for <char style="add">such things</char> must needs be; but the end <char style="add">shall</char> not <char style="add">be</char> yet.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 13:8" /><char style="wj">For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom: and there shall be earthquakes in divers places, and there shall be famines and troubles: these <char style="add">are</char> the beginnings of sorrows.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 13:9" />
    <char style="wj">¶ But take heed to yourselves: for they shall deliver you up to councils; and in the synagogues ye shall be beaten: and ye shall be brought before rulers and kings for my sake, for a testimony against them.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 13:10" /><char style="wj">And the gospel must first be published among all nations.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 13:11" /><char style="wj">But when they shall lead <char style="add">you</char>, and deliver you up, take no thought beforehand what ye shall speak, neither do ye premeditate: but whatsoever shall be given you in that hour, that speak ye: for it is not ye that speak, but the Holy Ghost.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 13:12" /><char style="wj">Now the brother shall betray the brother to death, and the father the son; and children shall rise up against <char style="add">their</char> parents, and shall cause them to be put to death.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 13:13" /><char style="wj">And ye shall be hated of all <char style="add">men</char> for my name’s sake: but he that shall endure unto the end, the same shall be saved.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 13:14" />
    <char style="wj">¶ But when ye shall see the abomination of desolation, spoken of by Daniel the prophet, standing where it ought not, (let him that readeth understand,) then let them that be in Judæa flee to the mountains:</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 13:15" /><char style="wj">And let him that is on the housetop not go down into the house, neither enter <char style="add">therein</char>, to take any thing out of his house:</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 13:16" /><char style="wj">And let him that is in the field not turn back again for to take up his garment.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 13:17" /><char style="wj">But woe to them that are with child, and to them that give suck in those days!</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 13:18" /><char style="wj">And pray ye that your flight be not in the winter.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 13:19" /><char style="wj">For <char style="add">in</char> those days shall be affliction, such as was not from the beginning of the creation which God created unto this time, neither shall be.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 13:20" /><char style="wj">And except that the Lord had shortened those days, no flesh should be saved: but for the elect’s sake, whom he hath chosen, he hath shortened the days.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 13:21" /><char style="wj">And then if any man shall say to you, Lo, here <char style="add">is</char> Christ; or, lo, <char style="add">he is</char> there; believe <char style="add">him</char> not:</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 13:22" /><char style="wj">For false Christs and false prophets shall rise, and shall shew signs and wonders, to seduce, if <char style="add">it were</char> possible, even the elect.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 13:23" /><char style="wj">But take ye heed: behold, I have foretold you all things.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 13:24" />
    <char style="wj">¶ But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun shall be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light,</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 13:25" /><char style="wj">And the stars of heaven shall fall, and the powers that are in heaven shall be shaken.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 13:26" /><char style="wj">And then shall they see the Son of man coming in the clouds with great power and glory.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 13:27" /><char style="wj">And then shall he send his angels, and shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from the uttermost part of the earth to the uttermost part of heaven.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 13:28" /><char style="wj">Now learn a parable of the fig tree; When her branch is yet tender, and putteth forth leaves, ye know that summer is near:</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 13:29" /><char style="wj">So ye in like manner, when ye shall see these things come to pass, know that it is nigh, <char style="add">even</char> at the doors.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 13:30" /><char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, that this generation shall not pass, till all these things be done.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 13:31" /><char style="wj">Heaven and earth shall pass away: but my words shall not pass away.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 13:32" />
    <char style="wj">¶ But of that day and <char style="add">that</char> hour knoweth no man, no, not the angels which are in heaven, neither the Son, but the Father.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 13:33" /><char style="wj">Take ye heed, watch and pray: for ye know not when the time is.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 13:34" /><char style="wj"><char style="add">For the Son of man is</char> as a man taking a far journey, who left his house, and gave authority to his servants, and to every man his work, and commanded the porter to watch.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 13:35" /><char style="wj">Watch ye therefore: for ye know not when the master of the house cometh, at even, or at midnight, or at the cockcrowing, or in the morning:</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 13:36" /><char style="wj">Lest coming suddenly he find you sleeping.</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 13:37" /><char style="wj">And what I say unto you I say unto all, Watch.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:37" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 13" />
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="MRK 14" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 14:1" />After two days was <char style="add">the feast of</char> the passover, and of unleavened bread: and the chief priests and the scribes sought how they might take him by craft, and put <char style="add">him</char> to death. <verse eid="MRK 14:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 14:2" />But they said, Not on the feast <char style="add">day</char>, lest there be an uproar of the people.<verse eid="MRK 14:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 14:3" />¶ And being in Bethany in the house of Simon the leper, as he sat at meat, there came a woman having an alabaster box of ointment of spikenard very precious; and she brake the box, and poured <char style="add">it</char> on his head. <verse eid="MRK 14:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 14:4" />And there were some that had indignation within themselves, and said, Why was this waste of the ointment made? <verse eid="MRK 14:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 14:5" />For it might have been sold for more than three hundred pence, and have been given to the poor. And they murmured against her. <verse eid="MRK 14:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 14:6" />And Jesus said, <char style="wj">Let her alone; why trouble ye her? she hath wrought a good work on me.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 14:7" /><char style="wj">For ye have the poor with you always, and whensoever ye will ye may do them good: but me ye have not always.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 14:8" /><char style="wj">She hath done what she could: she is come aforehand to anoint my body to the burying.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 14:9" /><char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, Wheresoever this gospel shall be preached throughout the whole world, <char style="add">this</char> also that she hath done shall be spoken of for a memorial of her.</char><verse eid="MRK 14:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 14:10" />¶ And Judas Iscariot, one of the twelve, went unto the chief priests, to betray him unto them. <verse eid="MRK 14:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 14:11" />And when they heard <char style="add">it</char>, they were glad, and promised to give him money. And he sought how he might conveniently betray him.<verse eid="MRK 14:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 14:12" />¶ And the first day of unleavened bread, when they killed the passover, his disciples said unto him, Where wilt thou that we go and prepare that thou mayest eat the passover? <verse eid="MRK 14:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 14:13" />And he sendeth forth two of his disciples, and saith unto them, <char style="wj">Go ye into the city, and there shall meet you a man bearing a pitcher of water: follow him.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 14:14" /><char style="wj">And wheresoever he shall go in, say ye to the goodman of the house, The Master saith, Where is the guestchamber, where I shall eat the passover with my disciples?</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 14:15" /><char style="wj">And he will shew you a large upper room furnished <char style="add">and</char> prepared: there make ready for us.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 14:16" />And his disciples went forth, and came into the city, and found as he had said unto them: and they made ready the passover. <verse eid="MRK 14:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 14:17" />And in the evening he cometh with the twelve. <verse eid="MRK 14:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 14:18" />And as they sat and did eat, Jesus said, <char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, One of you which eateth with me shall betray me.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 14:19" />And they began to be sorrowful, and to say unto him one by one, <char style="add">Is</char> it I? and another <char style="add">said, Is</char> it I? <verse eid="MRK 14:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 14:20" />And he answered and said unto them, <char style="wj"><char style="add">It is</char> one of the twelve, that dippeth with me in the dish.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 14:21" /><char style="wj">The Son of man indeed goeth, as it is written of him: but woe to that man by whom the Son of man is betrayed! good were it for that man if he had never been born.</char><verse eid="MRK 14:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 14:22" />¶ And as they did eat, Jesus took bread, and blessed, and brake <char style="add">it</char>, and gave to them, and said, <char style="wj">Take, eat: this is my body.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 14:23" />And he took the cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave <char style="add">it</char> to them: and they all drank of it. <verse eid="MRK 14:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 14:24" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">This is my blood of the new testament, which is shed for many.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 14:25" /><char style="wj">Verily I say unto you, I will drink no more of the fruit of the vine, until that day that I drink it new in the kingdom of God.</char><verse eid="MRK 14:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 14:26" />¶ And when they had sung an hymn, they went out into the mount of Olives. <verse eid="MRK 14:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 14:27" />And Jesus saith unto them, <char style="wj">All ye shall be offended because of me this night: for it is written, I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep shall be scattered.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 14:28" /><char style="wj">But after that I am risen, I will go before you into Galilee.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 14:29" />But Peter said unto him, Although all shall be offended, yet <char style="add">will</char> not I. <verse eid="MRK 14:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 14:30" />And Jesus saith unto him, <char style="wj">Verily I say unto thee, That this day, <char style="add">even</char> in this night, before the cock crow twice, thou shalt deny me thrice.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 14:31" />But he spake the more vehemently, If I should die with thee, I will not deny thee in any wise. Likewise also said they all. <verse eid="MRK 14:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 14:32" />And they came to a place which was named Gethsemane: and he saith to his disciples, <char style="wj">Sit ye here, while I shall pray.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 14:33" />And he taketh with him Peter and James and John, and began to be sore amazed, and to be very heavy; <verse eid="MRK 14:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 14:34" />And saith unto them, <char style="wj">My soul is exceeding sorrowful unto death: tarry ye here, and watch.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 14:35" />And he went forward a little, and fell on the ground, and prayed that, if it were possible, the hour might pass from him. <verse eid="MRK 14:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 14:36" />And he said, <char style="wj">Abba, Father, all things <char style="add">are</char> possible unto thee; take away this cup from me: nevertheless not what I will, but what thou wilt.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 14:37" />And he cometh, and findeth them sleeping, and saith unto Peter, <char style="wj">Simon, sleepest thou? couldest not thou watch one hour?</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 14:38" /><char style="wj">Watch ye and pray, lest ye enter into temptation. The spirit truly <char style="add">is</char> ready, but the flesh <char style="add">is</char> weak.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 14:39" />And again he went away, and prayed, and spake the same words. <verse eid="MRK 14:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 14:40" />And when he returned, he found them asleep again, (for their eyes were heavy,) neither wist they what to answer him. <verse eid="MRK 14:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 14:41" />And he cometh the third time, and saith unto them, <char style="wj">Sleep on now, and take <char style="add">your</char> rest: it is enough, the hour is come; behold, the Son of man is betrayed into the hands of sinners.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 14:42" /><char style="wj">Rise up, let us go; lo, he that betrayeth me is at hand.</char><verse eid="MRK 14:42" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 14:43" />¶ And immediately, while he yet spake, cometh Judas, one of the twelve, and with him a great multitude with swords and staves, from the chief priests and the scribes and the elders. <verse eid="MRK 14:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 14:44" />And he that betrayed him had given them a token, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, that same is he; take him, and lead <char style="add">him</char> away safely. <verse eid="MRK 14:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 14:45" />And as soon as he was come, he goeth straightway to him, and saith, Master, master; and kissed him.<verse eid="MRK 14:45" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 14:46" />¶ And they laid their hands on him, and took him. <verse eid="MRK 14:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 14:47" />And one of them that stood by drew a sword, and smote a servant of the high priest, and cut off his ear. <verse eid="MRK 14:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 14:48" />And Jesus answered and said unto them, <char style="wj">Are ye come out, as against a thief, with swords and <char style="add">with</char> staves to take me?</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 14:49" /><char style="wj">I was daily with you in the temple teaching, and ye took me not: but the scriptures must be fulfilled.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 14:50" />And they all forsook him, and fled. <verse eid="MRK 14:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 14:51" />And there followed him a certain young man, having a linen cloth cast about <char style="add">his</char> naked <char style="add">body</char>; and the young men laid hold on him: <verse eid="MRK 14:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 14:52" />And he left the linen cloth, and fled from them naked.<verse eid="MRK 14:52" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 14:53" />¶ And they led Jesus away to the high priest: and with him were assembled all the chief priests and the elders and the scribes. <verse eid="MRK 14:53" /><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 14:54" />And Peter followed him afar off, even into the palace of the high priest: and he sat with the servants, and warmed himself at the fire. <verse eid="MRK 14:54" /><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 14:55" />And the chief priests and all the council sought for witness against Jesus to put him to death; and found none. <verse eid="MRK 14:55" /><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 14:56" />For many bare false witness against him, but their witness agreed not together. <verse eid="MRK 14:56" /><verse number="57" style="v" sid="MRK 14:57" />And there arose certain, and bare false witness against him, saying, <verse eid="MRK 14:57" /><verse number="58" style="v" sid="MRK 14:58" />We heard him say, I will destroy this temple that is made with hands, and within three days I will build another made without hands. <verse eid="MRK 14:58" /><verse number="59" style="v" sid="MRK 14:59" />But neither so did their witness agree together. <verse eid="MRK 14:59" /><verse number="60" style="v" sid="MRK 14:60" />And the high priest stood up in the midst, and asked Jesus, saying, Answerest thou nothing? what <char style="add">is it which</char> these witness against thee? <verse eid="MRK 14:60" /><verse number="61" style="v" sid="MRK 14:61" />But he held his peace, and answered nothing. Again the high priest asked him, and said unto him, Art thou the Christ, the Son of the Blessed? <verse eid="MRK 14:61" /><verse number="62" style="v" sid="MRK 14:62" />And Jesus said, <char style="wj">I am: and ye shall see the Son of man sitting on the right hand of power, and coming in the clouds of heaven.</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:62" /><verse number="63" style="v" sid="MRK 14:63" />Then the high priest rent his clothes, and saith, What need we any further witnesses? <verse eid="MRK 14:63" /><verse number="64" style="v" sid="MRK 14:64" />Ye have heard the blasphemy: what think ye? And they all condemned him to be guilty of death. <verse eid="MRK 14:64" /><verse number="65" style="v" sid="MRK 14:65" />And some began to spit on him, and to cover his face, and to buffet him, and to say unto him, Prophesy: and the servants did strike him with the palms of their hands.<verse eid="MRK 14:65" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" sid="MRK 14:66" />¶ And as Peter was beneath in the palace, there cometh one of the maids of the high priest: <verse eid="MRK 14:66" /><verse number="67" style="v" sid="MRK 14:67" />And when she saw Peter warming himself, she looked upon him, and said, And thou also wast with Jesus of Nazareth. <verse eid="MRK 14:67" /><verse number="68" style="v" sid="MRK 14:68" />But he denied, saying, I know not, neither understand I what thou sayest. And he went out into the porch; and the cock crew. <verse eid="MRK 14:68" /><verse number="69" style="v" sid="MRK 14:69" />And a maid saw him again, and began to say to them that stood by, This is <char style="add">one</char> of them. <verse eid="MRK 14:69" /><verse number="70" style="v" sid="MRK 14:70" />And he denied it again. And a little after, they that stood by said again to Peter, Surely thou art <char style="add">one</char> of them: for thou art a Galilaean, and thy speech agreeth <char style="add">thereto</char>. <verse eid="MRK 14:70" /><verse number="71" style="v" sid="MRK 14:71" />But he began to curse and to swear, <char style="add">saying</char>, I know not this man of whom ye speak. <verse eid="MRK 14:71" /><verse number="72" style="v" sid="MRK 14:72" />And the second time the cock crew. And Peter called to mind the word that Jesus said unto him, <char style="wj">Before the cock crow twice, thou shalt deny me thrice.</char> And when he thought thereon, he wept.<verse eid="MRK 14:72" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 14" />
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="MRK 15" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 15:1" />And straightway in the morning the chief priests held a consultation with the elders and scribes and the whole council, and bound Jesus, and carried <char style="add">him</char> away, and delivered <char style="add">him</char> to Pilate. <verse eid="MRK 15:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 15:2" />And Pilate asked him, Art thou the King of the Jews? And he answering said unto him, <char style="wj">Thou sayest <char style="add">it</char>.</char> <verse eid="MRK 15:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 15:3" />And the chief priests accused him of many things: but he answered nothing. <verse eid="MRK 15:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 15:4" />And Pilate asked him again, saying, Answerest thou nothing? behold how many things they witness against thee. <verse eid="MRK 15:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 15:5" />But Jesus yet answered nothing; so that Pilate marvelled. <verse eid="MRK 15:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 15:6" />Now at <char style="add">that</char> feast he released unto them one prisoner, whomsoever they desired. <verse eid="MRK 15:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 15:7" />And there was <char style="add">one</char> named Barabbas, <char style="add">which lay</char> bound with them that had made insurrection with him, who had committed murder in the insurrection. <verse eid="MRK 15:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 15:8" />And the multitude crying aloud began to desire <char style="add">him to do</char> as he had ever done unto them. <verse eid="MRK 15:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 15:9" />But Pilate answered them, saying, Will ye that I release unto you the King of the Jews? <verse eid="MRK 15:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 15:10" />For he knew that the chief priests had delivered him for envy. <verse eid="MRK 15:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 15:11" />But the chief priests moved the people, that he should rather release Barabbas unto them. <verse eid="MRK 15:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 15:12" />And Pilate answered and said again unto them, What will ye then that I shall do <char style="add">unto him</char> whom ye call the King of the Jews? <verse eid="MRK 15:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 15:13" />And they cried out again, Crucify him. <verse eid="MRK 15:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 15:14" />Then Pilate said unto them, Why, what evil hath he done? And they cried out the more exceedingly, Crucify him.<verse eid="MRK 15:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 15:15" />¶ And <char style="add">so</char> Pilate, willing to content the people, released Barabbas unto them, and delivered Jesus, when he had scourged <char style="add">him</char>, to be crucified. <verse eid="MRK 15:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 15:16" />And the soldiers led him away into the hall, called Prætorium; and they call together the whole band. <verse eid="MRK 15:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 15:17" />And they clothed him with purple, and platted a crown of thorns, and put it about his <char style="add">head</char>, <verse eid="MRK 15:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 15:18" />And began to salute him, Hail, King of the Jews! <verse eid="MRK 15:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 15:19" />And they smote him on the head with a reed, and did spit upon him, and bowing <char style="add">their</char> knees worshipped him. <verse eid="MRK 15:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 15:20" />And when they had mocked him, they took off the purple from him, and put his own clothes on him, and led him out to crucify him. <verse eid="MRK 15:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 15:21" />And they compel one Simon a Cyrenian, who passed by, coming out of the country, the father of Alexander and Rufus, to bear his cross. <verse eid="MRK 15:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 15:22" />And they bring him unto the place Golgotha, which is, being interpreted, The place of a skull. <verse eid="MRK 15:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 15:23" />And they gave him to drink wine mingled with myrrh: but he received <char style="add">it</char> not. <verse eid="MRK 15:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 15:24" />And when they had crucified him, they parted his garments, casting lots upon them, what every man should take. <verse eid="MRK 15:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 15:25" />And it was the third hour, and they crucified him. <verse eid="MRK 15:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 15:26" />And the superscription of his accusation was written over, THE KING OF THE JEWS. <verse eid="MRK 15:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 15:27" />And with him they crucify two thieves; the one on his right hand, and the other on his left. <verse eid="MRK 15:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 15:28" />And the scripture was fulfilled, which saith, And he was numbered with the transgressors. <verse eid="MRK 15:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 15:29" />And they that passed by railed on him, wagging their heads, and saying, Ah, thou that destroyest the temple, and buildest <char style="add">it</char> in three days, <verse eid="MRK 15:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 15:30" />Save thyself, and come down from the cross. <verse eid="MRK 15:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 15:31" />Likewise also the chief priests mocking said among themselves with the scribes, He saved others; himself he cannot save. <verse eid="MRK 15:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 15:32" />Let Christ the King of Israel descend now from the cross, that we may see and believe. And they that were crucified with him reviled him. <verse eid="MRK 15:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 15:33" />And when the sixth hour was come, there was darkness over the whole land until the ninth hour. <verse eid="MRK 15:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 15:34" />And at the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, saying, <char style="wj">Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani?</char> which is, being interpreted, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? <verse eid="MRK 15:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 15:35" />And some of them that stood by, when they heard <char style="add">it</char>, said, Behold, he calleth Elias. <verse eid="MRK 15:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 15:36" />And one ran and filled a spunge full of vinegar, and put <char style="add">it</char> on a reed, and gave him to drink, saying, Let alone; let us see whether Elias will come to take him down. <verse eid="MRK 15:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 15:37" />And Jesus cried with a loud voice, and gave up the ghost. <verse eid="MRK 15:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 15:38" />And the veil of the temple was rent in twain from the top to the bottom.<verse eid="MRK 15:38" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 15:39" />¶ And when the centurion, which stood over against him, saw that he so cried out, and gave up the ghost, he said, Truly this man was the Son of God. <verse eid="MRK 15:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 15:40" />There were also women looking on afar off: among whom was Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James the less and of Joses, and Salome; <verse eid="MRK 15:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 15:41" />(Who also, when he was in Galilee, followed him, and ministered unto him;) and many other women which came up with him unto Jerusalem.<verse eid="MRK 15:41" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 15:42" />¶ And now when the even was come, because it was the preparation, that is, the day before the sabbath, <verse eid="MRK 15:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 15:43" />Joseph of Arimathaea, an honourable counsellor, which also waited for the kingdom of God, came, and went in boldly unto Pilate, and craved the body of Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 15:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 15:44" />And Pilate marvelled if he were already dead: and calling <char style="add">unto him</char> the centurion, he asked him whether he had been any while dead. <verse eid="MRK 15:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 15:45" />And when he knew <char style="add">it</char> of the centurion, he gave the body to Joseph. <verse eid="MRK 15:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 15:46" />And he bought fine linen, and took him down, and wrapped him in the linen, and laid him in a sepulchre which was hewn out of a rock, and rolled a stone unto the door of the sepulchre. <verse eid="MRK 15:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 15:47" />And Mary Magdalene and Mary <char style="add">the mother</char> of Joses beheld where he was laid.<verse eid="MRK 15:47" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 15" />
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="MRK 16" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 16:1" />And when the sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the <char style="add">mother</char> of James, and Salome, had bought sweet spices, that they might come and anoint him. <verse eid="MRK 16:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 16:2" />And very early in the morning the first <char style="add">day</char> of the week, they came unto the sepulchre at the rising of the sun. <verse eid="MRK 16:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 16:3" />And they said among themselves, Who shall roll us away the stone from the door of the sepulchre? <verse eid="MRK 16:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 16:4" />And when they looked, they saw that the stone was rolled away: for it was very great. <verse eid="MRK 16:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 16:5" />And entering into the sepulchre, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, clothed in a long white garment; and they were affrighted. <verse eid="MRK 16:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 16:6" />And he saith unto them, Be not affrighted: Ye seek Jesus of Nazareth, which was crucified: he is risen; he is not here: behold the place where they laid him. <verse eid="MRK 16:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 16:7" />But go your way, tell his disciples and Peter that he goeth before you into Galilee: there shall ye see him, as he said unto you. <verse eid="MRK 16:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 16:8" />And they went out quickly, and fled from the sepulchre; for they trembled and were amazed: neither said they any thing to any <char style="add">man</char>; for they were afraid.<verse eid="MRK 16:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 16:9" />¶ Now when <char style="add">Jesus</char> was risen early the first <char style="add">day</char> of the week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, out of whom he had cast seven devils. <verse eid="MRK 16:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 16:10" /><char style="add">And</char> she went and told them that had been with him, as they mourned and wept. <verse eid="MRK 16:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 16:11" />And they, when they had heard that he was alive, and had been seen of her, believed not.<verse eid="MRK 16:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 16:12" />¶ After that he appeared in another form unto two of them, as they walked, and went into the country. <verse eid="MRK 16:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 16:13" />And they went and told <char style="add">it</char> unto the residue: neither believed they them.<verse eid="MRK 16:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 16:14" />¶ Afterward he appeared unto the eleven as they sat at meat, and upbraided them with their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they believed not them which had seen him after he was risen. <verse eid="MRK 16:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 16:15" />And he said unto them, <char style="wj">Go ye into all the world, and preach the gospel to every creature.</char> <verse eid="MRK 16:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 16:16" /><char style="wj">He that believeth and is baptized shall be saved; but he that believeth not shall be damned.</char> <verse eid="MRK 16:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 16:17" /><char style="wj">And these signs shall follow them that believe; In my name shall they cast out devils; they shall speak with new tongues;</char> <verse eid="MRK 16:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 16:18" /><char style="wj">They shall take up serpents; and if they drink any deadly thing, it shall not hurt them; they shall lay hands on the sick, and they shall recover.</char><verse eid="MRK 16:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 16:19" />¶ So then after the Lord had spoken unto them, he was received up into heaven, and sat on the right hand of God. <verse eid="MRK 16:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 16:20" />And they went forth, and preached every where, the Lord working with <char style="add">them</char>, and confirming the word with signs following. Amen.<verse eid="MRK 16:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 16" />
</usx>