<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="NEH" style="id">Nehemiah</book>
  <para style="h">Nehemiah</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Book of Nehemiah</para>
  <para style="toc2">Nehemiah</para>
  <para style="toc3">Neh</para>
  <para style="mt1">The Book of Nehemiah</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="NEH 1" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 1:1" />The words of Nehemiah the son of Hachaliah. And it came to pass in the month Chisleu, in the twentieth year, as I was in Shushan the palace, <verse eid="NEH 1:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 1:2" />That Hanani, one of my brethren, came, he and <char style="add">certain</char> men of Judah; and I asked them concerning the Jews that had escaped, which were left of the captivity, and concerning Jerusalem. <verse eid="NEH 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 1:3" />And they said unto me, The remnant that are left of the captivity there in the province <char style="add">are</char> in great affliction and reproach: the wall of Jerusalem also <char style="add">is</char> broken down, and the gates thereof are burned with fire.<verse eid="NEH 1:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 1:4" />¶ And it came to pass, when I heard these words, that I sat down and wept, and mourned <char style="add">certain</char> days, and fasted, and prayed before the God of heaven,<verse eid="NEH 1:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 1:5" />And said, I beseech thee, O <char style="nd">LORD</char> God of heaven, the great and terrible God, that keepeth covenant and mercy for them that love him and observe his commandments: <verse eid="NEH 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 1:6" />Let thine ear now be attentive, and thine eyes open, that thou mayest hear the prayer of thy servant, which I pray before thee now, day and night, for the children of Israel thy servants, and confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we have sinned against thee: both I and my father’s house have sinned. <verse eid="NEH 1:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 1:7" />We have dealt very corruptly against thee, and have not kept the commandments, nor the statutes, nor the judgments, which thou commandedst thy servant Moses. <verse eid="NEH 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 1:8" />Remember, I beseech thee, the word that thou commandedst thy servant Moses, saying, <char style="add">If</char> ye transgress, I will scatter you abroad among the nations: <verse eid="NEH 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 1:9" />But <char style="add">if</char> ye turn unto me, and keep my commandments, and do them; though there were of you cast out unto the uttermost part of the heaven, <char style="add">yet</char> will I gather them from thence, and will bring them unto the place that I have chosen to set my name there. <verse eid="NEH 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 1:10" />Now these <char style="add">are</char> thy servants and thy people, whom thou hast redeemed by thy great power, and by thy strong hand. <verse eid="NEH 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 1:11" />O Lord, I beseech thee, let now thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy servant, and to the prayer of thy servants, who desire to fear thy name: and prosper, I pray thee, thy servant this day, and grant him mercy in the sight of this man. For I was the king’s cupbearer.<verse eid="NEH 1:11" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="NEH 2" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 2:1" />And it came to pass in the month Nisan, in the twentieth year of Artaxerxes the king, <char style="add">that</char> wine <char style="add">was</char> before him: and I took up the wine, and gave <char style="add">it</char> unto the king. Now I had not been <char style="add">beforetime</char> sad in his presence. <verse eid="NEH 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 2:2" />Wherefore the king said unto me, Why <char style="add">is</char> thy countenance sad, seeing thou <char style="add">art</char> not sick? this <char style="add">is</char> nothing <char style="add">else</char> but sorrow of heart. Then I was very sore afraid, <verse eid="NEH 2:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 2:3" />And said unto the king, Let the king live for ever: why should not my countenance be sad, when the city, the place of my fathers’ sepulchres, <char style="add">lieth</char> waste, and the gates thereof are consumed with fire? <verse eid="NEH 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 2:4" />Then the king said unto me, For what dost thou make request? So I prayed to the God of heaven. <verse eid="NEH 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 2:5" />And I said unto the king, If it please the king, and if thy servant have found favour in thy sight, that thou wouldest send me unto Judah, unto the city of my fathers’ sepulchres, that I may build it. <verse eid="NEH 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 2:6" />And the king said unto me, (the queen also sitting by him,) For how long shall thy journey be? and when wilt thou return? So it pleased the king to send me; and I set him a time.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">queen: Heb. wife</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 2:7" />Moreover I said unto the king, If it please the king, let letters be given me to the governors beyond the river, that they may convey me over till I come into Judah; <verse eid="NEH 2:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 2:8" />And a letter unto Asaph the keeper of the king’s forest, that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the palace which <char style="add">appertained</char> to the house, and for the wall of the city, and for the house that I shall enter into. And the king granted me, according to the good hand of my God upon me.<verse eid="NEH 2:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 2:9" />¶ Then I came to the governors beyond the river, and gave them the king’s letters. Now the king had sent captains of the army and horsemen with me. <verse eid="NEH 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 2:10" />When Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, heard <char style="add">of it</char>, it grieved them exceedingly that there was come a man to seek the welfare of the children of Israel. <verse eid="NEH 2:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 2:11" />So I came to Jerusalem, and was there three days.<verse eid="NEH 2:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 2:12" />¶ And I arose in the night, I and some few men with me; neither told I <char style="add">any</char> man what my God had put in my heart to do at Jerusalem: neither <char style="add">was there any</char> beast with me, save the beast that I rode upon. <verse eid="NEH 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 2:13" />And I went out by night by the gate of the valley, even before the dragon well, and to the dung port, and viewed the walls of Jerusalem, which were broken down, and the gates thereof were consumed with fire. <verse eid="NEH 2:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 2:14" />Then I went on to the gate of the fountain, and to the king’s pool: but <char style="add">there was</char> no place for the beast <char style="add">that was</char> under me to pass. <verse eid="NEH 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 2:15" />Then went I up in the night by the brook, and viewed the wall, and turned back, and entered by the gate of the valley, and <char style="add">so</char> returned. <verse eid="NEH 2:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 2:16" />And the rulers knew not whither I went, or what I did; neither had I as yet told <char style="add">it</char> to the Jews, nor to the priests, nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest that did the work.<verse eid="NEH 2:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 2:17" />¶ Then said I unto them, Ye see the distress that we <char style="add">are</char> in, how Jerusalem <char style="add">lieth</char> waste, and the gates thereof are burned with fire: come, and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, that we be no more a reproach. <verse eid="NEH 2:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 2:18" />Then I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me; as also the king’s words that he had spoken unto me. And they said, Let us rise up and build. So they strengthened their hands for <char style="add">this</char> good <char style="add">work</char>. <verse eid="NEH 2:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 2:19" />But when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian, heard <char style="add">it</char>, they laughed us to scorn, and despised us, and said, What <char style="add">is</char> this thing that ye do? will ye rebel against the king? <verse eid="NEH 2:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 2:20" />Then answered I them, and said unto them, The God of heaven, he will prosper us; therefore we his servants will arise and build: but ye have no portion, nor right, nor memorial, in Jerusalem.<verse eid="NEH 2:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="NEH 3" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 3:1" />Then Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brethren the priests, and they builded the sheep gate; they sanctified it, and set up the doors of it; even unto the tower of Meah they sanctified it, unto the tower of Hananeel. <verse eid="NEH 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 3:2" />And next unto him builded the men of Jericho. And next to them builded Zaccur the son of Imri.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">next unto…: Heb. at his hand</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 3:3" />But the fish gate did the sons of Hassenaah build, who <char style="add">also</char> laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof. <verse eid="NEH 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 3:4" />And next unto them repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah, the son of Koz. And next unto them repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabeel. And next unto them repaired Zadok the son of Baana. <verse eid="NEH 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 3:5" />And next unto them the Tekoites repaired; but their nobles put not their necks to the work of their Lord. <verse eid="NEH 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 3:6" />Moreover the old gate repaired Jehoiada the son of Paseah, and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah; they laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, and the locks thereof, and the bars thereof. <verse eid="NEH 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 3:7" />And next unto them repaired Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Jadon the Meronothite, the men of Gibeon, and of Mizpah, unto the throne of the governor on this side the river. <verse eid="NEH 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 3:8" />Next unto him repaired Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, of the goldsmiths. Next unto him also repaired Hananiah the son of <char style="add">one of</char> the apothecaries, and they fortified Jerusalem unto the broad wall.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fortified…: or, left Jerusalem unto the broad wall</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 3:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 3:9" />And next unto them repaired Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem. <verse eid="NEH 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 3:10" />And next unto them repaired Jedaiah the son of Harumaph, even over against his house. And next unto him repaired Hattush the son of Hashabniah. <verse eid="NEH 3:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 3:11" />Malchijah the son of Harim, and Hashub the son of Pahath-moab, repaired the other piece, and the tower of the furnaces.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">other…: Heb. second measure</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 3:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 3:12" />And next unto him repaired Shallum the son of Halohesh, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem, he and his daughters. <verse eid="NEH 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 3:13" />The valley gate repaired Hanun, and the inhabitants of Zanoah; they built it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof, and a thousand cubits on the wall unto the dung gate. <verse eid="NEH 3:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 3:14" />But the dung gate repaired Malchiah the son of Rechab, the ruler of part of Beth-haccerem; he built it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof. <verse eid="NEH 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 3:15" />But the gate of the fountain repaired Shallun the son of Col-hozeh, the ruler of part of Mizpah; he built it, and covered it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof, and the wall of the pool of Siloah by the king’s garden, and unto the stairs that go down from the city of David. <verse eid="NEH 3:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 3:16" />After him repaired Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of the half part of Beth-zur, unto <char style="add">the place</char> over against the sepulchres of David, and to the pool that was made, and unto the house of the mighty. <verse eid="NEH 3:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 3:17" />After him repaired the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani. Next unto him repaired Hashabiah, the ruler of the half part of Keilah, in his part. <verse eid="NEH 3:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 3:18" />After him repaired their brethren, Bavai the son of Henadad, the ruler of the half part of Keilah. <verse eid="NEH 3:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 3:19" />And next to him repaired Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, another piece over against the going up to the armoury at the turning <char style="add">of the wall</char>. <verse eid="NEH 3:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 3:20" />After him Baruch the son of Zabbai earnestly repaired the other piece, from the turning <char style="add">of the wall</char> unto the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Zabbai: also called, Zaccai</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 3:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 3:21" />After him repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah the son of Koz another piece, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib. <verse eid="NEH 3:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 3:22" />And after him repaired the priests, the men of the plain. <verse eid="NEH 3:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 3:23" />After him repaired Benjamin and Hashub over against their house. After him repaired Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah by his house. <verse eid="NEH 3:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 3:24" />After him repaired Binnui the son of Henadad another piece, from the house of Azariah unto the turning <char style="add">of the wall</char>, even unto the corner. <verse eid="NEH 3:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 3:25" />Palal the son of Uzai, over against the turning <char style="add">of the wall</char>, and the tower which lieth out from the king’s high house, that <char style="add">was</char> by the court of the prison. After him Pedaiah the son of Parosh. <verse eid="NEH 3:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 3:26" />Moreover the Nethinims dwelt in Ophel, unto <char style="add">the place</char> over against the water gate toward the east, and the tower that lieth out.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">dwelt…: or, which dwelt in Ophel, repaired unto</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ophel: or, tower</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 3:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 3:27" />After them the Tekoites repaired another piece, over against the great tower that lieth out, even unto the wall of Ophel. <verse eid="NEH 3:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 3:28" />From above the horse gate repaired the priests, every one over against his house. <verse eid="NEH 3:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 3:29" />After them repaired Zadok the son of Immer over against his house. After him repaired also Shemaiah the son of Shechaniah, the keeper of the east gate. <verse eid="NEH 3:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 3:30" />After him repaired Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph, another piece. After him repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah over against his chamber. <verse eid="NEH 3:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 3:31" />After him repaired Malchiah the goldsmith’s son unto the place of the Nethinims, and of the merchants, over against the gate Miphkad, and to the going up of the corner.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">going…: or, corner chamber</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 3:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 3:32" />And between the going up of the corner unto the sheep gate repaired the goldsmiths and the merchants.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">going…: or, corner chamber</char></note><verse eid="NEH 3:32" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="NEH 4" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 4:1" />But it came to pass, that when Sanballat heard that we builded the wall, he was wroth, and took great indignation, and mocked the Jews. <verse eid="NEH 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 4:2" />And he spake before his brethren and the army of Samaria, and said, What do these feeble Jews? will they fortify themselves? will they sacrifice? will they make an end in a day? will they revive the stones out of the heaps of the rubbish which are burned?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fortify…: Heb. leave to themselves</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 4:3" />Now Tobiah the Ammonite <char style="add">was</char> by him, and he said, Even that which they build, if a fox go up, he shall even break down their stone wall. <verse eid="NEH 4:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 4:4" />Hear, O our God; for we are despised: and turn their reproach upon their own head, and give them for a prey in the land of captivity:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">despised: Heb. despite</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 4:5" />And cover not their iniquity, and let not their sin be blotted out from before thee: for they have provoked <char style="add">thee</char> to anger before the builders. <verse eid="NEH 4:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 4:6" />So built we the wall; and all the wall was joined together unto the half thereof: for the people had a mind to work.<verse eid="NEH 4:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 4:7" />¶ But it came to pass, <char style="add">that</char> when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites, heard that the walls of Jerusalem were made up, <char style="add">and</char> that the breaches began to be stopped, then they were very wroth, <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">were made up: Heb. ascended</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 4:8" />And conspired all of them together to come <char style="add">and</char> to fight against Jerusalem, and to hinder it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to hinder…: Heb. to make an error to it</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 4:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 4:9" />Nevertheless we made our prayer unto our God, and set a watch against them day and night, because of them. <verse eid="NEH 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 4:10" />And Judah said, The strength of the bearers of burdens is decayed, and <char style="add">there is</char> much rubbish; so that we are not able to build the wall. <verse eid="NEH 4:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 4:11" />And our adversaries said, They shall not know, neither see, till we come in the midst among them, and slay them, and cause the work to cease. <verse eid="NEH 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 4:12" />And it came to pass, that when the Jews which dwelt by them came, they said unto us ten times, From all places whence ye shall return unto us <char style="add">they will be upon you</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">From all…: or, That from all places ye must return to us</char></note><verse eid="NEH 4:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 4:13" />¶ Therefore set I in the lower places behind the wall, <char style="add">and</char> on the higher places, I even set the people after their families with their swords, their spears, and their bows.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in the…: Heb. from the lower parts of the place, etc</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 4:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 4:14" />And I looked, and rose up, and said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, Be not ye afraid of them: remember the Lord, <char style="add">which is</char> great and terrible, and fight for your brethren, your sons, and your daughters, your wives, and your houses. <verse eid="NEH 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 4:15" />And it came to pass, when our enemies heard that it was known unto us, and God had brought their counsel to nought, that we returned all of us to the wall, every one unto his work.<verse eid="NEH 4:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 4:16" />And it came to pass from that time forth, <char style="add">that</char> the half of my servants wrought in the work, and the other half of them held both the spears, the shields, and the bows, and the habergeons; and the rulers <char style="add">were</char> behind all the house of Judah. <verse eid="NEH 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 4:17" />They which builded on the wall, and they that bare burdens, with those that laded, <char style="add">every one</char> with one of his hands wrought in the work, and with the other <char style="add">hand</char> held a weapon. <verse eid="NEH 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 4:18" />For the builders, every one had his sword girded by his side, and <char style="add">so</char> builded. And he that sounded the trumpet <char style="add">was</char> by me.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by his side: Heb. on his loins</char></note><verse eid="NEH 4:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 4:19" />¶ And I said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, The work <char style="add">is</char> great and large, and we are separated upon the wall, one far from another. <verse eid="NEH 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 4:20" />In what place <char style="add">therefore</char> ye hear the sound of the trumpet, resort ye thither unto us: our God shall fight for us. <verse eid="NEH 4:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 4:21" />So we laboured in the work: and half of them held the spears from the rising of the morning till the stars appeared. <verse eid="NEH 4:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 4:22" />Likewise at the same time said I unto the people, Let every one with his servant lodge within Jerusalem, that in the night they may be a guard to us, and labour on the day. <verse eid="NEH 4:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 4:23" />So neither I, nor my brethren, nor my servants, nor the men of the guard which followed me, none of us put off our clothes, <char style="add">saving that</char> every one put them off for washing.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">saving…: or, every one went with his weapon for water</char></note><verse eid="NEH 4:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="NEH 5" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 5:1" />And there was a great cry of the people and of their wives against their brethren the Jews. <verse eid="NEH 5:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 5:2" />For there were that said, We, our sons, and our daughters, <char style="add">are</char> many: therefore we take up corn <char style="add">for them</char>, that we may eat, and live. <verse eid="NEH 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 5:3" /><char style="add">Some</char> also there were that said, We have mortgaged our lands, vineyards, and houses, that we might buy corn, because of the dearth. <verse eid="NEH 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 5:4" />There were also that said, We have borrowed money for the king’s tribute, <char style="add">and that upon</char> our lands and vineyards. <verse eid="NEH 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 5:5" />Yet now our flesh <char style="add">is</char> as the flesh of our brethren, our children as their children: and, lo, we bring into bondage our sons and our daughters to be servants, and <char style="add">some</char> of our daughters are brought unto bondage <char style="add">already:</char> neither <char style="add">is it</char> in our power <char style="add">to redeem them;</char> for other men have our lands and vineyards.<verse eid="NEH 5:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 5:6" />¶ And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words. <verse eid="NEH 5:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 5:7" />Then I consulted with myself, and I rebuked the nobles, and the rulers, and said unto them, Ye exact usury, every one of his brother. And I set a great assembly against them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">I consulted…: Heb. my heart consulted in me</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 5:8" />And I said unto them, We after our ability have redeemed our brethren the Jews, which were sold unto the heathen; and will ye even sell your brethren? or shall they be sold unto us? Then held they their peace, and found nothing <char style="add">to answer</char>. <verse eid="NEH 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 5:9" />Also I said, It <char style="add">is</char> not good that ye do: ought ye not to walk in the fear of our God because of the reproach of the heathen our enemies? <verse eid="NEH 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 5:10" />I likewise, <char style="add">and</char> my brethren, and my servants, might exact of them money and corn: I pray you, let us leave off this usury. <verse eid="NEH 5:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 5:11" />Restore, I pray you, to them, even this day, their lands, their vineyards, their oliveyards, and their houses, also the hundredth <char style="add">part</char> of the money, and of the corn, the wine, and the oil, that ye exact of them. <verse eid="NEH 5:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 5:12" />Then said they, We will restore <char style="add">them</char>, and will require nothing of them; so will we do as thou sayest. Then I called the priests, and took an oath of them, that they should do according to this promise. <verse eid="NEH 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 5:13" />Also I shook my lap, and said, So God shake out every man from his house, and from his labour, that performeth not this promise, even thus be he shaken out, and emptied. And all the congregation said, Amen, and praised the <char style="nd">LORD</char>. And the people did according to this promise.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">emptied: Heb. empty, or, void</char></note><verse eid="NEH 5:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 5:14" />¶ Moreover from the time that I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even unto the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes the king, <char style="add">that is</char>, twelve years, I and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the governor. <verse eid="NEH 5:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 5:15" />But the former governors that <char style="add">had been</char> before me were chargeable unto the people, and had taken of them bread and wine, beside forty shekels of silver; yea, even their servants bare rule over the people: but so did not I, because of the fear of God. <verse eid="NEH 5:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 5:16" />Yea, also I continued in the work of this wall, neither bought we any land: and all my servants <char style="add">were</char> gathered thither unto the work. <verse eid="NEH 5:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 5:17" />Moreover <char style="add">there were</char> at my table an hundred and fifty of the Jews and rulers, beside those that came unto us from among the heathen that <char style="add">are</char> about us. <verse eid="NEH 5:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 5:18" />Now <char style="add">that</char> which was prepared <char style="add">for me</char> daily <char style="add">was</char> one ox <char style="add">and</char> six choice sheep; also fowls were prepared for me, and once in ten days store of all sorts of wine: yet for all this required not I the bread of the governor, because the bondage was heavy upon this people. <verse eid="NEH 5:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 5:19" />Think upon me, my God, for good, <char style="add">according</char> to all that I have done for this people.<verse eid="NEH 5:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 5" />
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="NEH 6" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 6:1" />Now it came to pass, when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and Geshem the Arabian, and the rest of our enemies, heard that I had builded the wall, and <char style="add">that</char> there was no breach left therein; (though at that time I had not set up the doors upon the gates;) <verse eid="NEH 6:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 6:2" />That Sanballat and Geshem sent unto me, saying, Come, let us meet together in <char style="add">some one of</char> the villages in the plain of Ono. But they thought to do me mischief. <verse eid="NEH 6:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 6:3" />And I sent messengers unto them, saying, I <char style="add">am</char> doing a great work, so that I cannot come down: why should the work cease, whilst I leave it, and come down to you? <verse eid="NEH 6:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 6:4" />Yet they sent unto me four times after this sort; and I answered them after the same manner. <verse eid="NEH 6:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 6:5" />Then sent Sanballat his servant unto me in like manner the fifth time with an open letter in his hand; <verse eid="NEH 6:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 6:6" />Wherein <char style="add">was</char> written, It is reported among the heathen, and Gashmu saith <char style="add">it, that</char> thou and the Jews think to rebel: for which cause thou buildest the wall, that thou mayest be their king, according to these words.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Gashmu: also called, Geshem</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 6:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 6:7" />And thou hast also appointed prophets to preach of thee at Jerusalem, saying, <char style="add">There is</char> a king in Judah: and now shall it be reported to the king according to these words. Come now therefore, and let us take counsel together. <verse eid="NEH 6:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 6:8" />Then I sent unto him, saying, There are no such things done as thou sayest, but thou feignest them out of thine own heart. <verse eid="NEH 6:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 6:9" />For they all made us afraid, saying, Their hands shall be weakened from the work, that it be not done. Now therefore, <char style="add">O God</char>, strengthen my hands.<verse eid="NEH 6:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 6:10" />Afterward I came unto the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah the son of Mehetabeel, who <char style="add">was</char> shut up; and he said, Let us meet together in the house of God, within the temple, and let us shut the doors of the temple: for they will come to slay thee; yea, in the night will they come to slay thee. <verse eid="NEH 6:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 6:11" />And I said, Should such a man as I flee? and who <char style="add">is there</char>, that, <char style="add">being</char> as I <char style="add">am</char>, would go into the temple to save his life? I will not go in. <verse eid="NEH 6:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 6:12" />And, lo, I perceived that God had not sent him; but that he pronounced this prophecy against me: for Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him. <verse eid="NEH 6:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 6:13" />Therefore <char style="add">was</char> he hired, that I should be afraid, and do so, and sin, and <char style="add">that</char> they might have <char style="add">matter</char> for an evil report, that they might reproach me. <verse eid="NEH 6:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 6:14" />My God, think thou upon Tobiah and Sanballat according to these their works, and on the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets, that would have put me in fear.<verse eid="NEH 6:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 6:15" />¶ So the wall was finished in the twenty and fifth <char style="add">day</char> of <char style="add">the month</char> Elul, in fifty and two days. <verse eid="NEH 6:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 6:16" />And it came to pass, that when all our enemies heard <char style="add">thereof</char>, and all the heathen that <char style="add">were</char> about us saw <char style="add">these things</char>, they were much cast down in their own eyes: for they perceived that this work was wrought of our God.<verse eid="NEH 6:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 6:17" />¶ Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah sent many letters unto Tobiah, and <char style="add">the letters</char> of Tobiah came unto them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sent…: Heb. multiplied their letters passing to Tobiah</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 6:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 6:18" />For <char style="add">there were</char> many in Judah sworn unto him, because he <char style="add">was</char> the son in law of Shechaniah the son of Arah; and his son Johanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah. <verse eid="NEH 6:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 6:19" />Also they reported his good deeds before me, and uttered my words to him. <char style="add">And</char> Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">words: or, matters</char></note><verse eid="NEH 6:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 6" />
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="NEH 7" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 7:1" />Now it came to pass, when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the porters and the singers and the Levites were appointed, <verse eid="NEH 7:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 7:2" />That I gave my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the ruler of the palace, charge over Jerusalem: for he <char style="add">was</char> a faithful man, and feared God above many. <verse eid="NEH 7:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 7:3" />And I said unto them, Let not the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun be hot; and while they stand by, let them shut the doors, and bar <char style="add">them:</char> and appoint watches of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every one in his watch, and every one <char style="add">to be</char> over against his house. <verse eid="NEH 7:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 7:4" />Now the city <char style="add">was</char> large and great: but the people <char style="add">were</char> few therein, and the houses <char style="add">were</char> not builded.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">large: Heb. broad in spaces</char></note><verse eid="NEH 7:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 7:5" />¶ And my God put into mine heart to gather together the nobles, and the rulers, and the people, that they might be reckoned by genealogy. And I found a register of the genealogy of them which came up at the first, and found written therein, <verse eid="NEH 7:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 7:6" />These <char style="add">are</char> the children of the province, that went up out of the captivity, of those that had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away, and came again to Jerusalem and to Judah, every one unto his city; <verse eid="NEH 7:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 7:7" />Who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. The number, <char style="add">I say</char>, of the men of the people of Israel <char style="add">was this;</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Azariah: also called, Seraiah</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 7:8" />The children of Parosh, two thousand an hundred seventy and two. <verse eid="NEH 7:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 7:9" />The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two. <verse eid="NEH 7:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 7:10" />The children of Arah, six hundred fifty and two. <verse eid="NEH 7:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 7:11" />The children of Pahath-moab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand and eight hundred <char style="add">and</char> eighteen. <verse eid="NEH 7:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 7:12" />The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. <verse eid="NEH 7:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 7:13" />The children of Zattu, eight hundred forty and five. <verse eid="NEH 7:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 7:14" />The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore. <verse eid="NEH 7:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 7:15" />The children of Binnui, six hundred forty and eight.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Binnui: also called, Bani</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 7:16" />The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and eight. <verse eid="NEH 7:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 7:17" />The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty and two. <verse eid="NEH 7:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 7:18" />The children of Adonikam, six hundred threescore and seven. <verse eid="NEH 7:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 7:19" />The children of Bigvai, two thousand threescore and seven. <verse eid="NEH 7:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 7:20" />The children of Adin, six hundred fifty and five. <verse eid="NEH 7:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 7:21" />The children of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety and eight. <verse eid="NEH 7:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 7:22" />The children of Hashum, three hundred twenty and eight. <verse eid="NEH 7:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 7:23" />The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and four. <verse eid="NEH 7:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 7:24" />The children of Hariph, an hundred and twelve.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hariph: also called, Jora</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 7:25" />The children of Gibeon, ninety and five.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Gibeon: also called, Gibbar</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 7:26" />The men of Beth-lehem and Netophah, an hundred fourscore and eight. <verse eid="NEH 7:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 7:27" />The men of Anathoth, an hundred twenty and eight. <verse eid="NEH 7:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 7:28" />The men of Beth-azmaveth, forty and two.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Beth-azmaveth: also called, Azmaveth</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 7:29" />The men of Kirjath-jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty and three.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Kirjath-jearim: also called, Kirjath-arim</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 7:30" />The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred twenty and one. <verse eid="NEH 7:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 7:31" />The men of Michmas, an hundred and twenty and two. <verse eid="NEH 7:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 7:32" />The men of Beth-el and Ai, an hundred twenty and three. <verse eid="NEH 7:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 7:33" />The men of the other Nebo, fifty and two. <verse eid="NEH 7:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 7:34" />The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. <verse eid="NEH 7:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 7:35" />The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty. <verse eid="NEH 7:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 7:36" />The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five. <verse eid="NEH 7:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NEH 7:37" />The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and one. <verse eid="NEH 7:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NEH 7:38" />The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty.<verse eid="NEH 7:38" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="NEH 7:39" />¶ The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three. <verse eid="NEH 7:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NEH 7:40" />The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two. <verse eid="NEH 7:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="NEH 7:41" />The children of Pashur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven. <verse eid="NEH 7:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="NEH 7:42" />The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.<verse eid="NEH 7:42" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="NEH 7:43" />¶ The Levites: the children of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, <char style="add">and</char> of the children of Hodevah, seventy and four.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.43 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hodevah: also called, Hodaviah or Judah</char></note><verse eid="NEH 7:43" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="NEH 7:44" />¶ The singers: the children of Asaph, an hundred forty and eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:44" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="NEH 7:45" />¶ The porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, an hundred thirty and eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:45" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="NEH 7:46" />¶ The Nethinims: the children of Ziha, the children of Hashupha, the children of Tabbaoth, <verse eid="NEH 7:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="NEH 7:47" />The children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon, <verse eid="NEH 7:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="NEH 7:48" />The children of Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the children of Shalmai, <verse eid="NEH 7:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="NEH 7:49" />The children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, <verse eid="NEH 7:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="NEH 7:50" />The children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, <verse eid="NEH 7:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="NEH 7:51" />The children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Phaseah, <verse eid="NEH 7:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="NEH 7:52" />The children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephishesim, <verse eid="NEH 7:52" /><verse number="53" style="v" sid="NEH 7:53" />The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur, <verse eid="NEH 7:53" /><verse number="54" style="v" sid="NEH 7:54" />The children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha, <verse eid="NEH 7:54" /><verse number="55" style="v" sid="NEH 7:55" />The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Tamah, <verse eid="NEH 7:55" /><verse number="56" style="v" sid="NEH 7:56" />The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.<verse eid="NEH 7:56" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="NEH 7:57" />¶ The children of Solomon’s servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida, <verse eid="NEH 7:57" /><verse number="58" style="v" sid="NEH 7:58" />The children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel, <verse eid="NEH 7:58" /><verse number="59" style="v" sid="NEH 7:59" />The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth of Zebaim, the children of Amon.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.59 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Amon: also called, Ami</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:59" /><verse number="60" style="v" sid="NEH 7:60" />All the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon’s servants, <char style="add">were</char> three hundred ninety and two. <verse eid="NEH 7:60" /><verse number="61" style="v" sid="NEH 7:61" />And these <char style="add">were</char> they which went up <char style="add">also</char> from Tel-melah, Tel-haresha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer: but they could not shew their father’s house, nor their seed, whether they <char style="add">were</char> of Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.61 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">seed: or, pedigree</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:61" /><verse number="62" style="v" sid="NEH 7:62" />The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred forty and two.<verse eid="NEH 7:62" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="63" style="v" sid="NEH 7:63" />¶ And of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Koz, the children of Barzillai, which took <char style="add">one</char> of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite to wife, and was called after their name. <verse eid="NEH 7:63" /><verse number="64" style="v" sid="NEH 7:64" />These sought their register <char style="add">among</char> those that were reckoned by genealogy, but it was not found: therefore were they, as polluted, put from the priesthood. <verse eid="NEH 7:64" /><verse number="65" style="v" sid="NEH 7:65" />And the Tirshatha said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood <char style="add">up</char> a priest with Urim and Thummim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.65 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the Tirshatha: or, the governor</char></note><verse eid="NEH 7:65" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" sid="NEH 7:66" />¶ The whole congregation together <char style="add">was</char> forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore, <verse eid="NEH 7:66" /><verse number="67" style="v" sid="NEH 7:67" />Beside their manservants and their maidservants, of whom <char style="add">there were</char> seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and they had two hundred forty and five singing men and singing women. <verse eid="NEH 7:67" /><verse number="68" style="v" sid="NEH 7:68" />Their horses, seven hundred thirty and six: their mules, two hundred forty and five: <verse eid="NEH 7:68" /><verse number="69" style="v" sid="NEH 7:69" /><char style="add">Their</char> camels, four hundred thirty and five: six thousand seven hundred and twenty asses.<verse eid="NEH 7:69" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="70" style="v" sid="NEH 7:70" />¶ And some of the chief of the fathers gave unto the work. The Tirshatha gave to the treasure a thousand drams of gold, fifty basons, five hundred and thirty priests’ garments.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.70 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">some: Heb. part.</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7.70 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Tirshatha: or, the governor</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:70" /><verse number="71" style="v" sid="NEH 7:71" />And <char style="add">some</char> of the chief of the fathers gave to the treasure of the work twenty thousand drams of gold, and two thousand and two hundred pound of silver. <verse eid="NEH 7:71" /><verse number="72" style="v" sid="NEH 7:72" />And <char style="add">that</char> which the rest of the people gave <char style="add">was</char> twenty thousand drams of gold, and two thousand pound of silver, and threescore and seven priests’ garments. <verse eid="NEH 7:72" /><verse number="73" style="v" sid="NEH 7:73" />So the priests, and the Levites, and the porters, and the singers, and <char style="add">some</char> of the people, and the Nethinims, and all Israel, dwelt in their cities; and when the seventh month came, the children of Israel <char style="add">were</char> in their cities.<verse eid="NEH 7:73" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 7" />
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="NEH 8" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 8:1" />And all the people gathered themselves together as one man into the street that <char style="add">was</char> before the water gate; and they spake unto Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moses, which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had commanded to Israel. <verse eid="NEH 8:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 8:2" />And Ezra the priest brought the law before the congregation both of men and women, and all that could hear with understanding, upon the first day of the seventh month.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: Heb. that understood in hearing</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 8:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 8:3" />And he read therein before the street that <char style="add">was</char> before the water gate from the morning until midday, before the men and the women, and those that could understand; and the ears of all the people <char style="add">were attentive</char> unto the book of the law.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from…: Heb. from the light</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 8:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 8:4" />And Ezra the scribe stood upon a pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpose; and beside him stood Mattithiah, and Shema, and Anaiah, and Urijah, and Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael, and Malchiah, and Hashum, and Hashbadana, Zechariah, <char style="add">and</char> Meshullam.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">pulpit…: Heb. tower of wood</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 8:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 8:5" />And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people; (for he was above all the people;) and when he opened it, all the people stood up:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sight: Heb. eyes</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 8:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 8:6" />And Ezra blessed the <char style="nd">LORD</char>, the great God. And all the people answered, Amen, Amen, with lifting up their hands: and they bowed their heads, and worshipped the <char style="nd">LORD</char> with <char style="add">their</char> faces to the ground. <verse eid="NEH 8:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 8:7" />Also Jeshua, and Bani, and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodijah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the law: and the people <char style="add">stood</char> in their place. <verse eid="NEH 8:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 8:8" />So they read in the book in the law of God distinctly, and gave the sense, and caused <char style="add">them</char> to understand the reading.<verse eid="NEH 8:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 8:9" />¶ And Nehemiah, which <char style="add">is</char> the Tirshatha, and Ezra the priest the scribe, and the Levites that taught the people, said unto all the people, This day <char style="add">is</char> holy unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God; mourn not, nor weep. For all the people wept, when they heard the words of the law.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the Tirshatha: or, the governor</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 8:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 8:10" />Then he said unto them, Go your way, eat the fat, and drink the sweet, and send portions unto them for whom nothing is prepared: for <char style="add">this</char> day <char style="add">is</char> holy unto our Lord: neither be ye sorry; for the joy of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> is your strength. <verse eid="NEH 8:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 8:11" />So the Levites stilled all the people, saying, Hold your peace, for the day <char style="add">is</char> holy; neither be ye grieved. <verse eid="NEH 8:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 8:12" />And all the people went their way to eat, and to drink, and to send portions, and to make great mirth, because they had understood the words that were declared unto them.<verse eid="NEH 8:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 8:13" />¶ And on the second day were gathered together the chief of the fathers of all the people, the priests, and the Levites, unto Ezra the scribe, even to understand the words of the law.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to understand…: or, that they might instruct in the words of the law</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 8:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 8:14" />And they found written in the law which the <char style="nd">LORD</char> had commanded by Moses, that the children of Israel should dwell in booths in the feast of the seventh month:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by: Heb. by the hand of</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 8:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 8:15" />And that they should publish and proclaim in all their cities, and in Jerusalem, saying, Go forth unto the mount, and fetch olive branches, and pine branches, and myrtle branches, and palm branches, and branches of thick trees, to make booths, as <char style="add">it is</char> written.<verse eid="NEH 8:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 8:16" />¶ So the people went forth, and brought <char style="add">them</char>, and made themselves booths, every one upon the roof of his house, and in their courts, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the street of the water gate, and in the street of the gate of Ephraim. <verse eid="NEH 8:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 8:17" />And all the congregation of them that were come again out of the captivity made booths, and sat under the booths: for since the days of Jeshua the son of Nun unto that day had not the children of Israel done so. And there was very great gladness. <verse eid="NEH 8:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 8:18" />Also day by day, from the first day unto the last day, he read in the book of the law of God. And they kept the feast seven days; and on the eighth day <char style="add">was</char> a solemn assembly, according unto the manner.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8.18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a solemn…: Heb. a restraint</char></note><verse eid="NEH 8:18" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 8" />
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="NEH 9" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 9:1" />Now in the twenty and fourth day of this month the children of Israel were assembled with fasting, and with sackclothes, and earth upon them. <verse eid="NEH 9:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 9:2" />And the seed of Israel separated themselves from all strangers, and stood and confessed their sins, and the iniquities of their fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">strangers: Heb. strange children</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 9:3" />And they stood up in their place, and read in the book of the law of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> their God <char style="add">one</char> fourth part of the day; and <char style="add">another</char> fourth part they confessed, and worshipped the <char style="nd">LORD</char> their God.<verse eid="NEH 9:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 9:4" />¶ Then stood up upon the stairs, of the Levites, Jeshua, and Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, <char style="add">and</char> Chenani, and cried with a loud voice unto the <char style="nd">LORD</char> their God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">stairs: or, scaffold</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 9:5" />Then the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabniah, Sherebiah, Hodijah, Shebaniah, <char style="add">and</char> Pethahiah, said, Stand up <char style="add">and</char> bless the <char style="nd">LORD</char> your God for ever and ever: and blessed be thy glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise. <verse eid="NEH 9:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 9:6" />Thou, <char style="add">even</char> thou, <char style="add">art</char> <char style="nd">LORD</char> alone; thou hast made heaven, the heaven of heavens, with all their host, the earth, and all <char style="add">things</char> that <char style="add">are</char> therein, the seas, and all that <char style="add">is</char> therein, and thou preservest them all; and the host of heaven worshippeth thee. <verse eid="NEH 9:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 9:7" />Thou <char style="add">art</char> the <char style="nd">LORD</char> the God, who didst choose Abram, and broughtest him forth out of Ur of the Chaldees, and gavest him the name of Abraham; <verse eid="NEH 9:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 9:8" />And foundest his heart faithful before thee, and madest a covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Jebusites, and the Girgashites, to give <char style="add">it, I say</char>, to his seed, and hast performed thy words; for thou <char style="add">art</char> righteous: <verse eid="NEH 9:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 9:9" />And didst see the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and heardest their cry by the Red sea; <verse eid="NEH 9:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 9:10" />And shewedst signs and wonders upon Pharaoh, and on all his servants, and on all the people of his land: for thou knewest that they dealt proudly against them. So didst thou get thee a name, as <char style="add">it is</char> this day. <verse eid="NEH 9:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 9:11" />And thou didst divide the sea before them, so that they went through the midst of the sea on the dry land; and their persecutors thou threwest into the deeps, as a stone into the mighty waters. <verse eid="NEH 9:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 9:12" />Moreover thou leddest them in the day by a cloudy pillar; and in the night by a pillar of fire, to give them light in the way wherein they should go. <verse eid="NEH 9:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 9:13" />Thou camest down also upon mount Sinai, and spakest with them from heaven, and gavest them right judgments, and true laws, good statutes and commandments:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">true…: Heb. laws of truth</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 9:14" />And madest known unto them thy holy sabbath, and commandedst them precepts, statutes, and laws, by the hand of Moses thy servant: <verse eid="NEH 9:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 9:15" />And gavest them bread from heaven for their hunger, and broughtest forth water for them out of the rock for their thirst, and promisedst them that they should go in to possess the land which thou hadst sworn to give them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">which…: Heb. which thou hadst lift up thine hand to give them</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 9:16" />But they and our fathers dealt proudly, and hardened their necks, and hearkened not to thy commandments, <verse eid="NEH 9:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 9:17" />And refused to obey, neither were mindful of thy wonders that thou didst among them; but hardened their necks, and in their rebellion appointed a captain to return to their bondage: but thou <char style="add">art</char> a God ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and forsookest them not.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a God…: Heb. a God of pardons</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 9:18" />Yea, when they had made them a molten calf, and said, This <char style="add">is</char> thy God that brought thee up out of Egypt, and had wrought great provocations; <verse eid="NEH 9:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 9:19" />Yet thou in thy manifold mercies forsookest them not in the wilderness: the pillar of the cloud departed not from them by day, to lead them in the way; neither the pillar of fire by night, to shew them light, and the way wherein they should go. <verse eid="NEH 9:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 9:20" />Thou gavest also thy good spirit to instruct them, and withheldest not thy manna from their mouth, and gavest them water for their thirst. <verse eid="NEH 9:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 9:21" />Yea, forty years didst thou sustain them in the wilderness, <char style="add">so that</char> they lacked nothing; their clothes waxed not old, and their feet swelled not. <verse eid="NEH 9:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 9:22" />Moreover thou gavest them kingdoms and nations, and didst divide them into corners: so they possessed the land of Sihon, and the land of the king of Heshbon, and the land of Og king of Bashan. <verse eid="NEH 9:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 9:23" />Their children also multipliedst thou as the stars of heaven, and broughtest them into the land, concerning which thou hadst promised to their fathers, that they should go in to possess <char style="add">it</char>. <verse eid="NEH 9:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 9:24" />So the children went in and possessed the land, and thou subduedst before them the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, and gavest them into their hands, with their kings, and the people of the land, that they might do with them as they would.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">as they…: Heb. according to their will</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 9:25" />And they took strong cities, and a fat land, and possessed houses full of all goods, wells digged, vineyards, and oliveyards, and fruit trees in abundance: so they did eat, and were filled, and became fat, and delighted themselves in thy great goodness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">wells: or, cisterns</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">fruit…: Heb. tree of food</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 9:26" />Nevertheless they were disobedient, and rebelled against thee, and cast thy law behind their backs, and slew thy prophets which testified against them to turn them to thee, and they wrought great provocations. <verse eid="NEH 9:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 9:27" />Therefore thou deliveredst them into the hand of their enemies, who vexed them: and in the time of their trouble, when they cried unto thee, thou heardest <char style="add">them</char> from heaven; and according to thy manifold mercies thou gavest them saviours, who saved them out of the hand of their enemies. <verse eid="NEH 9:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 9:28" />But after they had rest, they did evil again before thee: therefore leftest thou them in the hand of their enemies, so that they had the dominion over them: yet when they returned, and cried unto thee, thou heardest <char style="add">them</char> from heaven; and many times didst thou deliver them according to thy mercies;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">they did…: Heb. they returned to do evil</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 9:29" />And testifiedst against them, that thou mightest bring them again unto thy law: yet they dealt proudly, and hearkened not unto thy commandments, but sinned against thy judgments, (which if a man do, he shall live in them;) and withdrew the shoulder, and hardened their neck, and would not hear.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">withdrew…: Heb. they gave a withdrawing shoulder</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 9:30" />Yet many years didst thou forbear them, and testifiedst against them by thy spirit in thy prophets: yet would they not give ear: therefore gavest thou them into the hand of the people of the lands.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">forbear…: Heb. protract over them</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">in thy…: Heb. in the hand of thy prophets</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 9:31" />Nevertheless for thy great mercies’ sake thou didst not utterly consume them, nor forsake them; for thou <char style="add">art</char> a gracious and merciful God. <verse eid="NEH 9:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 9:32" />Now therefore, our God, the great, the mighty, and the terrible God, who keepest covenant and mercy, let not all the trouble seem little before thee, that hath come upon us, on our kings, on our princes, and on our priests, and on our prophets, and on our fathers, and on all thy people, since the time of the kings of Assyria unto this day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">trouble: Heb. weariness</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: Heb. that hath found us</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 9:33" />Howbeit thou <char style="add">art</char> just in all that is brought upon us; for thou hast done right, but we have done wickedly: <verse eid="NEH 9:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 9:34" />Neither have our kings, our princes, our priests, nor our fathers, kept thy law, nor hearkened unto thy commandments and thy testimonies, wherewith thou didst testify against them. <verse eid="NEH 9:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 9:35" />For they have not served thee in their kingdom, and in thy great goodness that thou gavest them, and in the large and fat land which thou gavest before them, neither turned they from their wicked works. <verse eid="NEH 9:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 9:36" />Behold, we <char style="add">are</char> servants this day, and <char style="add">for</char> the land that thou gavest unto our fathers to eat the fruit thereof and the good thereof, behold, we <char style="add">are</char> servants in it: <verse eid="NEH 9:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NEH 9:37" />And it yieldeth much increase unto the kings whom thou hast set over us because of our sins: also they have dominion over our bodies, and over our cattle, at their pleasure, and we <char style="add">are</char> in great distress. <verse eid="NEH 9:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NEH 9:38" />And because of all this we make a sure <char style="add">covenant</char>, and write <char style="add">it;</char> and our princes, Levites, <char style="add">and</char> priests, seal <char style="add">unto it</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9.38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">seal: Heb. are at the sealing, or, sealed</char></note><verse eid="NEH 9:38" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 9" />
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="NEH 10" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 10:1" />Now those that sealed <char style="add">were</char>, Nehemiah, the Tirshatha, the son of Hachaliah, and Zidkijah,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">those…: Heb. at the sealings</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the Tirshatha: or, the governor</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 10:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 10:2" />Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah, <verse eid="NEH 10:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 10:3" />Pashur, Amariah, Malchijah, <verse eid="NEH 10:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 10:4" />Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch, <verse eid="NEH 10:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 10:5" />Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah, <verse eid="NEH 10:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 10:6" />Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch, <verse eid="NEH 10:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 10:7" />Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin, <verse eid="NEH 10:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 10:8" />Maaziah, Bilgai, Shemaiah: these <char style="add">were</char> the priests. <verse eid="NEH 10:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 10:9" />And the Levites: both Jeshua the son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel; <verse eid="NEH 10:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 10:10" />And their brethren, Shebaniah, Hodijah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan, <verse eid="NEH 10:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 10:11" />Micha, Rehob, Hashabiah, <verse eid="NEH 10:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 10:12" />Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah, <verse eid="NEH 10:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 10:13" />Hodijah, Bani, Beninu. <verse eid="NEH 10:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 10:14" />The chief of the people; Parosh, Pahath-moab, Elam, Zatthu, Bani, <verse eid="NEH 10:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 10:15" />Bunni, Azgad, Bebai, <verse eid="NEH 10:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 10:16" />Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin, <verse eid="NEH 10:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 10:17" />Ater, Hizkijah, Azzur, <verse eid="NEH 10:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 10:18" />Hodijah, Hashum, Bezai, <verse eid="NEH 10:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 10:19" />Hariph, Anathoth, Nebai, <verse eid="NEH 10:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 10:20" />Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir, <verse eid="NEH 10:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 10:21" />Meshezabeel, Zadok, Jaddua, <verse eid="NEH 10:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 10:22" />Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah, <verse eid="NEH 10:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 10:23" />Hoshea, Hananiah, Hashub, <verse eid="NEH 10:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 10:24" />Hallohesh, Pileha, Shobek, <verse eid="NEH 10:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 10:25" />Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah, <verse eid="NEH 10:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 10:26" />And Ahijah, Hanan, Anan, <verse eid="NEH 10:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 10:27" />Malluch, Harim, Baanah.<verse eid="NEH 10:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 10:28" />¶ And the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the porters, the singers, the Nethinims, and all they that had separated themselves from the people of the lands unto the law of God, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, every one having knowledge, and having understanding; <verse eid="NEH 10:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 10:29" />They clave to their brethren, their nobles, and entered into a curse, and into an oath, to walk in God’s law, which was given by Moses the servant of God, and to observe and do all the commandments of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our Lord, and his judgments and his statutes;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">by: Heb. by the hand of</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 10:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 10:30" />And that we would not give our daughters unto the people of the land, nor take their daughters for our sons: <verse eid="NEH 10:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 10:31" />And <char style="add">if</char> the people of the land bring ware or any victuals on the sabbath day to sell, <char style="add">that</char> we would not buy it of them on the sabbath, or on the holy day: and <char style="add">that</char> we would leave the seventh year, and the exaction of every debt.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">every…: Heb. every hand</char></note><verse eid="NEH 10:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 10:32" />Also we made ordinances for us, to charge ourselves yearly with the third part of a shekel for the service of the house of our God; <verse eid="NEH 10:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 10:33" />For the shewbread, and for the continual meat offering, and for the continual burnt offering, of the sabbaths, of the new moons, for the set feasts, and for the holy <char style="add">things</char>, and for the sin offerings to make an atonement for Israel, and <char style="add">for</char> all the work of the house of our God. <verse eid="NEH 10:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 10:34" />And we cast the lots among the priests, the Levites, and the people, for the wood offering, to bring <char style="add">it</char> into the house of our God, after the houses of our fathers, at times appointed year by year, to burn upon the altar of the <char style="nd">LORD</char> our God, as <char style="add">it is</char> written in the law: <verse eid="NEH 10:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 10:35" />And to bring the firstfruits of our ground, and the firstfruits of all fruit of all trees, year by year, unto the house of the <char style="nd">LORD</char>: <verse eid="NEH 10:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 10:36" />Also the firstborn of our sons, and of our cattle, as <char style="add">it is</char> written in the law, and the firstlings of our herds and of our flocks, to bring to the house of our God, unto the priests that minister in the house of our God: <verse eid="NEH 10:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NEH 10:37" />And <char style="add">that</char> we should bring the firstfruits of our dough, and our offerings, and the fruit of all manner of trees, of wine and of oil, unto the priests, to the chambers of the house of our God; and the tithes of our ground unto the Levites, that the same Levites might have the tithes in all the cities of our tillage. <verse eid="NEH 10:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NEH 10:38" />And the priest the son of Aaron shall be with the Levites, when the Levites take tithes: and the Levites shall bring up the tithe of the tithes unto the house of our God, to the chambers, into the treasure house. <verse eid="NEH 10:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="NEH 10:39" />For the children of Israel and the children of Levi shall bring the offering of the corn, of the new wine, and the oil, unto the chambers, where <char style="add">are</char> the vessels of the sanctuary, and the priests that minister, and the porters, and the singers: and we will not forsake the house of our God.<verse eid="NEH 10:39" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 10" />
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="NEH 11" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 11:1" />And the rulers of the people dwelt at Jerusalem: the rest of the people also cast lots, to bring one of ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and nine parts <char style="add">to dwell</char> in <char style="add">other</char> cities. <verse eid="NEH 11:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 11:2" />And the people blessed all the men, that willingly offered themselves to dwell at Jerusalem.<verse eid="NEH 11:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 11:3" />¶ Now these <char style="add">are</char> the chief of the province that dwelt in Jerusalem: but in the cities of Judah dwelt every one in his possession in their cities, <char style="add">to wit</char>, Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon’s servants. <verse eid="NEH 11:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 11:4" />And at Jerusalem dwelt <char style="add">certain</char> of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin. Of the children of Judah; Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalaleel, of the children of Perez;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Perez: also called, Pharez</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 11:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 11:5" />And Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Col-hozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of Shiloni. <verse eid="NEH 11:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 11:6" />All the sons of Perez that dwelt at Jerusalem <char style="add">were</char> four hundred threescore and eight valiant men. <verse eid="NEH 11:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 11:7" />And these <char style="add">are</char> the sons of Benjamin; Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jesaiah. <verse eid="NEH 11:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 11:8" />And after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred twenty and eight. <verse eid="NEH 11:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 11:9" />And Joel the son of Zichri <char style="add">was</char> their overseer: and Judah the son of Senuah <char style="add">was</char> second over the city. <verse eid="NEH 11:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 11:10" />Of the priests: Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin. <verse eid="NEH 11:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 11:11" />Seraiah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, <char style="add">was</char> the ruler of the house of God. <verse eid="NEH 11:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 11:12" />And their brethren that did the work of the house <char style="add">were</char> eight hundred twenty and two: and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashur, the son of Malchiah, <verse eid="NEH 11:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 11:13" />And his brethren, chief of the fathers, two hundred forty and two: and Amashai the son of Azareel, the son of Ahasai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer, <verse eid="NEH 11:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 11:14" />And their brethren, mighty men of valour, an hundred twenty and eight: and their overseer <char style="add">was</char> Zabdiel, the son of <char style="add">one of</char> the great men.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the son…: or, the son of Haggedolim</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 11:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 11:15" />Also of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hashub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni; <verse eid="NEH 11:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 11:16" />And Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chief of the Levites, <char style="add">had</char> the oversight of the outward business of the house of God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">had…: Heb. were over</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 11:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 11:17" />And Mattaniah the son of Micha, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, <char style="add">was</char> the principal to begin the thanksgiving in prayer: and Bakbukiah the second among his brethren, and Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun. <verse eid="NEH 11:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 11:18" />All the Levites in the holy city <char style="add">were</char> two hundred fourscore and four. <verse eid="NEH 11:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 11:19" />Moreover the porters, Akkub, Talmon, and their brethren that kept the gates, <char style="add">were</char> an hundred seventy and two.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the gates: Heb. at the gates</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 11:20" />¶ And the residue of Israel, of the priests, <char style="add">and</char> the Levites, <char style="add">were</char> in all the cities of Judah, every one in his inheritance. <verse eid="NEH 11:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 11:21" />But the Nethinims dwelt in Ophel: and Ziha and Gispa <char style="add">were</char> over the Nethinims.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ophel: or, the tower</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 11:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 11:22" />The overseer also of the Levites at Jerusalem <char style="add">was</char> Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micha. Of the sons of Asaph, the singers <char style="add">were</char> over the business of the house of God. <verse eid="NEH 11:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 11:23" />For <char style="add">it was</char> the king’s commandment concerning them, that a certain portion should be for the singers, due for every day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a certain…: or, a sure ordinance</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 11:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 11:24" />And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabeel, of the children of Zerah the son of Judah, <char style="add">was</char> at the king’s hand in all matters concerning the people.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Zerah: also called, Zarah</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 11:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 11:25" />And for the villages, with their fields, <char style="add">some</char> of the children of Judah dwelt at Kirjath-arba, and <char style="add">in</char> the villages thereof, and at Dibon, and <char style="add">in</char> the villages thereof, and at Jekabzeel, and <char style="add">in</char> the villages thereof, <verse eid="NEH 11:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 11:26" />And at Jeshua, and at Moladah, and at Beth-phelet, <verse eid="NEH 11:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 11:27" />And at Hazar-shual, and at Beer-sheba, and <char style="add">in</char> the villages thereof, <verse eid="NEH 11:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 11:28" />And at Ziklag, and at Mekonah, and in the villages thereof, <verse eid="NEH 11:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 11:29" />And at En-rimmon, and at Zareah, and at Jarmuth, <verse eid="NEH 11:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 11:30" />Zanoah, Adullam, and <char style="add">in</char> their villages, at Lachish, and the fields thereof, at Azekah, and <char style="add">in</char> the villages thereof. And they dwelt from Beer-sheba unto the valley of Hinnom. <verse eid="NEH 11:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 11:31" />The children also of Benjamin from Geba <char style="add">dwelt</char> at Michmash, and Aija, and Beth-el, and <char style="add">in</char> their villages,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">from: or, of</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11.31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">at: or, to</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 11:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 11:32" /><char style="add">And</char> at Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah, <verse eid="NEH 11:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 11:33" />Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim, <verse eid="NEH 11:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 11:34" />Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat, <verse eid="NEH 11:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 11:35" />Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen. <verse eid="NEH 11:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 11:36" />And of the Levites <char style="add">were</char> divisions <char style="add">in</char> Judah, <char style="add">and</char> in Benjamin.<verse eid="NEH 11:36" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 11" />
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="NEH 12" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 12:1" />Now these <char style="add">are</char> the priests and the Levites that went up with Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua: Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra, <verse eid="NEH 12:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 12:2" />Amariah, Malluch, Hattush,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Malluch: also called, Melicu</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 12:3" />Shechaniah, Rehum, Meremoth,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Shechaniah: also called, Shebaniah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Rehum: also called, Harim</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Meremoth: also called, Meraioth</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 12:4" />Iddo, Ginnetho, Abijah,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ginnetho: also called, Ginnethon</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 12:5" />Miamin, Maadiah, Bilgah,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Miamin: also called, Miniamin</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Maadiah: also called, Moadiah</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 12:6" />Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah, <verse eid="NEH 12:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 12:7" />Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah, Jedaiah. These <char style="add">were</char> the chief of the priests and of their brethren in the days of Jeshua.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Sallu: also called, Sallai</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 12:8" />Moreover the Levites: Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah, <char style="add">and</char> Mattaniah, <char style="add">which was</char> over the thanksgiving, he and his brethren.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">the thanksgiving: that is, the psalms of thanksgiving</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 12:9" />Also Bakbukiah and Unni, their brethren, <char style="add">were</char> over against them in the watches.<verse eid="NEH 12:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 12:10" />¶ And Jeshua begat Joiakim, Joiakim also begat Eliashib, and Eliashib begat Joiada, <verse eid="NEH 12:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 12:11" />And Joiada begat Jonathan, and Jonathan begat Jaddua. <verse eid="NEH 12:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 12:12" />And in the days of Joiakim were priests, the chief of the fathers: of Seraiah, Meraiah; of Jeremiah, Hananiah; <verse eid="NEH 12:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 12:13" />Of Ezra, Meshullam; of Amariah, Jehohanan; <verse eid="NEH 12:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 12:14" />Of Melicu, Jonathan; of Shebaniah, Joseph; <verse eid="NEH 12:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 12:15" />Of Harim, Adna; of Meraioth, Helkai; <verse eid="NEH 12:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 12:16" />Of Iddo, Zechariah; of Ginnethon, Meshullam; <verse eid="NEH 12:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 12:17" />Of Abijah, Zichri; of Miniamin, of Moadiah, Piltai; <verse eid="NEH 12:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 12:18" />Of Bilgah, Shammua; of Shemaiah, Jehonathan; <verse eid="NEH 12:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 12:19" />And of Joiarib, Mattenai; of Jedaiah, Uzzi; <verse eid="NEH 12:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 12:20" />Of Sallai, Kallai; of Amok, Eber; <verse eid="NEH 12:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 12:21" />Of Hilkiah, Hashabiah; of Jedaiah, Nethaneel.<verse eid="NEH 12:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 12:22" />¶ The Levites in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan, and Jaddua, <char style="add">were</char> recorded chief of the fathers: also the priests, to the reign of Darius the Persian. <verse eid="NEH 12:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 12:23" />The sons of Levi, the chief of the fathers, <char style="add">were</char> written in the book of the chronicles, even until the days of Johanan the son of Eliashib. <verse eid="NEH 12:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 12:24" />And the chief of the Levites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Jeshua the son of Kadmiel, with their brethren over against them, to praise <char style="add">and</char> to give thanks, according to the commandment of David the man of God, ward over against ward. <verse eid="NEH 12:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 12:25" />Mattaniah, and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, Akkub, <char style="add">were</char> porters keeping the ward at the thresholds of the gates.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">thresholds: or, treasuries, or, assemblies</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 12:26" />These <char style="add">were</char> in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor, and of Ezra the priest, the scribe.<verse eid="NEH 12:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 12:27" />¶ And at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem they sought the Levites out of all their places, to bring them to Jerusalem, to keep the dedication with gladness, both with thanksgivings, and with singing, <char style="add">with</char> cymbals, psalteries, and with harps. <verse eid="NEH 12:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 12:28" />And the sons of the singers gathered themselves together, both out of the plain country round about Jerusalem, and from the villages of Netophathi; <verse eid="NEH 12:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 12:29" />Also from the house of Gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba and Azmaveth: for the singers had builded them villages round about Jerusalem. <verse eid="NEH 12:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 12:30" />And the priests and the Levites purified themselves, and purified the people, and the gates, and the wall. <verse eid="NEH 12:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 12:31" />Then I brought up the princes of Judah upon the wall, and appointed two great <char style="add">companies of them that gave</char> thanks, <char style="add">whereof one</char> went on the right hand upon the wall toward the dung gate: <verse eid="NEH 12:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 12:32" />And after them went Hoshaiah, and half of the princes of Judah, <verse eid="NEH 12:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 12:33" />And Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam, <verse eid="NEH 12:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 12:34" />Judah, and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah, <verse eid="NEH 12:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 12:35" />And <char style="add">certain</char> of the priests’ sons with trumpets; <char style="add">namely</char>, Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Michaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of Asaph: <verse eid="NEH 12:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 12:36" />And his brethren, Shemaiah, and Azarael, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethaneel, and Judah, Hanani, with the musical instruments of David the man of God, and Ezra the scribe before them. <verse eid="NEH 12:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NEH 12:37" />And at the fountain gate, which was over against them, they went up by the stairs of the city of David, at the going up of the wall, above the house of David, even unto the water gate eastward. <verse eid="NEH 12:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NEH 12:38" />And the other <char style="add">company of them that gave</char> thanks went over against <char style="add">them</char>, and I after them, and the half of the people upon the wall, from beyond the tower of the furnaces even unto the broad wall; <verse eid="NEH 12:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="NEH 12:39" />And from above the gate of Ephraim, and above the old gate, and above the fish gate, and the tower of Hananeel, and the tower of Meah, even unto the sheep gate: and they stood still in the prison gate. <verse eid="NEH 12:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NEH 12:40" />So stood the two <char style="add">companies of them that gave</char> thanks in the house of God, and I, and the half of the rulers with me: <verse eid="NEH 12:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="NEH 12:41" />And the priests; Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Michaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah, <char style="add">and</char> Hananiah, with trumpets; <verse eid="NEH 12:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="NEH 12:42" />And Maaseiah, and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and Jehohanan, and Malchijah, and Elam, and Ezer. And the singers sang loud, with Jezrahiah <char style="add">their</char> overseer.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.42 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sang…: Heb. made their voice to be heard</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="NEH 12:43" />Also that day they offered great sacrifices, and rejoiced: for God had made them rejoice with great joy: the wives also and the children rejoiced: so that the joy of Jerusalem was heard even afar off.<verse eid="NEH 12:43" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="NEH 12:44" />¶ And at that time were some appointed over the chambers for the treasures, for the offerings, for the firstfruits, and for the tithes, to gather into them out of the fields of the cities the portions of the law for the priests and Levites: for Judah rejoiced for the priests and for the Levites that waited.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.44 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of the law: that is, appointed by the law</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.44 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">for Judah…: Heb. for the joy of Judah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.44 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">waited: Heb. stood</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 12:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="NEH 12:45" />And both the singers and the porters kept the ward of their God, and the ward of the purification, according to the commandment of David, <char style="add">and</char> of Solomon his son. <verse eid="NEH 12:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="NEH 12:46" />For in the days of David and Asaph of old <char style="add">there were</char> chief of the singers, and songs of praise and thanksgiving unto God. <verse eid="NEH 12:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="NEH 12:47" />And all Israel in the days of Zerubbabel, and in the days of Nehemiah, gave the portions of the singers and the porters, every day his portion: and they sanctified <char style="add">holy things</char> unto the Levites; and the Levites sanctified <char style="add">them</char> unto the children of Aaron.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12.47 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sanctified: that is, set apart</char></note><verse eid="NEH 12:47" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 12" />
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="NEH 13" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 13:1" />On that day they read in the book of Moses in the audience of the people; and therein was found written, that the Ammonite and the Moabite should not come into the congregation of God for ever;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">they…: Heb. there was read</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">audience: Heb. ears</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 13:2" />Because they met not the children of Israel with bread and with water, but hired Balaam against them, that he should curse them: howbeit our God turned the curse into a blessing. <verse eid="NEH 13:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 13:3" />Now it came to pass, when they had heard the law, that they separated from Israel all the mixed multitude.<verse eid="NEH 13:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 13:4" />¶ And before this, Eliashib the priest, having the oversight of the chamber of the house of our God, <char style="add">was</char> allied unto Tobiah:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">having…: Heb. being set over</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 13:5" />And he had prepared for him a great chamber, where aforetime they laid the meat offerings, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tithes of the corn, the new wine, and the oil, which was commanded <char style="add">to be given</char> to the Levites, and the singers, and the porters; and the offerings of the priests.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">which…: Heb. the commandment of the Levites</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 13:6" />But in all this <char style="add">time</char> was not I at Jerusalem: for in the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon came I unto the king, and after certain days obtained I leave of the king:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">after…: Heb. at the end of days</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">obtained…: or, I earnestly requested</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 13:7" />And I came to Jerusalem, and understood of the evil that Eliashib did for Tobiah, in preparing him a chamber in the courts of the house of God. <verse eid="NEH 13:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 13:8" />And it grieved me sore: therefore I cast forth all the household stuff of Tobiah out of the chamber. <verse eid="NEH 13:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 13:9" />Then I commanded, and they cleansed the chambers: and thither brought I again the vessels of the house of God, with the meat offering and the frankincense.<verse eid="NEH 13:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 13:10" />¶ And I perceived that the portions of the Levites had not been given <char style="add">them:</char> for the Levites and the singers, that did the work, were fled every one to his field. <verse eid="NEH 13:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 13:11" />Then contended I with the rulers, and said, Why is the house of God forsaken? And I gathered them together, and set them in their place.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">place: Heb. standing</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 13:12" />Then brought all Judah the tithe of the corn and the new wine and the oil unto the treasuries.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">treasuries: or, storehouses</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 13:13" />And I made treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah: and next to them <char style="add">was</char> Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah: for they were counted faithful, and their office <char style="add">was</char> to distribute unto their brethren.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">treasuries: or, storehouses</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">next…: Heb. at their hand</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">their office…: Heb. it was upon them</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 13:14" />Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my good deeds that I have done for the house of my God, and for the offices thereof.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">good…: Heb. kindnesses</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">offices: or, observations</char></note><verse eid="NEH 13:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 13:15" />¶ In those days saw I in Judah <char style="add">some</char> treading wine presses on the sabbath, and bringing in sheaves, and lading asses; as also wine, grapes, and figs, and all <char style="add">manner of</char> burdens, which they brought into Jerusalem on the sabbath day: and I testified <char style="add">against them</char> in the day wherein they sold victuals. <verse eid="NEH 13:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 13:16" />There dwelt men of Tyre also therein, which brought fish, and all manner of ware, and sold on the sabbath unto the children of Judah, and in Jerusalem. <verse eid="NEH 13:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 13:17" />Then I contended with the nobles of Judah, and said unto them, What evil thing <char style="add">is</char> this that ye do, and profane the sabbath day? <verse eid="NEH 13:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 13:18" />Did not your fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this evil upon us, and upon this city? yet ye bring more wrath upon Israel by profaning the sabbath. <verse eid="NEH 13:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 13:19" />And it came to pass, that when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the sabbath, I commanded that the gates should be shut, and charged that they should not be opened till after the sabbath: and <char style="add">some</char> of my servants set I at the gates, <char style="add">that</char> there should no burden be brought in on the sabbath day. <verse eid="NEH 13:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 13:20" />So the merchants and sellers of all kind of ware lodged without Jerusalem once or twice. <verse eid="NEH 13:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 13:21" />Then I testified against them, and said unto them, Why lodge ye about the wall? if ye do <char style="add">so</char> again, I will lay hands on you. From that time forth came they no <char style="add">more</char> on the sabbath.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">about: Heb. before</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 13:22" />And I commanded the Levites that they should cleanse themselves, and <char style="add">that</char> they should come <char style="add">and</char> keep the gates, to sanctify the sabbath day. Remember me, O my God, <char style="add">concerning</char> this also, and spare me according to the greatness of thy mercy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">greatness: or, multitude</char></note><verse eid="NEH 13:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 13:23" />¶ In those days also saw I Jews <char style="add">that</char> had married wives of Ashdod, of Ammon, <char style="add">and</char> of Moab:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">had…: Heb. had made to dwell with them</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 13:24" />And their children spake half in the speech of Ashdod, and could not speak in the Jews’ language, but according to the language of each people.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">could…: Heb. they discerned not to speak</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">of each…: Heb. of people and people</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 13:25" />And I contended with them, and cursed them, and smote certain of them, and plucked off their hair, and made them swear by God, <char style="add">saying</char>, Ye shall not give your daughters unto their sons, nor take their daughters unto your sons, or for yourselves.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">cursed: or, reviled</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 13:26" />Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? yet among many nations was there no king like him, who was beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel: nevertheless even him did outlandish women cause to sin. <verse eid="NEH 13:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 13:27" />Shall we then hearken unto you to do all this great evil, to transgress against our God in marrying strange wives? <verse eid="NEH 13:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 13:28" />And <char style="add">one</char> of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the high priest, <char style="add">was</char> son in law to Sanballat the Horonite: therefore I chased him from me. <verse eid="NEH 13:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 13:29" />Remember them, O my God, because they have defiled the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood, and of the Levites.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13.29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">because…: Heb. for the defilings</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 13:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 13:30" />Thus cleansed I them from all strangers, and appointed the wards of the priests and the Levites, every one in his business; <verse eid="NEH 13:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 13:31" />And for the wood offering, at times appointed, and for the firstfruits. Remember me, O my God, for good.<verse eid="NEH 13:31" /></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 13" />
</usx>